<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 18:01:56">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.3.3  - Managing V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the Cisco I O S C L I commands and their functions to verify V LAN's and port memberships. Output examples are provided for the show v lan, show interfaces v lan, and show interfaces switchport commands.<br><br>Command syntax:<br>show v lan [brief | id v lan-id | name v lan-name | summary]<br><br>Display one line for each V LAN with the V LAN name, status, and its ports.<br>Command option: brief<br><br>Display information about a single V LAN identified by the V LAN ID number.<br>For v lan-id, the range is 1 to 4094.<br>Command option: id v lan-id<br><br>Display information about a single V LAN identified by name. The V LAN name is an ASCII (pronounced ASKEE) string from 1 to 32 characters.<br>Command option: name v lan-name<br><br>Display V LAN summary information.<br>Command option: summary<br><br>Command syntax:<br>show interfaces [interface-id | v lan v lan-id] | switchport<br><br>Display valid interfaces, including type, module, port number, and port channels. The channel range is 1 to 6.<br>Command option: interface-id<br><br>Display V LAN identification. The range is 1 to 4094.<br>Command option: v lan v lan-id<br><br>Display the administrative and operational status of a switching port, including port blocking and port protection settings.<br>Command option: switchport<br><br>show v lan command options examples:<br>Output from the show v lan name student command shows the following: <br>V LAN: 20<br>Name: student<br>Status: active<br>Ports: FA0/18<br><br>Output from the show v lan summary command shows the following:<br>Number of existing V LAN's: Six. <br>Number of existing VTP V LAN's: Six.<br>Number of existing extended V LAN's: Zero.<br><br>show v lan command options examples:<br>Output from the show interfaces v lan 20 command shows (highlighted): V lan 20 is up<br><br>Output from the show interfaces FA0/18 switchport command shows (highlighted): Access Mode V LAN: 20 (student)]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
