<textcomponents>

<component id="id_title">
	<text><![CDATA[<font size="+2"><b>Activity</b></font><br><br>Indicate whether a hierarchical addressing scheme using subnets should be used to structure the network.<br><br><b>Check Yes or No if subnets should be used.
</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_Button01">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Check</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_Button02">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Reset</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="txt_numrows">
	<text><![CDATA[5]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_numcols">
	<text><![CDATA[2]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_col1">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Yes</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_col2">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>No</b>]]></text>
</component>

	
<component id="txt_q1">
	<text><![CDATA[1.<textformat blockindent='13'> A small business that has 10 employees uses a 12-port switch to connect to a router to access the ISP.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_q2">
	<text><![CDATA[2.<textformat blockindent='13'> A large organization wants to break up some of their larger LANs to limit broadcasts and improve network performance. They do not want to purchase additional IP addresses from their ISP.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_q3">
	<text><![CDATA[3.<textformat blockindent='13'> An organization has five locations in different states. All sites need to be connected. They have been assigned 5 IP addresses by their ISP but wish to separate users at each location based on the type of applications they use at each location.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_q4">
	<text><![CDATA[4.<textformat blockindent='13'> An organization has been assigned a single IP address and wants to break up the address into smaller chunks to be used by different department within the organization.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_q5">
	<text><![CDATA[5.<textformat blockindent='13'> A home user purchases a Linksys WRT300N with integrated router, 4-port switch and wireless access point. One computer will connect to the switch and other users will access the Linksys via wireless.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="txt_a1">
	<text><![CDATA[2]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_a2">
	<text><![CDATA[1]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_a3">
	<text><![CDATA[1]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt_a4">
	<text><![CDATA[1]]></text>
</component>
 <component id="txt_a5">
	<text><![CDATA[2]]></text>
</component>


<!-- Correct Feedback -->
<component id="ID_titleCorrect">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Correct</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_correctText">
<text><![CDATA[You have identified the scenarios where a hierarchical addressing scheme using subnets solves the issues stated. Click Next to continue.]]></text></component>

<!-- Incorrect Feedback -->
<component id="ID_titleIncorrect">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Incorrect</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_IncorrectText">
<text><![CDATA[Please review the concept of a hierarchical addressing scheme using subnets and try again.]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>