<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[In this chapter you are introduced to StadiumCompany, a sports facility management company that manages a stadium located outside of a major city.  StadiumCompany needs to upgrade its existing computer network to provide state-of-the-art services.  To do this, StadiumCompany management outlines a three-phase project.  In the first phase, StadiumCompany is contracting with NetworkingCompany, a local Cisco business partner, to prepare a network design requirements document.  In the second phase, the stadium management plans to issue a contract for the detail network design.  Once the design is completed, the final phase will be the installation and implementation of the network upgrade.<BR><BR>StadiumCompany is also in the process of negotiating a contract with FilmCompany, a film production company located in the nearby major city.  FilmCompany will be responsible for producing, filming and delivering high quality video for download from the stadium website.  StadiumCompany management is also requiring FilmCompany to  produce live video displays during the sporting events and concerts held at the stadium.<BR><BR>As you job shadow the NetworkingCompany team, you will learn the skills needed to plan and design the StadiumCompany network upgrades. Your new design skills enable you to support the NetworkingCompany team plan and design similar upgrades for the smaller FilmCompany network. The network design portfolio you create during this work assignment will enable you to develop and present your network upgrade proposal to the FilmCompany management team.<BR><BR>In general, the StadiumCompany design project is used in the main text, media and PT activities. The FilmCompany design project is completed in the hands-on labs.<BR><BR><b>Click the buttons to download the StadiumCompany and FilmCompany stories.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<B>Download StadiumCompany Story]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<B>Download FilmCompany Story]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>
