<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 09:01:37">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.4.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Check your understanding text<br><br>This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question One. List and describe the three layers of the hierarchical network model.<br>Answer:<br>Access Layer - The Access Layer interfaces with end devices, such as PC's, printers, and IP phones, to provide access to the rest of the network. The Access Layer can include routers, switches, bridges, hubs, and wireless access points. The main purpose of the Access Layer is to provide a means of connecting devices to the network and controlling which devices are allowed to communicate on the network.<br><br>Distribution Layer - The Distribution Layer aggregates the data received from the Access Layer switches before it is transmitted to the Core Layer for routing to its final destination. The Distribution Layer controls the flow of network traffic using policies, and delineates broadcast domains by performing routing functions between virtual LAN's (V LAN's) defined at the Access Layer. Distribution Layer switches are typically high-performance devices that have high availability and redundancy to ensure reliability.<br><br>Core Layer - The Core Layer of the hierarchical design is the high-speed backbone of the internetwork. The Core Layer is critical for interconnectivity between Distribution Layer devices, so it is important for the core to be highly available and redundant. The core area also connects to Internet resources. The core aggregates the traffic from all the Distribution Layer devices, so it must be capable of forwarding large amounts of data quickly.<br><br>Question Two. Activity.<br>The diagram depicts an activity in which you must match each term with the correct description.<br>Terms:<br>A: Fixed Configuration Switch.<br>B: Forwarding Rate.<br>C: Quality of Service.<br>D: Power over Ethernet.<br>E: Modular Switch.<br>F: Link Aggregation.<br>G: Port Density.<br>H: Stackable Switch.<br>I: Redundancy.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One.Ratio of number of ports to number of switches.<br>Two.Ratio of quantity of data to time.<br>Three.Capable of interconnection via a special backplane cable.<br>Four.Ports cannot be added to the device.<br>Five.Binding together of distinct links for enhanced throughput.<br>Six.Allows for the installation of line cards or modules.<br>Seven. Capability of a device to power another device using Ethernet.<br>Eight. Capability to recover connectivity after a network failure.<br>Nine. Prioritization of network traffic.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
