<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_Prompt">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click each tip to view helpful interviewing information.</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_text01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Successful Interviewing Tips</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Learn About the Company</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button1_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Learn About the Company</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button1_text">
<text><![CDATA[Find out as much as you can about the company before the interview. What is their business? A service, manufactured goods, other? What are they most known for? What is their culture? What do industry analysts say about the company’s current direction and future potential? The Internet, a company or industry contact, the newspaper, the library, are all good sources for this information.]]></text>
</component><component id="ID_Button2">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Practice Speaking</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button2_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Practice Speaking</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button2_text">
<text><![CDATA[Further practice talking about your skills, experience and areas you are working on improving. Practice with classmates, a counsellor, a parent or sibling, a friend, even into a mirror! You will be less nervous if you’ve thought through how you want to express yourself.]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_Button3">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Dress for Success</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button3_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Dress for Success</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button3_text">
<text><![CDATA[Wear clean, pressed clothes in very good condition. A suit may not be necessary for most interviews, but dress conservatively and err on the side of being overdressed.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_Button4">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Bring Resume and Portfolio</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button4_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Bring Resume and Portfolio</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button4_text">
<text><![CDATA[Always bring several copies of your resume to the interview printed on quality paper, at least one per interviewer. Also bring any work you have done that shows the work you are capable of, such as network design plans and/or a site audit.]]></text>
</component>



<component id="ID_Button5">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Arrive Early</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button5_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Arrive Early</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button5_text">
<text><![CDATA[Time arrival 15 minutes prior to appointment. This gives you extra time in case the meeting location is changed or difficult to find.]]></text>
</component>



<component id="ID_Button6">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Be Truthful About your Skills and Experience</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button6_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Be Truthful About your Skills and Experience</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button6_text">
<text><![CDATA[It is important to find the right fit between your job interest, skills and experience and your potential employer’s culture and hiring needs. Express your eagerness and interest to learn a desired skill. Re-focus on the strengths you do bring to the situation, such as being a quick learner, collaborative, hard worker, etc. ]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_Button7">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Keep Good Posture and Smile!</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button7_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Keep Good Posture and Smile!</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Button7_text">
<text><![CDATA[Sit up straight with shoulders back, use eye contact and greet others as appropriate for your culture, and smile to make connections with your interviewers.]]></text>
</component>




]]></text>
</textcomponents>