<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 17:01:09">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.6.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.How does VTP affect V LAN administration?<br>A.Port to V LAN assignments for an entire VTP domain can all be done on a single switch.<br>B.V LAN's are only visible on switches that have ports assigned to them.<br>C.VTP propagates V LAN numbers, but not names, to all switches in a VTP domain.<br>D.VTP is required to allow V LAN naming across switches.<br>E.VTP propagates V LAN names to all switches in a VTP domain.<br><br>2.A Catalyst switch must be in which VTP mode to delete or add V LAN's to a management domain?<br>A.client.<br>B.server.<br>C.domain.<br>D.transparent.<br>E.designated.<br><br>3.What is the purpose of VTP transparent mode?<br>A.Permits V LAN creation on a single transparent switch and subsequent propagation to all other VTP switches.<br>B.Allows propagation of extended-range V LAN's.<br>C.Makes VTP traffic transparent to other devices by allowing V LAN's other than V LAN 1 to act as the management V LAN.<br>D.Enables VTP advertisements to pass through a non-participating switch.<br><br>4.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question. Switches A and B connect via a trunk and are running VTP. However, switch B is not getting V LAN update information. What could cause this problem? <br>A.FastEthernet cannot be used for trunking.<br>B.The switches are not set to the same VTP mode. <br>C.The VTP domain name is not the same on both switches.<br>D.The configuration revision number does not match on both switches. <br><br>5.A switch in a VTP domain sends an advertisement request. What is the response?<br>A.A configuration status reply is issued from the closest client switch.<br>B.A three-way handshake establishes a configuration session with the VTP server.<br>C.Summary and subset advertisements are sent by the VTP server.<br>D.The configuration version number is set to zero, and all switches in the domain issue advertisements regarding the state of their V LAN's.<br><br>6.Which function, when enabled on a switches network, prevents broadcast, multicast, and unknown unicast traffic to a V LAN from being flooded to switches that do not have that particular V LAN assigned to them?<br>A.Trunking.<br>B.VTP domain.<br>C.VTP pruning.<br>D.VTP transparent mode.<br><br>7.Which three conditions are required to add a new switch to an existing VTP domain? (Choose three.)<br>A.All VTP switches must use the same version of VTP.<br>B.Token ring switches must run VTP version 3 or higher.<br>C.The VTP pruning settings must be identical.<br>D.The VTP domain passwords must be unique.<br>E.The VTP domain names must be identical.<br>F.The connection to the VTP domain must be a trunked link.<br><br>8.Match the command to the associated description. (Not all options are used.)<br>Commands:<br>A.VTP mode client<br>B.VTP mode server<br>C.VTP version 2<br>D.VTP pruning<br>E.VTP domain LABS<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Specifies that the switch cannot create or delete V LAN's shared in VTP advertisements.<br>Two. Configures the name used to determine which switches belong to the same management group.<br>Three. Restricts flooded traffic to trunk links that the traffic must use to reach destination devices.<br><br>9.What is the purpose of the V LAN Trunking Protocol?<br>A.Maintaining consistency of V LAN configurations across the network.<br>B.Routing frames from one V LAN to another.<br>C.Routing frames along the best path between switches.<br>D.Tagging user data frames with V LAN membership information.<br>E.Distributing BPDU's to maintain loop-free switched paths.<br><br>10.Refer to the following diagram description to answer this question. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Two switches, SW1 and SW2, are connected with a single trunk link. Switch SW1 has two V LAN's defined, V LAN 20 and V LAN 30. Switch SW2 has three V LAN's defined, V LAN 10, V LAN 20, and V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch SW1 has three PC's attached, PC1, PC2, and PC3. PC1 is not in a V LAN. PC2 is in V LAN 20, and PC3 is in V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch SW2 has three PC's attached, PC4, PC5, and PC6. PC4 is in V LAN 10. PC5 is in V LAN 20, and PC6 is in V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch commands issued:<br>Switch SW1:<br>SW1#config terminal<br>SW1(config )#VTP mode server<br>SW1(config )#VTP domain Lab<br>SW1(config )#VTP password admin<br>SW1(config )#VTP version 2<br>SW1(config)#VTP pruning<br>SW1(config)#end<br><br>Switch SW2:<br>SW1#config terminal<br>SW1(config )#VTP mode client<br>SW1(config )#VTP domain Lab<br>SW1(config )#VTP password Admin<br>SW1(config )#VTP version 2<br>SW1(config)#VTP pruning<br>SW1(config )#end<br><br>Switches SW1 and SW2 are configured in the same VTP domain but failed to exchange V LAN information. What could be done to fix the problem?<br>A.Configure the same V LAN's on the VTP client and VTP server.<br>B.Configure the same VTP mode on the VTP client and VTP server.<br>C.Configure the same password on the VTP client and VTP server.<br>D.Configure different VTP domain names on the VTP client and VTP server.<br>E.Configure the VTP client in VTP transparent mode.<br>F.Configure the trunk link as an access link.<br><br>11.A network engineer is implementing a new V LAN design on an existing structure. The plan is to rename the VTP domain and implement 25 V LAN's. The engineer takes an existing production switch to the lab, enters the proposed V LAN's, and changes the VTP domain name. All new V LAN's are verified present with the show v lan command. The network administrator subsequently decides to retain the original domain name, so the name is changed back, and the switch is reconnected to the production network. The show v lan command shows that none of the new V LAN's are synchronizing on the other network switches. All switches can ping each other and trunking is correct. What is the likely problem?<br>A.No ports are assigned to the new V LAN's yet, so VTP pruning is disabling them.<br>B.The switch rejoined the network with the revision number set to zero.<br>C.The engineer failed to save the new V LAN configuration to NV RAM.<br>D.The other switches are all in server mode by default and do not accept VTP updates.<br><br>12.Match the description to the correct VTP mode. (Not all options are used.)<br><br>Descriptions:<br>A.Create, modify, and delete V LAN's and specify other configuration parameters, such as VTP version and VTP pruning, for the entire VTP domain.<br><br>B.Advertise VTP configuration parameters, such as VTP version and VTP pruning, for the entire VTP domain, but cannot create, modify, and delete V LAN's.<br><br>C.Advertise and synchronize V LAN configuration to other switches in the same VTP domain, but cannot create, change, or delete V LAN's.<br><br>D.Forward VTP advertisements that are received out the trunk ports, but cannot advertise and synchronize the V LAN configuration based on received advertisements.<br><br>E.Cannot forward VTP advertisements nor advertise and synchronize the V LAN configuration based on received advertisements.<br><br>VTP Modes:<br>One. VTP Transparent Mode.<br>Two. VTP Client Mode.<br>Three. VTP Server Mode.<br><br>13.Refer to the following diagram description to answer this question. There are four switches, Switch1, Switch2, Switch3, and Switch4, interconnected by trunked links and are configured for VTP.<br><br>Switch1 is connected to Switch2, Switch2 is connected to Switch3, and Switch3 is connected to Switch4. Switch1 is in server mode, Switch2 is in client mode, Switch3 is in transparent mode, and Switch4 is in server mode. <br><br>A new V LAN is added to Switch1. Which three actions occur? (Choose three.)<br>A.Switch1 sends a VTP update to Switch2.<br>B.Switch2 adds the V LAN to its database and passes the update to Switch3.<br>C.Switch3 passes the VTP update to Switch4.<br>D.Switch3 adds the V LAN to its database.<br>E.Switch4 does not add the V LAN to its database.<br>F.Switch4 does not receive the update.<br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
