<textcomponents>
<component id="btn1Title">
	<text>Cisco Security Appliances</text>
</component>
<component id="btn1Body">
	<text><![CDATA[Dedicated firewall devices with specialized computers that do not have peripherals or hard drives. Appliance-based firewalls can inspect traffic faster and are less prone to failure. ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="btn2Title">
	<text>Server-Based Firewall</text>
</component>
<component id="btn2Body">
	<text><![CDATA[Firewall applications that generally provide a solution that combines an SPI firewall and access control based on IP address or application. Server based firewalls can be less secure than dedicated, appliance-based firewalls because of the security weaknesses of the general purpose OS.  ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="btn3Title">
	<text>Linksys Wireless Router with Integrated Firewall</text>
</component>
<component id="btn3Body">
	<text><![CDATA[Most home integrated routers have built-in basic firewall capabilities that support packet, application and web site filtering. Higher-end routers that run special operating systems like Cisco Internetwork Operating System (IOS) also have firewall capabilities that can be configured.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="btn4Title">
	<text>Personal Firewall</text>
</component>
<component id="btn4Body">
	<text><![CDATA[Client-side firewalls that typically filter using SPI. The user may be prompted to allow certain applications to connect or may define a list of automatic exceptions. Personal firewalls are often used when a host device is connected directly to an ISP modem. It may interfere with Internet access if not properly configured. It is not recommended to use more than one personal firewall at a time since they can conflict with one another. ]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Cisco Security Appliances</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt02">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Server-Based Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt03">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Linksys Wireless Router with Integrated Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt04">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Personal Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt06">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Anti-Spyware</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt07">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_inst">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each device for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>