<transcript lastedited="01.05.09 08:01:32">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.8.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Which O S I layer is associated with IP addressing?<br>A.1<br>B.2<br>C.3<br>D.4<br><br>2.Which type of addressing is found at the O S I Layer 2? (Choose two.)<br>A.logical<br>B.physical<br>C.MAC<br>D.IP<br>E.port<br><br>3.When a server responds to a web request, what occurs next in the encapsulation process after the web page data is formatted and separated into TCP segments?<br>A.The client de-encapsulates the segment and opens the web page.<br>B.The client adds the appropriate physical addresses to the segments so that the server can forward the data.<br>C.The server converts the data to bits for transport across the medium.<br>D.The server adds the source and destination IP address to each segment header to deliver the packets to the destination.<br>E.The server adds the source and destination physical addresses to the packet header.<br><br>4.Which term describes a specific set of rules that determines the formatting of messages and the process of encapsulation used to forward data?<br>A.segmentation<br>B.protocol<br>C.multiplexing<br>D.Q o S<br>E.reassembly<br><br>5.Which two are protocols associated with Layer 4 of the O S I model? (Choose two.)<br>A.IP<br>B.TCP<br>C.FTP<br>D.TFTP<br>E.UDP<br><br>6.Match the terms with their corresponding definition. (Not all items are used.)<br>Terms:<br>A. Multiplexing<br>B. PDU<br>C. Q o S<br>D. Encapsulation<br>E. Segmentation<br>F. Protocol<br><br>Definitions:<br>One. Dividing data streams into smaller pieces suitable for transmission.<br>Two. The process of adding layer-specific information or labels necessary to transmit data.<br>Three. Interleaving multiple data streams onto a shared communication channel or network medium.<br>Four. Formal rules outlining the structure and process of network communication.<br>Five. Term used for a data packet, often implying a specific layer or protocol.<br><br>7.Match the networking terms to the appropriate O S I layer. (Not all terms are used.)<br>Terms:<br>Frames<br>IP address<br>MAC address<br>Logical addressing<br>Packets<br>Physical addressing<br>Port numbers<br>Segments<br>Bits<br>Sequence numbers<br><br>Layers:<br>Transport<br>Network<br>Data Link<br><br>8.Match the functional description of each O S I layer to the appropriate name of the layer.<br>Descriptions:<br>A. Defines procedures for accessing the media.<br>B. Standardizes the data formats between systems.<br>C. Routes packets according to a unique network address.<br>D. Cabling, voltages, bits, and data rates.<br>E. Manages users sessions and dialogues.<br>F. Defines interfaces between application software.<br>G. End-to-end message delivery over the network.<br><br>Layers:<br>Seven. Application<br>Six. Presentation<br>Five. Session<br>Four. Transport<br>Three. Network<br>Two. Data Link<br>One. Physical<br><br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
