<transcript lastedited="06.13.08 07:06:09">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.2.6 Message Timing]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Single Diagram <br><br>Diagram 1, Interaction<br><br>The diagram depicts three different aspects of message timing that are commonly used to control the flow of data between hosts, as described below:<br><br>Access Method<br>The man and the woman are communicating with each other. The woman begins the communication with a question, What time is the movie? The man also starts to talk. His question to the woman is, What time are we meeting for dinner? Because both are speaking (transmitting) at the same time, the message received by each person (or computer host) is not clear, so the message must be repeated (a re transmit is required). Both the man and the woman reply to their first attempt at communicating by saying to each other,  Sorry, I did not understand you.<br><br>Flow Control<br><br>The woman and the man are communicating by telephone. The woman sends three quick messages, Hello, can you hear me?, Hello, can you hear me?, Hello, can you hear me? The man receives these messages but does not have an opportunity to respond, and cannot distinguish the beginning and the end of the message. He is unsure if the content has been received in its entirety or whether there has been a corruption in the stream of information that has caused the repetition. <br>Hence the mans reply is the symbol of a question mark.<br><br>Response Timeout<br><br>The diagram depicts a man and a woman on the telephone. The woman queries the man, Hello, can you hear me? The man does not respond. She repeats her question but there is still no response from the man. The woman tries one last time to communicate with the man. She is resolved at this point to stop her communication with the man, due to his lack of response.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
