<textcomponents>

<component id="boxtitle1">
<text>Number of Hosts and Users</text>
</component>

<component id="box1">
<text>How many network users, printers, and servers will the network support? To determine the number of network users the network must support, be sure to consider the number of users that will be added over the next 12 months, and how many network printers and network servers the network has to accommodate.</text>
</component>

<component id="boxtitle2">
<text>Internet Service and Equipment</text>
</component>

<component id="box2">
<text>How does your business connect to the Internet? Does the ISP provide the equipment or do you own it? Often when using a high-speed Internet connection such as DSL or Cable, the service provider owns the equipment needed to connect to the Internet (e.g. a DSL router or cable modem).  If the connectivity is upgraded, the equipment that provides the connectivity may also need to be upgraded or replaced.</text>
</component>

<component id="boxtitle3">
<text>Existing Network Devices</text>
</component>

<component id="box3">
<text>How many networking devices are installed in your network?  What functions do they perform? Understanding the existing number and types of networking equipment that are currently installed is critical to being able to plan for the upgrade.  It is also necessary to document any configurations that are loaded on the existing devices.</text>
</component>

<component id="boxtitle4">
<text>Security Requirements</text>
</component>

<component id="box4">
<text>Do you currently have a firewall in place to protect your network? When a private network connects to the Internet, it opens physical links to more than 50,000 unknown networks and all their unknown users. While this connectivity brings exciting opportunities for information sharing, it also brings threats to information not meant for sharing. Integrated Services Routers incorporate firewall features along with other functionality.</text>
</component>

<component id="boxtitle5">
<text>Application Requirements</text>
</component>

<component id="box5">
<text>What applications does the network need to support?  Do you require services for applications such as IP telephony or videoconferencing? It is important to identify the needs of particular applications, especially voice and video.  These applications may require additional network device configuration, and new ISP services to support the necessary quality.</text>
</component>

<component id="boxtitle6">
<text>Wireless Requirements</text>
</component>

<component id="box6">
<text>Would you like a wired, wireless, or wired + wireless local area network (LAN)? How many square feet must your wireless LAN (WLAN) cover? It is possible to connect computers, printers, and other devices to the network using a traditional wired network (10/100 switched Ethernet), a wireless-only network (802.11x), or to implement a combination of wired and wireless networking. Each wireless access point which connects the wireless desktop and wireless laptop computers to the network has a given range. To estimate the number of access points that are required it is necessary to have the number of square feet and the physical characteristics of the location that the wireless network must cover.</text>
</component>


<component id="ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Describe and perform procedures for conducting a site survey</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click each picture to view the types of questions that can be asked to gather the site survey information and upgrade requirements. </b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Number of Hosts and Users</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Internet Service and Equipment</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Existing Network Devices</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Security Requirements</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Application Requirements</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Requirements</b>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>