<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 15:11:42">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.6.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question 1. Which of the following best describes the mapping between V LAN's and IP subnets in a modem switched network?<br><br>A.	One IP subnet to many V LAN's.<br>B.	One V LAN to many IP subnets.<br>C.	Two IP subnets to one V LAN.<br>D.	Two V LAN's to one IP subnet.<br>E.	One IP subnet to one V LAN.<br>F.	Varies with the model of Cisco Catalyst switch.<br><br>Answer: E<br><br>Question 2. Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question:<br><br>Exhibit diagram description:<br>Network Topology:<br>Switches S1 and S2 are connected by a trunk link using a crossover cable. Switch S2 has three computers, PC1, PC2, and PC3, connected to it. The link from S1 to S2 is a trunk link with one switch port, and five V LAN's, 1, 10, 20, 30, and 99.<br><br>PC1: Faculty<br>V LAN 10 <br>172.17.10.21<br><br>PC2: Student<br>V LAN 20 <br>172.17.20.22<br><br>PC3: Guest<br>V LAN 30<br>172.17.30.23<br><br>The dashed line indicates a trunk line. S1 and S2 are members of V LAN 99. Which two of the following are true? (Choose two.)<br><br>A.	All PC's can successfully ping each other.<br>B.	No PC can successfully ping another PC.<br>C.	Switch S1 can successfully ping switch S2.<br>D.	All the PC's can successfully ping switch S1.<br>E.	All the PC's can successfully ping switch S2.<br><br>Answer: B, C<br><br>Question 3. Which of the following is normally performed at the switch (config-v lan)# prompt?<br><br>A.	Adding V LAN's.<br>B.	Deleting V LAN's.<br>C.	Assigning ports to V LAN's.<br>D.	Naming V LAN's.<br>E.	Assigning the native V LAN.<br><br>Answer: D<br><br>Question 4. Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question: <br><br>Exhibit diagram description:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S1 port F0/2 is connected to a Web/TFTP server. Switch S1 port F0/1 is connected to S2 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S1 port F0/3 is connected to S3 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. Switch S2 port F0/11 is connected to PC1. Switch S3 port F0/11 is connected to PC4. <br><br>Web/TFTP Server:<br>V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.30<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.21<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.24<br><br>The link from S1 to S2 and the link from S1 to S3 are trunk links. The allowed V LAN trunks are 10 and 99. The native V LAN is 99.<br><br>Scenario:<br>Computer PC1 cannot connect to the internal web server, Web/TFTP.<br>What are some of the possible causes of the lack of connectivity?<br>A.	Native V LAN mismatch on the trunk between switches S1 and S2.<br>B.	Trunk mode mismatch between switches S1 and S2.<br>C.	Misconfigured set of allowed V LAN's on the trunk between switches S1 and S2.<br>D.	Misconfigured IP addresses associated with V LAN 10.<br>E.	A link is down along the path between PC1 and the Web/TFTP server.<br><br>Answer: A, B, C, D, E.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
