<transcript lastedited="06.13.08 03:06:56">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.4.3 Adapter Cards]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Single Diagram<br><br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br><br>The diagram gives a brief description of the following adapter cards.<br><br>Video Cards <br>A video card accepts information from the computer and translates it into a format that can be displayed on a monitor screen. A video card often contains large amounts of RAM and dedicated processor chips for manipulating video content. A video card is selected based on speed, resolution, and price. Graphic artists and gamers require faster speed and higher resolution cards. Video cards must match the capabilities of all connected monitors.<br><br>Sound Cards<br>A sound card accepts digital information from the system and converts it into signals that are transmitted to a speaker that outputs an audio signal. A high end sound card can produce an audio output that rivals some of the best stereo equipment available.<br><br>Network Interface Cards<br>A NIC enables a computer system to exchange information with other systems in a local network. The speed of the network and type of technology help determine what type of NIC is required. The most common networking technology is currently Ethernet.<br><br>Modems<br>A modem enables a computer system to participate in remote networks, such as the Internet. Traditionally, modems allowed the computer to connect to the public telephone network. Currently, modems are also used to connect to DSL and cable networks.<br><br>Controller Cards<br>While most motherboards have a number of interfaces allowing connection of devices such as printers, mice, and external modems, additional interfaces can be added in the form of an expansion card. There are also a number of adapter cards that act as controllers for specialized hardware devices, such as an external hard disk drive.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
