<textcomponents>
<component id="titletxt1">
<text><![CDATA[Video Cards]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt1">
<text><![CDATA[Video cards accept information from computers and translate it into a format that can be displayed on a monitor screen. Video cards often contain large amounts of RAM and dedicated processor chips for manipulating video content. The choice of video cards is made based on video speed, resolution and price. Graphic artists and gamers require faster speed and higher resolution cards. Video cards must match the capabilities of the connected monitors.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt2">
<text><![CDATA[Sound cards accept digital information from the system and convert them into a signal that is transmitted to a speaker that outputs an audio signal. High-end sound cards can produce an audio output that rivals some of the best stereo equipment available.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt2">
<text><![CDATA[Sound Cards]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt3">
<text><![CDATA[Network interface cards (NICs) enable a computer system to exchange information with other systems in a local network. The speed of the network and the type of technology help determine what NIC is required. The most common networking technology is currently Ethernet.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt3">
<text><![CDATA[Network Interface Cards]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt4">
<text><![CDATA[Modems enable computer systems to participate in remote networks such as the Internet.  Traditionally these devices allowed the computer to connect to the public telephone network.  Recently, modems that connect to DSL and cable networks are becoming more commonplace.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt4">
<text><![CDATA[Modems]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt5">
<text><![CDATA[While most motherboards have a number of interfaces allowing connection of devices such as printers, mice and external modems, additional interfaces can be added in the form of an expansion card. There are also a number of adapter cards that act as controllers for specialized hardware devices such as an external hard disk drive.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt5">
<text><![CDATA[Controller Cards]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each adapter card type for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>
