<transcript lastedited="03.30.09 10:03:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.6.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Match the wire colors listed to the numbers that represent the wiring pinouts for 568B patch cables.<br>Wire Colors:<br>Orange<br>Blue<br>Green<br>Brown<br><br>Wiring Pinouts:<br>7 and 8<br>1 and 2<br>3 and 6<br>4 and 5<br><br>2.Match each pin in group 1 to the correct pin in group 2 to properly create a RJ-45 connector for a router console cable.<br>Group 1 Pins:<br>Pin 1<br>Pin 2<br>Pin 3<br>Pin 4<br>Pin 5<br>Pin 6<br>Pin 7<br>Pin 8<br><br>Group 2 Pins:<br>Pin 1<br>Pin 2<br>Pin 3<br>Pin 4<br>Pin 5<br>Pin 6<br>Pin 7<br>Pin 8<br><br>3.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Diagram description:<br>A PC is connected to a switch. At the PC end of the cable is an RJ-45 to DB-9 adapter labeled Terminal. At the switch end of the cable is an RJ-45 to RJ-45 adapter. The cable is labeled Rollover Cable.<br><br>What kind of connection is represented in the diagram based on the description?<br>A.Console connection<br>B.Ethernet connection<br>C.ISDN connection<br>D.Leased line connection<br><br>4.What is the purpose of encoding?<br>A.Identification of start and stop bits in a frame.<br>B.Denotes the physical layer connectors of computers in relation to the way they connect to the network media.<br>C.Controls the way frames are placed on the media at the Data Link Layer.<br>D.Represents the data bits by using different voltages, light patterns, or electromagnetic waves as they are placed onto the physical media.<br><br>5.What best describes the purpose of the Physical Layer?<br>A.Ensures reliable transmission of data across a physical link.<br>B.Determines connectivity and path selection between two end systems.<br>C.Establishes physical addressing, network topology, and media access.<br>D.Defines the functional specifications for links between end systems and the electrical, optical, and radio signals.<br><br>6.Through what process does UTP cable help to avoid crosstalk?<br>A.Shielding of cable<br>B.Twisting of pairs<br>C.Grounding the endpoints<br>D.Cladding in cable<br><br>7.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Diagram description:<br>PC A, B, and C, a switch, and a router are shown in specific locations on a building floorplan. The switch is connected to a router. The vertical dimension of the building floorplan is 75 meters. The horizontal dimension of the building floorplan is 125 meters. <br><br>The 3 PC's are connected to the switch with cables of varying lengths. The switch and router are located in the northeast corner of the floorplan. PC A is located in the southeast corner of the floorplan. PC B is located in the middle north of the floorplan, and PC C is located in the southwest corner of the floorplan.<br><br>The PC's have the following IP addresses:<br>PC A IP address: 192.168.1.13/24<br>PC B IP address: 192.168.1.11/24<br>PC A IP address: 192.168.1.12/24<br><br>The network in the diagram is wired with Cat 5e cable, and PC C is unable to communicate with the network. What Physical Layer problem would cause PC C to not connect to the network?<br>A.Wrong operating system<br>B.Incorrect IP address<br>C.Cable length<br>D.Incorrect prefix<br>E.Switch type<br><br>8.What are the advantages of using fiber optic cable over copper cable? (Choose three.)<br>A.Copper is more expensive<br>B.Immunity to electromagnetic interference<br>C.Careful cable handling<br>D.Longer maximum cable length<br>E.Efficient electrical current transfer<br>F.Greater bandwidth potential<br><br>9.What cable type would be used to connect a computer directly to another computer?<br>A.Straight-through<br>B.Rollover<br>C.Crossover<br>D.Console<br><br>10.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Diagram description:<br>The diagram shows fiber media cable components including, from the outermost to the innermost layer, the jacket (typically PVC), strengthening material (Aramid yarn), buffer, cladding, and core.<br><br>What is the purpose of cladding in fiber optic cables?<br>A.Cable grounding<br>B.Noise cancellation<br>C.Prevents light loss<br>D.EMI protection<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
