<transcript lastedited="01.05.09 13:01:54">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.3.2 - IP Packets - Carrying Data End to End]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts how IP packets are routed.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>-	Hosts PC1 and PC2 are connected to switch S1 in LAN1 (network 192.168.2.0/24).<br>-	Switch S1 is connected to router R1.<br>-	Host PC3 is connected to switch S2 in LAN2 (network 192.168.3.0/24).<br>-	Switch S2 is connected to router R1.<br>-	Router R1 is connected to router R3. <br>-	Host PC4 is connected to switch S3 in LAN3 (network 192.168.4.0/24).<br>-	Switch S3 is connected to router R2.<br>-	Router R2 is connected to router R3. <br>-	Host PC5 is connected to switch S4 in LAN4 (network 192.168.5.0/24).<br>-	Switch S4 is connected to router R3. <br><br>Scenario: <br>PC2 with IP address 192.168.2.30/24 in LAN1 needs to send a packet to destination PC5 with IP address 192.168.5.6/24 in LAN4. The packet is routed as follows.<br><br>Step 1: PC2 (192.168.2.30/24) asks: "Is this packet destined for a device on this network? No. It is destined for device 192.168.5.6/24, a device on another network."<br><br>Step 2: PC2 sends the packet to the router R1 gateway interface with IP address 192.168.2.1/24.<br><br>Step 3: Router R1 asks: "Is this packet destined for a directly connected device? No. Forward the packet to the next router." The packet is forwarded to router R2. <br><br>Step 4: Router R2 asks: "Is this packet destined for a directly connected device? No. Forward the packet to the next router." The packet is forwarded to router R3.<br><br>Step 5: Router R3 asks: "Is this packet destined for a directly connected device? Yes. Forward the packet to this device." The packet is forwarded to PC5.<br><br>Step 6: The IP packet arrives at its destination. The IP header is removed, and the TCP segment is passed to Layer 4 on device PC5.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
