<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[Click the command buttons to view the network functions.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_reset">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Reset</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Wireshark</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button2">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Create Trunk Links</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button3">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Assign IP Addresses</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button4">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Configure EIGRP</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button5">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Configure Access Lists</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button6">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Display Video</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="button7">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Packet Tracer</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="routerIcon">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Router<BR>Output</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Wireshark is a free software protocol analyzer, or "packet sniffer" application used for network troubleshooting, analysis, software and protocol development, and education.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[A trunk is a communications channel between two points. It usually refers to large-bandwidth channels between switching centers that handle many simultaneous voice and data signals.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Network Technician]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[Router]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[VLAN Switch]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[IP Camera]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[VLAN 4]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[VLAN 2]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[VLAN 1]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[VLAN 3]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[Assign IP Addresses to all devices per the network design. Verify the configuration by using ping. Ping is a computer network tool used to test whether a particular host is reachable across an IP network. It works by sending ICMP "echo request" packets to the target host and listens for a response. ]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[Enhanced Interior Gateway Routing Protocol (EIGRP) is a Cisco proprietary routing protocol. EIGRP is an advanced distance-vector routing protocol with optimization to minimize both the routing instability incurred after topology changes, as well as the use of bandwidth and processing power in the router.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt13">
<text><![CDATA[An ACL is a list of permissions attached to an object. The list specifies who or what is allowed to access the object and what operations are allowed to be performed on the object.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt14">
<text><![CDATA[Display Video on PC across the network. Collect information on bandwidth usage, quality of video stream. Add traffic on the network using a traffic simulation program and observe the quality of the video.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt15">
<text><![CDATA[Packet Tracer is a stand-alone simulation environment created to design, configure, and troubleshoot CCNA-level networks. It is intended to teach beginning networking students how and why devices in a network work the way they do. A student is able to observe the behavior of data frames and packets as they traverse through routers, switches, and other devices.]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>