<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_openISP1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP A</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_openISP2">
<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP B</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_titleISP1">
<text><![CDATA[ISP A]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_descriptionISP1">
<text><![CDATA[$40 per month - no monthly contract<BR>10  email accounts<BR>Unlimited monthly access<BR>24/7 1-800 support<BR>VoIP services $30 per month<BR>DSL access<BR>1 GB Web hosting and FTP services]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_titleISP2">
<text><![CDATA[ISP B]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_descriptionISP2">
<text><![CDATA[$80 per month (2 year contract)<BR>30 email accounts - extra for a fee<BR>DSL and Cable access<BR>Toll-free customer support -24/7<BR>VoIP service - $30 per month<BR>2 GB Web hosting and FTP services<BR>Maintains customer equipment on-site<BR>Maintains on-line database and security services<BR>Video conferencing services for an additional $15 month]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario1Texta">
<text><![CDATA[1)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario1Textb">
<text><![CDATA[2)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario1Textc">
<text><![CDATA[3)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario1Text">
<text><![CDATA[A small business needs an ISP to host their informational website. Customers call the company to place their orders. In addition, the business needs VoIP services to reduce long-distance phone charges and FTP services to share and store files. Cost and flexibility are factors as the company plans to grow over the next few years and may require additional services that they do not need presently.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario2Text">
<text><![CDATA[A business with 50 employees would like to offer their employees on-site training with video conferencing. Employees must be able to access an internal company website for training materials and information. All 50 employees require email accounts.  ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_scenario3Text">
<text><![CDATA[A small business wants to create an e-commerce website that allows for online ordering of their products and services. The e-commerce website must be maintained on the ISP premise.  A database is needed to maintain customer records.  Technical support and security are major considerations.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Activity">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Activity</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Activity2">
<text><![CDATA[Match the requirements of an end-user to various ISPs.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Activity3">
<text><![CDATA[<b><B>After reading the scenario, place a check in the box that would be the most appropriate ISP for each user.</B></b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_columnISP1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP A</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_columnISP2">
<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP B</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_columnISP3">
<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP C</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_openCheck">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Check</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_openReset">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Reset</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_titleCorrect">
<text><![CDATA[Correct]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_correctText">
<text><![CDATA[You have correctly matched the business needs with the most appropriate ISP.<BR><BR>In scenario 1, the business would select ISP A due to flexibility of no contract and the low cost.  In scenario 2, the business would select ISP B due to the availability of video conferencing. In scenario 3, the business would select ISP B due to equipment co-location requirements and secure database services. Click Next to continue.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_titleIncorrect">
<text><![CDATA[Incorrect]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_incorrectText">
<text><![CDATA[Please review the ISP information and scenarios. Then try again.]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>