<transcript lastedited="01.26.09 11:01:56">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[11.6.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question 1. List the network services provided by the Cisco I O S.<br>Answer: <br>-	Basic routing and switching functions.<br>-	Reliable and secure access to networked resources.<br>-	Network scalability.<br><br>Question 2. Describe three methods of accessing a Cisco device for C L I management and configuration.<br>Answer: <br>-	Console<br>-	Telnet or SSH<br>-	AUX port<br><br>Question 3. Compare the functions and use of the running-configuration and startup-configuration files.<br>Answer: <br>-	The running configuration file is used during the current operation of the device.<br>-	The startup configuration file is stored in NV RAM and loaded to provide the device configuration when the device is started or restarted.<br><br>Question 4. Distinguish the features of the Cisco I O S user EXEC mode and privileged EXEC mode.<br>Answer: <br>User Executive Mode<br>The user executive mode, or user EXEC for short, has limited capabilities but is useful for some basic operations. The user EXEC mode is at the top of the modal hierarchical structure. This mode is the first entrance into the C L I of a Cisco I O S router.<br><br>The user EXEC mode allows only a limited number of basic monitoring commands. This is often referred to as view only mode. The user EXEC level does not allow the execution of any commands that might change the configuration of the device.<br><br>The user EXEC mode can be identified by the prompt ending with the > symbol.<br><br>Switch><br><br>Privileged EXEC Mode<br>The execution of configuration and management commands requires that the network administrator use the privileged EXEC mode or a specific mode further down the hierarchy. <br><br>The privileged EXEC mode can be identified by the prompt ending with the # symbol.<br><br>Switch#<br><br>Question 5. What is the difference between entering a question mark with no space and a question mark with a space directly after a partial command at the appropriate prompt? <br><br>For example, "cl question mark" and "clock question mark".<br>Answer: When using the question mark without a space, as with "cl question mark", all available commands that begin with the characters "cl" are listed.<br><br>When using the question mark with a space, as with "clock space question mark" all available subcommands that begin with clock are listed.<br><br>Question 6. What mode does a prompt of Router# indicate? How is this mode invoked?<br>Answer: The prompt indicates privileged EXEC mode. It is invoked from user EXEC mode by using the enable command.<br><br>Question 7. State the purpose and difference of the configuration commands service password-encryption and enable secret class.<br>Answer: The service password-encryption command applies weak encryption to all unencrypted passwords. This encryption does not apply to passwords because they are sent over media. The purpose of this command is to keep unauthorized individuals from viewing passwords in the configuration file.<br><br>The enable secret command provides security to privileged EXEC mode by encrypting the password.<br><br>Question 8. Why are delimiting characters required when setting a message of the day banner?<br>Answer: The banner m o t d command requires delimiters to identify the content of the banner message.<br><br>Question 9. What information should be included in a message of the day login banner on a Cisco device?<br>Answer: The exact content or wording of a banner depends on the local laws and corporate policies. Here are some examples of information to include in a banner:<br>-	Use of the device is specifically for authorized personnel.<br>-	Activity may be monitored.<br>-	Legal action will be pursued for any unauthorized use.<br><br>Question 10. Give three methods of saving or backing up the active configuration of a Cisco device.<br>Answer: Configuration files can be stored on a Trivial File Transfer Protocol or TFTP server, a CD, a USB memory stick, or a floppy disk stored in a safe place. A configuration file should also be included in the network documentation.<br><br>Question 11. What is the purpose of the no shutdown command when configuring interfaces on a router?<br>Answer: By default, interfaces are disabled. To enable an interface, enter the no shutdown command from interface configuration mode. <br><br>Question 12. What information should be included in an interface description on a Cisco router?<br>Answer: The host name helps to identify the device on a network, and the interface description indicates the purpose of the interface. A description of what an interface does or where it is connected should be part of the configuration of each interface. This description can be useful for <br>troubleshooting.<br><br>Question 13. List the steps to follow to verify that a host can successfully connect to and access a network.<br>Answer: Steps to verify host connection are the following:<br>-	Test the stack.<br>-	Test the NIC.<br>-	Test another local host.<br>-	Test the gateway.<br>-	Test access to a remote host.<br><br>Question 14. What is the purpose of capturing the results of network tests such as ping, trace, and arp?<br>Answer: They are used to create a record of network traffic for troubleshooting and network performance analysis.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
