<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 15:09:50">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.1.2 - OSPF Metrics and Convergence]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts R1 directly connected to three routers, R2, R3, and R4. All three routers have networks connected to them, labeled network A, B, and C respectively. The link cost between R1 and R2 is 20. The link cost between R1 and R3 is 5. The link cost between R1 and R4 is 20. The link cost between R3 and R4 is 10.<br><br>The SPF tree and path for each network from R1.<br>Destination Network A: Path from R1 to R2 has a cost of 20 (Least Cost Path).<br>Destination Network B: Path from R1 to R3 has a cost of 5 (Least Cost Path), Path from R1 to R4 to R3 has a cost of 25.<br>Destination Network C: Path from R1 to R3 to R4 has a cost of 15 (Least Cost Path), Path from R1 to R4 has a cost of 20.<br><br>The SPF tree and path for each network from R2.<br>Destination Network A.<br>It is directly connected, therefore, it has a cost of 0 (Least Cost Path).<br>Destination Network B.<br>Path from R2 to R1 to R3 has a cost of 25 (Least Cost Path), Path from R2 to R1 to R4 to R3 has a cost of 50.<br>Destination Network C.<br>Path from R2 to R1 to R3 to R4 has a cost of 35 (Least Cost Path), Path from R2 to R1 to R4 has a cost of 20.<br><br>The SPF tree and path for each network from R3.<br>Destination Network A.<br>Path from R3 to R1 to R2 has a cost of 25 (Least Cost Path), Path from R3 to R4 to R1 to R2 has a cost of 50.<br>Destination Network B.<br>It is directly connected, therefore, it has a cost of 0 (Least Cost Path).<br>Destination Network C.<br>Path from R3 to R4 has a cost of 10 (Least Cost Path), Path from R3 to R2 to R4 has a cost of 25.<br><br>The SPF tree and path for each network from R4.<br>Destination Network A.<br>Path from R4 to R3 to R1 to R2 has a cost of 35 (Least Cost Path), <br>Path from R4 to R1 to R2 has a cost of 40.<br>Destination Network B.<br>Path from R4 to R3 has a cost 10 (Least Cost Path), Path from R4 to R1 to R3 has a cost 25.<br>Destination Network C.<br>It is directly connected, therefore, it has a cost of 0 (Least Cost Path).<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
