<transcript lastedited="10.14.08 17:10:42">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.5.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Four Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br><br>Diagram 1, Image<br>The diagram depicts two networks with network and host identified.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br>Without an IP address a host cannot participate on the Internet. This chapter discussed the importance of IP addressing, its hierarchical structure, and the methods of obtaining an address for a networking device.<br><br>Each logical IP address is made up of two parts; the network ID and the unique host ID on that network.<br>An IP address is a series of 32 binary bits (ones and zeros) that are grouped into four 8-bit bytes, called octets.<br>The four octets are each converted into a decimal number, which is referred to as dotted-decimal notation.<br>The IP address and subnet mask work together to determine which portion of the IP address represents the network address and which portion represents the host address.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br>The diagram depicts IP address classes and address information.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br>IP addresses are classified in many different ways.<br><br>IP addresses are grouped into five classes. Classes A, B, and C are commercial. Class D is for multicasting, and Class E is experimental.<br>Each class of IP address has its own default subnet mask.<br>IP addresses are also classified as public or private. Public addresses are unique and are used on the Internet.<br>Private addresses can be used internally by hosts in any organization. <br>Private addresses must be translated to Internet routable addresses in order for hosts to communicate on the Internet.<br>Hosts can use IP addresses to communicate one-to-one (unicast), one-to-many (multicast), or one-to-all (broadcast).<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br>The diagram depicts DHCP address assignment sources. <br><br>Diagram 3 text<br>IP addresses can be assigned, either statically or dynamically.<br><br>If assigning addresses statically, the IP address, subnet mask, and the default gateway must all be configured manually.<br>Static addresses are typically required for servers that are accessed from the Internet.<br>DHCP is the preferred method of assigning IP addresses on large networks because it reduces the burden on network support staff.<br>The Integrated Services Router (ISR), or another multifunction device, acts as a DHCP client to receive its unique IP configuration from the ISP. It then acts as a DHCP server to assign IP addresses to internal hosts on the local network.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br>The diagram depicts an integrated router acting as a DHCP client and server.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br>Private IP addresses from inside an organization must be translated to a unique public IP address before the packet goes onto the Internet.<br><br>Routers provide a boundary that separates local networks from the Internet.<br>A hosts default gateway is the router interface connected to the local network that is used to communicate with destinations on other networks.<br>Many gateway routers translate private LAN IP addresses to Internet routable IP addresses using a process called Network Address Translation (NAT).<br>When more than one private IP address is translated to a single public IP address, the router keeps track of each source IP address and port number being translated, so return traffic is directed to the correct host.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
