<chapter type="" id="en1406000000">
<title><content-text>Teleworker Services</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1406000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406000100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm9522791329">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406000000/en1406000100/en1406000101/cm9522791329.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406000000/en1406000100/en1406000101/cm9522791329text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Teleworking is working away from a traditional workplace, usually from a home office. The reasons for choosing teleworking are varied and include everything from personal convenience to allowing injured or shut-in employees opportunities to continue working during periods of convalescence. </p> <p>Teleworking is a broad term referring to conducting work by connecting to a workplace from a remote location, with the assistance of telecommunications. Efficient teleworking is possible because of broadband Internet connections, virtual private networks (VPN), and more advanced technologies, including Voice over IP (VoIP) and videoconferencing. Teleworking can save money otherwise spent on travel, infrastructure, and facilities support. </p> <p>Modern enterprises employ people who cannot commute to work every day or for whom working out of a home office is more practical. These people, called teleworkers, must connect to the company network so that they can work from their home offices. </p> <p>This chapter explains how organizations can provide secure, fast, and reliable remote network connections for teleworkers.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1406010000">
<title><content-text>Business Requirements for Teleworker Services</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406010100">
<title><content-text>The Business Requirements for Teleworker Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2520318719">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010100/en1406010101/cm2520318719.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010100/en1406010101/cm2520318719text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>More and more companies are finding it beneficial to have teleworkers. With advances in broadband and wireless technologies, working away from the office no longer presents the challenges it did in the past. Workers can work remotely almost as if they were in the next cubicle or office. Organizations can cost-effectively distribute data, voice, video, and real-time applications extended over one common network connection, across their entire workforce no matter how remote and scattered they might be. </p> <p>The benefits of telecommuting extend well beyond the ability for businesses to make profits. Telecommuting affects the social structure of societies, and can have positive effects on the environment. </p> <p>For day-to-day business operations, it is beneficial to be able to maintain continuity in case weather, traffic congestion, natural disasters, or other unpredictable events affect workers from getting to the workplace. On a broader scale, the ability of businesses to provide increased service across time zones and international boundaries is greatly enhanced using teleworkers. Contracting and outsourcing solutions are easier to implement and manage.</p> <p>From a social perspective, teleworking options increase the employment opportunities for various groups, including parents with small children, the handicapped, and people living in remote areas. Teleworkers enjoy more quality family time, less travel-related stress, and in general provide their employers with increased productivity, satisfaction, and retention. In the age of climate change, teleworking is another way people can reduce their carbon footprint.</p> <p>When designing network architectures that support a teleworking solution, designers must balance organizational requirements for security, infrastructure management, scalability, and affordability against the practical needs of teleworkers for ease of use, connection speeds, and reliability of service. </p> <p>To allow businesses and teleworkers to function effectively, we must balance the selection of technologies and carefully design for telecommuting services. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406010200">
<title><content-text>The Teleworker Solution</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8691423219">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010200/en1406010201/cm8691423219.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010200/en1406010201/cm8691423219text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Organizations need secure, reliable, and cost-effective networks to connect corporate headquarters, branch offices, and suppliers. With the growing number of teleworkers, enterprises have an increasing need for secure, reliable, and cost-effective ways to connect to people working in small offices and home offices (SOHOs), and other remote locations, with resources on corporate sites.</p> <p>The figure illustrates the remote connection topologies that modern networks use to connect remote locations. In some cases, the remote locations only connect to the headquarters location, while in other cases, remote locations connect to multiple sites. The branch office in the figure connects to the headquarters and partner sites while the teleworker has a single connection to the headquarters. </p> <p><b>Click the Options button in the figure.</b></p> <p>The figure displays three remote connection technologies available to organizations for supporting teleworker services:</p> <p><ul><li> Traditional private WAN Layer 2 technologies, including Frame Relay, ATM, and leased lines, provide many remote connection solutions. The security of these connections depends on the service provider. </li><li> IPsec Virtual Private Networks (VPNs) offer flexible and scalable connectivity. </li><li> Site-to-site connections can provide a secure, fast, and reliable remote connection to teleworkers. This is the most common option for teleworkers, combined with remote access over broadband, to establish a secure VPN over the public Internet. (A less reliable means of connectivity using the Internet is a dialup connection.)</li></ul></p> <p>The term broadband refers to advanced communications systems capable of providing high-speed transmission of services, such as data, voice, and video, over the Internet and other networks. Transmission is provided by a wide range of technologies, including digital subscriber line (DSL) and <content-link target="{575F6060-320B-482B-9952-67EE6F6BCBC7}" type="glossary">fiber-optic cable</content-link>, coaxial cable, wireless technology, and satellite. The broadband service data transmission speeds typically exceed 200 <content-link target="{9ACFA05D-4D77-456D-9A52-2881940DF1F8}" type="glossary">kilobits per second</content-link> (kb/s), or 200,000 bits per second, in at least one direction: downstream (from the Internet to the user's computer) or upstream (from the user's computer to the Internet).</p> <p>This chapter describes how each of these technologies operates, and introduces some of the steps needed to ensure that teleworker connections are secure.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2037427411">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010200/en1406010202/cm2037427411.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406010000/en1406010200/en1406010202/cm2037427411text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To connect effectively to their organization's networks, teleworkers need two key sets of components: home office components and corporate components. The option of adding IP telephony components is becoming more common as providers extend broadband service to more areas. Soon, voice over IP (VoIP) and videoconferencing components will become expected parts of the teleworkers toolkit.</p> <p>As shown in the figure, telecommuting needs the following components:</p> <p><ul><li> Home Office Components - The required home office components are a laptop or desktop computer, broadband access (cable or DSL), and a VPN router or VPN client software installed on the computer. Additional components might include a wireless <content-link target="{81BB9F2F-8B1F-4532-B624-361AA9AF31F3}" type="glossary">access point</content-link>. When traveling, teleworkers need an Internet connection and a VPN client to connect to the corporate network over any available dialup, network, or broadband connection.</li><li> Corporate Components - Corporate components are VPN-capable routers, VPN concentrators, multifunction security appliances, authentication, and central management devices for resilient aggregation and termination of the VPN connections.</li></ul></p> <p>Typically, providing support for VoIP and videoconferencing requires upgrades to these components. Routers need Quality of Service (QoS) functionality. QoS refers to the capability of a network to provide better service to selected network traffic, as required by voice and video applications. An in-depth discussion of QoS is beyond the scope of this course. </p> <p>The figure shows an encrypted VPN tunnel connecting the teleworker to the corporate network. This is the heart of secure and reliable teleworker connections. A VPN is a private data network that uses the public telecommunication infrastructure. VPN security maintains privacy using a <content-link target="{AB340226-A8ED-4718-840A-C6D75E8EE978}" type="glossary">tunneling</content-link> protocol and security procedures. </p> <p>This course presents the IPsec (IP Security) protocol as the favored approach to building secure VPN tunnels. Unlike earlier security approaches that apply security at the Application layer of the Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model, IPsec works at the network or packet processing layer.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1406020000">
<title><content-text>Broadband Services</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406020100">
<title><content-text>Connecting Teleworkers to the WAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9470947506">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020100/en1406020101/cm9470947506.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020100/en1406020101/cm9470947506text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Teleworkers typically use diverse applications (for example, e-mail, web-based applications, mission-critical applications, real-time collaboration, voice, video, and videoconferencing) that require a high-bandwidth connection. The choice of access network technology and the need to ensure suitable bandwidth are the first considerations to address when connecting teleworkers.</p> <p>Residential cable, DSL and broadband wireless are three options that provide high bandwidth to teleworkers. The low bandwidth provided by a dialup modem connection is usually not sufficient, although it is useful for mobile access while traveling. A modem dialup connection should only be considered when other options are unavailable.</p> <p>Teleworkers require a connection to an ISP to access the Internet. ISPs offer various connection options. The main connection methods used by home and small business users are:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Dialup access</b> - An inexpensive option that uses any phone line and a modem. To connect to the ISP, a user calls the ISP access phone number. Dialup is the slowest connection option, and is typically used by mobile workers in areas where higher speed connection options are not available.</li><li> <b>DSL</b> - Typically more expensive than dialup, but provides a faster connection. DSL also uses telephone lines, but unlike dialup access, DSL provides a continuous connection to the Internet. DSL uses a special high-speed modem that separates the DSL signal from the telephone signal and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or LAN.</li><li> <b>Cable modem</b> - Offered by cable television service providers. The Internet signal is carried on the same coaxial cable that delivers cable television. A special cable modem separates the Internet signal from the other signals carried on the cable and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or LAN. </li><li> <b>Satellite</b> - Offered by satellite service providers. The computer connects through Ethernet to a satellite modem that transmits radio signals to the nearest point of presence (POP) within the satellite network.</li></ul></p> <p>In this section, you will learn how broadband services, such as DSL, cable, and broadband wireless, extend enterprise networks to enable teleworker access.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406020200">
<title><content-text>Cable</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2164973549">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020201/cm2164973549.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020201/cm2164973549text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Accessing the Internet through a cable network is a popular option used by teleworkers to access their enterprise network. The cable system uses a coaxial cable that carries <content-link target="{076410C5-D212-4ADE-B9A1-0786B8D8F24D}" type="glossary">radio frequency</content-link> (<content-link target="{44F00E8D-D919-40EC-87A6-260F29B7F8A0}" type="glossary">RF</content-link>) signals across the network. Coaxial cable is the primary medium used to build cable TV systems.</p> <p>Cable television first began in Pennsylvania in 1948. John Walson, the owner of an appliance store in a small mountain town, needed to solve poor over-the-air reception problems experienced by customers trying to receive TV signals from Philadelphia through the mountains. Walson erected an antenna on a utility pole on a local mountaintop that enabled him to demonstrate the televisions in his store with strong broadcasts coming from the three Philadelphia stations. He connected the antenna to his appliance store via a cable and modified signal boosters. He then connected several of his customers who were located along the cable path. This was the first community antenna television (<content-link target="{D81992F2-72A6-4336-BE14-8D8D5FB13132}" type="glossary">CATV</content-link>) system in the United States. </p> <p>Walson's company grew over the years, and he is recognized as the founder of the cable television industry. He was also the first cable operator to use microwave to import distant television stations, the first to use coaxial cable to improve picture quality, and the first to distribute pay television programming. </p> <p>Most cable operators use satellite dishes to gather TV signals. Early systems were one-way, with cascading amplifiers placed in series along the network to compensate for signal loss. These systems used taps to couple video signals from the main trunks to subscriber homes via <content-link target="{E95D255B-1A4E-4FEE-B5B4-50104189DBC6}" type="glossary">drop cables</content-link>. </p> <p>Modern cable systems provide two-way communication between subscribers and the cable operator. Cable operators now offer customers advanced telecommunications services, including high-speed Internet access, digital cable television, and residential telephone service. Cable operators typically deploy hybrid fiber-coaxial (HFC) networks to enable high-speed transmission of data to cable modems located in a SOHO. </p> <p>The figure illustrates the components of a typical modern cable system.</p> <p><b>Roll over each component in the figure </b>for a description of what it does.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6510357455">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020202/cm6510357455.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020202/cm6510357455text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The electromagnetic spectrum encompasses a broad range of frequencies. </p> <p><content-link target="{5DFD9C93-9F61-40DB-95CF-89A3E0BE9662}" type="glossary">Frequency</content-link> is the rate at which current (or voltage) cycles occur, computed as the number of "waves" per second. Wavelength is the speed of propagation of the electromagnetic signal divided by its frequency in <content-link target="{6E38C9FA-A781-4679-B71F-069C858E1363}" type="glossary">cycles per second</content-link>. </p> <p>Radio waves, generally called RF, constitute a portion of the electromagnetic spectrum between approximately 1 kilohertz (kHz) through 1 terahertz. When users tune a radio or TV set to find different radio stations or TV channels, they are tuning to different electromagnetic frequencies across that RF spectrum. The same principle applies to the cable system.</p> <p>The cable TV industry uses a portion of the RF electromagnetic spectrum. Within the cable, different frequencies carry TV channels and data. At the subscriber end, equipment such as TVs, VCRs, and high-definition TV set-top boxes tune to certain frequencies that allow the user to view the channel or, using a cable modem, to receive high-speed Internet access.</p> <p>A cable network is capable of transmitting signals on the cable in either direction at the same time. The following frequency scope is used:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Downstream</b> - The direction of an RF signal transmission (TV channels and data) from the source (headend) to the destination (subscribers). Transmission from source to destination is called the forward path. Downstream frequencies are in the range of 50 to 860 megahertz (MHz). </li><li> <b>Upstream</b> - The direction of the RF signal transmission from subscribers to the headend, or the return or reverse path. Upstream frequencies are in the range of 5 to 42 MHz.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5962940380">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020203/cm5962940380.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020203/cm5962940380text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Data-over-Cable Service Interface Specification (DOCSIS) is an international standard developed by CableLabs, a non-profit research and development consortium for cable-related technologies. CableLabs tests and certifies cable equipment vendor devices, such as cable modems and cable modem termination systems, and grants DOCSIS-certified or qualified status.</p> <p>DOCSIS defines the communications and operation support interface requirements for a data-over-cable system, and permits the addition of high-speed data transfer to an existing CATV system. Cable operators employ DOCSIS to provide Internet access over their existing hybrid fiber-coaxial (HFC) infrastructure. </p> <p> </p> <p>DOCSIS specifies the OSI Layer 1 and Layer 2 requirements:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Physical layer</b> - For data signals that the cable operator can use, DOCSIS specifies the channel widths (bandwidths of each channel) as 200 kHz, 400 kHz, 800 kHz, 1.6 MHz, 3.2 MHz, and 6.4 MHz. DOCSIS also specifies modulation techniques (the way to use the RF signal to convey digital data).</li><li> <b><content-link target="{5B128F17-505E-49E2-B801-7EB2297067B7}" type="glossary">MAC</content-link> layer</b> - Defines a deterministic <content-link target="{A3CE1583-9B6D-465F-813B-5A6009A7F183}" type="glossary">access method</content-link>, time-division multiple access (TDMA) or synchronous code division multiple access method (S-CDMA).</li></ul></p> <p>To understand the MAC layer requirements for DOCSIS, an explanation of how various communication technologies divide channel access is helpful. TDMA divides access by time. Frequency-division multiple access (FDMA) divides access by frequency. Code division multiple access (CDMA) employs spread-spectrum technology and a special coding scheme in which each transmitter is assigned a specific code. </p> <p>An analogy that illustrates these concepts starts with a room representing a channel. The room is full of people needing to speak to one another-in other words, needing channel access. One solution is for the people to take turns speaking (time division). Another is for each person to speak at different pitches (frequency division). In CDMA, they would speak different languages. People speaking the same language can understand each other, but not other people. In radio CDMA used by many North American cell phone networks, each group of users has a shared code. Many codes occupy the same channel, but only users associated with a particular code can understand each other. S-CDMA is a proprietary version of CDMA developed by Terayon Corporation for data transmission across coaxial cable networks. S-CDMA scatters digital data up and down a wide frequency band and allows multiple subscribers connected to the network to transmit and receive concurrently. S-CDMA is secure and extremely resistant to noise.</p> <p>Plans for frequency allocation bands differ between North American and European cable systems. Euro-DOCSIS is adapted for use in Europe. The main differences between DOCSIS and Euro-DOCSIS relate to channel bandwidths. TV technical standards vary across the world, which affects the way DOCSIS variants develop. International TV standards include NTSC in North American and parts of Japan; PAL in most of Europe, Asia, Africa, Australia, Brazil, and Argentina; and SECAM in France and some Eastern European countries. </p> <p>More information is available at these websites:</p> <p><ul><li> About DOCSIS: <content-link target="http://www.cablemodem.com/specifications" type="external">http://www.cablemodem.com/specifications</content-link> </li><li> About Euro-DOCSIS: <content-link target="http://www.euro-docsis.com" type="external">http://www.euro-docsis.com</content-link></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8210024441">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020204/cm8210024441.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020200/en1406020204/cm8210024441text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Delivering services over a cable network requires different radio frequencies. Downstream frequencies are in the 50 to 860 MHz range, and the upstream frequencies are in the 5 to 42 MHz range. </p> <p>Two types of equipment are required to send digital modem signals upstream and downstream on a cable system:</p> <p><ul><li> Cable modem termination system (CMTS) at the headend of the cable operator</li><li> Cable modem (CM) on the subscriber end</li></ul></p> <p><b>Roll over the components in the figure</b> and observe the role each plays.</p> <p>A headend CMTS communicates with CMs located in subscriber homes. The headend is actually a router with databases for providing Internet services to cable subscribers. The architecture is relatively simple, using a mixed optical-coaxial network in which <content-link target="{FC5E8550-E67D-4D06-B31E-BFB63E98AE9E}" type="glossary">optical fiber</content-link> replaces the lower bandwidth coaxial. </p> <p>A web of fiber trunk cables connects the headend to the nodes where optical-to-RF signal conversion takes place. The fiber carries the same broadband content for Internet connections, telephone service, and streaming video as the coaxial cable carries. Coaxial feeder cables originate from the node that carries RF signals to the subscribers. </p> <p>In a modern HFC network, typically 500 to 2,000 active data subscribers are connected to a cable network segment, all sharing the upstream and downstream bandwidth. The actual bandwidth for Internet service over a CATV line can be up to 27 Mb/s on the download path to the subscriber and about 2.5 Mb/s of bandwidth on the upload path. Based on the cable network architecture, cable operator provisioning practices, and traffic load, an individual subscriber can typically get an access speed of between 256 kb/s and 6 Mb/s.</p> <p>When high usage causes congestion, the cable operator can add additional bandwidth for data services by allocating an additional TV channel for high-speed data. This addition may effectively double the downstream bandwidth that is available to subscribers. Another option is to reduce the number of subscribers served by each network segment. To reduce the number of subscribers, the cable operator further subdivides the network by laying the fiber-optic connections closer and deeper into the neighborhoods. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406020300">
<title><content-text>DSL</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2414244009">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020301/cm2414244009.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020301/cm2414244009text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>DSL is a means of providing high-speed connections over installed copper wires. In this section, we look at DSL as one of the key teleworker solutions available.</p> <p>Several years ago, Bell Labs identified that a typical voice conversation over a local loop only required bandwidth of 300 Hz to 3 kHz. For many years, the telephone networks did not use the bandwidth above 3 kHz. Advances in technology allowed DSL to use the additional bandwidth from 3 kHz up to 1 MHz to deliver high-speed data services over ordinary copper lines. </p> <p>As an example, asymmetric DSL (ADSL) uses a frequency range from approximately 20 kHz to 1 MHz. Fortunately, only relatively small changes to existing telephone company infrastructure are required to deliver high-bandwidth data rates to subscribers. The figure shows a representation of bandwidth space allocation on a copper wire for ADSL. The blue area identifies the frequency range used by the voice-grade telephone service, which is often referred to as the <content-link target="{8704CCC1-9779-416D-824A-FEED3B0FBFD7}" type="glossary">plain old telephone service</content-link> (<content-link target="{BD84A2F1-6BD7-4698-9C7D-09767DBE9310}" type="glossary">POTS</content-link>). The other colored spaces represent the frequency space used by the upstream and downstream DSL signals.</p> <p>The two basic types of DSL technologies are asymmetric (ADSL) and symmetric (SDSL). All forms of DSL service are categorized as ADSL or SDSL, and there are several varieties of each type. ADSL provides higher downstream bandwidth to the user than upload bandwidth. SDSL provides the same capacity in both directions. </p> <p>The different varieties of DSL provide different bandwidths, some with capabilities exceeding those of a T1 or E1 leased line. The transfer rates are dependent on the actual length of the local loop, and the type and condition of its cabling. For satisfactory service, the loop must be less than 5.5 kilometers (3.5 miles).</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8263626696">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020302/cm8263626696.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020302/cm8263626696text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Service providers deploy DSL connections in the last step of a local telephone network, called the local loop or last mile. The connection is set up between a pair of modems on either end of a copper wire that extends between the customer premises equipment (CPE) and the DSL access multiplexer (DSLAM). A DSLAM is the device located at the central office (CO) of the provider and concentrates connections from multiple DSL subscribers. </p> <p><b>Click the DSL Connections button in the figure.</b></p> <p>The figure shows the key equipment needed to provide a DSL connection to a SOHO. The two key components are the DSL transceiver and the DSLAM:</p> <p><ul><li> <b><content-link target="{459CEACA-55BB-4528-840B-58D981C4348F}" type="glossary">Transceiver</content-link></b> - Connects the computer of the teleworker to the DSL. Usually the transceiver is a DSL modem connected to the computer using a USB or Ethernet cable. Newer DSL transceivers can be built into small routers with multiple 10/100 switch ports suitable for home office use. </li><li> <b>DSLAM</b> - Located at the CO of the carrier, the DSLAM combines individual DSL connections from users into one high-capacity link to an ISP, and thereby, to the Internet.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Click the DSL Router button and DSLAM in the figure.</b></p> <p>The advantage that DSL has over cable technology is that DSL is not a shared medium. Each user has a separate direct connection to the DSLAM. Adding users does not impede performance, unless the DSLAM Internet connection to the ISP, or the Internet, becomes saturated. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5916670104">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020303/cm5916670104.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020300/en1406020303/cm5916670104text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The major benefit of ADSL is the ability to provide data services along with POTS voice services. </p> <p>When the service provider puts analog voice and ADSL on the same wire, the provider splits the POTS channel from the ADSL modem using filters or splitters. This setup guarantees uninterrupted regular phone service even if ADSL fails. When filters or splitters are in place, the user can use the phone line and the ADSL connection simultaneously without adverse effects on either service.</p> <p>ADSL signals distort voice transmission and are split or filtered at the customer premises. There are two ways to separate ADSL from voice at the customer premises: using a microfilter or using a splitter.</p> <p>A microfilter is a passive low-pass filter with two ends. One end connects to the telephone, and the other end connects to the telephone wall jack. This solution eliminates the need for a technician to visit the premises and allows the user to use any jack in the house for voice or ADSL service.</p> <p>POTS splitters separate the DSL traffic from the POTS traffic. The POTS splitter is a passive device. In the event of a power failure, the voice traffic still travels to the voice switch in the CO of the carrier. Splitters are located at the CO and, in some deployments, at the customer premises. At the CO, the POTS splitter separates the voice traffic, destined for POTS connections, and the data traffic destined for the DSLAM.</p> <p>The figure shows the local loop terminating on the customer premises at the demarcation point. The actual device is the <content-link target="{9E88FB2C-6CC7-4C69-B013-F41FF2C22DDF}" type="glossary">network interface</content-link> device (NID). This point is usually where the phone line enters the customer premises. At this point, a splitter can be attached to the phone line. The splitter forks the phone line; one branch provides the original house telephone wiring for telephones, and the other branch connects to the ADSL modem. The splitter acts as a low-pass filter, allowing only the 0 to 4 kHz frequencies to pass to or from the telephone. Installing the POTS splitter at the NID usually means that a technician must go to the customer site. </p> <p>Because of this additional labor and technical support, most home installations today use microfilters, as shown in the figure. Using microfilters also has the advantage of providing wider connectivity through the residence. Since the POTS splitter separates the ADSL and voice signals at the NID, there is usually only one ADSL outlet available in the house.</p> <p><b>Click the Microfilter button in the figure.</b></p> <p>The figure shows a typical SOHO DSL layout using microfilters. In this solution, the user can install inline microfilters on each telephone, or install wall-mounted microfilters in place of regular telephone jacks. If you roll over the microfilters on the graphic, photos of Cisco products are shown.</p> <p><b>Click the Splitter button in the figure.</b></p> <p>If the service provider were to have installer a splitter, it would be placed between the NID and the inside telephone distribution system. One wire would go directly to the DSL modem, and the other would carry the DSL signal to the telephones. If you roll over the splitter box on the graphic, a typical wiring scheme will be revealed.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406020400">
<title><content-text>Broadband Wireless</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2012908866">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020401/cm2012908866.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020401/cm2012908866text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Broadband access by ADSL or cable provides teleworkers with faster connections than dialup, but until recently, SOHO PCs had to connect to a modem or a router over a Cat 5 (Ethernet) cable. Wireless networking, or Wi-Fi (wireless fidelity), has improved that situation, not only in the SOHO, but on enterprise campuses as well. </p> <p>Using 802.11 networking standards, data travels from place to place on radio waves. What makes 802.11 networking relatively easy to deploy is that it uses the unlicensed radio spectrum to send and receive data. Most radio and TV transmissions are government regulated and require a license to use. </p> <p>Beginning in 2007, computer manufacturers started building wireless network adapters into most laptop computers. As the price of chipsets for Wi-Fi continues to drop, it is becoming a very economical networking option for desktop computers as well. </p> <p>The benefits of Wi-Fi extend beyond not having to use or install wired network connections. Wireless networking provides mobility. Wireless connections provide increased flexibility and productivity to the teleworker.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3211848817">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020402/cm3211848817.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020402/cm3211848817text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Until recently, a significant limitation of wireless access has been the need to be within the local transmission range (typically less than 100 feet) of a wireless router or wireless access point that has a wired connection to the Internet. Once a worker left the office or home, wireless access was not readily available. </p> <p>However, with advances in technology, the reach of wireless connections has been extended. The concept of hotspots has increased access to wireless connections across the world. A hotspot is the area covered by one or more interconnected access points. Public gathering places, like coffee shops, parks, and libraries, have created Wi-Fi hotspots, hoping to increase business. By overlapping access points, hotspots can cover many square miles. </p> <p>New developments in broadband wireless technology are increasing wireless availability. These include:</p> <p><ul><li> Municipal Wi-Fi</li><li> WiMAX</li><li> Satellite Internet</li></ul></p> <p>Municipal governments have also joined the Wi-Fi revolution. Often working with service providers, cities are deploying municipal wireless networks. Some of these networks provide high-speed Internet access at no cost or for substantially less than the price of other broadband services. Other cities reserve their Wi-Fi networks for official use, providing police, fire fighters, and city workers remote access to the Internet and municipal networks. </p> <p><b>Click the Single Router button in the figure.</b></p> <p>The figure shows a typical home deployment using a single wireless router. This deployment uses the hub-and-spoke model. If the single wireless router fails, all connectivity is lost. Use your mouse to roll over the text box.</p> <p><b>Click the Mesh button in the figure.</b></p> <p>Most municipal wireless networks use a mesh topology rather than a hub-and-spoke model. A mesh is a series of access points (radio transmitters) as shown in the figure. Each access point is in range and can communicate with at least two other access points. The mesh blankets its area with radio signals. Signals travel from access point to access point through this cloud.</p> <p>A meshed network has several advantages over single router hotspots. Installation is easier and can be less expensive because there are fewer wires. Deployment over a large urban area is faster. From an operational point of view, it is more reliable. If a node fails, others in the mesh compensate for it. </p> <p><b>Click the WiMAX button in the figure.</b></p> <p>WiMAX (Worldwide Interoperability for Microwave Access) is telecommunications technology aimed at providing wireless data over long distances in a variety of ways, from point-to-point links to full mobile cellular type access. WiMAX operates at higher speeds, over greater distances, and for a greater number of users than Wi-Fi. Because of its higher speed (bandwidth) and falling component prices, it is predicted that WiMAX will soon supplant municipal mesh networks for wireless deployments.</p> <p>A WiMAX network consists of two main components:</p> <p><ul><li> A tower that is similar in concept to a cellular telephone tower. A single WiMAX tower can provide coverage to an area as large as 3,000 square miles, or almost 7,500 square kilometers.</li><li> A WiMAX receiver that is similar in size and shape to a PCMCIA card, or built into a laptop or other wireless device.</li></ul></p> <p>A WiMAX tower station connects directly to the Internet using a high-bandwidth connection (for example, a T3 line). A tower can also connect to other WiMAX towers using line-of-sight microwave links. WiMAX is thus able to provide coverage to rural areas out of reach of "last mile" cable and DSL technologies.</p> <p><b>Click the Satellite button in the figure.</b></p> <p>Satellite Internet services are used in locations where land-based Internet access is not available, or for temporary installations that are continually on the move. Internet access using satellites is available worldwide, including for vessels at sea, airplanes in flight, and vehicles moving on land.</p> <p>There are three ways to connect to the Internet using satellites: one-way multicast, one-way terrestrial return, and two-way.</p> <p><ul><li> One-way multicast satellite Internet systems are used for <content-link target="{729F8D32-FC85-45B2-975C-5C379DA99A8B}" type="glossary">IP multicast</content-link>-based data, audio, and video distribution. Even though most IP protocols require two-way communication, for Internet content, including web pages, one-way satellite-based Internet services can be "pushed" pages to local storage at end-user sites by satellite Internet. Full interactivity is not possible. </li><li> One-way terrestrial return satellite Internet systems use traditional dialup access to send outbound data through a modem and receive downloads from the satellite.</li><li> Two-way satellite Internet sends data from remote sites via satellite to a hub, which then sends the data to the Internet. The satellite dish at each location needs precise positioning to avoid interference with other satellites.</li></ul></p> <p>The figure illustrates a two-way satellite Internet system. Upload speeds are about one-tenth of the download speed, which is in the range of 500 kb/s. </p> <p>The key installation requirement is for the antenna to have a clear view toward the equator, where most orbiting satellites are stationed. Trees and heavy rains can affect reception of the signals. </p> <p>Two-way satellite Internet uses IP multicasting technology, which allows one satellite to serve up to 5,000 communication channels simultaneously. IP multicast sends data from one point to many points at the same time by sending data in a compressed format. Compression reduces the size of the data and the bandwidth.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3068746124">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020403/cm3068746124.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020403/cm3068746124text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Wireless networking complies with a range of standards that routers and receivers use to communicate with each other. The most common standards are included in the <content-link target="{291B6664-783D-49A7-B760-7F1B83CF07BB}" type="glossary">IEEE 802.11</content-link> wireless local area network (<content-link target="{61D57DB2-6926-4D96-9E79-A9FF1F2BBFD3}" type="glossary">WLAN</content-link>) standard, which addresses the 5 GHz and 2.4 GHz public (unlicensed) spectrum bands. </p> <p>The terms 802.11 and Wi-Fi appear interchangeably, but this is incorrect. Wi-Fi is an industry-driven interoperability certification based on a subset of 802.11. The Wi-Fi specification came about because market demand led the <content-link target="{69136B62-83B2-48BA-81F8-BAED53A8E9A0}" type="glossary">Wi-Fi Alliance</content-link> to begin certifying products before amendments to the 802.11 standard were complete. The 802.11 standard has since caught up with and passed Wi-Fi.</p> <p>From the point of view of teleworkers, the most popular access approaches to connectivity are those defined by the <content-link target="{590692FF-58EC-496D-99E5-2E119DEBE72F}" type="glossary">IEEE 802.11b</content-link> and <content-link target="{33B49950-F647-422C-9FA5-3D4885C483D4}" type="glossary">IEEE 802.11g</content-link> protocols. Security was originally intentionally weak in these protocols because of the restrictive export requirements of multiple governments. The latest standard, 802.11n, is a proposed amendment that builds on the previous 802.11 standards by adding multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO). </p> <p>The 802.16 (or WiMAX) standard allows transmissions up to 70 Mb/s, and has a range of up to 30 miles (50 km). It can operate in licensed or unlicensed bands of the spectrum from 2 to 6 GHz.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406020404">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm5919909628">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020404/cm5919909628/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1406000000/en1406020000/en1406020400/en1406020404/cm5919909628/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In this activity, you will demonstrate your ability to add broadband devices and connections to Packet Tracer. Although you cannot configure DSL and cable modems, you can simulate end-to-end connectivity to teleworker devices.</p> <p>Detailed instructions are provided within the activity as well as in the PDF link below.</p> <p><content-link target="E4_PTAct_6_2_5.pdf" type="internalfile">Activity Instructions (PDF)</content-link></p> <p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon for more details.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1406030000">
<title><content-text>VPN Technology</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406030100">
<title><content-text>VPNs and Their Benefits</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2926840035">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030100/en1406030101/cm2926840035.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030100/en1406030101/cm2926840035text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Internet is a worldwide, publicly accessible IP network. Because of its vast global proliferation, it has become an attractive way to interconnect remote sites. However, the fact that it is a public infrastructure poses security risks to enterprises and their internal networks. Fortunately, VPN technology enables organizations to create private networks over the public Internet infrastructure that maintain confidentiality and security. </p> <p>Organizations use VPNs to provide a virtual WAN infrastructure that connects branch offices, home offices, business partner sites, and remote telecommuters to all or portions of their corporate network. To remain private, the traffic is encrypted. Instead of using a dedicated Layer 2 connection, such as a leased line, a VPN uses virtual connections that are routed through the Internet.</p> <p>Earlier in this course, an analogy involving getting priority tickets for a stadium show was introduced. An extension to that analogy will help explain how a VPN works. Picture the stadium as a public place in the same way as the Internet is a public place. When the show is over, the public leaves through public aisles and doorways, jostling and bumping into each other along the way. Petty thefts are threats to be endured. </p> <p>Consider how the performers leave. Their entourage all link arms and form cordons through the mobs and protect the celebrities from all the jostling and pushing. In effect, these cordons form tunnels. The celebrities are whisked through tunnels into limousines that carry them cocooned to their destinations. This section describes how VPNs work in much the same way, bundling data and safely moving it across the Internet through protective tunnels. An understanding of VPN technology is essential to be able to implement secure teleworker services on enterprise networks.</p> <p><b>Analogy: Each LAN Is an IsLANd</b></p> <p> </p> <p>We will use another analogy to illustrate the VPN concept from a different point of view. Imagine that you live on an island in a huge ocean. There are thousands of other islands all around you, some very close and others farther away. The normal way to travel is to take a ferry from your island to whichever island you wish to visit. Traveling on a ferry means that you have almost no privacy. Anything you do can be seen by someone else.</p> <p>Assume that each island represents a private LAN, and the ocean is the Internet. When you travel by ferry, it is similar to when you connect to a web server or to another device through the Internet. You have no control over the wires and routers that make up the Internet, just like you have no control over the other people on the ferry. This leaves you susceptible to security issues if you try to connect between two private networks using a public resource.</p> <p>Your island decides to build a bridge to another island so that there is an easier, more secure and direct way for people to travel between the two. It is expensive to build and maintain the bridge, even though the island you are connecting with is very close. But the need for a reliable, secure path is so great that you do it anyway. Your island would like to connect to a second island that is much farther away, but you decide that it is too expensive.</p> <p>This situation is very much like having a leased line. The bridges (leased lines) are separate from the ocean (Internet), yet they are able to connect the islands (LANs). Many companies have chosen this route because of the need for security and reliability in connecting their remote offices. However, if the offices are very far apart, the cost can be prohibitively high-just like trying to build a bridge that spans a great distance.</p> <p>So how does VPN fit into this analogy? We could give each inhabitant of the islands their own small submarine with these properties:</p> <p><ul><li> Fast</li><li> Easy to take with you wherever you go</li><li> Able to hide you completely from any other boats or submarines</li><li> Dependable</li><li> Costs little to add additional submarines to your fleet once the first is purchased</li></ul></p> <p>Although they are traveling in the ocean along with other traffic, the inhabitants of our two islands could travel back and forth whenever they wanted to with privacy and security. That is essentially how a VPN works. Each remote member of your network can communicate in a secure and reliable manner using the Internet as the medium to connect to the private LAN. A VPN can grow to accommodate more users and different locations much easier than a leased line. In fact, scalability is a major advantage that VPNs have over typical leased lines. Unlike leased lines, where the cost increases in proportion to the distances involved, the geographic locations of each office matter little in the creation of a VPN.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5714130531">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030100/en1406030102/cm5714130531.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030100/en1406030102/cm5714130531text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Organizations using VPNs benefit from increased flexibility and productivity. Remote sites and teleworkers can connect securely to the corporate network from almost any place. Data on a VPN is encrypted and undecipherable to anyone not entitled to have it. VPNs bring remote hosts inside the firewall, giving them close to the same levels of access to network devices as if they were in a corporate office.</p> <p>The figure shows leased lines in red. The blue lines represent VPN-based connections. Consider these benefits when using VPNs:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Cost savings</b> - Organizations can use cost-effective, third-party Internet transport to connect remote offices and users to the main corporate site. This eliminates expensive dedicated WAN links and modem banks. By using broadband, VPNs reduce connectivity costs while increasing remote connection bandwidth.</li><li> <b>Security</b> - Advanced encryption and authentication protocols protect data from unauthorized access. </li><li> <b>Scalability</b> - VPNs use the Internet infrastructure within ISPs and carriers, making it easy for organizations to add new users. Organizations, big and small, are able to add large amounts of capacity without adding significant infrastructure.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030200">
<title><content-text>Types of VPNs</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8930009983">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030200/en1406030201/cm8930009983.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030200/en1406030201/cm8930009983text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Organizations use site-to-site VPNs to connect dispersed locations in the same way as a leased line or Frame Relay connection is used. Because most organizations now have Internet access, it makes sense to take advantage of the benefits of site-to-site VPNs. As illustrated in the figure, site-to-site VPNs also support company intranets and business partner extranets. </p> <p>In effect, a site-to-site VPN is an extension of classic WAN networking. Site-to-site VPNs connect entire networks to each other. For example, they can connect a branch office network to a company headquarters network. </p> <p>In a site-to-site VPN, hosts send and receive TCP/IP traffic through a VPN <content-link target="{FB725A1C-0CBD-42E3-AD35-B855760B8D04}" type="glossary">gateway</content-link>, which could be a router, PIX firewall appliance, or an Adaptive Security Appliance (ASA). The VPN gateway is responsible for encapsulating and encrypting outbound traffic for all of the traffic from a particular site and sending it through a VPN tunnel over the Internet to a peer VPN gateway at the target site. On receipt, the peer VPN gateway strips the headers, decrypts the content, and relays the packet toward the target host inside its private network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6813504493">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030200/en1406030202/cm6813504493.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030200/en1406030202/cm6813504493text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Mobile users and telecommuters use remote access VPNs extensively. In the past, corporations supported remote users using dialup networks. This usually involved a toll call and incurring long distance charges to access the corporation. </p> <p>Most teleworkers now have access to the Internet from their homes and can establish remote VPNs using broadband connections. Similarly, a mobile worker can make a local call to a local ISP to access the corporation through the Internet. In effect, this marks an evolutionary advance in dialup networks. Remote access VPNs can support the needs of telecommuters, mobile users, as well as extranet consumer-to-business. </p> <p>In a remote-access VPN, each host typically has VPN client software. Whenever the host tries to send any traffic, the VPN client software encapsulates and encrypts that traffic before sending it over the Internet to the VPN gateway at the edge of the target network. On receipt, the VPN gateway handles the data in the same way as it would handle data from a site-to-site VPN.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030300">
<title><content-text>VPN Components</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8985437344">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030300/en1406030301/cm8985437344.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030300/en1406030301/cm8985437344text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A VPN creates a private network over a public network infrastructure while maintaining confidentiality and security. VPNs use cryptographic tunneling protocols to provide protection against packet sniffing, sender authentication, and message integrity. </p>  <p>The figure illustrates a typical VPN topology. Components required to establish this VPN include:</p> <p><ul><li> An existing network with servers and workstations</li><li> A connection to the Internet</li><li> VPN gateways, such as routers, firewalls, VPN concentrators, and ASAs, that act as endpoints to establish, manage, and control VPN connections</li><li> Appropriate software to create and manage VPN tunnels</li></ul></p> <p>The key to VPN effectiveness is security. VPNs secure data by encapsulating or encrypting the data. Most VPNs can do both. </p> <p><ul><li> Encapsulation is also referred to as tunneling, because encapsulation transmits data transparently from network to network through a shared network infrastructure.</li><li> Encryption codes data into a different format using a secret key. Decryption decodes encrypted data into the original unencrypted format.</li></ul></p> <p>Encapsulation and encryption are discussed in more detail later in this course.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030400">
<title><content-text>Characteristics of Secure VPNs</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6942124176">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030400/en1406030401/cm6942124176.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030400/en1406030401/cm6942124176text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>VPNs use advanced encryption techniques and tunneling to permit organizations to establish secure, end-to-end, private network connections over the Internet.</p> <p>The foundation of a secure VPN is data confidentiality, data integrity, and authentication:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Data confidentiality</b> - A common security concern is protecting data from eavesdroppers. As a design feature, data confidentiality aims at protecting the contents of messages from interception by unauthenticated or unauthorized sources. VPNs achieve confidentiality using mechanisms of encapsulation and encryption. </li><li> <b>Data integrity</b> - Receivers have no control over the path the data has traveled and therefore do not know if the data has been seen or handled while it journeyed across the Internet. There is always the possibility that the data has been modified. Data integrity guarantees that no tampering or alterations occur to data while it travels between the source and destination. VPNs typically use hashes to ensure data integrity. A hash is like a checksum or a seal that guarantees that no one has read the content, but it is more robust. Hashes are explained in the next topic.</li><li> <b>Authentication</b> - Authentication ensures that a message comes from an authentic source and goes to an authentic destination. User identification gives a user confidence that the party with whom the user establishes communications is who the user thinks the party is. VPNs can use passwords, digital certificates, smart cards, and biometrics to establish the identity of parties at the other end of a network.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030500">
<title><content-text>VPN Tunneling</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2636476154">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030500/en1406030501/cm2636476154.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030500/en1406030501/cm2636476154text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Incorporating appropriate data confidentiality capabilities into a VPN ensures that only the intended sources and destinations are capable of interpreting the original message contents.</p> <p>Tunneling allows the use of public networks like the Internet to carry data for users as though the users had access to a private network. Tunneling encapsulates an entire packet within another packet and sends the new, composite packet over a network. This figure lists the three classes of protocols that tunneling uses.</p> <p>To illustrate the concept of tunneling and the classes of tunneling protocols, consider an example of sending a holiday card through traditional mail. The holiday card has a message inside. The card is the passenger protocol. The sender puts the card inside an envelope (encapsulating protocol) with proper addressing applied. The sender then drops the envelope into a mailbox for delivery. The postal system (carrier protocol) picks up and delivers the envelope to the mailbox of the recipient. The two endpoints in the carrier system are the "tunnel interfaces." The recipient removes the holiday card (extracts the passenger protocol) and reads the message. </p> <p><b>Click the Encapsulation button in the figure </b>to view an illustration of the encapsulation process.</p> <p>This figure illustrates an e-mail message traveling through the Internet over a VPN connection. PPP carries the message to the VPN device, where the message is encapsulated within a Generic Route Encapsulation (<content-link target="{CE7C6F74-D2A7-421B-A8CA-3930C0437EE2}" type="glossary">GRE</content-link>) packet. GRE is a tunneling protocol developed by Cisco Systems that can encapsulate a wide variety of protocol packet types inside IP tunnels, creating a virtual point-to-point link to Cisco routers at remote points over an IP internetwork. In the figure, the outer packet source and destination addressing is assigned to "tunnel interfaces" and is made routable across the network. Once a composite packet reaches the destination tunnel interface, the inside packet is extracted.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030600">
<title><content-text>VPN Data Integrity</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7025817164">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030601/cm7025817164.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030601/cm7025817164text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If plain text data is transported over the public Internet, it can be intercepted and read. To keep the data private, it needs to be encrypted. VPN encryption encrypts the data and renders it unreadable to unauthorized receivers.</p> <p>For encryption to work, both the sender and the receiver must know the rules used to transform the original message into its coded form. VPN encryption rules include an algorithm and a key. An algorithm is a mathematical function that combines a message, text, digits, or all three with a key. The output is an unreadable cipher string. Decryption is extremely difficult or impossible without the correct key.</p> <p>In the example, Gail wants to send a financial document to Jeremy across the Internet. Gail and Jeremy have previously agreed on a secret shared key. At Gail's end, the VPN client software combines the document with the secret shared key and passes it through an encryption algorithm. The output is undecipherable cipher text. The cipher text is then sent through a VPN tunnel over the Internet. At the other end, the message is recombined with the same shared secret key and processed by the same encryption algorithm. The output is the original financial document, which is now readable to Jeremy.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030602">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4235490217">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030602/cm4235490217.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030602/cm4235490217text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The degree of security provided by any encryption algorithm depends on the length of the key. For any given key length, the time that it takes to process all of the possibilities to decrypt cipher text is a function of the computing power of the computer. Therefore, the shorter the key, the easier it is to break, but at the same time, the easier it is to pass the message.</p> <p>Some of the more common encryption algorithms and the length of keys they use are as follows:</p> <p><ul><li> <b><content-link target="{3E4652B3-69AD-44AE-8E5C-7DF155AEB530}" type="glossary">Data Encryption Standard</content-link> (DES) algorithm</b> - Developed by IBM, DES uses a 56-bit key, ensuring high-performance encryption. DES is a symmetric key cryptosystem. Symmetric and asymmetric keys are explained below.</li><li> <b>Triple DES (3DES) algorithm</b> - A newer variant of DES that encrypts with one key, decrypts with another different key, and then encrypts one final time with another key. 3DES provides significantly more strength to the encryption process.</li><li> <b>Advanced Encryption Standard (<content-link target="{E65ECB42-A48C-47BA-9400-D0D729FAC7A1}" type="glossary">AES</content-link>)</b> - The National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) adopted AES to replace the existing DES encryption in cryptographic devices. AES provides stronger security than DES and is computationally more efficient than 3DES. AES offers three different key lengths: 128, 192, and 256-bit keys.</li><li> <b>Rivest, Shamir, and Adleman (RSA)</b> - An asymmetrical key cryptosystem. The keys use a bit length of 512, 768, 1024, or larger.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Symmetric Encryption</b></p> <p>Encryption algorithms such as DES and 3DES require a shared secret key to perform encryption and decryption. Each of the two computers must know the key to decode the information. With symmetric key encryption, also called secret key encryption, each computer encrypts the information before sending it over the network to the other computer. Symmetric key encryption requires knowledge of which computers will be talking to each other so that the same key can be configured on each computer. </p> <p>For example, a sender creates a coded message where each letter is substituted with the letter that is two letters down in the alphabet; "A" becomes "C," and "B" becomes "D", and so on. In this case, the word SECRET becomes UGETGV. The sender has already told the recipient that the secret key is "shift by 2." When the recipient receives the message UGETGV, the recipient computer decodes the message by shifting back two letters and calculating SECRET. Anyone else who sees the message sees only the encrypted message, which looks like nonsense unless the person knows the secret key. </p> <p>The question is, how do the encrypting and decrypting devices both have the shared secret key? You could use e-mail, courier, or overnight express to send the shared secret keys to the administrators of the devices. Another easier and more secure method is asymmetric encryption.</p> <p><b>Asymmetric Encryption</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Asymmetric encryption uses different keys for encryption and decryption. Knowing one of the keys does not allow a hacker to deduce the second key and decode the information. One key encrypts the message, while a second key decrypts the message. It is not possible to encrypt and decrypt with the same key. </p> <p>Public key encryption is a variant of asymmetric encryption that uses a combination of a private key and a public key. The recipient gives a public key to any sender with whom the recipient wants to communicate. The sender uses a private key combined with the recipient's public key to encrypt the message. Also, the sender must share their public key with the recipient. To decrypt a message, the recipient will use the public key of the sender with their own private key.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030603">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6210349465">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030603/cm6210349465.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030600/en1406030603/cm6210349465text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Hashes contribute to data integrity and authentication by ensuring that unauthorized persons do not tamper with transmitted messages. A hash, also called a message digest, is a number generated from a string of text. The hash is smaller than the text itself. It is generated using a formula in such a way that it is extremely unlikely that some other text will produce the same hash value. </p> <p>The original sender generates a hash of the message and sends it with the message itself. The recipient decrypts the message and the hash, produces another hash from the received message, and compares the two hashes. If they are the same, the recipient can be reasonably sure the integrity of the message has not been affected.</p> <p>In the figure, someone is trying to send Jeremy a check for US$100. At the remote end, Alex Jones (likely a criminal) is trying to cash the check for $1,000. As the check progressed through the Internet, it was altered. Both the recipient and dollar amounts were changed. In this case, if a data integrity algorithm was used, the hashes would not match, and the transaction would no longer be valid.</p> <p>VPN data is transported over the public Internet. As shown, there is potential for this data to be intercepted and modified. To guard against this threat, hosts can add a hash to the message. If the transmitted hash matches the received hash, the integrity of the message has been preserved. However, if there is no match, the message was altered.</p> <p>VPNs use a message authentication code to verify the integrity and the authenticity of a message, without using any additional mechanisms. A keyed hashed message authentication code (HMAC) is a data integrity algorithm that guarantees the integrity of the message.</p> <p>A HMAC has two parameters: a message input and a secret key known only to the message originator and intended receivers. The message sender uses a HMAC function to produce a value (the message authentication code), formed by condensing the secret key and the message input. The message authentication code is sent along with the message. The receiver computes the message authentication code on the received message using the same key and HMAC function as the sender used, and compares the result computed with the received message authentication code. If the two values match, the message has been correctly received and the receiver is assured that the sender is a member of the community of users that share the key. The cryptographic strength of the HMAC depends upon the cryptographic strength of the underlying hash function, on the size and quality of the key, and the size of the hash output length in bits.</p> <p>There are two common HMAC algorithms:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Message Digest 5 (MD5) </b>- Uses a 128-bit shared secret key. The variable length message and 128-bit shared secret key are combined and run through the HMAC-MD5 hash algorithm. The output is a 128-bit hash. The hash is appended to the original message and forwarded to the remote end.</li><li> <b>Secure Hash Algorithm 1 (SHA-1)</b> - Uses a 160-bit secret key. The variable length message and the 160-bit shared secret key are combined and run through the HMAC-SHA-1 hash algorithm. The output is a 160-bit hash. The hash is appended to the original message and forwarded to the remote end.</li></ul></p> <p> </p> <p><b>Click the VPN Authentication button in the figure.</b></p> <p>When conducting business long distance, it is necessary to know who is at the other end of the phone, e-mail, or fax. The same is true of VPN networks. The device on the other end of the VPN tunnel must be authenticated before the communication path is considered secure. There are two peer authentication methods:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Pre-shared key (PSK)</b> - A secret key that is shared between the two parties using a secure channel before it needs to be used. PSKs use symmetric key cryptographic algorithms. A PSK is entered into each peer manually and is used to authenticate the peer. At each end, the PSK is combined with other information to form the authentication key.</li><li> <b>RSA signature</b> - Uses the exchange of digital certificates to authenticate the peers. The local device derives a hash and encrypts it with its private key. The encrypted hash (digital signature) is attached to the message and forwarded to the remote end. At the remote end, the encrypted hash is decrypted using the public key of the local end. If the decrypted hash matches the recomputed hash, the signature is genuine.</li></ul></p> <p>Take a look at an <content-link target="http://www.securecottage.com/demo/rsa2.html" type="external">RSA demonstration</content-link> for an example of RSA encryption.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1406030700">
<title><content-text>IPsec Security Protocols</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406030701">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1281471108">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030701/cm1281471108.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030701/cm1281471108text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>IPsec is protocol suite for securing IP communications which provides encryption, integrity, and authentication. IPsec spells out the messaging necessary to secure VPN communications, but relies on existing algorithms. </p> <p>There are two main IPsec framework protocols.</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Authentication Header (AH)</b> - Use when confidentiality is not required or permitted. AH provides data authentication and integrity for IP packets passed between two systems. It verifies that any message passed from R1 to R2 has not been modified during transit. It also verifies that the origin of the data was either R1 or R2. AH does not provide data confidentiality (encryption) of packets. Used alone, the AH protocol provides weak protection. Consequently, it is used with the ESP protocol to provide data encryption and tamper-aware security features.</li><li> <b>Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP)</b> - Provides confidentiality and authentication by encrypting the IP packet. IP packet encryption conceals the data and the identities of the source and destination. ESP authenticates the inner IP packet and ESP header. Authentication provides data origin authentication and data integrity. Although both encryption and authentication are optional in ESP, at a minimum, one of them must be selected.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Click the IPsec Framework button in the figure.</b></p> <p>IPsec relies on existing algorithms to implement encryption, authentication, and key exchange. Some of the standard algorithms that IPsec uses are as follows:</p> <p><ul><li> DES - Encrypts and decrypts packet data.</li><li> 3DES - Provides significant encryption strength over 56-bit DES.</li><li> AES - Provides stronger encryption, depending on the key length used, and faster throughput.</li><li> MD5 - Authenticates packet data, using a 128-bit shared secret key.</li><li> SHA-1 - Authenticates packet data, using a 160-bit shared secret key.</li><li> DH - Allows two parties to establish a shared secret key used by encryption and hash algorithms, for example, DES and MD5, over an insecure communications channel.</li></ul></p> <p>The figure shows how IPsec is configured. IPsec provides the framework, and the administrator chooses the algorithms used to implement the security services within that framework. There are four IPsec framework squares to be filled. </p> <p><ul><li> When configuring an IPsec gateway to provide security services, first choose an IPsec protocol. The choices are ESP or ESP with AH. </li><li> The second square is an encryption algorithm if IPsec is implemented with ESP. Choose the encryption algorithm that is appropriate for the desired level of security: DES, 3DES, or AES. </li><li> The third square is authentication. Choose an authentication algorithm to provide data integrity: MD5 or SHA. </li><li> The last square is the Diffie-Hellman (DH) algorithm group. Which establishes the sharing of key information between peers. Choose which group to use, DH1 or DH2.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1406030702">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm5622236968">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030702/cm5622236968.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030702/cm5622236968text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Activity: VPN Technology</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1406030703">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm1244091972">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030703/cm1244091972.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406030000/en1406030700/en1406030703/cm1244091972text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>actvity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1406040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406040100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm3362359496">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040101/cm3362359496.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040101/cm3362359496text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In this chapter, you learned of the growing importance of teleworkers. You can describe an organization's requirements for providing teleworker services in terms of what the teleworker needs and what the organization needs to provide: reliable, cost-effective connectivity. Among the favored ways to connect teleworkers, you can describe how to use broadband services including DSL, cable, and wireless. Further, you know how VPN technology can be used to provide secure teleworker services in organizations, including the importance, benefits, role, and impact of VPN technology, and the types of access, components, tunneling, and encryption.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1406040102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6196155544">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040102/cm6196155544.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040102/cm6196155544text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1406040103">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm4773849930">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040103/cm4773849930/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1406000000/en1406040000/en1406040100/en1406040103/cm4773849930/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>This activity requires you to configure a <content-link target="{6E89A6DC-697D-41AA-B471-A2A0D10C2631}" type="glossary">default route</content-link> as well as <content-link target="{0A49B739-6A1E-405D-BF5F-8EFF7DC10541}" type="glossary">dynamic routing</content-link> using RIP version 2. You will also add broadband devices to the network. Finally, you will set up ACLs on two routers to control network traffic.</p> <p>Detailed instructions are provided within the activity as well as in the PDF link below.</p> <p><content-link target="E4_PTAct_6_4_1.pdf" type="internalfile">Activity Instructions (PDF)</content-link></p> <p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon for more details.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1406050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1406050100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1406050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm1636015362">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1406000000/en1406050000/en1406050100/en1406050101/cm1636015362/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1406000000/en1406050000/en1406050100/en1406050101/cm1636015362/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Chapter Quiz</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
