<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 10:09:34">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.3.1 - Router Hardware]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts four boxes, each housing a different network topology configuration. The four boxes are labeled Broadcast Containment, Security, Locations, and Logical Grouping. A brief description of each is given.<br><br>Broadcast Containment<br>Routers in the Distribution Layer limit broadcasts to the local network where they need to be heard. Although broadcasts are necessary, too many hosts connected on the same local network generate excessive broadcast traffic and slow down the network.<br><br>The Broadcast Containment box in the diagram displays one distribution router connected to two switches with four computers directly connected to each switch.<br><br>Security<br>Routers in the Distribution Layer separate and protect certain groups of computers where confidential information resides. Routers also hide the addresses of internal computers from the outside world to help prevent attacks, and control who gets into or out of the local network<br><br>The Security box in the diagram displays a distribution router and two directly connected switches. Four computers are connected per switch.  <br><br>Locations<br>Routers in the Distribution Layer can interconnect local networks at various locations of an organization, some of which maybe geographically separated.<br><br>The Location box in the diagram displays two sites labeled A and B, each housing a small corporate network. The routers in both these sites have been linked by a virtual link to indicate communication between them.  <br><br>Logical Grouping<br>Routers in the Distribution Layer logically group users, such as departments within a company, who have common needs or require access to the same resources.<br><br>The Logical Grouping box in the diagram displays two logical blocks, each having a dedicated network. The individual networks have been labeled Accounting and Engineering. Each are connected to the same distribution router. This router is directly connected to the two switches, Accounting and Engineering. Each switch is directly connected to four computers.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
