<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[1]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[2]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[3]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[4]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[5]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[Click the buttons to follow the steps used to register on Cisco.com.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[Step 1: List a business goal that must be met by the new design:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Provide better atmosphere and safety for people attending events.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt09OLD">
<text><![CDATA[Reduce costs by consolidating the separate voice, video and data networks.<br><br>Provide better customer service by improving the access to the web site for viewing of schedules, purchasing and printing of tickets, and purchasing of merchandise.<br><br>Support the growth of the stadium company as it expands and adds new types of entertainment, new partners and vendors.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[Step 2. Determine what changes or additions are necessary for the business to meet its goal:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[1. Provide 24 hr. access to the cameras and stored video, both through the local network and over the Internet.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[2. Support an automated ticket scanning process to speed customer entry into the stadium.<br>3. Provide additional wireless coverage to meet customer demands.<br>4. Improve and expand the number of vendors and services offered within the stadium complex.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt13">
<text><![CDATA[Step 3. Decide what the technical requirements are to meet each network goal:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_test1">
<text><![CDATA[1. Provide 24 hr. access to the cameras and stored video, both through the local network and over the Internet.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt14">
<text><![CDATA[<LI>Connect the security monitoring network to the LAN.</LI>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt15">
<text><![CDATA[<LI>Provide restricted access to the camera devices and video storage server.</LI><LI>Provide web access to the cameras and stored video.</LI><LI>Ensure availability of the security monitoring network.</LI>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt16">
<text><![CDATA[Step 4. Determine the design implications of each technical requirement:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt17">
<text><![CDATA[Connect the security monitoring network to the LAN.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt18">
<text><![CDATA[<LI>Decide where in the LAN to connect the security monitoring network (Access Layer? Distribution Layer? Core Layer?)</LI><LI>Decide on necesssary  equipment capabilites - what bandwidth is necessary? How many connections are required? Is it a routed or switched connection?</LI>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt19">
<text><![CDATA[Step 5. Decide which design elements must be present in the final design:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt20">
<text><![CDATA[<LI>A routed connection to the Core Layer provides access to the video from both the local LAN and the Internet.<LI></LI>The firewall features on the router enable configuration of access restrictions, to ensure only authorized stations view the video.</LI>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[Click the numbered buttons to view how one of the business goals for the stadium network is analyzed.]]></text>
</component>



</textcomponents>