<transcript lastedited="10.01.08 10:10:57">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.6.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 4 Quiz: Addressing in an Enterprise Network<br><br>1.What is the best route summarization for the following list of networks?<br>Networks<br>209.48.200.0<br>209.48.201.0<br>209.48.202.0<br>209.48.203.0<br><br>A.209.48.200.0 /20<br>B.209.48.200.0 /22<br>C.209.48.201.0 /20<br>D.209.48.201.0 /21<br><br>2.Given a host with the IP address 172.32.65.13 and a default subnet mask, to which network does the host belong?<br>A.172.32.65.0<br>B.172.32.65.32<br>C.172.32.0.0<br>D.172.32.32.0<br><br>3.A Class C network address has been subnetted into eight subnetworks.  Using VLSM, the last subnet will be divided into eight smaller subnetworks.  What bit mask must be used to create eight smaller subnetworks, each having two usable host addresses?<br>A./26<br>B./27<br>C./28<br>D./29<br>E./30<br>F./31<br><br>4.Which address is a valid subnet if a 26 bit mask is used for subnetting?<br>A.172.16.43.16<br>B.172.16.128.32<br>C.172.16.243.64<br>D.172.16.157.96<br>E.172.16.47.224<br>F.172.16.192.252<br><br>5.A network technician is trying to determine the correct IP address configuration for Host A.  What is a valid configuration for Host A?  To answer this question refer to the network topology described below.<br><br>Network Topology<br>The network consists of two routers, named Router 1 and Router 2, and one switch, named Switch.  Router 1 connects to Router 2 via a serial link through Router 1's IP: 192.168.1.1 /24 and Router 2's IP: 192.168.1.2 /24.  Router 2 connects to the ISP via a serial link using Router 2's IP 10.1.1.5 /30.  Router 1 connects to Switch through Router 1's IP 192.168.100.17/28, and Switch's IP 192.168.100.18 /28.  Host A is connected to Switch.<br><br>A.IP address: 192.168.100.19; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.248; Default Gateway: 192.16.1.2<br>B.IP address: 192.168.100.20; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.240; Default Gateway: 192.168.100.17<br>C.IP address: 192.168.100.21; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.248; Default Gateway: 192.16.100.18<br>D.IP address: 192.168.100.22; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.240; Default Gateway: 10.1.1.5<br>E.IP address: 192.168.100.30; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.240; Default Gateway: 192.168.1.1<br>F.IP address: 192.168.100.31; Subnet Mask: 255.255.255.240; Default Gateway: 192.168.100.18<br><br>6.What is true regarding the differences between NAT and PAT?<br>A.PAT uses the word overload at the end of the access-list statement to share a single registered address.<br>B.Static NAT allows an unregistered address to map to multiple registered addresses.<br>C.Dynamic NAT allows hosts to receive the same global address each time external access is required.<br>D.PAT uses unique source port numbers to distinguish between translations.<br><br>7.Determine which characteristics correspond to the associated NAT techniques.  There will be two characteristics per NAT technique.<br>Characteristics<br>provides one-to-one fixed mappings of local and global addresses<br>assigns the translated addresses of IP hosts from a pool of public addresses<br>can map multiple addresses to a single address of the external interface<br>assigns unique source port numbers of an inside global address on a session-by-session basis<br>allows external hosts to establish sessions with an internal host<br>defines translations on a host-to-host basis<br><br>NAT Techniques<br>Dynamic NAT<br>NAT with Overload<br>Static NAT<br><br>8.Which address is an inside global address?  To answer this question refer to the network topology described below.<br>Network Topology<br>The network consists of two routers named RTR1 and RTR2, and two switches.<br>RTR1 is connected to RTR2 via a serial link through RTR1's S 0 /0 and RTR2's S 0 /0 with the network IP address of 10.10.30.1 /30.<br>RTR1 is connected to a switch via RTR1's F a 0 /0 with the network IP address of 10.10.10.0 /24.  This switch is connected to a host depicted by a man sitting at a computer.<br>RTR2 is connected to a switch via RTR2's Fa 0 /0 with the network IP address of 10.10.20.1 /24.  This switch is connected to a server with an IP network address of 10.10.20.5 /24.<br>RTR2 is connected to the Internet via RTR2's S 0 /0 with the network IP: address of 209.13.24.3 /24.  <br><br>A.10.10.20.1<br>B.10.10.20.5<br>C.10.10.30.1<br>D.209.13.24.3<br><br>9.The command show ip nat translations has been issued.  Which type of NAT translation is being performed?  Use the output below to answer this question.<br>Pro... - tcp<br>Inside global... - 192.168.3.1:1098<br>Inside local. - 10.1.0.1:1098<br>Outside local.. - 209.4.5.6:23<br>Outside global - 209.4.5.6:23<br><br>Pro... - tcp<br>Inside global... - 192.168.3.1:1345<br>Inside local. - 10.1.0.2:1345<br>Outside local.. - 209.4.5.6:23<br>Outside global - 209.4.5.6:23<br><br>Pro... - tcp<br>Inside global... - 192.168.3.1:1989<br>Inside local. - 10.1.0.3:1989<br>Outside local.. - 209.4.5.7:21<br>Outside global - 209.4.5.7:21<br><br>A.NAT static configuration<br>B.NAT simple configuration<br>C.NAT overloading configuration<br>D.NAT overlapping configuration<br><br>10.What is the purpose of a subnet mask in a network?<br>A.A subnet mask is necessary when a default gateway is not specified.<br>B.A subnet mask is required only when bits are borrowed on a network.<br>C.A subnet mask is used to identify the network portion of an IP address.<br>D.A subnet mask is used to separate the 48-bit address into the OUI and the vendor serial number.<br><br>11.How many addresses will be available for dynamic NAT translation when a router is configured with the following commands?<br>Commands<br>Router(config)# ip nat pool TAME 10.186.2.24 10.186.2.30 netmask 255.255.255.224<br>Router(config)# ip nat inside source list 9 pool TAME<br><br>A.6<br>B.7<br>C.8<br>D.9<br>E.10<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
