<transcript lastedited="01.21.09 18:01:36">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.6.3 - Switches - Selective Forwarding]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts selective forwarding of individual frames from a receiving port to the port where the destination node is connected. A 12-port switch is shown with the following connections in the switching table:<br><br>Host with MAC address 0A is connected to port 1.<br>Host with MAC address 0B is connected to port 3.<br>Host with MAC address 0C is connected to port 6.<br>Host with MAC address 0D is connected to port 9.<br><br>Two frames are shown:<br>Frame 1: Destination address is 0C, and the source address is 0A.<br>Frame 2: Destination address is 0C, and the source address is 0D.<br><br>As the animation progresses, source host 0A and 0D transmit to destination host 0C. The switch looks up the destination MAC address in the frame header and compares it to the list of addresses in its MAC address table. The switch sees that it has two frames destined for the same host. It buffers the frames in its memory buffers and sends them out the designated port one at a time.<br><br>Next the animation displays a new block diagram showing some of the key internal components of the switch. These include the MAC address table, switching logic, memory buffers, CPU, and Flash. Host 0A transmits a frame to destination host 0C. The switch uses its switching logic to look up the destination address in its MAC address table and buffers the frame in its memory buffers. It then sends the frame to host 0C on port 6. <br><br>The animation continues showing source hosts 0A and 0B transmitting simultaneously to destination host 0C. The switch looks up the destination address in its MAC address table and buffers the two frames in its memory buffers. It then sends the frames one at a time to host 0C on port 6.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
