<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:31">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.1.1  - What Is VTP?]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts VTP components and terminology, including VTP domain, VTP advertisements, VTP modes, VTP server, VTP client, VTP transparent, and VTP pruning. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>There are six Access Layer switches, S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, and S6, which are connected to four Distribution Layer switches, D1, D2, D3, and D4. The Distribution Layer switches are connected to two Core Layer switches, C1 and C2. The two Core Layer switches are connected to single switch at the top of the hierarchy, S0.<br><br>Switches S1, S2, and S3 are each connected to switches D1 and D2. Switches S4, S5, and S6 are each connected to D3 and D4. Switches D1 and D2 are connected to C1. Switches D3 and D4 are connected to C2. Switches C1 and C2 are connected to switch S0. All switch interconnections use crossover cables.<br><br>As the following VTP terms are rolled over, various components are highlighted in the network.<br><br>VTP Domain<br>Switches C1, D1, D2, S1, S2, and S3 make up VTP Domain 1. Switches C2, D3, D4, S4, S5, and S5 make up VTP Domain 2.<br><br>VTP Advertisements<br>Examples of VTP advertisement packets are shown being sent between C1, D1, and D2 and between S6 and D4.<br><br>VTP Modes<br>Switches C1 and C2 are highlighted as VTP servers. Switches S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, D1, and D3 are highlighted as VTP clients. Switches D2 and D4 are highlighted as VTP transparent.<br><br>VTP Server<br>Switches C1 and C2 are highlighted as VTP servers.<br><br>VTP Client<br>Switches S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, D1, and D3 are highlighted as VTP clients. <br><br>VTP Transparent<br>Switches D2 and D4 are highlighted as VTP transparent.<br><br>VTP Pruning<br>Trunk links between switches D3 and S6, D4 and S4, and D4 and C2 are shown as blocked, indicating that flooded traffic is restricted.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
