<chapter type="" id="en0502000000">
<title><content-text>Help Desk</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en0502000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502000101">
<content-media type="AnimationFullScreen" id="cm4912382941">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502000000/en0502000100/en0502000101/cm4912382941.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502000000/en0502000100/en0502000101/cm4912382941text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0502010000">
<title><content-text>Help Desk Technicians</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502010100">
<title><content-text>ISP Help Desk Organization</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4868138557">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010100/en0502010101/cm4868138557.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010100/en0502010101/cm4868138557text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Many business operations depend on the connection to the local network and to the Internet. Because of this, solving network problems is a top priority for businesses.</p> <p>ISPs provide the Internet connection for businesses, and they provide their customers support for problems that occur with Internet connectivity. This support usually includes assistance with customer equipment problems. ISP support is typically provided through the ISP help desk. Whether the problem is connecting to the Internet or getting email, the ISP help desk is usually the first place a user or business turns to for help.</p> <p>ISP help desk technicians have the knowledge and experience to fix problems and get users connected. ISP help desk technicians provide solutions to customer problems with the goal of network optimization and customer retention. </p> <p>A good help desk team ensures that problems are resolved quickly and to the satisfaction of the customer. Providing Internet services is a highly competitive business, and poor service can cause the ISP to lose customers to competing ISPs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2642034456">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010100/en0502010102/cm2642034456.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010100/en0502010102/cm2642034456text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At an ISP, there are usually three levels of customer support:</p> <p><ul><li> Level 1 is for immediate support handled by junior-level help desk technicians.</li><li> Level 2 handles calls that are escalated to more experienced telephone support. </li><li> Level 3 is for calls that cannot be resolved by phone support and require a visit by an on-site technician.</li></ul></p> <p>In addition to ISPs, many other types of medium to large businesses employ help desk or customer support teams. The titles assigned to the technicians may vary from those described here, although the three-level hierarchy is the most common structure. Depending on the size of the organization, the help desk can consist of one person that performs all three levels of support, or it can be a comprehensive call center with elaborate call routing facilities and escalation rules. Some ISPs and businesses contract out their help desk functions to a third-party call center company, which provides the services of Level 1 and Level 2 technicians.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502010200">
<title><content-text>Roles of ISP Technicians</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm4324463581">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010201/cm4324463581.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010201/cm4324463581text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a user initially contacts the help desk to resolve an issue, the call or message is usually directed to a Level 1 support technician. Level 1 support is usually an entry-level position that provides junior technicians with valuable experience. Many customer issues are resolved by the Level 1 support technician.</p> <p>Issues that cannot be resolved are sent to Level 2 support, which typically has fewer agents available. The duties and responsibilities of the Level 2 technician are similar to that of the Level 1 technician, but they are at a higher skill level. These agents are expected to solve problems that are more challenging and require more knowledge.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6718760587">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010202/cm6718760587.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010202/cm6718760587text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Many larger service providers have expanded their businesses to include managed services or on-site support of a customer network. Organizations that provide managed services are sometimes referred to as <content-link target="{9D4E4FEA-A987-4111-94A2-69E198A0C3D2}" type="glossary">Managed Service</content-link> Providers (MSP). Managed services can be provided by ISPs, telecommunications service providers, or other types of computer and network support organizations. When an ISP is providing managed services, it often requires technicians to visit customer sites for the purpose of installation and support. This type of service represents Level 3 support. </p> <p>Level 3 support is usually in accordance with a Service Level Agreement (<content-link target="{64E47444-8853-4B94-B85B-19FFAB213E0E}" type="glossary">SLA</content-link>). An SLA resembles an insurance policy, because it provides coverage or service if there is a computer or network problem.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502010203">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm9624978566">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010203/cm9624978566.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010200/en0502010203/cm9624978566text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Identify the responsibilities of each level of network technician.</p><p><b>For each task, select the appropriate technician.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502010300">
<title><content-text>Interacting with Customers</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm9724005607">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010301/cm9724005607.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010301/cm9724005607text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Help desk technicians may be required to provide phone support, email support, web-based support, online chat support, and possibly on-site support. They are often the first point of contact for frustrated and anxious customers. Until a problem is solved, help desk technicians may continue to get calls and correspondence asking for status updates and time estimates to resolve an issue.</p> <p>The help desk technician must be able to stay focused in an environment with frequent interruptions and perform multiple tasks efficiently and accurately. It can be difficult to consistently maintain a positive attitude and provide a high level of service. The help desk technician has to have excellent interpersonal skills and effective communication skills, both oral and written. The technician must be able to work independently and as part of a team.</p> <p>It is important for the help desk technician to be able to handle customer issues with speed, efficiency, and professionalism. Help desk technicians should conduct themselves in accordance with the company's customer service philosophy. A customer service philosophy is an organization-wide ethic shared by everyone from top management to operational staff.</p> <p>Basic <content-link target="{33D3A086-5683-4919-B6AC-B7313B45403D}" type="glossary">incident management</content-link> procedures must be followed every time a help desk technician receives a call and begins troubleshooting issues. Incident management includes opening a trouble ticket and following a problem-solving strategy. Problem-solving techniques include using troubleshooting flowcharts, addressing questions in a template format, and maintaining proper ticket escalation procedures.</p> <p>A help desk script is used by the help desk technician to gather information and cover the important facts about customer incident.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1029987658">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010302/cm1029987658.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010302/cm1029987658text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to technical ability, help desk technicians must be able to greet customers pleasantly and be professional and courteous throughout the call. </p> <p>Customer service and interpersonal skills are especially important when handling difficult clients and incidents. The help desk technician must know how to relieve customer stress and respond to abusive customers. </p> <p>Opening trouble tickets and logging information on the tickets are critical to help desk operation. When there are many calls relating to a single problem or symptom, it is helpful to have information on how the problem was resolved in the past. It is also important to relay to the customer what is being done to solve the problem. Good information on open trouble tickets helps communicate accurate status, both to the customer and other ISP personnel.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502010303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2960622579">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010303/cm2960622579.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010303/cm2960622579text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>While many issues can be handled remotely, some problems require an on-site visit to the customer premises to install and troubleshoot equipment. When a technician goes on-site, it is important to represent their organization in a professional manner. A professional knows how to make the customer feel at ease and confident in the technician's skills.</p> <p>On the first visit to a customer location, it is important for the technician to make a good impression. Personal grooming and the way the technician is dressed are the first things the customer notices. If the technician makes a bad first impression, it may be difficult to change that impression and gain the confidence of the customer. Many employers provide a uniform or have a dress code for their on-site technicians.</p> <p>The language and attitude of the technician also reflect on the organization that the technician represents. A customer may be anxious or concerned about how the new equipment will operate. When speaking with a customer, the technician should be polite and respectful, and answer all customer questions. If the technician does not know an answer to a customer question or if additional information is required, the technician should write down the customer inquiry and follow up on it as soon as possible.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502010304">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm7594337856">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010304/cm7594337856.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502010000/en0502010300/en0502010304/cm7594337856text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Examine each statement and decide to which part of the customer support process it belongs.</p><p><b>For each statement, select the appropriate item.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0502020000">
<title><content-text>OSI Model</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502020100">
<title><content-text>Using the OSI Model</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm9598144494">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020100/en0502020101/cm9598144494.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020100/en0502020101/cm9598144494text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a network connectivity problem is reported to the help desk, many methods are available to diagnose the problem. One common method is to troubleshoot the problem using a layered approach. A layered approach requires that the network technician be familiar with the various functions that occur as messages are created, delivered, and interpreted by the network devices and hosts on the network. </p> <p>Moving data across a network is best visualized using the seven layers of the Open Systems Interconnection model, commonly referred to as the OSI model. The OSI model breaks network communications down into multiple processes. Each process is a small part of the larger task. </p> <p>For example, in a vehicle manufacturing plant, the entire vehicle is not assembled by one person. Rather the vehicle moves from station to station where specialized teams add specific components. The complex task of assembling a vehicle is made easier by breaking it into manageable and logical tasks. This process also makes troubleshooting easier. When a problem occurs in the manufacturing process, it is possible to isolate the problem to the specific task where the defect was introduced, and then fix it.</p> <p>In a similar manner, the OSI model can be used as a means to focus on a layer when troubleshooting to identify and resolve network problems.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9040420739">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020100/en0502020102/cm9040420739.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020100/en0502020102/cm9040420739text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The seven layers of the OSI model are divided into two parts: upper layers and lower layers.</p> <p>The term upper layer is sometimes used to refer to any layer above the transport layer of the OSI model. The upper layers deal with application functionality and are generally implemented only in software. The highest layer, the <content-link target="{3342305F-8DCF-4C71-A3DD-887A15812146}" type="glossary">application layer</content-link>, is closest to the end user.</p> <p>The term lower layer is sometimes used to refer to any layer below the session layer. The combined functionality of the lower layers handles data transport. The physical layer and the data link layer are implemented in both hardware and software. The physical layer is closest to the physical network medium, or network cabling. The physical layer actually places information on the medium.</p> <p>End stations, like clients and servers, usually work with all seven layers. Networking devices are only concerned with the lower layers. Hubs work on Layer 1, switches on Layers 1 and 2, routers on Layers 1, 2 and 3, and firewalls on Layers 1, 2, 3, and 4.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502020200">
<title><content-text>OSI Model Protocols and Technologies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4649646351">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020201/cm4649646351.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020201/cm4649646351text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When using the OSI model as a framework for troubleshooting, it is important to understand which functions are performed at each layer, and what network information is available to the devices or software programs performing these functions. For example, many processes must occur for email to successfully travel from the client to the server. The OSI model divides the task of sending and receiving email into smaller, distinct steps that correspond with the seven layers.</p> <p><b>Step 1: Upper layers create the data.</b></p> <p>When a user sends an email message, the <content-link target="{5CF42969-6E48-475D-A364-DC221091D8FB}" type="glossary">alphanumeric character</content-link>s within the message are converted to data that can travel across the network. Layers 7, 6, and 5 are responsible for ensuring that the message is placed in a format that can be understood by the application running on the destination host. This process is called <content-link target="{6CA221E5-07C4-4A49-A6F0-301574659C48}" type="glossary">encoding</content-link>. The upper layers then send the encoded messages to the lower layers for transport across the network. Transporting the email to the correct server relies on the configuration information provided by the user. Problems that occur at the application layer are often related to errors in the configuration of the user software programs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6981046784">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020202/cm6981046784.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020202/cm6981046784text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Step 2: Layer 4 packages the data for end-to-end transport.</b></p> <p>The data that comprises the email message is packaged for network transport at Layer 4. Layer 4 breaks the message down into smaller segments. A header is placed on each <content-link target="{604F2C67-75EA-43CD-A785-B01E3AD794E7}" type="glossary">segment</content-link> indicating the <content-link target="{6F0F3B18-F7F1-4B92-BBFA-016F3A0B5D13}" type="glossary">TCP</content-link> or <content-link target="{6CA90D65-6059-4728-AC68-AB0F4D9BF986}" type="glossary">UDP</content-link> <content-link target="{EDFF3A52-C27D-49A1-AEF0-858E0EC0BAC7}" type="glossary">port number</content-link> that corresponds to the correct application layer application. Functions in the transport layer indicate the type of delivery service. Email utilizes TCP segments, therefore packet delivery is acknowledged by the destination. Layer 4 functions are implemented in software that runs on the source and destination hosts. However, because firewalls often use the TCP and UDP port numbers to filter traffic, problems that occur at Layer 4 can be caused by improperly configured firewall filter lists.</p> <p><b>Step 3: Layer 3 adds the network IP address information.</b> </p> <p>The email data received from the transport layer is put into a packet that contains a header with the source and destination network IP addresses. Routers use the destination address to direct the packets across the network along the appropriate path. Incorrectly configured IP address information on the source or destination system can cause Layer 3 problems to occur. Because routers also use IP address information, router configuration errors can cause problems at this layer.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6352824037">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020203/cm6352824037.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020203/cm6352824037text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Step 4: Layer 2 adds the data link layer header and trailer.</b></p> <p>Each network device in the path from the source to the destination, including the sending host, encapsulates the packet into a frame. The frame contains the physical address of the next directly-connected network device on the link. Each device in the chosen network path requires framing so that it can connect to the next device. Switches and network interface cards (NICs) use the information in the frame to deliver the message to the correct destination device. Incorrect NIC drivers, interface cards, and hardware problems with switches can cause Layer 2 problems to occur.</p> <p><b>Step 5: Layer 1 converts the data to bits for transmission.</b></p> <p>The frame is converted into a pattern of 1s and 0s (bits) for transmission on the medium. A clocking function enables the devices to distinguish these bits as they travel across the medium. The medium can change along the path between the source and destination. For example, the email message can originate on an Ethernet LAN, cross a fiber campus backbone, and cross a serial <content-link target="{E1CFA27E-2097-4F10-8479-191FD3F89F58}" type="glossary">WAN</content-link> link until it reaches its destination on another remote Ethernet LAN. Layer 1 problems can be caused by loose or incorrect cables, malfunctioning interface cards, or electrical interference.</p> <p>At the receiving host, the processes described in steps 1 through 5 are reversed, with the message traveling back up the layers to the appropriate application.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502020204">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm3167531272">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020204/cm3167531272.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020200/en0502020204/cm3167531272text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Identify the layer to which the protocol or technology belongs.</p><p><b>For each protocol or technology displayed, click the appropriate layer.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502020300">
<title><content-text>Troubleshooting the OSI Model</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2046182159">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020301/cm2046182159.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020301/cm2046182159text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As a theoretical model, the OSI model defines the protocols, hardware, and other specifications that operate at the seven layers.</p> <p>The OSI model also provides a systematic basis for troubleshooting a network. In any troubleshooting scenario, the basic problem-solving procedure includes the following steps:</p> <p>1. Define the problem.</p> <p>2. Isolate the cause of the problem.</p> <p>3. Solve the problem.</p> <p><ul><li>Identify and prioritize alternative solutions.</li><li>Select one alternative as the solution.</li><li>Implement the solution.</li><li>Evaluate the solution.</li></ul></p> <p>If an identified solution does not fix the problem, undo any changes and proceed to the next possible solution. Go through the steps until a solution works.</p> <p>In addition to the basic problem-solving procedures, the OSI model can be used as a guideline for troubleshooting. Using a layered model, there are three different troubleshooting approaches that a technician can use to isolate the problem:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Bottom-Up</b> - The bottom-up approach starts with the physical components of the network and works its way up the layers of the OSI model. Bottom-up troubleshooting is an effective and efficient approach for suspected physical problems.</li><li><b> Top-Down</b> - The top-down approach starts with the user application and works its way down the layers of the OSI model. This approach starts with the assumption that the problem is with the application and not the network infrastructure. </li><li> <b>Divide-and-Conquer</b> - The divide-and-conquer approach is generally used by more experienced network technicians. The technician makes an educated guess targeting the problem layer and then based on the observed results, moves up or down the OSI layers.</li></ul></p> <p>Using the OSI model as a guide, the help desk technician can query the customer to help define the problem and isolate the cause.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8225001476">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020302/cm8225001476.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020302/cm8225001476text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The help desk technician usually has a standard checklist or script to follow when troubleshooting a problem. Often the script takes a bottom-up approach to troubleshooting. This is because physical problems are usually the simplest to diagnose and repair, and the bottom-up approach starts with the Physical Layer.</p> <p><b>Layer 1 Troubleshooting</b></p> <p>The technician starts with Layer 1 issues first. Remember, Layer 1 deals with the physical connectivity of the network devices. Layer 1 problems often involve cabling and electricity, and are the reasons for many help desk calls. Some of the more common Layer 1 problems include:</p> <p><ul><li> Device power turned off</li><li> Device power unplugged</li><li> Loose network cable connection</li><li> Incorrect cable type</li><li> Faulty network cable</li><li> Faulty wireless access point</li><li> Incorrect wireless settings, such as the SSID</li></ul></p> <p>To troubleshoot at Layer 1, first check that all devices have the proper electrical supply, and that the devices are turned on. This may seem to be an obvious solution, but many times the person reporting the problem may overlook a device that is within the network path from source to destination. If there are any LEDs that display the status of the connectivity, verify with the customer that they are indicating correctly. If on-site, visually inspect all network cabling and reconnect cables to ensure a proper connection. If the problem is with wireless, verify that the wireless access point is operational and that wireless settings are configured correctly.</p> <p>When remotely troubleshooting a problem, the technician should advise the caller through each step, what to look for, and what to do if an error is found. If it is determined that all Layer 1 issues have been addressed, it is time to travel up the OSI model to Layer 2.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2279597213">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020303/cm2279597213.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020303/cm2279597213text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Layer 2 Troubleshooting</b></p> <p>Network switches and host NICs perform Layer 2 functions. Layer 2 problems can be caused by faulty equipment, incorrect device drivers, or an improperly configured switch. When remotely troubleshooting a problem, it may be difficult to isolate a Layer 2 problem.</p> <p>An on-site technician can check whether the NIC is installed and working properly. Reseating the NIC, or replacing a suspected faulty NIC with a known good NIC, helps to isolate the problem. The same process can be done with any network switch.</p> <p><b>Layer 3 Troubleshooting</b></p> <p>At Layer 3, the technician needs to investigate the logical addressing used in the network, such as the IP address scheme. If the network is using IP addressing, the technician verifies that the device has the proper settings, such as:</p> <p><ul><li> IP address within the assigned network</li><li> Correct <content-link target="{95684BEC-16FE-46B5-AEEF-D242FD5683EA}" type="glossary">subnet mask</content-link></li><li> Correct default gateway</li><li> Other settings as required, such as <content-link target="{7DBD3723-7A9A-499D-A936-D2AF56A8A2B0}" type="glossary">DHCP</content-link> or DNS</li></ul></p> <p>At Layer 3, several utilities can assist with the troubleshooting process. Three of the most common command line tools are:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ipconfig</b></span> - Shows IP settings on the computer</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> - Tests basic network connectivity</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> - Determines if the routing path between the source and destination is available</p> <p>Most network problems can usually be resolved using these Layer 1, 2, and 3 troubleshooting techniques.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502020304">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6908099565">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020304/cm6908099565.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020304/cm6908099565text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Layer 4 Troubleshooting</b></p> <p>If Layers 1 through 3 all appear to be operating normally and the technician can successfully <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> the IP address of the remote server, it is time to check the higher layers. For example, if a network firewall is used along the path, it is important to check that the application TCP or UDP port is open and no filter lists are blocking traffic to that port. </p> <p><b>Layers 5 through 7 Troubleshooting</b></p> <p>The technician should also check the application configuration. For example, if troubleshooting an email issue, ensure that the application is configured with the correct sending and receiving email server information. It is also necessary to ensure that domain name resolution is functioning as expected. </p> <p>For remote technicians, higher layer issues can be checked by using other network utility tools, such as a packet sniffer, to view traffic as it crosses the network. A network application, such as Telnet, can also be used to view configurations.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502020305">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm8034713751">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020305/cm8034713751.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502020000/en0502020300/en0502020305/cm8034713751text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Identify if a network issue is occurring at Layer 1, Layer 2, Layer 3, Layer 4, or Layers 5 through 7.</p><p><b>Based on the scenario, check the appropriate layer.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0502030000">
<title><content-text>ISP Troubleshooting</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502030100">
<title><content-text>Help Desk Troubleshooting Scenarios</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5908043383">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030101/cm5908043383.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030101/cm5908043383text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The number and types of calls received by the help desk can vary extensively. Some of the most common calls include problems with email, host configuration, and connectivity.</p> <p><b>Email Issues</b></p> <p> </p> <p><ul><li> Can receive but not send</li><li> Can send but not receive</li><li> Cannot send or receive </li><li> Nobody can reply to messages</li></ul></p> <p>A common cause of many email problems is using the wrong POP, <content-link target="{9744C254-6688-4087-B0F6-7D80D6859BBF}" type="glossary">IMAP</content-link>, or <content-link target="{1FD6C4B7-EF18-4CF9-9494-CBF6101A6376}" type="glossary">SMTP</content-link> server names. It is best to check with the email administrator to confirm the proper name of the POP or IMAP server and SMTP server. In some cases, the same server name for both POP/IMAP and SMTP are used. Also, confirm that the username and password are correct. Since the password is not usually displayed, it is a good idea to carefully re-enter it.</p> <p>When troubleshooting these issues over the phone, it is important to step the customer through the configuration parameters carefully. Many customers are unfamiliar with the terminology and the settings of the various configuration parameters. If possible, connect to the customer device via remote management software. This allows the technician to perform the necessary steps for the customer.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8848940280">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030102/cm8848940280.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030102/cm8848940280text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Host Configuration Issues</b></p> <p>A common issue that can prevent connectivity to the Internet or other network resources is improperly configured host addressing information. This can include an incorrect IP address, subnet mask, or default gateway. </p> <p>In environments where the IP addressing information is manually configured, it is possible that the IP configuration was simply entered incorrectly. In environments where hosts are configured to dynamically receive an IP address from an assignment server, such as a DHCP server, the server may fail or become unreachable due to network issues. </p> <p>If a host is configured to receive an address dynamically, and an assignment server is unavailable or unreachable, a <content-link target="{95CC27A0-45B5-4EE1-A4BB-5D2E3CFD7001}" type="glossary">link-local address</content-link> will be automatically assigned to the local host by the operating system. IPv4 addresses in the address block 169.254.0.1 to 169.254.255.254 (169.254.0.0 /16) are designated as link-local addresses. A link-local process will randomly select an IP address within the 169.254.0.0/16 range. But what prevents two hosts from randomly selecting the same IP address?</p> <p>Once the link-local process selects an IP address, it sends an <content-link target="{8078363A-3832-4068-9F9E-B9CCA753F984}" type="glossary">ARP</content-link> query with that IP onto the network to see if any other devices are using that address. If there is no response, the IP address is assigned to the device, otherwise another IP address is selected, and the ARP query is repeated. Microsoft refers to link-local addresses as Automatic Private IP Addressing (APIPA).</p> <p>If multiple hosts on the same network obtain a link-local address, client/server and peer-to-peer applications between those hosts will work properly. However, because link-local addresses are in the private Class B address space, communication outside of the local network is not possible.</p> <p>When troubleshooting both manually and dynamically configured hosts, use the host command <span class="cmd"><b>ipconfig /all</b></span> to verify that the host is using the appropriate IP configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030103">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5940054809">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030103/cm5940054809.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030103/cm5940054809text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Customer Connectivity Issues</b></p> <p>Connectivity problems are more common with new customers trying to connect for the first time. However, sometimes existing customers encounter connectivity issues. First-time customers may have problems with installing the hardware as well as software configuration settings. Existing customers notice connectivity problems when they cannot open a web page or connect to instant messaging or email.</p> <p>There are many reasons why a customer has no connectivity, including the following:</p> <p><ul><li> Delinquent payments for services</li><li> Hardware failures</li><li> Physical layer failures</li><li> Incorrect application settings </li><li> Missing application plug-ins</li><li> Missing applications</li></ul></p> <p>In many cases, the problem is simply a faulty cable, or a cable plugged into an incorrect port. These types of issues can be resolved by checking the cable connection or replacing the cable.</p> <p>Other problems, such as software issues, may be more difficult to detect. One example is an incorrectly loaded <content-link target="{98B3CE04-8372-47D3-BCDC-D473FD159383}" type="glossary">TCP/IP</content-link> <content-link target="{968F3D09-048D-449F-9CD3-42D5F7FFA20B}" type="glossary">stack</content-link>, preventing IP from operating correctly. The TCP/IP stack can be tested and verified using a loopback address. The loopback is a special address, the reserved IPv4 address 127.0.0.1, which hosts use to direct traffic to themselves. The loopback address creates a shortcut method for TCP/IP applications and services that run on the same device to communicate. </p> <p>You can ping the loopback address to test the configuration of TCP/IP on the local host. If you are unable to get a response when pinging the loopback address, suspect an improperly configured or installed TCP/IP stack.</p> <p>Addresses 127.0.0.1 through 127.255.255.254 are reserved for testing purposes. Any address within this block will loop back within the local host. No address within this block should ever appear on any network. Despite the fact that the entire 127.0.0.0/8 network range is reserved, the only address typically used for loopback testing is the 127.0.0.1 address. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030104">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1649491836">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030104/cm1649491836/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030100/en0502030104/cm1649491836/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Troubleshoot and resolve a network connectivity issue.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502030200">
<title><content-text>Creating and Using Help Desk Records</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6480592509">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030200/en0502030201/cm6480592509.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030200/en0502030201/cm6480592509text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a Level 1 help desk technician receives a call, there is a process followed to gather information. There are also specific systems for storing and retrieving relevant information. It is extremely important to gather the information correctly in the event that a call has to be escalated to Layer 2 or require an on-site visit. </p> <p>The information gathering and recording process starts as soon as the technician answers the phone. When the customer identifies who they are, the technician accesses the relevant customer information. Typically, a database application is used to manage the customer information. </p> <p>The information is transferred to a trouble ticket, or incident report. This document can be a piece of paper in a paper filing system or an electronic tracking system designed to follow the troubleshooting process from beginning to end. Each person who works on the problem is expected to record what was done on the trouble ticket. When an on-site call is required, the trouble ticket information can be converted to a work order that the on-site technician can take to the customer site.</p> <p>When a problem is resolved, the solution is documented in the customer work order or trouble ticket, and in a knowledge-base document for future reference.</p> <p>Occasionally, the Level 1help desk technician may receive a call that cannot be resolved quickly. In this instance, the technician is responsible for passing the call to a Level 2 technician who is more qualified to resolve the issue. Passing the call to a higher level technician is known as the call escalation process.</p> <p>Both Level 1 and Level 2 help desk technicians attempt to solve customer problems using the telephone, web tools, and possibly remote desktop sharing applications.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4365217838">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030200/en0502030202/cm4365217838.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030200/en0502030202/cm4365217838text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If the help desk technicians are not able to fix the problem remotely, it is often necessary to send a Level 3 on-site technician to the customer premise location. It is the job of the on-site technician to visit the customer premise to physically work on the problem equipment. The help desk technician can make an appointment with the customer for the on-site technician to perform the repairs, or it may be the responsibility of the on-site technician to arrange the appointment.</p> <p>To properly troubleshoot the problem, the on-site technician reviews the trouble ticket to see what was previously done. This review gives the technician some background information and a logical starting point. It also helps the technician decide which tools and supplies to bring, rather than having to leave the customer site to obtain supplies.</p> <p>On-site technicians typically work on the network at the customer location, although there are instances where the technician is unable to make the needed repairs and must bring the damaged equipment back to the ISP site for additional troubleshooting.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0502030300">
<title><content-text>Customer Site Procedures</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3355870661">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030301/cm3355870661.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030301/cm3355870661text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are four steps an on-site technician performs before beginning any troubleshooting or repair at the customer site:</p> <p><b>Step 1</b>. Provide proper identification to the customer.</p> <p><b>Step 2</b>. Review the trouble ticket or work order with the customer to verify that the information is correct.</p> <p><b>Step 3</b>. Communicate the current status of any identified problems and the actions the technician expects to take at the customer site that day.</p> <p><b>Step 4</b>. Obtain permission from the customer to begin the work.</p> <p>The technician must verify all items on the trouble ticket. Once the technician is familiar with all issues, the work can begin. The technician is responsible for checking all device and network settings, and running any necessary utilities. The technician may also have to swap out suspected faulty hardware with known good hardware to determine if a hardware problem exists. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2945077985">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030302/cm2945077985.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030302/cm2945077985text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When performing any troubleshooting tasks the customer site, especially when installing new or replacing existing equipment, it is important to minimize the risk of injury by following good safety practices. Many employers offer safety training as part of their employee services.</p> <p><b>Ladders</b></p> <p>Use ladders to reach high locations to install networking cable and to install or troubleshoot wireless access points in places that are difficult to reach. To reduce the risk of falling off the ladder or dropping equipment while climbing on the ladder, work with a partner whenever possible.</p> <p><b>High or Dangerous Locations</b></p> <p>Sometimes network equipment and cables are located in high and dangerous places, such as on the side of a building, on roof tops, or in an internal structure such as an elevator shaft, that is not accessible by a ladder. Work performed at this type of location must be done very carefully. Using a safety harness reduces the risk of falling.</p> <p><b>Electrical Equipment</b></p> <p>If there is a risk of damaging or coming in contact with any electrical lines when handling hardware, consult with the electrician of the customer about measures that can be taken to reduce the risk of electrical shock. Coming in contact with electrical equipment may result in serious personal injury.</p> <p><b>Awkward Spaces</b></p> <p>Network equipment is often located in narrow and awkward spaces. Ensure that the work area is properly lighted and ventilated. Determine the best way to lift, install, and remove equipment to minimize the risks.</p> <p><b>Heavy Equipment</b></p> <p>Networking devices can be large and heavy. Plan to have the correct equipment and trained personnel when heavy equipment needs to be installed or moved at a customer site.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502030303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1626115430">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030303/cm1626115430.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502030000/en0502030300/en0502030303/cm1626115430text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After the technician makes any configuration changes or installs new equipment, the technician must observe the results to ensure proper operation. When finished, the technician communicates the nature of the identified problem to the customer, what solution was applied, and any follow-up procedures. Before the problem can be considered fully resolved, the technician must obtain the acceptance of the customer. The technician can then close the trouble ticket and document the solution.</p> <p>A copy of the documentation is left with the customer. The document includes the original help desk call problem and the actions taken to solve the problem. The technician records the solution, and the customer acceptance is indicated on the trouble ticket. For future reference, the technician also records the problem and the solution in the help desk documentation and FAQs.</p> <p>In some cases, an on-site technician can uncover network problems that require upgrades or reconfiguration of the network devices. When this occurs, it may be outside of the scope of the original trouble ticket. These issues are usually communicated to both the customer and the ISP network personnel for further action.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en0502040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0502040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm7776767730">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502040000/en0502040100/en0502040101/cm7776767730.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0502000000/en0502040000/en0502040100/en0502040101/cm7776767730text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en0502050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0502050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0502050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm9319458875">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0502000000/en0502050000/en0502050100/en0502050101/cm9319458875/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en0502000000/en0502050000/en0502050100/en0502050101/cm9319458875/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
