<chapter type="" id="en0501000000">
<title><content-text>The Internet and Its Uses</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en0501000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0501000101">
<content-media type="AnimationFullScreen" id="cm9810822672">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501000000/en0501000100/en0501000101/cm9810822672.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501000000/en0501000100/en0501000101/cm9810822672text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0501010000">
<title><content-text>What is the Internet?</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501010100">
<title><content-text>The Internet and Standards</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501010101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm2825547691">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010100/en0501010101/cm2825547691.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010100/en0501010101/cm2825547691text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The <content-link target="{62CC2A94-D6F6-4163-B076-F3B00D34A736}" type="glossary">Internet</content-link> is a worldwide, publicly accessible network of networks. It enables individuals and businesses alike, through interconnected computer networks, to share information, resources, and services. </p> <p>In the beginning, the Internet was used strictly for scientific, educational, and military research. In 1991, regulations changed to allow businesses and consumers to connect as well. The Internet has grown rapidly, and is now global. New technologies are continuously being developed that make the Internet easier and more attractive to use. Online applications are available to the Internet user, including email, web browsing, streaming music and video, gaming, and instant messaging.</p> <p>The way people interact, share information, and even do business is changing to keep up with the continuous evolution of this global network. The Internet is creating a wider audience and consumer base for whatever message, product, or service can be delivered. For many businesses, having Internet access has become critical, not only for communication but also for day-to-day operation. Some of the business uses of the Internet include:</p> <p><ul><li> <content-link target="{56B0F775-C3AC-46DA-A3A8-5BB5B92297E3}" type="glossary">E-commerce</content-link></li><li> Communications</li><li> Collaboration and training</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501010102">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8363800338">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010100/en0501010102/cm8363800338.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010100/en0501010102/cm8363800338text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>With the increasing number of new devices and technologies coming online, how is it possible to manage all the changes and still reliably deliver services such as email? The answer is Internet standards.</p> <p>A standard is a set of rules that determines how something must be done. Networking and Internet standards ensure that all devices connecting to the network use the same set of rules. Using standards, it is possible for different types of devices to send information to each other over the Internet. For example, the way in which an email is formatted, forwarded, and received by all devices is done according to a standard. If one person sends an email via a personal computer, another person can use a mobile phone to receive and read the email as long as the mobile phone uses the same standards as the personal computer. </p> <p>An Internet standard is the end result of a comprehensive cycle of discussion, problem solving, and testing. When a new standard is proposed, each stage of the development and approval process is recorded in a numbered Request for Comments (RFC) document so that the evolution of the standard is tracked.</p> <p>There are thousands of Internet standards that help define the rules for how devices communicate on networks. These different standards are developed, published, and maintained by a variety of different organizations. Because these organizations create and maintain standards, millions of individuals are able to connect to the Internet using a variety of devices, including personal computers, mobile phones, handheld personal digital assistants (PDAs), MP3 players, and even televisions.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0501010200">
<title><content-text>ISP and ISP Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7727031371">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010200/en0501010201/cm7727031371.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010200/en0501010201/cm7727031371text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Regardless of the type of device that an individual or business uses to connect to the Internet, the device must connect through an Internet service provider (<content-link target="{A967B545-885E-4C04-926A-934A698E2488}" type="glossary">ISP</content-link>). An ISP is a company or organization through which a subscriber obtains Internet access. A subscriber can be a business, a private consumer, a government body, or even another ISP. </p> <p>In addition to offering connection to the Internet, an ISP can offer other services to subscribers, including:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Equipment co-location</b> - A business may opt to have some or all internal network equipment physically located on the ISP premises. </li><li> <b>Web hosting</b> - The ISP provides the server and application software for storing web pages and web content for the business website. </li><li> <b>FTP</b> - The ISP provides the server and application software for the <content-link target="{D57539CD-A063-4575-87B9-7742E68CF5F8}" type="glossary">FTP</content-link> site of a business.</li><li> <b>Applications and media hosting</b> - The ISP provides the server and software to allow a business to provide <content-link target="{ED0E5447-6695-418B-9900-AE404AFFFE7F}" type="glossary">stream</content-link>ing media such as music, video, or applications such as online databases.</li><li> <b>Voice over IP</b> - A business can save on long distance telephone charges, especially for internal calls between geographically distant offices, by using Voice over IP (VoIP).</li><li> <b>Technical support - </b>Many businesses do not have the in-house technical expertise to manage large internal networks. Some ISPs provide technical support and consulting services for an additional fee.</li><li> <b>Point of Presence </b>(<b><content-link target="{0D82480E-437A-4492-82AB-D218A9FF6598}" type="glossary">POP</content-link>)</b> - A business has the option of connecting to the ISP through POP, using a variety of access technologies. </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0501010202">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm5612533565">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010200/en0501010202/cm5612533565.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501010000/en0501010200/en0501010202/cm5612533565text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the requirements of an end user to various ISPs.</p><p><b>After reading the scenario, place a check in the box that is the most appropriate ISP for each user.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0501020000">
<title><content-text>ISPs</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501020100">
<title><content-text>Delivering Internet Services to End Users</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm3226928926">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020101/cm3226928926.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020101/cm3226928926text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To gain access to the Internet, it is first necessary to have a connection to an ISP. ISPs offer various connection options. The main connection methods used by home and small business users are:</p> <p><b>Dialup access</b></p> <p><content-link target="{E5CAD009-1A03-4E92-AF0F-5D882EA34F7F}" type="glossary">Dialup</content-link> access is an inexpensive option that uses any phone line and a modem. To connect to the ISP, a user calls the ISP access phone number. Dialup is the slowest connection option, and is typically used by mobile workers and in areas where higher speed connection options are not available.</p>  <p><b>DSL</b></p> <p>Digital subscriber line, or <content-link target="{9F837E19-DB5E-4BC2-9869-C3F2B09A3E9B}" type="glossary">DSL</content-link>, is more expensive than dialup, but provides a faster connection. DSL also uses telephone lines, but unlike dialup access, DSL provides a continuous connection to the Internet. This connection option uses a special high-speed modem that separates the DSL signal from the telephone signal and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or <content-link target="{C02056E2-9284-4AEC-BA70-4A4DD5562034}" type="glossary">LAN</content-link>. </p> <p><b>Cable modem</b></p> <p>A <content-link target="{862B947C-2375-4D5F-B84F-C564BA808E8F}" type="glossary">cable modem</content-link> is a connection option offered by cable television service providers. The Internet signal is carried on the same coaxial cable that delivers cable television to homes and businesses. A special cable modem separates the Internet signal from the other signals carried on the cable and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or LAN. </p> <p><b>Satellite</b></p> <p>Satellite connection is an option offered by satellite service providers. The user's computer connects through Ethernet to a satellite modem that transmits radio signals to the nearest Point of Presence, or POP, within the satellite network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7836999443">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020102/cm7836999443.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020102/cm7836999443text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><content-link target="{5F9E2FB9-3E46-467D-923B-C2F16D4CD564}" type="glossary">Bandwidth</content-link> is measured in bits per second (bps). Higher bandwidth speeds are measured in kilobits per second (kbps), megabits per second (Mbps), or gigabits per second (Gbps).</p> <p>There are three main types of high-bandwidth connection options that are used by businesses:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>T1 connections </b>transmit data up to 1.544 Mbps. T1 connections are symmetrical, meaning that the upload bandwidth is the same as the download bandwidth. A medium-sized business may need only one T1 connection. E1 is a European standard that transmits data at 2.048 Mbps. </li><li> <b>T3 connections</b> transmit data up to 45 Mbps. Although considerably more expensive than a T1 connection, larger businesses may need a <content-link target="{E7C410D0-FB15-473F-8710-BB37D2721AE3}" type="glossary">T3 connection</content-link> to accommodate the number of employees. Large businesses with multiple locations might use a combination of T1 and T3 lines. E3 is a European standard that transmits data at 34.368 Mbps.</li><li> <b>Metro Ethernet</b> offers a wide range of high-bandwidth options, including Gbps links. Large companies with many branches in the same city, such as banks, use <content-link target="{223151BB-A5A2-4D72-87CB-ADD19C59BF62}" type="glossary">Metro Ethernet</content-link>. Metro Ethernet connects the main office location and all the branches using switched technology. Metro Ethernet allows the transfer of large amounts of data faster and less expensively than other high-bandwidth connection options.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8400548611">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020103/cm8400548611.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020100/en0501020103/cm8400548611text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After the type of connection is established, it is necessary to connect to the ISP to get access to the Internet. Individual computers and business networks connect to the ISP at the POP. POPs are located at the edge of the ISP network and serve a particular geographical region. They provide a local point of connection and <content-link target="{1B9DAB3F-15ED-49CA-B171-01AAE154B767}" type="glossary">authentication</content-link> (password control) for multiple end users. An ISP may have many POPs, depending on the size of the POP and the area that it services. </p> <p>Within the ISP network, high-speed routers and switches move data between the various POPs. Multiple links interconnect the POPs to provide alternate routes in case one of the links becomes overloaded with <content-link target="{6A5CEC0D-1F86-4051-8F7D-3DC55BF61370}" type="glossary">traffic</content-link> or fails.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0501020200">
<title><content-text>Internet Hierarchy</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4430015664">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020200/en0501020201/cm4430015664.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020200/en0501020201/cm4430015664text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Internet has a hierarchical structure. At the top of this <content-link target="{32C6DBD8-9F02-4847-A080-EE825FFA3752}" type="glossary">hierarchy</content-link> are the ISP organizations. The ISP POPs connect to an Internet Exchange Point (IXP). In some countries, this is called a Network Access Point (<content-link target="{50928C2E-9AB0-43D4-8318-9E96D22A9D52}" type="glossary">NAP</content-link>). An IXP or NAP is where multiple ISPs join together to gain access to each other's networks and exchange information. There are currently over 100 major exchange points located worldwide. </p> <p>The Internet backbone consists of this group of networks owned by various organizations and interconnected through IXPs and <content-link target="{1FCD309F-8693-4BA7-B305-2AEBE5A897F7}" type="glossary">private peer</content-link>ing connections. </p> <p>The Internet backbone is like an information super highway that provides high-speed data links to interconnect the POPs and IXPs in major metropolitan areas around the world. The primary <content-link target="{5EA20B9A-480D-4AA7-8C98-6CA7AD8E3F1F}" type="glossary">medium</content-link> that connects the Internet backbone is fiber-optic cable. This cable is typically installed underground to connect cities within continents. Fiber-optic cables also run under the sea to connect continents, countries, and cities.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7788691471">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020200/en0501020202/cm7788691471.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020200/en0501020202/cm7788691471text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs are classified into different tiers according to how they access the Internet backbone:</p> <p><ul><li> <b><content-link target="{00185EC9-A9B2-4AB1-B1B8-79698F2E6D0A}" type="glossary">Tier 1</content-link></b> ISPs are the top of the hierarchy. Tier 1 ISPs are huge organizations that connect directly with each other through private peering, physically joining their individual network backbones together to create the global Internet backbone. Within their own networks, the Tier 1 ISPs own the routers, high-speed data links, and other pieces of equipment that join them to other Tier 1 ISP networks. This includes the undersea cables that connect the continents.</li><li> <b><content-link target="{D9A5AA4E-CEE5-462A-8776-1173C15AA883}" type="glossary">Tier 2</content-link></b> ISPs are the next tier in terms of backbone access. Tier 2 ISPs can also be very large, even extending across several countries, but very few have networks that span entire continents or between continents. To provide their customers with global Internet access, some Tier 2 ISPs pay Tier 1 ISPs to carry their traffic to other parts of the world. Some Tier 2 ISPs exchange global traffic with other ISPs less expensively through <content-link target="{FEC67BD3-9C77-4138-BEED-10CE0C22ACB8}" type="glossary">public peer</content-link>ing at IXPs. A large IXP may bring together hundreds of ISPs in a central physical location for access to multiple networks over a shared connection. </li><li> <b><content-link target="{B1BA675C-CE87-482C-9FEC-106FC9B8AEFC}" type="glossary">Tier 3</content-link></b> ISPs are the farthest away from the backbone. Tier 3 ISPs are generally found in major cities and provide customers local access to the Internet. Tier 3 ISPs pay Tier 1 and 2 ISPs for access to the global Internet and Internet services.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0501020300">
<title><content-text>Using Tools to Map the Internet</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8816849425">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020301/cm8816849425.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020301/cm8816849425text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network utilities create a map of the various interconnections to visualize how ISP networks interconnect. These utilities also illustrate the speed at which each connecting point can be reached.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command tests the accessibility of a specific <content-link target="{7FA6D8E1-A8C2-46B6-8E83-C10A24FB02C5}" type="glossary">IP address</content-link>. The <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command sends an <content-link target="{820097F7-803A-4DE5-BD32-55EF3C3FA30F}" type="glossary">ICMP</content-link> (Internet Control Message Protocol) echo request <content-link target="{876AC4F1-3E66-4271-9502-4BC225A469B1}" type="glossary">packet</content-link> to the destination address and then waits for an echo reply packet to return from that host. ICMP is an Internet protocol that is used to verify communications. It measures the time that elapses between when the request packet is sent and the response packet is received. The <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command output indicates whether the reply was received successfully and displays the round-trip time for the transmissions. </p> <p>To use the <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command, enter the following command at the Cisco command line interface (CLI) router prompt or at the Windows command prompt:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ping</b> &lt;<i>ip address></i></span></p> <p>where <span class="cmd">&lt;<i>ip address> </i></span> is the IP address of the destination device.</p> <p>For example, <b><span class="cmd">ping 192.168.30.1</span></b>.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2681282342">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020302/cm2681282342.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020302/cm2681282342text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If a packet does not reach the destination, or if delays are encountered along the way, how is it determined where the problem is located or through which routers the packet has passed?</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> utility displays the path that a packet takes from the source to the destination host. Each router that the packet passes through is called a <content-link target="{6399A9B6-F32D-4F6F-929F-12664EAAFA8B}" type="glossary">hop</content-link>. Traceroute displays each hop along the way. It also calculates the time between when the packet is sent and when a reply is received from the router at each hop. </p> <p>If a problem occurs, use the output of the <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> utility to help determine where a packet was lost or delayed. The output also shows the various ISP organizations that the packet must pass through during its journey from source to destination.</p> <p>The Windows <span class="cmd"><b>tracert</b></span> utility works the same way. There are also a number of visual <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> programs that provide a graphical display of the route that a packet takes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm6042232704">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020303/cm6042232704/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020303/cm6042232704/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> to check ISP connectivity through the Internet.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501020304">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2667255269">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020304/cm2667255269/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0501000000/en0501020000/en0501020300/en0501020304/cm2667255269/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Interpret the output of <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span>.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0501030000">
<title><content-text>ISP Connectivity</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501030100">
<title><content-text>ISP Requirements</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5209714462">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030101/cm5209714462.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030101/cm5209714462text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>An ISP requires a variety of devices to accept input from end users and provide services. To participate in a transport network, the ISP must be able to connect to other ISPs. An ISP must also be able to handle large volumes of traffic.</p> <p>Some of the devices required to provide services include:</p> <p><ul><li> Access devices that enable end users to connect to the ISP, such as a DSL Access Multiplexer (DSLAM) for DSL connections, a Cable Modem Termination System (<content-link target="{3EF0148D-C112-4421-A729-B9EEB6F08605}" type="glossary">CMTS</content-link>) for cable connections, modems for dialup connections, or wireless bridging equipment for wireless access.</li><li> Border gateway routers to enable the ISP to connect and transfer data to other ISPs, IXPs, or large business <content-link target="{20515C80-7796-4CE6-91DE-BF51AD2CA193}" type="glossary">enterprise</content-link> customers. </li><li> Servers for such things as email, network address assignment, web space, FTP hosting, and multimedia hosting. </li><li> Power conditioning equipment with substantial battery backup to maintain continuity if the main power grid fails. </li><li> High capacity air conditioning units to maintain controlled temperatures.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3367243304">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030102/cm3367243304.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030102/cm3367243304text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs, like other businesses, want to expand so that they can increase their income. The ability to expand their business depends on gaining new subscribers and selling more services. However, as the number of subscribers grows, the traffic on the network of the ISP also grows.</p> <p>Eventually, the increased traffic may overload the network, causing router errors, lost packets, and excessive delays. In an overloaded network, subscribers can wait for minutes for a web page to load, or may even lose network connection. These customers may choose to switch to a competing ISP to get better performance.</p> <p>Loss of customers directly translates to loss of income for an ISP. For this reason, it is important that the ISP provides a <content-link target="{5144D653-522E-4AB0-8DFD-2AA96DB45650}" type="glossary">reliable</content-link> and scalable network. </p> <p><content-link target="{7FBA3003-B854-491D-867A-D7E40441DE41}" type="glossary">Scalability</content-link> is the capacity of a network to allow for future change and growth. Scalable networks can expand quickly to support new users and applications without affecting the performance of the service being delivered to existing users.</p> <p>The most scalable devices are those that are modular and provide expansion slots for adding modules. Different modules can have different numbers of ports. In the case of a chassis router, some modules also offer different interface options, allowing for different connection options on the same chassis.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501030103">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9656234084">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030103/cm9656234084/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030100/en0501030103/cm9656234084/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Identify appropriate equipment to meet the business needs of ISP customers.</p> <p>View <content-link target="1.3.1.3_printable-instructions.pdf" type="internalfile">printable instructions</content-link>.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0501030200">
<title><content-text>Roles and Responsibilities within an ISP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7638230782">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030201/cm7638230782.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030201/cm7638230782text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISP organizations consist of many teams and departments which are responsible for ensuring that the network operates smoothly and that the services are available.</p> <p>Network support services are involved in all aspects of network management, including planning and provisioning of new equipment and circuits, adding new subscribers, network repair and maintenance, and customer service for network <content-link target="{98B0BB4A-5DBA-4F46-A9B4-D4090E9700D3}" type="glossary">connectivity</content-link> issues.</p> <p>When a new business subscriber orders ISP services, the various network support service teams work together to ensure that the order is processed correctly and that the network is ready to deliver those services as quickly as possible. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501030202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1260362176">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030202/cm1260362176.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030202/cm1260362176text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Each of the network support service teams have their own roles and responsibilities:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Customer Service </b>receives the order from the customer and ensures that the specified requirements of the customer are accurately entered into the order tracking database. </li><li> <b>Planning and Provisioning </b>determines whether the new customer has existing network hardware and circuits and if new circuits need to be installed.</li><li> The<b> On-site Installation </b>is advised of which circuits and equipment to use and then installs them at the customer site.</li><li> The<b> Network Operations Center (NOC) </b>monitors and tests the new connection and ensures that it is performing properly.</li><li> The<b> Help Desk </b>is notified by the NOC when the circuit is ready for operation and then contacts the customer to guide them through the process of setting up passwords and other necessary account information.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0501030203">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm2633928468">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030203/cm2633928468.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501030000/en0501030200/en0501030203/cm2633928468text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Match the role to its description. </p><p><b>Drag the role to its defined description.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en0501040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0501040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm4473533506">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501040000/en0501040100/en0501040101/cm4473533506.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0501000000/en0501040000/en0501040100/en0501040101/cm4473533506text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en0501050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0501050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0501050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm3063357156">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0501000000/en0501050000/en0501050100/en0501050101/cm3063357156/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en0501000000/en0501050000/en0501050100/en0501050101/cm3063357156/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
