<chapter type="" id="en0508000000">
<title><content-text>ISP Responsibility</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en0508000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0508000101">
<content-media type="AnimationFullScreen" id="cm8245673602">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508000000/en0508000100/en0508000101/cm8245673602.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508000000/en0508000100/en0508000101/cm8245673602text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0508010000">
<title><content-text>ISP Security Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508010100">
<title><content-text>ISP Security Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2209812484">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010100/en0508010101/cm2209812484.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010100/en0508010101/cm2209812484text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Any active Internet connection for a computer can make that computer a target for malicious activity. <content-link target="{88A7F722-6CC4-443E-AFC6-C38112BAADA8}" type="glossary">Malware</content-link>, or malicious software such as a computer virus, <content-link target="{AAEE422F-04E1-4F5B-8098-A4583C83981A}" type="glossary">worm</content-link>, or <content-link target="{72B273A2-1A16-4882-A2CD-B5D76D8D576A}" type="glossary">spyware</content-link>, can arrive in an email or be downloaded from a website. Problems that cause large-scale failures in ISP networks often originate from unsecured desktop systems at the ISP customer locations. </p> <p>If the ISP is hosting any web or e-commerce sites, the ISP may have confidential files with financial data or bank account information stored on their servers. The ISP is required to maintain the customer data in a secure way. </p> <p>ISPs play a big role in helping to protect the home and business users that use their services. The security services that they provide also protect the servers that are located at the service provider premise. Service providers are often called upon to help their customers secure their local networks and workstations to reduce the risks of compromise.</p> <p>There are many actions that can be taken both at the local site and the ISP to secure operating systems, data stored on operating systems, and data transmitted between computer systems.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4513989115">	<title><content-text>Click each OS security practice for more information.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010100/en0508010102/cm4513989115.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010100/en0508010102/cm4513989115text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If an ISP is providing web hosting or email services for a customer, it is important that the ISP protect that information from malicious attack. This protection can be complicated because ISPs often use a single server, or cluster of servers, to maintain data that belongs to more than one customer.</p> <p>To help prevent attacks on these vulnerabilities, many ISPs provide managed desktop security services for their customers. An important part of the job of an on-site support technician is to implement security best practices on client computers. Some of the security services that an ISP support technician can provide include:</p> <p><ul><li> Helping clients to create secure passwords for devices</li><li> Securing applications using patch management and software upgrades</li><li> Removing unnecessary applications and services that can create vulnerabilities</li><li> Ensuring applications and services are available to the users that need them and no one else</li><li> Configuring desktop firewalls and virus-checking software</li><li> Performing security scans on software and services to determine vulnerabilities that the technician must protect from attack</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508010200">
<title><content-text>Security Practices</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2990948803">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010200/en0508010201/cm2990948803.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010200/en0508010201/cm2990948803text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is critical that ISPs have measures in place to protect the information of its customers from malicious attack. Common data security features and procedures include:</p> <p><ul><li> Encrypting data stored on server hard drives</li><li> Using permissions to secure access to files and folders</li><li> Permit or deny access based on the user account or group membership</li><li> Assign different levels of access permission based on the user account or group membership</li></ul></p> <p>When assigning permissions to files and folders, a security best practice is to apply permissions based on the "principle of least privilege". This means giving users access to only those resources that are required for them to be able do their job. It also means giving the appropriate level of permission, for example read-only access or write access. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2974020573">	<title><content-text>Click Play to view how AAA is used in a network.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010200/en0508010202/cm2974020573.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010200/en0508010202/cm2974020573text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><content-link target="{1B9DAB3F-15ED-49CA-B171-01AAE154B767}" type="glossary">Authentication</content-link>, <content-link target="{7B2EF5BC-E629-409D-A677-848FAEF71A65}" type="glossary">Authorization</content-link>, and <content-link target="{E1D29B4F-0805-434D-8AFC-E4BB18CCC937}" type="glossary">Accounting</content-link> (<content-link target="{DDDA5C93-71E2-4D7B-BF9D-0BD22518A2CD}" type="glossary">AAA</content-link>) is a three-step process used by network administrators to make it difficult for attackers to gain access to a network. </p> <p>Authentication requires users to prove their identity using a username and password. Authentication databases are typically stored on servers that use the RADIUS or TACACS protocols.</p> <p>Authorization gives users rights to access specific resources and perform specific tasks. </p> <p>Accounting tracks which applications are used and the length of time that they are used. </p> <p>For example, authentication acknowledges that a user named "student" exists and is able to log on. Authorization services specify that user student can access host server XYZ using Telnet. Accounting tracks that user student accessed host server XYZ using Telnet on a specific day for 15 minutes.</p> <p>AAA can be used on various types of network connections. AAA requires a database to keep track of user credentials, permissions, and account statistics. Local authentication is the simplest form of AAA and keeps a local database on the gateway router. If an organization has more than a handful of users authenticating with AAA, the organization must use a database on a separate server.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508010300">
<title><content-text>Data Encryption</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3882314097">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010301/cm3882314097.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010301/cm3882314097text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs must also be concerned with securing data that is transmitted to and from their servers. By default, data sent over the network is unsecured and transmitted in clear text. Unauthorized individuals can intercept unsecured data as it is being transmitted. Capturing data in transit bypasses all file system security that is set on the data. There are methods available to protect against this security issue.</p> <p><b>Encryption</b></p> <p><content-link target="{8F3C8E8D-052A-4A5C-BF00-3239380BC330}" type="glossary">Digital encryption</content-link> is the process of encrypting all transmitted data between the client and the server. Many of the protocols used to transmit data offer a secure version that uses digital encryption. As a best practice, use the secure version of a protocol whenever the data being exchanged between two computers is confidential. </p> <p>For example, if a user must submit a username and password to log on to an e-commerce website, a secure protocol is required to protect the username and password information from being captured. Secure protocols are also needed any time a user must submit a credit card or bank account information. </p> <p>When surfing the Internet and viewing publicly accessible websites, securing the transmitted data is not necessary. Using a secure protocol in this situation can lead to additional computational overhead and slower response time.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3081709660">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010302/cm3081709660.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010302/cm3081709660text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are many network protocols used by applications. Some offer secure versions and some do not:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Web servers</b> - Web servers use HTTP by default, which is not a secure protocol. Using HTTPS, which uses the secure socket layer (SSL) protocol, enables the exchange of data to be performed securely. </li><li> <b>Email servers</b> - Email servers use several different protocols, including SMTP, POP3, and IMAP4. When a user logs on to an email server, POP3 and IMAP4 require a username and password for authentication. By default, this information is sent without security and can be captured. POP3 can be secured by using SSL. SMTP and IMAP4 can use either SSL or Transport Layer Security (<content-link target="{17E04ADB-7AB0-4DC3-873B-8DCA905924EA}" type="glossary">TLS</content-link>) as a security protocol.</li><li> <b>Telnet servers</b> - Using Telnet to remotely log into a Cisco router or switch creates an unsecure connection. Telnet sends authentication information and any commands a user types across the network in clear text. Use the Secure Shell (SSH) protocol to authenticate and work with the router or switch securely.</li><li> <b>FTP servers</b> - FTP is also an unsecure protocol. When logging into an FTP server, authentication information is sent in clear text. FTP can use SSL to securely exchange authentication and data. Some versions of FTP can also use SSH.</li><li> <b>File servers</b> - File servers can use many different protocols to exchange data, depending on the computer operating system. In most cases, file server protocols do not offer a secure version.</li></ul></p> <p>IP Security (<content-link target="{9CEC12F9-4AA1-489C-AF43-2FA09D4EF6B5}" type="glossary">IPSec</content-link>) is another Network Layer security protocol that can be used to secure any Application Layer protocol used for communication. This includes file server protocols that do not offer any other security protocol version.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508010303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7622145441">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010303/cm7622145441/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508010000/en0508010300/en0508010303/cm7622145441/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Perform the data security tasks needed to analyze and secure local and transmitted data.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0508020000">
<title><content-text>Security Tools</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508020100">
<title><content-text>Access Control Lists and Port Filtering</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm1675516779">	<title><content-text>Click each denial of service attack to see how the attack occurs.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020101/cm1675516779.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020101/cm1675516779text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Even with the use of AAA and encryption, there are still many different types of attacks that an ISP must protect against. ISPs are especially vulnerable to denial-of-service (<content-link target="{51FF954C-D290-4789-9B27-B2ACB3ADD7B2}" type="glossary">DoS</content-link>) attacks, because the ISP may host sites for many different registered domain names that may or may not require authentication. Currently, there are three key types of DoS attacks.</p> <p><b>DoS</b></p> <p>A standard DoS attack is when a server or service is attacked to prevent legitimate access to that service. Some examples of standard DoS attacks are <content-link target="{FF57CEED-3D6B-4F82-B4E7-CD26B4E087B9}" type="glossary">SYN flood</content-link>s, ping floods, <content-link target="{88F6252B-6329-40F9-9EE0-9DF571FF339B}" type="glossary">LAND attack</content-link>s, bandwidth consumption attacks, and <content-link target="{E67EF1AA-47E4-456D-84DA-3049BE1A6D11}" type="glossary">buffer overflow attack</content-link>s.</p> <p><b>DDoS</b></p> <p>A distributed denial-of-service (<content-link target="{6D042E58-B8BC-4B88-A41A-DB725D86551A}" type="glossary">DDoS</content-link>) attack occurs when multiple computers are used to attack a specific target. The attacker has access to many compromised computer systems, usually on the Internet. Because of this, the attacker can remotely launch the attack. DDoS attacks are usually the same kinds of attacks as standard DoS attacks, except that DDoS attacks are run from many computer systems simultaneously.</p> <p><b>DRDoS</b></p> <p>A distributed reflected denial-of-service (DRDoS) attack occurs when an attacker sends a spoofed, or mock, request to many computer systems on the Internet, with the source address modified to be the targeted computer system. The computer systems that receive the request respond. When the computer systems respond to the request, all the requests are directed at the target computer system. Because the attack is reflected, it is very difficult to determine the originator of the attack.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6956548266">	<title><content-text>Click each security method for more information on port filtering and access lists.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020102/cm6956548266.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020102/cm6956548266text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs must be able to filter out network traffic, such as DoS attacks, that can be harmful to the operation of their network or servers. <content-link target="{55013E50-F431-46C0-B2EE-D3260198C6AE}" type="glossary">Port filter</content-link>ing and access control lists (<content-link target="{DC5DF43E-EADD-418E-9B4E-E946D75B7849}" type="glossary">ACL</content-link>) can be used to control traffic to servers and networking equipment. </p> <p><b>Port Filtering</b></p> <p>Port filtering controls the flow of traffic based on a specific TCP or UDP port. Many server operating systems have options to restrict access using port filtering. Port filtering is also used by network routers and switches to help control traffic flow and to secure access to the device.</p> <p><b>Access Control Lists</b></p> <p>ACLs define traffic that is permitted or denied through the network based on the source and destination IP addresses. ACLs can also permit or deny traffic based on the source and destination ports of the protocol being used. Additonally, ICMP and routing update traffic can be controlled using ACLs. Administrators create ACLs on network devices, such as routers, to control whether or not traffic is forwarded or blocked.</p> <p>ACLs are only the first line of defense and are not enough to secure a network. ACLs only prevent access to a network; they do not protect the network from all types of malicious attacks.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020103">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5318530561">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020103/cm5318530561/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020100/en0508020103/cm5318530561/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Determine where to implement ACLs and port filters to help protect the network.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508020200">
<title><content-text>Firewalls</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4811631382">	<title><content-text>Click each type of firewall for more information.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020201/cm4811631382.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020201/cm4811631382text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A firewall is network hardware or software that defines which traffic can come into and go out of sections of the network and how traffic is handled. </p> <p>ACLs are one of the tools used by firewalls. ACLs control which type of traffic is allowed to pass through the firewall. The direction the traffic is allowed to travel can also be controlled. In a medium-sized network, the amount of traffic and networking protocols needing to be controlled is quite large, and firewall ACLs can become very complicated. </p> <p>Firewalls use ACLs to control which traffic is passed or blocked. They are constantly evolving as new capabilities are developed and new threats are discovered. </p> <p>Different firewalls offer different types of features. For example, a dynamic packet filter firewall or stateful firewall keeps track of the actual communication process occurring between the source and destination devices. It does this by using a state table. When a communication stream is approved, only traffic that belongs to one of these communication streams is permitted through the firewall. The Cisco IOS Firewall software is embedded in the Cisco IOS software and allows the user to turn a router into a network layer firewall with dynamic or stateful inspection. </p> <p>Firewalls are constantly evolving as new capabilities are developed and new threats are discovered. The more functionality embedded in a firewall, the more time it takes for packets to be processed.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3849609736">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020202/cm3849609736.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020202/cm3849609736text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Firewalls can provide perimeter security for the entire network and for internal local network segments, such as server farms. </p> <p>Within an ISP network or a medium-sized business, firewalls are typically implemented in multiple layers. Traffic that comes in from an untrusted network first encounters a packet filter on the border router. Permitted traffic goes through the border router to an internal firewall to route traffic to a demilitarized zone (<content-link target="{C623F044-8C3E-48E3-921C-5D6443DBA77F}" type="glossary">DMZ</content-link>). A DMZ is used to store servers that users from the Internet are allowed to access. Only traffic that is permitted access to these servers is permitted into the DMZ. Firewalls also control what kind of traffic is permitted into the protected, local network itself. The traffic that is allowed into the internal network is usually traffic that is being sent due to a specific request by an internal device. For example, if an internal device requests a web page from an external server, the firewall permits the requested web page to enter the internal network. </p> <p>Some organizations can choose to implement internal firewalls to protect sensitive areas. Internal firewalls are used to restrict access to areas of the network that need to have additional protection. Internal firewalls separate and protect business resources on servers from users inside the organization. Internal firewalls prevent external and internal hackers, as well as unintentional internal attacks and malware.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020203">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1706627881">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020203/cm1706627881/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020200/en0508020203/cm1706627881/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>In this activity, you are a technician who provides network support for a medium-sized business. The business has grown and includes a research and development department working on a new, very confidential project. The livelihood of the project depends on protecting the data used by the research and development team. Your job is to install firewalls to help protect the network, based on specific requirements.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508020300">
<title><content-text>IDS and IPS</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7220089450">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020301/cm7220089450.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020301/cm7220089450text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs also have a responsibility to prevent, when possible, intrusions into their networks and the networks of customers who purchase managed services. There are two tools often utilized by ISPs to accomplish this. </p> <p><b>Intrusion Detection System (IDS)</b></p> <p>An <content-link target="{A1789CD3-CBC3-4D5A-A421-56522FB012A9}" type="glossary">IDS</content-link> is a software- or hardware-based solution that passively listens to network traffic. Network traffic does not pass through an IDS device. Instead, the IDS device monitors traffic through a network interface. When the IDS detects malicious traffic, it sends an alert to a preconfigured management station.</p> <p><b>Intrusion Prevention System (IPS)</b></p> <p>An <content-link target="{3F48CA60-31E1-48E1-9872-F653DE5BFAA1}" type="glossary">IPS</content-link> is an active physical device or software feature. Traffic travels in one interface of the IPS and out the other. The IPS examines the actual data packets that are in the network traffic and works in real time to permit or deny packets that want access into the network</p> <p>IDS and IPS technologies are deployed as sensors. An IDS or an IPS sensor can be any of the following:</p> <p><ul><li> Router configured with Cisco IOS version IPS</li><li> Appliance (hardware) specifically designed to provide dedicated IDS or IPS services </li><li> Network module installed in an adaptive security appliance (ASA), switch, or router</li></ul></p> <p>IDS and IPS sensors respond differently to incidences detected on the network, but both have roles within a network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020302">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1009122156">	<title><content-text>Click Play to see how an IDS works to protect a network.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020302/cm1009122156.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020302/cm1009122156text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>IDS solutions are reactive when it comes to detecting intrusions. They detect intrusions based on a <content-link target="{F873AC17-D30D-4317-8AD6-8EAFE4E00F3E}" type="glossary">signature</content-link> for network traffic or computer activity. They do not stop the initial traffic from passing through to the destination, but react to the detected activity. </p> <p>When properly configured, the IDS can block further malicious traffic by actively reconfiguring network devices, such as security appliances or routers, in response to malicious traffic detection. It is important to realize that the original malicious traffic has already passed through the network to the intended destination and cannot be blocked. Only subsequent traffic is blocked. In this regard, IDS devices cannot prevent some intrusions from being successful.</p> <p>IDS solutions are often used on the untrusted perimeter of a network, outside of the firewall. Here the IDS can analyze the type of traffic that is hitting the firewall and determine how attacks are executed. The firewall can be used to block most malicious traffic. An IDS can also be placed inside the firewall to detect firewall misconfigurations. When the IDS sensor is placed here, any alarms that go off indicate that malicious traffic has been allowed through the firewall. These alarms mean that the firewall has not been configured correctly.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020303">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5617100444">	<title><content-text>Click Play to see how IPS works to protect a network.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020303/cm5617100444.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020303/cm5617100444text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>IPS</b></p> <p>Unlike IDS solutions, which are reactive, IPS solutions are proactive. They block all suspicious activity in real time. An IPS is able to examine almost the entire data packet from Layer 2 to Layer 7 of the OSI model. When the IPS detects malicious traffic, it blocks the malicious traffic immediately. The IPS then sends an alert to a management station about the intrusion. The original and subsequent malicious traffic is blocked as the IPS proactively prevents attacks. </p> <p>An IPS is an intrusion detection appliance, not software. The IPS is most often placed inside the firewall. This is because it can examine most of the data packet and, therefore, be used to protect server applications if malicious traffic is being sent. The firewall typically does not examine the entire data packet, whereas the IPS does. The firewall drops most of the packets that are not allowed, but may still allow some malicious packets through. The IPS has a smaller number of packets to examine, so it can examine the entire packet. This allows the IPS to immediately stop new attacks that the firewall was not originally configured to deny. IPS can also stop attacks that the firewall is unable to deny based on limitations of the firewall.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0508020304">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm9701423981">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020304/cm9701423981.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020300/en0508020304/cm9701423981text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Determine how to protect the network from intrusions using IPS and IDS network equipment.</p><p><b>Instructional Text (if any):</b></p> <p><b>Click each statement that applies.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508020400">
<title><content-text>Wireless Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5179173737">	<title><content-text>Click each method of securing your wireless network for more information.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020401/cm5179173737.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020401/cm5179173737text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Some ISPs offer services to create wireless hot spots for customers to log on to wireless local-area networks (<content-link target="{F782C3BA-C23C-4343-9CB8-7B470C5732B2}" type="glossary">WLAN</content-link>s). A wireless network is easy to implement, but is vulnerable when not properly configured. Because the wireless signal travels through walls, it can be accessed outside the business premises. A wireless network can be secured by changing the default settings, enabling authentication, or enabling MAC address filtering.</p> <p><b>Changing Default Settings</b></p> <p>The default values for the SSID, usernames, and passwords on a wireless access point should be changed. Additionally, broadcasting of the SSID should be disabled. </p> <p><b>Enabling Authentication</b></p> <p>Authentication is the process of permitting entry to a network based on a set of credentials. It is used to verify that the device attempting to connect to the network is trusted. There are three types of authentication methods that can be used:</p>  <p><ul><li> <b>Open authentication </b>- Any and all clients are able to have access regardless of who they are. Open authentication is most often used on public wireless networks. </li><li> <b>Pre-shared key (<content-link target="{9E7D841C-291F-42B6-94E8-7BF72C1978D7}" type="glossary">PSK</content-link>)</b> - Requires a matching, preconfigured key on both the server and the client. When connecting, the access point sends a random string of bytes to the client. The client accepts the string, encrypts it (or scrambles it) based on the key, and sends it back to the access point. The access point gets the encrypted string and uses its key to decrypt (or unscramble) it. If they match, authentication is successful.</li><li> <b>Extensible Authentication Protocol (<content-link target="{649B2BB5-3BBA-4122-9658-F20348AF2345}" type="glossary">EAP</content-link>)</b> - Provides mutual, or two-way, authentication and user authentication. When EAP software is installed on the client, the client communicates with a backend authentication server, such as RADIUS. </li></ul></p> <p><b>Enabling MAC Address Filtering</b></p> <p>MAC address filtering prevents unwanted computers from connecting to a network by restricting MAC addresses. It is possible, however, to clone a MAC address. Therefore, other security measures should be implemented along with MAC address filtering.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020402">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5845476976"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020402/cm6429545348.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020402/cm6429545348text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is important to set encryption on transmitted packets sent across a wireless network. There are three major encryption types for wireless networks: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>WEP</b> - Wired Equivalent Privacy (<content-link target="{AF9B3597-EAF2-4F4C-A118-3BEE38FB7BBF}" type="glossary">WEP</content-link>) provides data security by encrypting data that is sent between wireless nodes. WEP uses a 64, 128, or 256 bit pre-shared hexadecimal key to encrypt the data. A major weakness of WEP is its use of static encryption keys. The same key is used by every device to encrypt every packet transmitted. There are many WEP cracking tools available on the Internet. WEP should be used only with older equipment that does not support newer wireless security protocols. </li><li> <b>WPA</b> - Wifi Protected Access (<content-link target="{20E9D8C0-A123-468D-8D6B-B2363A735F53}" type="glossary">WPA</content-link>) is a newer wireless encryption protocol that uses an improved encryption algorithm called Temporal Key Integrity Protocol (<content-link target="{511F98C4-11BA-4DDE-BBE8-AA345071FD1F}" type="glossary">TKIP</content-link>). TKIP generates a unique key for each client and rotates the security keys at a configurable interval. WPA provides a mechanism for mutual authentication. Because both the client and the access point have the key, it is never transmitted.</li><li> <b>WPA2</b> - WPA2 is a new, improved version of WPA. WPA2 uses the more secure Advanced Encryption Standard (<content-link target="{53A43FDA-9D5E-4B71-9104-B2845BFE7B6F}" type="glossary">AES</content-link>) technology.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020403">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2730736021">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020403/cm2730736021/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020400/en0508020403/cm2730736021/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>In this activity, you will configure WEP security on both a Linksys wireless router and a workstation. </p> <p>*Note: WPA is not supported by Packet tracer at this time. However, WEP and WPA are enabled by a similar process.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508020500">
<title><content-text>Host Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4652244688">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020501/cm4652244688.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020501/cm4652244688text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Regardless of the layers of defense that exist on the network, all servers are still susceptible to attack if they are not properly secured. ISP servers are especially vulnerable because they are generally accessible from the Internet. New vulnerabilities for servers are discovered every day, so it is critical for an ISP to protect its servers from known and unknown vulnerabilities whenever possible. One way they accomplish this is by using host-based firewalls.</p> <p>A host-based firewall is software that runs directly on a host operating system. It protects the host from malicious attacks that might have made it through all other layers of defense. Host-based firewalls control inbound and outbound network traffic. These firewalls allow filtering based on a computer address and port, therefore offering additional protection over regular port filtering.</p> <p>Host-based firewalls typically come with predefined rules that block all incoming network traffic. Exceptions are added to the firewall rule set to permit the correct mixture of inbound and outbound network traffic. When enabling host-based firewalls, it is important to balance the need to allow the network resources required to complete job tasks, with the need to prevent applications from being left vulnerable to malicious attacks. Many server operating systems are preconfigured with a simple host-based firewall with limited options. More advanced third-party packages are also available. </p> <p>ISPs use host-based firewalls to restrict access to the specific services a server offers. By using a host-based firewall, the ISP protects their servers and the data of their customers by blocking access to the extraneous ports that are available.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020502">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8385273442">	<title><content-text>Click each type of attack for more information.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020502/cm8385273442.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020502/cm8385273442text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISP servers that utilize host-based firewalls are protected from a variety of different types of attacks and vulnerabilities.</p> <p><b>Known Attacks</b></p> <p>Host-based firewalls recognize malicious activity based on updatable signatures or patterns. They detect a known attack and block traffic on the port used by the attack. </p> <p><b>Exploitable Services</b></p> <p>Host-based firewalls protect exploitable services running on servers by preventing access to the ports that the service is using. Some host-based firewalls can also inspect the contents of a packet to see if it contains malicious code. Web and email servers are common targets for service exploits, and can be protected if the host-based firewall is capable of performing packet inspection. </p> <p><b>Worms and Viruses</b></p> <p>Worms and viruses propagate by exploiting vulnerabilities in services and other weaknesses in operating systems. Host-based firewalls prevent this malware from gaining access to servers. They can also help prevent the spread of worms and viruses by controlling outbound traffic originating from a server.</p> <p><b>Back Doors and Trojans</b></p> <p><content-link target="{B7836B22-A515-4AB0-B60D-E6E133E09A8C}" type="glossary">Back door</content-link>s and <content-link target="{14B7B29C-55B3-4218-80C7-7F6728C3D10C}" type="glossary">Trojan Horse</content-link>s allow hackers to remotely gain access to servers on a network. The software typically works by sending a message to let the hacker know of a successful infection. It then provides a service that the hacker can use to gain access to the system. Host-based firewalls can prevent a Trojan from sending a message by limiting outbound network access. It can also prevent the attacker from connecting to any services.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020503">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2408729470">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020503/cm2408729470.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020503/cm2408729470text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to host-based firewalls, anti-X software can be installed as a more comprehensive security measure. Anti-X software protects computer systems from viruses, worms, spyware, malware, <content-link target="{C36EDA9E-116E-4A30-B1E1-A1CC5801F886}" type="glossary">phishing</content-link>, and even <content-link target="{36BFEB64-6F64-48CD-B5F1-F4241243EFD4}" type="glossary">spam</content-link>. Many ISPs offer customers anti-X software as part of their comprehensive security services. Not all anti-X software protects against the same threats. The ISP should constantly review which threats the anti-X software actually protects against and make recommendations based on a threat analysis of the company.</p> <p>Many anti-X software packages allow for remote management. This includes a notification system that can alert the administrator or support technician about an infection via email or pager. Immediate notification to the proper individual can drastically reduce the impact of the infection. Using anti-X software does not diminish the number of threats to the network but reduces the risk of being infected.</p> <p>Occasionally infections and attacks still occur and can be very destructive. It is important to have an incident management process to track all incidences and the corresponding resolutions to help prevent the infection from reoccurring. Incident management is required by ISPs that manage and maintain customer data, because the ISP has committed to the protection and the integrity of the data they host for their customers. For example, if the ISP network was the target of a hacker and, as a result, thousands of credit card numbers that were stored in a database that the ISP manages were stolen, the customer would need to be notified so that they could notify the card holders.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508020504">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1301130749">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020504/cm1301130749/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508020000/en0508020500/en0508020504/cm1301130749/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Recommend an anti-X software package for a small business.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0508030000">
<title><content-text>Monitoring and Managing the ISP</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508030100">
<title><content-text>Service Level Agreements</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5671277119">	<title><content-text>Roll over the parts of the SLA for more information.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030100/en0508030101/cm5671277119.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030100/en0508030101/cm5671277119text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>An ISP and a user usually have a contract known as a service level agreement (SLA). It documents the expectations and obligations of both parties. An SLA typically includes the following parts:</p> <p><ul><li> Service description</li><li> Costs</li><li> Tracking and reporting </li><li> Problem management</li><li> Security </li><li> Termination</li><li> Penalties for service outages</li><li> Availability, performance, and reliability</li></ul></p> <p>The SLA is an important document that clearly outlines the management, monitoring, and maintenance of a network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030102">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm6759690321">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030100/en0508030102/cm6759690321/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030100/en0508030102/cm6759690321/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Examine an SLA and practice interpreting the sections of the SLA.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508030200">
<title><content-text>Monitoring Network Link Performance</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1700342012">	<title><content-text>Click Play to view an example of in-band versus out-of-band management.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030200/en0508030201/cm1700342012.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030200/en0508030201/cm1700342012text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The ISP is responsible for monitoring and checking device connectivity. This responsibility includes any equipment that belongs to the ISP and equipment at the customer end that the ISP agreed to monitor in the SLA. Monitoring and configuration can be performed either out-of-band with a direct console connection, or in-band using a network connection. </p> <p>Out-of-band management is useful in initial configurations if the device is not accessible via the network, or if a visual inspection of the device is necessary. </p> <p>Most ISPs are not able to visually inspect or have physical access to all devices. An in-band management tool allows for easier administration because the technician does not require a physical connection. For this reason, in-band management is preferred over out-of-band management for managing servers and networking devices that are accessible on the network. Additionally, conventional in-band tools can provide more management functionality than may be possible with out-of-band management, such as an overall view of the network design. Traditional in-band management protocols include Telnet, SSH, HTTP, and Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP).</p> <p>There are many embedded tools, commercial tools, and shareware tools available that use these management protocols. For example, HTTP access is through a web browser. Some applications, such as Cisco SDM, use this access for in-band management.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1382009058">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030200/en0508030202/cm1382009058/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030200/en0508030202/cm1382009058/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Download, install, and then conduct a network capture with Wireshark.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508030300">
<title><content-text>Device Management Using In-band Tools</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1172095799">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030301/cm1172095799.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030301/cm1172095799text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After a new network device is installed at the customer premise, it must be monitored from the remote ISP location. There are times that minor configuration changes need to be made without the physical presence of a technician at the customer site.</p> <p>A Telnet client can be used over an IP network connection to connect to a device in-band for the purpose of monitoring and administering it. A connection using Telnet is called a Virtual Terminal (VTY) session or connection. Telnet is a client/server protocol. The connecting device runs the Telnet client. To support Telnet client connections, the connected device, or server, runs a service called a Telnet daemon.</p> <p>Most operating systems include an Application Layer Telnet client. On a Microsoft Windows PC, Telnet can be run from the command prompt. Other common terminal emulation applications that run as Telnet clients are HyperTerminal, Minicom, and TeraTerm. Devices such as routers run both the Telnet client and the Telnet daemon, and can act as either the client or server.</p> <p>After a Telnet connection is established, users can perform any authorized function on the server, just as if they were using a command line session on the server itself. If authorized, users can start and stop processes, configure the device, and even shut down the system.</p> <p>A Telnet session can be initiated using the router CLI with the <span class="cmd"><b>telnet</b></span> command followed by the IP address or domain name. A Telnet client can connect to multiple servers simultaneously. On a Cisco router, the keystroke sequence Ctrl-Shift-6 X to toggles between Telnet sessions. Additionally, a Telnet server can support multiple client connections. On a router acting as a server, the <span class="cmd"><b>show sessions</b></span> command displays all client connections.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9484162007">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030302/cm9484162007/" mime="application/pdf" scale="false" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030302/cm9484162007/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use Telnet to manage remote network devices.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030303">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5494086573">	<title><content-text>Roll over the network technician for an example of a Syslog application.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030303/cm5494086573.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030303/cm5494086573text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>While the Telnet protocol supports user authentication, it does not support the transport of encrypted data. All data exchanged during a Telnet session is transported as plain text across the network. This means that the data can be intercepted and easily understood, including the username and password used to authenticate the device.</p> <p>If security is a concern, the Secure Shell (SSH) protocol offers an alternate and secure method for server access. SSH provides secure remote login and other network services. It also provides stronger authentication than Telnet and supports the transport of session data using encryption. As a best practice, network professionals should always use SSH in place of Telnet whenever possible.</p> <p>There are two versions of the SSH server service. Which SSH version is supported depends on the Cisco IOS image loaded on the device. There are many different SSH client software packages available for PCs. An SSH client must support the SSH version configured on the server.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030304">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3679442121">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030304/cm3679442121/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030300/en0508030304/cm3679442121/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure a remote router using SSH.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508030400">
<title><content-text>Using SNMP and Syslog</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9326364897">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030401/cm9326364897.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030401/cm9326364897text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>SNMP is a network management protocol that enables administrators to gather data about the network and corresponding devices. SNMP management system software is available in tools such as <content-link target="{488AFBC4-A056-4779-A857-2FE869F77FF3}" type="glossary">CiscoWorks</content-link>. There are free versions of CiscoWorks available for download on the Internet. SNMP management agent software is often embedded in operating systems on servers, routers, and switches. </p> <p>SNMP is made up of four main components:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Management station</b> - Computer with the SNMP management application loaded that is used by the administrator to monitor and configure the network.</li><li> <b>Management agent</b> - Software installed on a device managed by SNMP.</li><li> <b>Management Information Base</b> (<content-link target="{BECFF5A0-50AF-4507-9083-90AF48A24033}" type="glossary">MIB</content-link>) - Database that a device keeps about itself concerning network performance parameters.</li><li> <b>Network management protocol</b> - Communication protocol used between the management station and the management agent.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030402">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2561337784">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030402/cm2561337784.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030402/cm2561337784text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The management station contains the SNMP management applications that the administrator uses to configure devices on the network. It also stores data about those devices. The management station collects information by polling the devices. A poll occurs when the management station requests specific information from an agent. </p> <p>The agent reports to the management station by responding to the polls. When the management station polls an agent, the agent calls on statistics that have accumulated in the MIB.</p> <p>Agents can also be configured with traps. A <content-link target="{6C540930-B159-44A2-8E54-121D4BB72EBF}" type="glossary">trap</content-link> is an alarm-triggering event. Certain areas of the agent are configured with thresholds, or maximums, that must be maintained, such as the amount of traffic that can access a specific port. If the threshold is exceeded, the agent sends an alert message to the management station. Traps free the management station from continuously polling network devices. </p> <p>Management stations and managed devices are identified by a community ID, called a community string. The community string on the SMNP agent must match the community string on the SMNP management station. When an agent is required to send information to a management station due to a poll or trap event, it will first verify the management station using the community string.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508030403">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm1372097041">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030403/cm1372097041.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508030000/en0508030400/en0508030403/cm1372097041text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Storing <content-link target="{35BBC7E5-9B71-421A-9673-08FB3887C3AA}" type="glossary">device log</content-link>s and reviewing them periodically is an important part of network monitoring. <content-link target="{2042B77E-D9A2-4EBA-828D-CA928E74132F}" type="glossary">Syslog</content-link> is the standard for logging system events. Like SNMP, syslog is an Application Layer protocol that enables devices to send information to a <content-link target="{960D589E-E60D-4DA3-A9FC-CE7F7C8B54B2}" type="glossary">syslog daemon</content-link> that is installed and running on a management station.</p> <p>A syslog system is composed of syslog servers and syslog clients. These servers accept and process log messages from syslog clients. A syslog client is a monitored device that generates and forwards log messages to syslog servers.</p> <p>Log messages normally consist of a ID, type of message, a time stamp (date, time), which device has sent the message, and the message text. Depending on which network equipment is sending the syslog messages, it can contain more items than those listed.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0508040000">
<title><content-text>Backups and Disaster Recovery</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508040100">
<title><content-text>Backup Media</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm1931558644">	<title><content-text>Click each data loss problem to learn more.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040101/cm1931558644.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040101/cm1931558644text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network management and monitoring software helps ISPs and businesses identify and correct network issues. This software can also help to correct the causes of network failures, such as those caused by malware and malicious activity, network functionality, and failed devices. </p> <p>Regardless of the cause of failure, an ISP that hosts websites or email for customers must protect the web and email content from being lost. Losing the data stored on a website could mean hundreds, or even thousands, of hours recreating the content, not to mention the lost business that results from the downtime while the content is being restored. </p> <p>Losing email messages that were stored on the ISP email server could potentially be devastating for a business that relies on the data within the emails. Some businesses are legally required to maintain records of all email correspondence, so losing email data is not acceptable.</p> <p>Data backup is essential. The job of an IT professional is to reduce the risks of data loss and provide mechanisms for quick recovery of any data that is lost.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5693350274">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040102/cm5693350274.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040102/cm5693350274text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When an ISP needs to back up its data, the cost of a backup solution and its effectiveness must be balanced. The choice of backup media can be complex because there are many factors that affect the choice. </p> <p>Some of the factors include:</p> <p><ul><li> Amount of data </li><li> Cost of media</li><li> Performance of media</li><li> Reliability of media</li><li> Ease of offsite storage</li></ul></p> <p>There are many types of backup media available, including tapes, optical discs, hard disks, and solid state devices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5224246964">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040103/cm5224246964.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040103/cm5224246964text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Tape remains one of the most common types of backup media available. Tapes have large capacities and remain the most cost-effective media on the market. For data volumes in excess of a single tape, autoloaders and libraries can swap tapes during the backup procedure, allowing the data to be stored on as many tapes as required. These devices can be expensive and are not typically found in small to medium-sized businesses. However, depending on the volume of data, there may be no alternative other than an autoloader or library.</p> <p>Tape media is prone to failure, and tape drives require regular cleaning to maintain functionality. Tapes also have a high failure rate because they wear out through use. Tapes should only be used for a fixed amount of time before removing them from circulation. Some of the different types of tapes are:</p> <p><ul><li> Digital data storage (DDS)</li><li> Digital audio tape (DAT)</li><li> Digital linear tape (DLT)</li><li> Linear tape-open (LTO)</li></ul></p> <p>Each type has different capacities and performance characteristics.</p> <p><b>Optical Media Discs</b></p> <p><content-link target="{62339A52-29D4-41ED-8316-E26C9E69D8BB}" type="glossary">Optical media</content-link> is a common choice for smaller amounts of data. CDs have a storage capacity of 700 MB, DVDs can support up to 8.5 GB on a single-sided dual layer disc, and HD-DVD and Blu-Ray discs can have capacities in excess of 25 GB per disc. ISPs may use optical media for transferring web content data to their customers. Customers may also use this media to transfer website content to the ISP web hosting site. Optical media can easily be accessed by any computer system with a CD or DVD drive.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1627541917">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040104/cm1627541917.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040100/en0508040104/cm1627541917text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Hard Disks</b></p> <p>Hard disk-based backup systems are becoming more and more popular because of the low cost of high-capacity drives. However, hard disks make offsite storage difficult. Large disk arrays such as direct attached storage (<content-link target="{5FAA28E6-2F12-45E4-82F9-71A0646B0D86}" type="glossary">DAS</content-link>), network attached storage (<content-link target="{E1A708B9-E80A-48D0-AE7B-1314F31C3BAC}" type="glossary">NAS</content-link>), and storage area networks (<content-link target="{B5096E2A-A725-4C83-901F-3FC0A48AA545}" type="glossary">SAN</content-link>s) are not transportable. </p> <p>Many implementations of hard disk-based backup systems work in conjunction with tape backup systems for offsite storage. Using both hard disks and tapes in a <content-link target="{236A1B42-5458-413D-B228-5F2F5438503C}" type="glossary">tiered backup</content-link> solution provides a quick restore time with the data available locally on the hard disks combined with a long-term archival solution.</p> <p><b>Solid State Storage Devices</b></p> <p><content-link target="{A711C83F-6B99-4198-8C12-87FA40BEC2D5}" type="glossary">Solid state storage</content-link> refers to all nonvolatile storage media that does not have any moving parts. Examples of solid state media range from small postage-stamp-sized drives holding 1 GB of data, to router-sized packages capable of storing 1000 GB (1TB) of data. </p> <p>Solid state devices are ideal when fast storage and retrieval of data is important. Applications for solid state data storage systems include database acceleration, high-definition video access and editing, data retrieval, and SANS. High-capacity solid state storage devices can be extremely expensive, but as the technology matures, the prices will come down.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508040200">
<title><content-text>Methods of File Backup</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4834248779">	<title><content-text>Click Play to view how backups work.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040201/cm4834248779.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040201/cm4834248779text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After backup media is chosen, a backup method must be selected. </p> <p><b>Normal </b></p> <p>A normal, or full, backup copies all selected files, in their entirety. Each file is then marked as having been backed up. With normal backups, only the most recent backup is required to restore files. This speeds up and simplifies the restore process. However, because all data is backed up, a full backup takes the most amount of time.</p> <p><b>Differential</b></p> <p>A <content-link target="{CA76CE6B-92E6-4771-A5FB-2641D8660D11}" type="glossary">differential backup</content-link> copies only the files that have been changed since the last full backup. With differential backups, a full backup on the first day of the backup cycle is necessary. Only the files that are created or changed since the time of the last full backup are then saved. The differential backup process continues until another full backup is run. This reduces the amount of time required to perform the backup. When it is time to restore data, the last normal backup is restored and the latest differential backup restores all changed files since the last full backup.</p> <p><b>Incremental</b></p> <p>An <content-link target="{527F6978-DC1A-4610-AA0F-C284FEE4ADA8}" type="glossary">incremental backup</content-link> differs from a differential backup on one important point. Whereas a differential backup saves files that were changed since the last full backup, an incremental backup only saves files that were created or changed since the last incremental backup. This means that if an incremental backup is run every day, the backup media would only contain files created or changed on that day. Incremental backups are the quickest backup. However, they take the longest time to restore because the last normal backup and every incremental backup since the last full backup must be restored.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8262135267">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040202/cm8262135267.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040202/cm8262135267text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Backup systems require regular maintenance to keep them running properly. There are measures that help to ensure that backups are successful:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Swap media</b> - Many backup scenarios require daily swapping of media to maintain a history of backed up data. Data loss could occur if the tape or disk is not swapped daily. Because swapping the tapes is a manual task, it is prone to failure. Users need to use a notification method, such as calendar or task scheduling.</li><li> <b>Review backup logs</b> - Virtually all backup software produces logs. These logs report on the success of the backup or specify where it failed. Regular monitoring of backup logs allows for quick identification of any backup issues that require attention.</li><li> <b>Perform trial restores</b> - Even if a backup logs shows that the backup was successful, there could be other problems not indicated in the log. Periodically perform a trial restore of data to verify that the backup data is usable and that the restore procedure works. </li><li> <b>Perform drive maintenance</b> - Many backup systems require special hardware to perform backups. Tape backup systems use a tape backup drive to read and write to the tapes. Tape drives can become dirty from use and can lead to mechanical failure. Perform routine cleaning of the tape drive using designated cleaning tapes. Hard drive-based backup systems can benefit from an occasional defragmentation to improve the overall performance of the system.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4246520353">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040203/cm4246520353/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040200/en0508040203/cm4246520353/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Plan a backup solution for a small business.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508040300">
<title><content-text>Cisco IOS Software Backup and Recovery</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040301">
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2687535244">	<title><content-text>Click Play to view how an ISP might prepare for a disaster.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040301/cm2687535244.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040301/cm2687535244text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to backing up server files, it is also necessary for the ISP to protect configurations and the Cisco IOS software used on networking devices owned by the ISP. The Cisco networking device software and configuration files can be saved to a network server using TFTP and variations of the <span class="cmd">copy</span> command. The command to save the IOS file is very similar to the command to backup and save a running configuration file. <br/> <br/> To back up Cisco IOS software, there are three basic steps: <br/> <br/> <b>Step 1</b>. Ping the TFTP server where the file should be saved. This verifies connectivity to the TFTP server. Use the <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command. <br/> <br/> <b>Step 2</b>. On the router, verify the IOS image in flash. Use the <span class="cmd"><b>show flash</b></span> command to view the filename of the IOS image and file size. Confirm that the TFTP server has enough disk space to store the file. <br/> <br/> <b>Step 3</b>. Copy the IOS image to the TFTP server using the command: </p> <p><br/> <span class="cmd"><b>Router# copy flash tftp</b></span></p> <p><br/> When using the copy command, the router will prompt the user for the source filename, the IP address of the TFTP server, and the destination filename.</p> <p>Images stored on the TFTP server can be used to restore or upgrade the Cisco IOS software on routers and switches in a network.</p> <p>The steps to upgrade an IOS image file on a router are similar to the steps used to backup the file to the TFTP server. Be sure to use the show flash command to verify the bytes available in flash and confirm that there is enough room for the IOS file before starting the upgrade or restore.</p> <p>To upgrade the Cisco IOS software, use the command:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>copy tftp: flash:</b></span></p> <p>When upgrading, the router will prompt the user to enter the IP address of the TFTP server followed by the filename of the image on the server that should be used. The router may prompt the user to erase the flash memory if there is not sufficient memory available for both the old and the new images. As the image is erased from flash, a series of "e"s appears to indicate the erase process. When the new image is loaded, it is verified, and the networking device is ready to be reloaded with the new Cisco IOS image.</p> <p>If the IOS image is lost and must be restored, a separate process, using the ROMmon mode is required.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4166840708"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040302/cm4166840708/" mime="application/pdf" scale="false" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040302/cm4166840708/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use a TFTP to backup and restore a Cisco IOS image.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8839037529">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040303/cm8839037529.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040303/cm8839037529text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If the router is set to boot up from flash, but the Cisco IOS image in flash is erased, corrupted, or inaccessible because of lack of memory, the image may need to be restored. The quickest way to restore a Cisco IOS image to the router is by using TFTP in ROM monitor (ROMmon) mode. </p> <p>The ROMmon TFTP transfer works on a specified LAN port, and defaults to the first available LAN interface. To use TFTP in ROMmon mode, the user must first set a few environmental variables, including the IP address, and then use the <span class="cmd"><b>tftpdnld</b></span> command to restore the image. </p> <p>To set a ROMmon environment variable, type the variable name, an equal sign (=), and the value for the variable. For example, to set the IP address to 10.0.0.1, type IP_ADDRESS=10.0.0.1.</p> <p>The required environment variables are: </p> <p><ul><li> IP_ADDRESS - IP address on the LAN interface </li><li> IP_SUBNET_MASK - Subnet mask for the LAN interface </li><li> DEFAULT_GATEWAY - Default gateway for the LAN interface </li><li> TFTP_SERVER - IP address of the TFTP server </li><li> TFTP_FILE - Cisco IOS filename on the server</li></ul></p> <p>Use the <span class="cmd"><b>set</b></span> command to view and verify the ROMmon environment variables. </p> <p>After the variables are set, the <span class="cmd"><b>tftpdnld</b></span> command is entered. As each datagram of the Cisco IOS file is received, an exclamation point (!) is displayed. As the Cisco IOS file is copied, the existing flash is erased. This includes all files that may be present in flash memory, not just the current IOS file. For this reason, it is important to back up these files to a TFTP server for safekeeping, in the event that it becomes necessary to restore the IOS image. </p> <p>When the ROMmon prompt appears <span class="cmd">(rommon 1>)</span>, the router can be restarted using the <span class="cmd"><b>reset</b></span> command or typing<b> i</b>. The router should now boot from the new Cisco IOS image in flash.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040304">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5905913742">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040304/cm5905913742/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040300/en0508040304/cm5905913742/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use ROMmon and tftpdnld to manage an IOS image.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0508040400">
<title><content-text>Disaster Recovery Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8192611940">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040401/cm8192611940.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040401/cm8192611940text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Data backup is an important part of any disaster recovery plan. A disaster recovery plan is a comprehensive document that describes how to restore operation quickly and keep a business running during or after a disaster occurs. The objective of the disaster recovery plan is to ensure that the business can adapt to the physical and social changes that a disaster causes. A disaster can include anything from natural disasters that affect the network structure to malicious attacks on the network itself. </p> <p>The disaster recovery plan can include information such as offsite locations where services can be moved, information on switching out network devices and servers, and backup connectivity options. It is important when building a disaster recovery plan to fully understand the services that are critical to maintaining operation. Services that might need to be available during a disaster include: </p> <p><ul><li> Databases</li><li> Application servers</li><li> System management servers</li><li> Web</li><li> Data stores</li><li> Directory</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1999023858">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040402/cm1999023858.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040402/cm1999023858text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When designing a disaster recovery plan, it is important to understand the needs of the organization. It is also important to gain the support necessary for a disaster recovery plan. There are several steps to accomplish designing an effective recovery plan.</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Vulnerability assessment</b> - Assess how vulnerable the critical business processes and associated applications are to common disasters. </li><li> <b>Risk assessment</b> - Analyze the risk of a disaster occurring and the associated effects and costs to the business. Part of a risk assessment is creating a list of the top-ten potential disasters and the effects, including the scenario of the business being completely destroyed.</li><li> <b>Management awareness</b> - Use the information gathered on vulnerability and risks to get senior management approval on the disaster recovery project. Maintaining equipment and locations in the event of a possible disaster recovery could be expensive. Senior management must understand the possible effect of any disaster situation. </li><li> <b>Planning group</b> - Establish a planning group to manage the development and implementation of the disaster recovery strategy and plan. When a disaster occurs, be it small or large scale, it is important that individuals understand their roles and responsibilities.</li><li> <b>Prioritize</b> - Assign a priority for each disaster scenario, such as mission critical, important, or minor, for the business network, applications, and systems.</li></ul></p> <p>The disaster recovery planning process should first engage the top managers, and then eventually include all personnel that work with critical business processes. Everyone must be involved and support the plan for it to be successful.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508040403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3456721637">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040403/cm3456721637.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040403/cm3456721637text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After the services and applications that are most critical to a business are identified, that information should be used to create a disaster recovery plan. There are five major phases to creating and implementing a disaster recovery plan: </p> <p><b>Phase 1 - Network Design Recovery Strategy</b></p> <p>Analyze the network design. Some aspects of the network design that should be included in the disaster recovery are:</p> <p><ul><li> Is the network designed to survive a major disaster? Are there backup connectivity options and is there redundancy in the network design?</li><li> Availability of offsite servers that can support applications such as email and database services.</li><li> Availability of backup routers, switches, and other network devices should they fail.</li><li> Location of services and resources that the network needs. Are they spread over a wide geography?</li></ul></p> <p><b>Phase 2 - Inventory and Documentation</b></p> <p>Create an inventory of all locations, devices, vendors, used services, and contact names. Verify cost estimates that are created in the risk assessment step. </p> <p><b>Phase 3 - Verification</b></p> <p>Create a verification process to prove that the disaster recover strategy works. Practice disaster recovery exercises to ensure that the plan is up to date and workable. </p> <p><b>Phase 4 - Approval and Implementation</b></p> <p>Obtain senior management approval and develop a budget to implement the disaster recovery plan.</p> <p><b>Phase 5 - Review</b></p> <p>After the disaster recovery plan has been implemented for a year, review the plan.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0508040404">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6992894887">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040404/cm6992894887.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508040000/en0508040400/en0508040404/cm6992894887text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Identify the actions that are associated with each phase of creating a disaster recovery plan.</p><p><b>Drag each disaster recovery plan phase to the corresponding action.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en0508050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508050100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0508050101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm6776785674">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508050000/en0508050100/en0508050101/cm6776785674.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0508000000/en0508050000/en0508050100/en0508050101/cm6776785674text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en0508060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0508060100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0508060101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm5089563937">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0508000000/en0508060000/en0508060100/en0508060101/cm5089563937/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en0508000000/en0508060000/en0508060100/en0508060101/cm5089563937/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge. </p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
