<chapter type="CourseSummary" id="en0510000000">
<title><content-text>Course Summary</content-text></title>
<section type="" id="en0510000000">
<title><content-text>Putting It All Together</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0510000100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0510000101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm6773373836">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000101/cm6773373836.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000101/cm6773373836text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0510000102">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1655451413">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000102/cm1655451413/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000102/cm1655451413/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Use the knowledge and skills presented in this course to perform a simulated network upgrade.</p> <p><ul><li> Create an IP addressing plan for a small network</li><li> Implement a network equipment upgrade </li><li> Verify device configurations and network connectivity </li></ul></p> <p>View <content-link target="D2_PTAct_10_0_1_2.pdf" type="internalfile">printable instructions</content-link>.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0510000103">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5889800770">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000103/cm5889800770/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000103/cm5889800770/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Lab Activity</head></b></p> <p>Use the knowledge and skills presented in this course to perform this lab activity.</p> <p><ul><li> Given a customer work order, implement a network upgrade.</li><li> Review an existing customer network. </li><li> Create an IP addressing scheme for the upgraded network. </li><li> Create a physical diagram of the new network. </li><li> Use a configuration checklist and configure networking devices. </li><li> Use an installation checklist and connect the networking devices. </li><li> Use a verification checklist and verify connectivity and routing table updates.</li></ul></p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0510000104">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm8579630922">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000104/cm8579630922.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0510000000/en0510000000/en0510000100/en0510000104/cm8579630922text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>This CCNA Discovery course is the second course in the Cisco Networking Academy Discovery course series. This course, along with the Networking for Home and Small Businesses course, has provided you with an opportunity to gain the knowledge, skills and abilities to prepare you to take the first exam in the Cisco Certified Network Associate Series. </p> <p>In order to successfully pass the certification exam, you need to review the material presented in both courses. The Cisco certification exams require a hands-on component that is presented throughout the exam as simulations, which are similar to the e-labs contained within this course. Practice of all the hands-on labs and Packet Tracer activities is also recommended as preparation for the exam. Cisco provides an on-line certification preparation center, as well, to help ensure your success on the exam. </p> <p>The Cisco CCNA Prep Center can be found at: </p> <p><content-link target="http://forums.cisco.com/eforum/servlet/PrepCenter?page=main" type="external">http://forums.cisco.com/eforum/servlet/PrepCenter?page=main</content-link></p> <p>To further your networking education, and to prepare for the Cisco CCNA exam, it is recommended that you continue through the last two courses in the CCNA Discovery Series: </p> <p>Introducing Routing and Switching in the Enterprise - Learn how enterprise networks support critical business applications. Further refine and enhance your networking skills as you prepare for the Cisco CCNA certification.</p> <p>Designing and Supporting Computer Networks - Learn the concepts that contribute to good network design. These skills prepare you for entry-level pre-sale positions with network vendors, as well as provide the fundamental knowledge necessary for students to start their own small network support businesses.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
