<chapter type="" id="en0505000000">
<title><content-text>Configuring Network Devices</content-text></title>
<section type="" id="en0505000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm4101269007">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505000000/en0505000100/en0505000101/cm4101269007.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505000000/en0505000100/en0505000101/cm4101269007text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0505010000">
<title><content-text>Initial ISR Router Configuration</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505010100">
<title><content-text>ISR</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9883367214">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010101/cm9883367214.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010101/cm9883367214text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Integrated Services Router (ISR) is one of the most popular networking devices to meet the growing communications needs of businesses. The ISR combines features such as routing and LAN switching functions, security, voice, and WAN connectivity into a single device. This makes the ISR ideal for small to medium-sized businesses and for ISP-managed customers.</p> <p>The optional integrated switch module allows small businesses to connect LAN devices directly to the 1841 ISR. With the integrated switch module, if the number of LAN hosts exceeds the number of switch ports, additional switches or hubs can be connected in a daisy chain to extend the number of LAN ports available. If the switch module is not included, external switches are connected to the router interfaces of the ISR. </p> <p>The ISR routing function allows a network to be broken into multiple local networks using subnetting and supports internal LAN devices connecting to the Internet or WAN. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505010102">
<content-media type="Photozoom" id="cm6345175741">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010102/cm6345175741.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010102/cm6345175741text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2232568196">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010103/cm2232568196.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010100/en0505010103/cm2232568196text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Internetwork Operating System (IOS) software provides features that enable a Cisco device to send and receive network traffic using a wired or wireless network. Cisco IOS software is offered to customers in modules called images. These images support various features for businesses of every size.</p> <p>The entry-level Cisco IOS software image is called the IP Base image. The Cisco IOS IP Base software supports small to medium-sized businesses and supports routing between networks. </p> <p>Other Cisco IOS software images add services to the IP Base image. For example, the Advanced Security image provides advanced security features, such as private networking and firewalls. </p> <p>Many different types and versions of Cisco IOS images are available. Images are designed to operate on specific models of routers, switches, and ISRs. </p> <p>It is important to know which image and version is loaded on a device before beginning the configuration process.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505010200">
<title><content-text>Physical Setup of the ISR</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm1126907111">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010201/cm1126907111.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010201/cm1126907111text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Each ISR is shipped with the cables and documentation needed to power up the device and begin the installation. When a new device is received, it is necessary to unpack the device and verify that all the hardware and equipment is included. </p> <p>Items shipped with a new Cisco 1841 ISR include:</p> <p><ul><li> RJ-45 to DB-9 console cable</li><li> DB-9 to DB-25 modem adapter</li><li> Power cord</li><li> Product registration card, called the Cisco.com card</li><li> Regulatory compliance and safety information for Cisco 1841 routers</li><li> Router and Security Device Manager (SDM) Quick Start guide</li><li> Cisco 1800 Series Integrated Services Router (Modular) Quick Start guide</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1465475661">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010202/cm1465475661.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010202/cm1465475661text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To install a new Cisco 1841 ISR requires special tools and equipment, which most ISPs and technician labs usually have available. Any additional equipment required depends on the model of the device and any optional equipment ordered. </p> <p>Typically, the tools required to install a new device include: </p> <p><ul><li> PC with a terminal emulation program, such as HyperTerminal</li><li> Cable ties and a No. 2 Phillips screwdriver</li><li> Cables for WAN interfaces, LAN interfaces, and USB interfaces</li></ul></p> <p>It may also be necessary to have equipment and devices required for WAN and broadband communication services, such as a modem. Additionally, Ethernet switches may be required to connect LAN devices or expand LAN connectivity, depending on whether the integrated switch module is included and the number of LAN ports required.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010203">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8529704704">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010203/cm8529704704.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010200/en0505010203/cm8529704704text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Before beginning any equipment installation, be sure to read the Quick Start guide and other documentation that is included with the device. The documentation contains important safety and procedural information to prevent accidental damage to the equipment during installation.</p> <p>Follow these steps to power up an 1841 ISR.</p> <p>1. Securely mount and ground the device chassis, or case.</p> <p>2. Seat the external compact flash card.</p> <p>3. Connect the power cable.</p> <p>4. Configure the terminal emulation software on the PC and connect the PC to the console port.</p> <p>5. Turn on the router.</p> <p>6. Observe the startup messages on the PC as the router boots up.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505010300">
<title><content-text>Bootup Process</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9583162307">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010301/cm9583162307.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010301/cm9583162307text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The router bootup process has three stages.</p> <p>1. Perform Power-on self test (POST) and load the bootstrap program.</p> <p>The POST is a process that occurs on almost every computer when it boots up. POST is used to test the router hardware. After POST, the bootstrap program is loaded. </p> <p>2. Locate and load the Cisco IOS software.</p> <p>The bootstrap program locates the Cisco IOS software and loads it into RAM. Cisco IOS files can be located in one of three places: flash memory, a <content-link target="{301C6D78-1AB5-4F88-90F0-CF2E39BC42F3}" type="glossary">TFTP</content-link> server, or another location indicated in the startup configuration file. By default, the Cisco IOS software loads from flash memory. The configuration settings must be changed to load from one of the other locations.</p> <p>3. Locate and execute the startup configuration file or enter setup mode.</p> <p>After the Cisco IOS software is loaded, the bootstrap program searches for the startup configuration file in NVRAM. This file contains the previously saved configuration commands and parameters, including interface addresses, routing information, passwords, and other configuration parameters.</p> <p>If a configuration file is not found, the router prompts the user to enter setup mode to begin the configuration process.</p> <p>If a startup configuration file is found, it is copied into RAM and a prompt containing the host name is displayed. The prompt indicates that the router has successfully loaded the Cisco IOS software and configuration file.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010302">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4896275279">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010302/cm4896275279.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010302/cm4896275279text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To avoid the loss of data, it is important to have a clear understanding of the difference between the startup configuration file and the running configuration file.</p> <p><b>Startup Configuration File</b></p> <p>The startup configuration file is the saved configuration file that sets the properties of the device each time the device is powered up. This file is stored in non-volatile RAM(NVRAM), meaning that it is saved even when power to the device is turned off.</p> <p>When a Cisco router is first powered up, it loads the Cisco IOS software to working memory, or RAM. Next, the startup configuration file is copied from NVRAM to RAM. When the startup configuration file is loaded into RAM, the file becomes the initial running configuration.</p> <p><b>Running Configuration File</b></p> <p>The term running configuration refers to the current configuration running in RAM on the device. This file contains the commands used to determine how the device operates on the network. </p> <p>The running configuration file is stored in the working memory of the device. Changes to the configuration and various device parameters can be made when the file is in working memory. However, the running configuration is lost each time the device is shut down, unless the running configuration is saved to the startup configuration file. </p> <p>Changes to the running configuration are not automatically saved to the startup configuration file. It is necessary to manually copy the running configuration to the startup configuration file.</p> <p>When configuring a device via the Cisco command line interface (CLI) the command <span class="cmd"><b>copy running-config startup-config</b></span>, or the abbreviated version <span class="cmd"><b>copy run start</b></span>, saves the running configuration to the startup configuration file. When configuring a device via the Cisco SDM GUI, there is an option to save the router running configuration to the startup configuration file each time a command is completed.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010303">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5538665754">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010303/cm5538665754.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010303/cm5538665754text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After the startup configuration file is loaded and the router boots successfully, the <span class="cmd"><b>show version</b></span> command can be used to verify and troubleshoot some of the basic hardware and software components used during the bootup process. The output from the <span class="cmd"><b>show version</b></span> command includes:</p> <p><ul><li> The Cisco IOS software version being used.</li><li> The version of the system bootstrap software, stored in ROM memory, that was initially used to boot the router.</li><li> The complete filename of the Cisco IOS image and where the bootstrap program located it.</li><li> Type of CPU on the router and amount of RAM. It may be necessary to upgrade the amount of RAM when upgrading the Cisco IOS software.</li><li> The number and type of physical interfaces on the router.</li><li> The amount of NVRAM. NVRAM is used to store the startup-config file.</li><li> The amount of flash memory on the router. Flash is used to permanently store the Cisco IOS image. It may be necessary to upgrade the amount of flash when upgrading the Cisco IOS software.</li><li> The current configured value of the software configuration register in hexadecimal.</li></ul></p> <p>The configuration register tells the router how to boot up. For example, the factory default setting for the configuration register is 0x2102. This value indicates that the router attempts to load a Cisco IOS software image from flash and loads the startup configuration file from NVRAM. It is possible to change the configuration register and, therefore, change where the router looks for the Cisco IOS image and the startup configuration file during the bootup process. If there is a second value in parentheses, it denotes the configuration register value to be used during the next reload of the router.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010304">
﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3356241150">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010304/cm3356241150.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010304/cm3356241150text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are times when the router does not successfully boot. This failure can be caused by a number of factors, including a corrupt or missing Cisco IOS file, an incorrect location for the Cisco IOS image specified by the configuration register, or inadequate memory to load a new Cisco IOS image. If the router fails to boot the IOS, it then boots up in ROM monitor (ROMmon) mode. ROMmon software is a simple command set stored in read only memory (ROM) that can be used to troubleshoot boot errors and recover the router when the IOS is not present.</p> <p>When the router boots up to ROMmon mode, one of the first steps in troubleshooting is to look in flash memory for a valid image using the <span class="cmd"><b>dir flash:</b></span> command. If an image is located, attempt to boot the image with the <span class="cmd"><b>boot flash:</b> </span> command. </p> <p><span class="cmd">rommon 1><b>boot flash:c2600-is-mz.121-5</b></span></p> <p>If the router boots properly with this command, there are two possible reasons why the Cisco IOS image did not load from flash initially. First, use the <span class="cmd"><b>show version</b></span> command to check the configuration register to ensure that it is configured for the default boot sequence. If the configuration register value is correct, use the <span class="cmd"><b>show startup-config</b></span> command to see if there is a <span class="cmd"><b>boot</b> <b>system</b></span> command that instructs the router to use a different location for the Cisco IOS image. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010305">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5482373379">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010305/cm5482373379/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010300/en0505010305/cm5482373379/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Power up an ISR and view the router system and configuration files using show commands.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505010400">
<title><content-text>Cisco IOS Programs</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4310730854">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010401/cm4310730854.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010401/cm4310730854text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are two methods to connect a PC to a network device to perform configuration and monitoring tasks: out-of-band management and in-band management.</p> <p><b>Out-of-band Management</b></p> <p>Out-of-band management requires a computer to be directly connected to the console port or auxiliary port (AUX) of the network device being configured. This type of connection does not require the local network connections on the device to be active. Technicians use out-of-band management to initially configure a network device, because until properly configured, the device cannot participate in the network. Out-of-band management is also useful when the network connectivity is not functioning correctly and the device cannot be reached over the network. Performing out-of-band management tasks requires a terminal emulation client installed on the PC.</p> <p><b>In-band Management</b></p> <p>Use in-band management to monitor and make configuration changes to a network device over a network connection. For a computer to connect to the device and perform in-band management tasks, at least one network interface on the device must be connected to the network and be operational. Either Telnet, <content-link target="{E207A5A8-A77E-43D1-A136-C98E80EFE954}" type="glossary">HTTP</content-link> or SSH can be used to access a Cisco device for in-band management. A web browser or a Telnet client program can be used to monitor the network device or make configuration changes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6385905250">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010402/cm6385905250.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010402/cm6385905250text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco IOS command line interface (CLI) is a text-based program that enables entering and executing Cisco IOS commands to configure, monitor, and maintain Cisco devices. The Cisco CLI can be used with either in-band or out-of-band management tasks. </p> <p>Use CLI commands to alter the configuration of the device and to display the current status of processes on the router. For experienced users, the CLI offers many time-saving features for creating both simple and complex configurations. Almost all Cisco networking devices use a similar CLI. When the router has completed the power-up sequence, and the <span class="cmd">Router></span> prompt appears, the CLI can be used to enter Cisco IOS commands.</p> <p>Technicians familiar with the commands and operation of the CLI find it easy to monitor and configure a variety of different networking devices. The CLI has an extensive help system that assists users in setting up and monitoring devices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2910114825">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010403/cm2910114825.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010403/cm2910114825text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to the Cisco IOS CLI, other tools are available to assist in configuring a Cisco router or ISR. Security Device Manager (SDM) is a web-based GUI device management tool. Unlike CLI, SDM can be used only for in-band management tasks.</p> <p>SDM Express simplifies the initial router configuration. It uses a step-by-step approach to create a basic router configuration quickly and easily. </p> <p>The full SDM package offers more advanced options, such as:</p> <p><ul><li> Configuring additional LAN and WAN connections</li><li> Creating firewalls</li><li> Configuring VPN connections</li><li> Performing security tasks</li></ul></p> <p>SDM supports a wide range of Cisco IOS software releases and is available free of charge on many Cisco routers. SDM is pre-installed on the flash memory of the Cisco 1800 Series ISR. If the router has SDM installed, it is good practice to use SDM to perform the initial router configuration. This configuration is done by connecting to the router via a preset network port on the router.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505010404">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4978134903">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010404/cm4978134903.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010404/cm4978134903text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Not all Cisco devices support SDM. In addition, SDM does not support all the commands that are available through the CLI. Consequently, it is sometimes necessary to use the CLI to complete a device configuration that is started using SDM. Familiarity with both methods is critical to successfully support Cisco devices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505010405">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm7520563400">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010405/cm7520563400.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505010000/en0505010400/en0505010405/cm7520563400text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Determine when to use CLI or SDM.</p><p><b>Based on the description, check CLI or SDM.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0505020000">
<title><content-text>Using Cisco SDM Express and SDM</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505020100">
<title><content-text>Cisco SDM Express</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7826939708">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020100/en0505020101/cm7826939708.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020100/en0505020101/cm7826939708text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When adding a new device to a network, it is critical to ensure that the device functions correctly. The addition of one poorly configured device can cause an entire network to fail. </p> <p>Configuring a networking device, such as a router, can be a complex task, no matter which tool is used to enter the configuration. Therefore, follow best practices for installing a new device to ensure that all device settings are properly configured and documented.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4171134967">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020100/en0505020102/cm4171134967.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020100/en0505020102/cm4171134967text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Cisco SDM Express is a tool bundled within the Cisco Router and Security Device Manager that makes it easy to create a basic router configuration. To start using SDM Express, connect an Ethernet cable from the PC NIC to the Ethernet port specified in the quick start guide on the router or ISR being configured. </p> <p>SDM Express uses eight configuration screens to assist in creating a basic router configuration:</p> <p><ul><li> Overview</li><li> Basic Configuration</li><li> LAN IP Address</li><li> DHCP</li><li> Internet (WAN)</li><li> Firewall</li><li> Security Settings</li><li> Summary</li></ul></p> <p>The SDM Express GUI provides step-by-step guidance to create the initial configuration of the router. After the initial configuration is completed, the router is available on the LAN. The router can also have a WAN connection, a firewall, and up to 30 security enhancements configured. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505020200">
<title><content-text>SDM Express Configuration Options</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2865968530">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020201/cm2865968530.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020201/cm2865968530text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The SDM Express Basic Configuration screen contains basic settings for the router that is being configured. The following information is required:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Host name</b> - The name assigned to the router being configured. </li><li> <b>Domain name for the organization</b> - An example of a domain name is cisco.com, but domain names can end with a different suffix, such as .org or .net.</li><li> <b>Username and password </b>- The username and password used to access SDM Express to configure and monitor the router. The password must be at least six characters long.</li><li> <b>Enable secret password </b>- The password that controls user access to the router, which affects the ability to make configuration changes using the CLI , Telnet, or the console ports. The password must be at least six characters long.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1613199517">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020202/cm1613199517.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020202/cm1613199517text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The LAN configuration settings enable the router interface to participate on the connected local network. </p> <p><ul><li> <b>IP address</b> - Address for the LAN interface in dotted-decimal format. It can be a private IP address if the device is installed in a network that uses Network Address Translation (NAT) or Port Address Translation (PAT).</li></ul></p> <p>It is important to take note of this address. When the router is restarted, this address is the one used to access SDM Express, not the address that was provided in the Quick Start guide.</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Subnet mask</b> - Identifies the network portion of the IP address.</li><li> <b>Subnet bits</b> - Number of bits used to define the network portion of the IP address. The number of bits can be used instead of the subnet mask.</li><li> <b>Wireless parameters</b> - Optional. Appear if the router has a wireless interface, and Yes was clicked in the Wireless Interface Configuration window. Specifies the SSID of the wireless network.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6589283379">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020203/cm6589283379.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020203/cm6589283379text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>DHCP is a simple way to assign IP addresses to host devices. DHCP dynamically allocates an IP address to a network host when the host is powered up, and reclaims the address when the host is powered down. In this way, addresses can be reused when hosts no longer need them. Using SDM Express, a router can be configured as a DHCP server to assign addresses to devices, such as PCs, on the internal local network.</p> <p>To configure a device for DHCP, select the <b>Enable DHCP Server on the LAN Interface</b> checkbox. Checking this box enables the router to assign private IP addresses to devices on the LAN. IP addresses are leased to hosts for a period of one day.</p> <p>DHCP uses a range of allowable IP addresses. By default, the valid address range is based on the IP address and subnet mask entered for the LAN interface. </p> <p>The starting address is the lowest address in the IP address range. The starting IP address can be changed, but it must be in the same network or subnet as the LAN interface.</p> <p>The highest IP address can be changed to decrease the pool size. It must be in the same network as the IP starting address.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2452468305">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020204/cm2452468305.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020204/cm2452468305text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Additional DHCP configuration parameters include: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>Domain name for the organization </b>- This name is given to the hosts as part of the DHCP configuration.</li><li> <b>Primary domain name server </b>- IP address of the primary DNS server. Used to resolve URLs and names on the network. </li><li> <b>Secondary domain name server</b> - IP address of a secondary DNS sever, if available. Used if the primary DNS server does not respond.</li></ul></p> <p>Selecting <b>Use these DNS values for DHCP clients</b> enables the DHCP server to assign DHCP clients with the configured DNS settings. This option is available if a DHCP server has been enabled on the LAN interface.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505020205">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6041810537">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020205/cm6041810537.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020200/en0505020205/cm6041810537text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Identify the configuration parameters from the SDM Express.</p><p><b>Drag the Configuration Parameter to the information that must be entered.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505020300">
<title><content-text>Configuring WAN Connections Using SDM Express</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7392986685">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020301/cm7392986685.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020301/cm7392986685text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Configuring an Internet (WAN) Connection</b></p> <p>A serial connection can be used to connect networks that are separated by large geographic distances. These WAN network interconnections require a telecommunications service provider (TSP). </p> <p>Serial connections are usually lower speed links, compared to Ethernet links, and require additional configuration. Prior to setting up the connection, determine the type of connection and protocol <content-link target="{321DE0F4-E887-4884-9EC4-D4D010E81D74}" type="glossary">encapsulation</content-link> required.</p> <p>The protocol encapsulation must be the same at both ends of a serial connection. Some encapsulation types require authentication parameters, like username and password, to be configured. Encapsulation types include:</p> <p><ul><li> High-Level Data Link Control (HDLC)</li><li> Frame Relay</li><li> Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP)</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8112245005">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020302/cm8112245005.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020302/cm8112245005text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The WAN configuration window has additional WAN parameters.</p> <p><b>Address Type List </b></p> <p>Depending on the type of encapsulation selected, different methods of obtaining an IP address for the serial interface are available:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Static IP address</b> - Available with Frame Relay, PPP, and HDLC encapsulation types. To configure a static IP address, enter the IP address and subnet mask.</li><li> <b>IP unnumbered </b>- Sets the serial interface address to match the IP address of one of the other functional interfaces of the router. Available with Frame Relay, PPP, and HDLC encapsulation types.</li><li> <b>IP negotiated </b>- The router obtains an IP address automatically through PPP.</li><li> <b>Easy IP (IP Negotiated)</b> - The router obtains an IP address automatically through PPP.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm8366395124">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020303/cm8366395124/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020300/en0505020303/cm8366395124/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure an ISR using Cisco SDM Express </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505020400">
<title><content-text>Configuring NAT Using Cisco SDM</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020401">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4986628120">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020400/en0505020401/cm4986628120.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020400/en0505020401/cm4986628120text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Either Cisco SDM Express or Cisco SDM can be used to configure a router. </p> <p>SDM supports many of the same features that SDM Express supports; however, SDM has more advanced configuration options. For this reason, after the router basic configuration is completed using SDM Express, many users switch to SDM. For example, enabling NAT requires the use of SDM. </p> <p>The Basic NAT Wizard configures Dynamic NAT with PAT, by default. PAT enables the hosts on the internal local network to share the single registered IP address assigned to the WAN interface. In this manner, hosts with internal private addresses can have access to the Internet.</p> <p>Only the hosts with the internal address ranges specified in the SDM configuration are translated. It is important to verify that all address ranges that need access to the Internet are included.</p> <p>Steps for configuring NAT include:</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Enable NAT configuration using SDM.</p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Navigate through the Basic NAT Wizard.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Select the interface and set IP ranges.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Review the configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505020402">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm6509793832">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020400/en0505020402/cm6509793832/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505020000/en0505020400/en0505020402/cm6509793832/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure Dynamic NAT using the Cisco SDM basic NAT wizard.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0505030000">
<title><content-text>Configuring a Router Using IOS CLI</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505030100">
<title><content-text>Command Line Interface Modes</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9414569674">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030101/cm9414569674.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030101/cm9414569674text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Using the Cisco IOS CLI to configure and monitor a device is very different from using SDM. The CLI does not provide step-by-step configuration assistance; therefore, it requires more planning and expertise to use. </p> <p><b>CLI Command Modes</b></p> <p>The Cisco IOS supports two levels of access to the CLI: user EXEC mode and privileged EXEC mode. </p> <p>When a router or other Cisco IOS device is powered up, the access level defaults to user EXEC mode. This mode is indicated by the command line prompt: </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>Router></b></span></p> <p>Commands that can be executed in user EXEC mode are limited to obtaining information about how the device is operating, and troubleshooting using some <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> commands and the ping and traceroute utilities.</p> <p>To enter commands that can alter the operation of the device requires privileged level access. Enable the privileged EXEC mode by entering <span class="cmd"><b>enable</b></span> at the command prompt and pressing Enter. </p> <p>The command line prompt changes to reflect the mode change. The prompt for privileged EXEC mode is:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>Router#</b></span></p> <p>To disable the privileged mode and return to user mode, enter <span class="cmd"><b>disable</b></span> or <span class="cmd"><b>exit</b></span> at the command prompt.</p> <p>Both modes can be protected with a password, or a username and password combination.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4355341444">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030102/cm4355341444.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030102/cm4355341444text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Various configuration modes are used to set up a device. Configuring a Cisco IOS device begins with entering privileged EXEC mode. From privileged EXEC mode, the user can access the other configuration modes.</p> <p>In most cases, commands are applied to the running configuration file using a terminal connection. To use these commands, the user must enter global configuration mode. </p> <p>To enter global configuration, type the command <span class="cmd"><b>configure terminal</b></span> or <span class="cmd"><b>config t</b></span>. Global configuration mode is indicated by the command line prompt:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>Router(config)#</b></span></p> <p>Any commands entered in this mode take effect immediately and can alter the operation of the device. </p> <p>From global configuration mode, the administrator can enter other sub-modes. </p> <p>Interface configuration mode is used to configure LAN and WAN interfaces. To access interface configuration mode, from global configuration type the command <span class="cmd"><b>interface [type] [number]</b></span>. Interface configuration mode is indicated by the command prompt:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>Router(config-if)#</b></span></p> <p>Another commonly used sub-mode is the router configuration submode represented by the following prompt:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>Router(config-router)#</b></span></p> <p>This mode is used to configure routing parameters.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030103">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm8381564975">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030103/cm8381564975.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030100/en0505030103/cm8381564975text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>E-Lab</b></p> <p>Using the Cisco CLI explore the various configuration modes.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030200">
<title><content-text>Using the Cisco IOS CLI</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8767171663">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030201/cm8767171663.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030201/cm8767171663text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco IOS CLI is full of features that help in recalling commands needed to configure a device. These features are one reason why network technicians prefer to use the Cisco IOS CLI to configure routers.</p> <p>The context-sensitive help feature is especially useful when configuring a device. Entering <span class="cmd"><b>help</b></span> or the <span class="cmd"><b>?</b> </span> at the command prompt displays a brief description of the help system.</p> <p>Router# <b><span class="cmd">help</span></b></p> <p>Context-sensitive help can provide suggestions for completing a command. If the first few characters of a command are known but the exact command is not, enter as much of the command as possible, followed by a <b>?</b>. Note that there is no space between the command characters and the ?.</p> <p>Additionally, to get a list of the parameter options for a specific command, enter part of the command, followed by a space, and then the ?. For example, entering the command <span class="cmd"><b>configure</b> </span> followed by a space and a ? shows a list of the possible variations. Choose one of the entries to complete the command string. Once the command string is completed, a &lt;cr> appears. Press Enter to issue the command. </p> <p>If a ? is entered and nothing matches, the help list will be empty. This indicates that the command string is not a supported command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2166413514">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030202/cm2166413514.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030202/cm2166413514text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Users sometimes make a mistake when typing a command. The CLI indicates if an unrecognized or incomplete command is entered. The % symbol marks the beginning of an error message. For example, if the command <span class="cmd"><b>interface</b></span> is entered with no other parameters, an error message displays indicating an incomplete command:</p> <p>% Incomplete command</p> <p>Use the ? to get a list of the available parameters. </p> <p>If an incorrect command is entered, the error message would read:</p> <p>% Invalid input detected</p> <p>It is sometimes hard to see the mistake within an incorrectly entered command. Fortunately, the CLI provides an error indicator. The caret symbol (^) appears at the point in the command string where there is an incorrect or unrecognized character. The user can return to the point where the error was made and use the help function to determine the correct command to use.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4218480607">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030203/cm4218480607.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030203/cm4218480607text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another feature of the Cisco IOS CLI is the ability to recall previously typed commands. This feature is particularly useful for recalling long or complex commands or entries.</p> <p>The command history is enabled by default and the system records 10 command lines in the history buffer. To change the number of command lines the system records during a session, use the <span class="cmd"><b>terminal history size</b></span> or the <span class="cmd"><b>history size</b></span> command. The maximum number of command lines is 256. </p> <p>To recall the most recent command in the history buffer, press Ctrl-P or the Up Arrow key. Repeat this process to recall successively older commands. To return to a more recent command in the history buffer, press Ctrl-N or the Down Arrow key. Repeat this process to recall successively more recent commands.</p> <p>The CLI recognizes partially typed commands based on their first unique character. For example, type "int" instead of "interface". If a short cut, such as "int" is entered, pressing the Tab key will automatically complete the entire command entry of "interface". </p> <p>On most computers, additional select and copy functions are available using various function keys. A previous command string may be copied and then pasted or inserted as the current command entry.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505030204">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6363864613">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030204/cm6363864613.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030204/cm6363864613text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the commands to their function.</p><p><b>Drag the correct keystroke combination to the proper definition.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030205">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm7841774879">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030205/cm7841774879/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030200/en0505030205/cm7841774879/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Explore the features of the Cisco IOS CLI.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030300">
<title><content-text>Using Show Commands</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1277697517">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030301/cm1277697517.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030301/cm1277697517text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco IOS CLI includes show commands that display relevant information about the configuration and operation of the device.</p> <p>Network technicians use the show commands extensively for viewing configuration files, checking the status of device interfaces and processes, and verifying the device operational status. Show commands are available whether the device was configured using the CLI or SDM.</p> <p>The status of nearly every process or function of the router can be displayed using a show command. Some of the more popular show commands are:</p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show interfaces</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show arp</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show protocols</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show version</b></span></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030302">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm9619972313">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030302/cm9619972313.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030302/cm9619972313text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>E-Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use the show run and show interface commands to answer questions about the router configuration.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030303">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1526932755">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030303/cm1526932755/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030300/en0505030303/cm1526932755/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Use Cisco IOS show commands on a router located at the ISP.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030400">
<title><content-text>Basic Configuration</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9785293781">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030401/cm9785293781.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030401/cm9785293781text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The initial configuration of a Cisco IOS device involves configuring the device name and then the passwords that are used to control access to the various functions of the device.</p> <p>A device should be given a unique name as one of the first configuration tasks. This task is accomplished in global configuration mode with the following command.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>hostname &lt;</b><i>name</i><b>></b></span></p> <p>When the Enter key is pressed, the prompt changes from the default host name, which is Router, to the newly configured host name. </p> <p>The next configuration step is to configure passwords to prevent access to the device by unauthorized individuals.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>enable password</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>enable secret</b></span> commands are used to restrict access to privileged EXEC mode, preventing unauthorized users from making configuration changes to the router.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>enable password &lt;</b><i>password</i><b>></b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>enable secret &lt;</b><i>password</i><b>></b></span></p> <p>The difference between the two commands is that the enable password is not encrypted by default. If the enable password is set, followed by the enable secret password, the <span class="cmd"><b>enable secret</b></span> command overrides the <span class="cmd"><b>enable password</b></span> command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4960886708">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030402/cm4960886708.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030402/cm4960886708text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Other basic configurations of a router include configuring a banner, enabling synchronous logging, and disabling domain lookup.</p> <p><b>Banners</b></p> <p>A banner is text that a user sees when initially logging on to the router. Configuring an appropriate banner is part of a good security plan. At a very minimum, a banner should warn against unauthorized access. Never configure a banner that welcomes an unauthorized user. </p> <p>There are two types of banners: message-of-the-day (MOTD) and login information. The purpose for two separate banners is to be able to change one without affecting the entire banner message. </p> <p>To configure the banners, the commands are <span class="cmd"><b>banner motd</b></span> and <span class="cmd"> <b>banner login</b></span>. For both types, a delimiting character, such as a #, is used at the beginning and at the end of the message. The delimiter allows the user to configure a multiline banner.</p> <p>If both banners are configured, the login banner appears after the MOTD but before the login credentials.</p> <p><b>Synchronous Logging </b></p> <p>The Cisco IOS software often sends unsolicited messages, such as a change in the state of a configured interface. Sometimes these messages occur in the middle of typing a command. The message does not affect the command, but can cause the user confusion when typing. To keep the unsolicited output separate from the typed input, the <span class="cmd"><b>logging synchronous</b></span> command can be entered in global configuration mode. </p> <p><b>Disabling Domain Lookup</b></p> <p>By default, when a host name is entered in enable mode, the router assumes that the user is attempting to telnet to a device. The router tries to resolve unknown names entered in enable mode by sending them to the DNS server. This process includes any words entered that the router does not recognize, including mistyped commands. If this capability is not wanted, the <span class="cmd"><b>no ip domain-lookup</b></span> command turns off this default feature.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6453506483">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030403/cm6453506483.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030403/cm6453506483text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are multiple ways to access a device to perform configuration tasks. One of these ways is to use a PC attached to the console port on the device. This type of connection is frequently used for initial device configuration.</p> <p>Setting a password for console connection access is done in global configuration mode. These commands prevent unauthorized users from accessing user mode from the console port.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Route(config)# <b>line console 0</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>password &lt;</b><i>password</i><b>></b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>login</b></span></p> <p>When the device is connected to the network, it can be accessed over the network connection. When the device is accessed through the network, it is considered a vty connection. The password must be configured on the vty port.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Route(config)# <b>line vty 0 4</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>password &lt;</b><i>password</i><b>></b></span></p> <span class="cmd"><p>Router(config)# <b>login</b></p></span>  <p>0 4 represents 5 simultaneous in-band connections. It is possible to set a different password for each connection by specifing specific line connection numbers, such as <span class="cmd"><b>line vty 0</b></span>. </p> <p>To verify that the passwords are set correctly, use the <span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span> command. These passwords are stored in the running-configuration in clear text. It is possible to set encryption on all passwords stored within the router so that they are not easily read by unauthorized individuals. The global configuration command <span class="cmd"><b>service password-encryption</b></span> ensures that all passwords are encrypted.</p> <p>Remember, if the running configuration is changed, it must be copied to the startup configuration file or the changes are lost when the device is powered down. To copy the changes made to the running configuration back to the stored startup configuration file, use the <span class="cmd"><b>copy run start</b></span> command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030404">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm5357656203">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030404/cm5357656203/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030400/en0505030404/cm5357656203/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Use Cisco IOS CLI to perform an initial router configuration.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030500">
<title><content-text>Configuring An Interface</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1797532503">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030501/cm1797532503.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030501/cm1797532503text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To direct traffic from one network to another, router interfaces are configured to participate in each of the networks. A router interface connecting to a network will typically have an IP address and subnet mask assigned that is within the host range for the connected network. </p> <p>There are different types of interfaces on a router. Serial and Ethernet interfaces are the most common. Local network connections use Ethernet interfaces.</p> <p>WAN connections require a serial connection through an ISP. Unlike Ethernet interfaces, serial interfaces require a clock signal to control the timing of the communications, called a clock rate. In most environments, data communications equipment (DCE) devices, such as a modem or CSU/DSU, provide the clock rate.</p> <p>When a router connects to the ISP network using a serial connection, a CSU/DSU is required if the WAN is digital. A modem is required if the WAN is analog. These devices convert the data from the router into a form acceptable for crossing the WAN, and convert data from the WAN into an acceptable format for the router. By default, Cisco routers are data terminal equipment (DTE) devices. Because the DCE devices control the timing of the communication with the router, the Cisco DTE devices accept the clock rate from the DCE device. </p> <p>Though uncommon, it is possible to connect two routers directly together using a serial connection. In this instance, no CSU/DSU or modem is used, and one of the routers must be configured as a DCE device to provide clocking. If the router is connected as the DCE device, a clock rate must be set on the router interface to control the timing of the DCE/DTE connection.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5926012706">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030502/cm5926012706.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030502/cm5926012706text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Configuring an interface on the router must be done in global configuration mode. Configuring an Ethernet interface is very similar to configuring a serial interface. One of the main differences is that a serial interface must have a clock rate set if it is acting as a DCE device.</p> <p>The steps to configure an interface include:</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Specify the type of interface and the interface port number.</p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Specify a description of the interface.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Configure the interface IP address and subnet mask.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Set the clock rate, if configuring a serial interface as a DCE.</p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Enable the interface.</p> <p>After an interface is enabled, it may be necessary to turn off an interface for maintenance or troubleshooting. In this case, use the <span class="cmd">shutdown</span> command.</p> <p>When configuring the serial interface on a 1841, the serial interface is designated by 3 digits, C/S/P, where C=Controller#, S=Slot# and P=Port#. The 1841 has two modular slots. The designation Serial0/0/0 indicates that the serial interface module is on controller 0, in slot 0, and that the interface to be used is the first one (0). The second interface is Serial0/0/1. The serial module is normally installed in slot 0 but may be installed in slot 1. If this is the case, the designation for the first serial interface would be Serial0/1/0 and the second would be Serial0/1/1.</p> <p>For built in ports, such as the FastEthernet ports the designation is 2 digits, C/P, where C=Controller#, and P=Port#. The designation Fa0/0 represents controller 0 and interface 0.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030503">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4781313786">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030503/cm4781313786.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030503/cm4781313786text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>E-Lab Activity </head></b></p> <p>Configure the serial interfaces on two routers.</p><p><b>Click the icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030504">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm4696158706">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030504/cm4696158706/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030504/cm4696158706/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure the Ethernet and Serial interfaces of a router.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030505">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9671887772">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030505/cm9671887772/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030500/en0505030505/cm9671887772/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Lab Activity </head></b></p> <p>Configure basic settings on a router using the Cisco IOS CLI.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030600">
<title><content-text>Configuring a Default Route</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030601">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1714028202">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030600/en0505030601/cm1714028202.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030600/en0505030601/cm1714028202text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A router forwards packets from one network to another based on the destination IP address specified in the packet. It examines the routing table to determine where to forward the packet to reach the destination network. If the router does not have a route to a specific network in its routing table, a default route can be configured to tell the router how to forward the packet. The default route is used by the router only if the router does not know where to send a packet.</p> <p>Usually, the default route points to the next hop router on the path to the Internet. The information needed to configure the default route is the IP address of the next hop router, or the interface that the router uses to forward traffic with an unknown destination network. </p> <p>Configuring the default route on a Cisco ISR must be done in global configuration mode.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>ip route 0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 &lt;</b><i>next-hop-IP-address</i><b>></b></span></p> <p>or</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)# <b>ip route 0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 &lt;</b><i>interface-type</i><b>> &lt;</b><i>number</i><b>></b></span></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030602">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm3189389398">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030600/en0505030602/cm3189389398/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030600/en0505030602/cm3189389398/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure a default route on routers in a medium-sized business network topology.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030700">
<title><content-text>Configuring DHCP Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030701">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1943833659">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030701/cm1943833659.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030701/cm1943833659text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco IOS CLI can be used to configure a router to function as a DHCP server. </p> <p>Using a router configured with DHCP simplifies the management of IP addresses on a network. The administrator needs to update only a single, central router when IP configuration parameters change. Configuring DHCP using the CLI is a little more complex than configuring it using SDM. </p> <p>There are eight basic steps to configuring DHCP using the CLI.</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Create a DHCP address pool.</p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Specify the network or subnet.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Exclude specific IP addresses.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Specify the domain name.</p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Specify the IP address of the DNS server.</p> <p><b>Step 6.</b> Set the default gateway.</p> <p><b>Step 7. </b>Set the lease duration.</p> <p><b>Step 8.</b> Verify the configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030702">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm4667833775">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030702/cm4667833775/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030702/cm4667833775/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure a router as a DHCP server for attached clients. </p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030703">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3031702344">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030703/cm3031702344/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030700/en0505030703/cm3031702344/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use the Cisco SDM and IOS CLI to configure a router as a DHCP server.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030800">
<title><content-text>Configuring Static NAT Using Cisco IOS CLI</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030801">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm6082671949">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030801/cm6082671949.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030801/cm6082671949text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>NAT enables hosts with internal private addresses to communicate on the Internet. When configuring NAT, at least one interface must be configured as the inside interface. The inside interface is connected to the internal, private network. Another interface, usually the external interface used to access the Internet, must be configured as the outside interface. When devices on the internal network communicate out through the external interface, the addresses are translated to one or more registered IP addresses.</p> <p>There are occasions when a server located on an internal network must be accessible from the Internet. This accessibility requires that the server has a specific registered address that external users can specify. One way to provide this address to an internal server is to configure a static translation. </p> <p>Static NAT ensures that addresses assigned to hosts on the internal network are always translated to the same registered IP address. </p> <p>Configuring NAT and static NAT using the Cisco IOS CLI requires a number of steps.</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Specify the inside interface.</p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Set the primary IP address of the inside interface.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Identify the inside interface using the <span class="cmd"><b>ip nat inside</b></span> command.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Specify the outside interface.</p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Set the primary IP address of the outside interface.</p> <p><b>Step 6.</b> Identify the outside interface using the <span class="cmd"><b>ip nat outside</b></span> command.</p> <p><b>Step 7. </b>Define the static address translation. </p> <p><b>Step 8.</b> Verify the configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030802">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1971663095">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030802/cm1971663095.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030802/cm1971663095text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are several router CLI commands to view NAT operations for verification and troubleshooting. </p> <p>One of the most useful commands is <span class="cmd"><b>show ip nat translations</b></span>. The output displays the detailed NAT assignments. The command shows all static translations that have been configured and any dynamic translations that have been created by traffic. Each translation is identified by protocol and its inside and outside local and global addresses.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>show ip nat statistics</b></span> command displays information about the total number of active translations, NAT configuration parameters, how many addresses are in the pool, and how many have been allocated.</p> <p>Additionally, use the <span class="cmd"><b>show run</b></span> command to view NAT configurations. </p> <p>By default, if dynamic NAT is configured, translation entries time out after 24 hours. It is sometimes useful to clear the dynamic entries sooner than 24 hours. This is especially true when testing the NAT configuration. To clear dynamic entries before the timeout has expired, use the <span class="cmd"><b>clear ip nat translation *</b></span> command in the enable mode. Only the dynamic translations are removed from the table. Static translations cannot be cleared from the translation table.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030803">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9082737876">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030803/cm9082737876/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030803/cm9082737876/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure static NAT on a router.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030804">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5693213226">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030804/cm5693213226/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030800/en0505030804/cm5693213226/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure PAT using Cisco SDM and static NAT using Cisco IOS CLI.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505030900">
<title><content-text>Backing Up a Cisco Router Configuration</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030901">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm3165770970">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030901/cm3165770970.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030901/cm3165770970text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After a router is configured, the running configuration should be saved to the startup configuration file. It is also a good idea to save the configuration file in another location, such as a network server. If the NVRAM fails or becomes corrupt and the router cannot load the startup configuration file, another copy is available. There are multiple ways that a configuration file can be saved. </p> <p>One way configuration files can be saved to a network server is using TFTP. The TFTP server must be accessible to the router via a network connection. </p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Enter the <span class="cmd"><b>copy startup-config tftp</b></span> command. </p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Enter the IP address of the host where the configuration file will be stored. </p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Enter the name to assign to the configuration file or accept the default.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Confirm each choice by answering yes. </p> <p>The running configuration can also be stored on a TFTP server using the <span class="cmd"><b>copy running-config tftp</b></span> command.</p> <p>To restore the backup configuration file, the router must have at least one interface configured and be able to access the TFTP server over the network. </p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Enter the <span class="cmd"><b>copy tftp running-config</b></span> command. </p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Enter the IP address of the remote host where the TFTP server is located. </p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Enter the name of the configuration file or accept the default name. </p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Confirm the configuration filename and the TFTP server address.</p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Using the <span class="cmd"><b>copy run start</b></span> command, copy the running-configuration to the startup-configuration file to ensure that the restored configuration is saved.</p> <p>When restoring your configuration, it is possible to copy the tftp file to the startup configuration file. However, this does require a router reboot in order to load the startup configuration file into the running configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030902">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6970051303">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030902/cm6970051303.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030902/cm6970051303text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another way to create a backup copy of the configuration is to capture the output of the <span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span> command. To do this from the terminal session, copy the output, paste it into a text file, and then save the text file. </p> <p>The following steps are used to capture the configuration from a HyperTerminal screen.</p> <p><b>Step 1. </b>Select <b>Transfer</b>. </p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Select <b>Capture Text. </b></p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Specify a name for the text file to capture the configuration. </p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Select <b>Start</b> to start capturing text. </p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Use the <span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span> command to display the configuration on the screen. </p> <p><b>Step 6.</b> Press the spacebar when each "-More -" prompt appears. </p> <p>After the complete configuration has been displayed, the following steps stop the capture.</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Select <b>Transfer</b>. </p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Select <b>Capture Text. </b></p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Select <b>Stop</b>. </p> <p>After the capture is complete, the configuration file must be edited to remove extra text, such as the "building configuration" Cisco IOS message. Also, the <span class="cmd"><b>no shutdown</b></span> command must be added to the end of each interface section. Click <b>File</b> > <b>Save</b> to save the configuration. The configuration file can be edited from a text editor such as Notepad.</p> <p>The backup configuration can be restored from a HyperTerminal session. Before the configuration is restored, any other configurations should be removed from the router using the <span class="cmd"><b>erase startup-config</b></span> command at the privileged EXEC prompt. The router is then restarted using the <span class="cmd"><b>reload</b></span> command. </p> <p>The following steps copy the backup configuration to the router.</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Enter router global configuration mode. </p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Select <b>Transfer</b> > <b>Send Text File</b> in HyperTerminal. </p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Select the name of the file for the saved backup configuration. </p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Restore the startup configuration with the <span class="cmd"><b>copy run start</b></span> command</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030903">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm5529176804">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030903/cm5529176804/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030903/cm5529176804/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Back up the running configuration to a TFTP server.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030904">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4541969049">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030904/cm4541969049/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030904/cm4541969049/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity </b></p> <p>Use HyperTerminal to save and load the running configuration.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505030905">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5051113765">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030905/cm5051113765/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505030000/en0505030900/en0505030905/cm5051113765/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use TFTP to save and load the running configuration. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0505040000">
<title><content-text>Connecting the CPE to the ISP</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505040100">
<title><content-text>Installing the CPE</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8201833695">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040101/cm8201833695.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040101/cm8201833695text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the main responsibilities of an on-site network technician is to install and upgrade equipment located at a customer home or business. Network devices installed at the customer location are called customer premises equipment (<content-link target="{C7A963F2-C2DD-45C7-B0E1-4214D25CE4DD}" type="glossary">CPE</content-link>) and include devices such as routers, modems, and switches.</p> <p>The installation or upgrade of a router can be disruptive for a business. Many businesses rely on the Internet for their correspondence and have e-commerce services that must be accessed during the day. Planning the installation or upgrade is a critical step in ensuring successful operation. Additionally, planning enables options to be explored on paper, where it is easy and inexpensive to correct errors. </p> <p>The ISP technical staff usually meets with business customers for planning. During planning sessions, the technician determines the configuration of the router to meet customer needs and the network software that may be affected by the new installation or upgrade.</p> <p>The technician works with the IT personnel of the customer to decide which router configuration to use and to develop the procedure that verifies the router configuration. From this information, the technician completes a configuration checklist.</p> <p>The configuration checklist provides a list of the most commonly configured components. It typically includes an explanation of each component and the configuration setting. The list is a tool for ensuring that everything is configured correctly on new router installations. It is also helpful for troubleshooting previously configured routers. </p> <p>There are many different formats for configuration checklists, including some that are quite complex. ISPs should ensure that support technicians have, and know how to use, router configuration checklists.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7503775870">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040102/cm7503775870.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040102/cm7503775870text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When new equipment is required, the devices are typically configured and tested at the ISP site before being installed at the customer site. Anything that is not functioning as expected can be replaced or fixed immediately. If a router is being installed, the network technician makes sure that the router is fully configured and that the router configuration is verified. </p> <p>When the router is known to be configured correctly, all network cables, power cables, management cables, manufacturer documentation, manufacturer software, configuration documentation, and the special tools needed for router installation are assembled. An inventory checklist is used to verify that all necessary equipment needed to install the router is present. Usually, the network technician signs the checklist, indicating that everything has been verified. The signed and dated inventory checklist is included with the router when it is packaged for shipping to the customer premises.</p> <p>The router is now ready to be installed by the on-site technician. It is important to find a time that provides the minimum amount of disruption. It may not be possible to install or upgrade network equipment during normal business hours. If the installation will cause the network to be down, the network technician, the ISP sales person, and a representative of the company prepare a router installation plan. This plan ensures that the customer experiences a minimum of disruption in service while the new equipment is installed. Additionally, the router installation plan identifies who the customer contact is and what the arrangements are for access to the site after business hours. As part of the installation plan, an installation checklist is created to ensure that equipment is installed appropriately.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3678219725">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040103/cm3678219725.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040103/cm3678219725text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The on-site network technician must install the router at the customer premises using the router installation plan and checklist. When installing customer equipment, it is important to complete the job in a professional manner. This means that all network cables are labeled and fastened together or run through proper cable management equipment. Excess lengths of cable are coiled and secured out of the way. </p> <p>Documentation should be updated to include the current configuration of the router, and network diagrams should be updated to show the location of the equipment and cables installed.</p> <p>After the router is successfully installed and tested, the network technician completes the installation checklist. The completed checklist is then verified by the customer representative. The verification of the router installation often involves demonstrating that the router is correctly configured and that services that depend on the router work as expected.</p> <p>When the customer representative is satisfied that the router has been correctly installed and is operational, the customer signs and dates the checklist. Sometimes there is a formal acceptance document in addition to the checklist. This procedure is often called the sign-off phase. It is critical that the customer representative signs off on the job, because the ISP can then bill the customer for the work.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040104">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6244781839">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040104/cm6244781839.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040100/en0505040104/cm6244781839text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Installation Documentation</b></p> <p>When customer equipment is configured and installed on the customer premises, it is important to document the entire process. Documentation includes all aspects of equipment configuration, diagrams of equipment installation, and checklists to validate the correct installation. If a new configuration is needed, the documentation is compared with the previous router configuration to determine if and how the new configuration has changed. Activity logs are used to track modifications and access to equipment. Properly maintained activity logs help when troubleshooting problems.</p> <p>The technician starts documenting the work during router installation. All cables and equipment are correctly labeled and indicated on a diagram to simplify future identification. </p> <p>The technician uses the installation and verification checklist when installing a router. This checklist displays the tasks to be completed at the customer premises. The checklist helps the network technician avoid errors and ensures that the installation is done efficiently and correctly. </p> <p>A copy of the final documentation is left with the customer.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505040200">
<title><content-text>Customer Connections over a WAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8780556263">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040200/en0505040201/cm8780556263.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040200/en0505040201/cm8780556263text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>New equipment at the customer site must be connected back to the ISP to provide Internet services. When customer equipment is upgraded, it is sometimes necessary to also upgrade the type of connectivity provided by the ISP.</p> <p><b>Wide Area Networks</b></p> <p>When a company or organization has locations that are separated by large geographical distances, it may be necessary to use the telecommunications service provider (TSP) to interconnect the LANs at the different locations. The networks that connect LANs in geographically separated locations are referred to as wide area networks (WANs).</p> <p>TSPs operate large regional networks that can span long distances. Traditionally, TSPs transported voice and data communications on separate networks. Increasingly, these providers are offering converged information network services to their subscribers. </p> <p>Individual organizations usually lease connections through the TSP network. Although the organization maintains all the policies and administration of the LANs at both ends of the connection, the policies within the communications service provider network are controlled by the ISP.</p> <p>ISPs sell various types of WAN connections to their clients. WAN connections vary in the type of connector used, in bandwidth, and in cost. As small businesses grow, they require the increased bandwidth offered by some of the more expensive WAN connections. One of the jobs at an ISP or medium-sized business is to assess what type of WAN connection is needed.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm5717463038">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040200/en0505040202/cm5717463038.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040200/en0505040202/cm5717463038text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are three types of serial WAN connections.</p> <p><b>Point-to-Point</b></p> <p>A point-to-point connection is a predefined communications path from the customer premises through a TSP network. It is a dedicated circuit with fixed bandwidth available at all time. Point-to-point lines are usually leased from the TSP. These lines are often called leased lines. Point-to-point connections are typically the most expensive of the WAN connection types, and are priced based on the bandwidth required and the distance between the two connected points. An example of a point-to-point WAN connection is a T1 or E1 link.</p> <p><b>Circuit-Switched</b></p> <p>A circuit-switched connection functions similarly to the way a phone call is made over a telephone network. When making a phone call to a friend, the caller picks up the phone, opens the circuit, and dials the number. The caller hangs up the phone when finished and the closes the circuit. An example of a circuit-switched WAN connection is an <content-link target="{6DECF767-BA16-42A4-9DE5-89BF88E915AC}" type="glossary">ISDN</content-link> or dialup connection.</p> <p><b>Packet-Switched</b></p> <p>In a packet-switched connection, networks have connections into the TSP switched network. Many customers share this TSP network. Instead of the circuit being physically reserved from source to destination, as in a circuit-switched network, each customer has its own virtual circuit. A virtual circuit is a logical path between the sender and receiver, not a physical path. An example of a packet-switched network is Frame Relay.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505040300">
<title><content-text>Choosing a WAN Connection</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8876557206">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040301/cm8876557206.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040301/cm8876557206text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When choosing a WAN, the decision is largely dependent on the bandwidth and cost of the WAN connection. Smaller businesses are not able to afford some of the more expensive WAN connection options, such as SONET or ATM WAN connections. They usually install the less expensive DSL, cable, and T1 connections. In addition, higher bandwidth WAN connections may not be available in geographically isolated locations. If the offices supported are close to an urban center, there are more WAN choices.</p> <p>Another factor that affects the decision on which WAN to choose is how the business plans to use the connection. If the business provides services over the Internet, it may require higher upstream bandwidth. For example, if a business hosts a web server for an e-commerce business, it needs enough upstream bandwidth to accommodate the number of external customers that visit its site. On the other hand, if the business uses an ISP to manage its e-commerce site, the business does not need as much upstream bandwidth.</p> <p>For some businesses, the ability to get a service level agreement (SLA) with their WAN connection affects their decision. Less expensive WAN connections like dialup, DSL, and cable typically do not come with an SLA, whereas more expensive connections do.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9271648107">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040302/cm9271648107.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040302/cm9271648107text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are many things to consider when planning a WAN upgrade. The ISP initiates the process by analyzing the customer needs and reviewing the available options. A proposal is then generated for the customer. The proposal addresses the existing infrastructure, the customer requirements, and possible WAN options. </p> <p><b>Existing Infrastructure</b></p> <p>This is an explanation of the current infrastructure being used by the business. It helps the customer understand how the existing WAN connection provides services to their home or business.</p> <p><b>Customer Requirements</b></p> <p>This section of the proposal describes why a WAN upgrade is necessary for the customer. It outlines where the current WAN connection does not meet the customer needs. It also includes a list of requirements that the new WAN connection must meet to satisfy the current and future customer requirements.</p> <p><b>WAN Options</b></p> <p>This is a list of all the available WAN choices with the corresponding bandwidth, cost, and other features that are applicable for the business is included in the proposal. The recommended choice is indicated, including possible other options. </p> <p>The WAN upgrade proposal is presented to the business decision-makers. They review the document and consider the options. When they have made their decision, the ISP works with the customer to develop a schedule and coordinate the WAN upgrade process.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2095972212">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040303/cm2095972212/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040300/en0505040303/cm2095972212/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Complete a WAN upgrade plan based on the business scenario presented. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505040400">
<title><content-text>Configuring WAN Connections</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4381047718">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040400/en0505040401/cm4381047718.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040400/en0505040401/cm4381047718text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>How a WAN is configured depends on the type of WAN connection required. Some WAN connections support Ethernet interfaces. Other WAN connections support serial interfaces. </p> <p>Leased-line WAN connections typically use a serial connection, and require a channel service unit and data service unit (CSU/DSU) to attach to the ISP network. The ISP equipment needs to be configured so that it can communicate through the CSU/DSU to the customer premises. </p> <p>For a serial connection, it is important to have a preconfigured clock rate that is the same on both ends of the connection. The clock rate is set by the DCE device, which is typically the CSU/DSU. The DTE device, typically the router, accepts the clock rate set by the DCE. </p> <p>The Cisco default serial encapsulation is HDLC. It can be changed to PPP, which provides a more flexible encapsulation and supports authentication by the remote device.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505040402">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm4180922287">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040400/en0505040402/cm4180922287/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505040000/en0505040400/en0505040402/cm4180922287/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Configure a serial WAN connection from a Cisco ISR to a CSU/DSU at an ISP.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0505050000">
<title><content-text>Initial Cisco 2960 Switch Configuration</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505050100">
<title><content-text>Standalone Switches</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8209654403">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050101/cm8209654403.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050101/cm8209654403text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although the integrated swith module of the 1841 ISR is adequate for connecting a small number of hosts to the LAN, it may be necessary to add larger, more capable switches to support additional users as the network grows.</p> <p>A switch is a device that directs a stream of messages from one port to another based on the destination MAC address within the frame. A switch cannot route traffic between two different local networks. In the context of the OSI model, a switch performs Layer 2 functions. Layer 2 is the Data Link Layer.</p> <p>Several models of Ethernet switches are available to meet various user requirements. The Cisco Catalyst 2960 Series Ethernet switch is designed for the networks of medium-sized businesses and branch offices.</p> <p>The Catalyst 2960 Series of switch are fixed-configuration, standalone devices that do not support modules or flash card slots. Because the physical configuration cannot change, fixed-configuration switches must be chosen based on the required number and type of ports. 2960 Series switches can provide 10/100 Fast Ethernet and 10/100/1000 Gigabit Ethernet connectivity. These switches use Cisco IOS software and can be configured using a GUI-based Cisco Network Assistant or through the CLI.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505050102">
<content-media type="Photozoom" id="cm5388009129">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050102/cm5388009129.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050102/cm5388009129text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050103">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm4068458997">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050103/cm4068458997.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050103/cm4068458997text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>All switches support both half-duplex or full-duplex mode. </p> <p>When a port is in half-duplex mode, at any given time, it can either send or receive data but not both. When a port is in full-duplex mode, it can simultaneously send and receive data, doubling the throughput. </p> <p>Both the port and the connected device must be set to the same duplex mode. If they are not the same, a duplex mismatch occurs, which can lead to excessive collisions and degraded communication.</p> <p>The speed and duplex can be set manually, or the switch port can use autonegotiation. Autonegotiation allows the switch to autodetect the speed and duplex of the device that is connected to the port. Autonegotiation is enabled by default on many Cisco switches. </p> <p>For autonegotiation to be successful, both devices must support it. If the switch is in autonegotiation mode and the connected device does not support it, the switch uses the speed of the other device (10, 100, or 1000) and is set to half-duplex mode. Defaulting to half duplex can create problems if the non-autonegotiating device is set to full duplex. </p> <p>If the connected device does not autonegotiate, manually configure the duplex settings on the switch to match the duplex settings on the connected device. The speed parameter can adjust itself, even if the connected port does not autonegotiate.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2017339495">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050104/cm2017339495.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050100/en0505050104/cm2017339495text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Switch settings, including the speed and duplex port parameters, can be configured using the Cisco IOS CLI. When configuring a switch using the Cisco IOS CLI, the interface and command structure is very similar to the Cisco routers. </p> <p>As with the Cisco routers, there is a variety of choices for the Cisco IOS image for switches. The IP-base software image is supplied with the Cisco Catalyst 2960 switch. This image provides the switch with basic switching capabilities and IP services. Other Cisco IOS software images supply additional services to the IP-base image.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505050200">
<title><content-text>Power Up the Cisco 2960 Switch</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1655254645">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050200/en0505050201/cm1655254645.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050200/en0505050201/cm1655254645text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Powering up a Cisco 2960 switch is similar to powering up a Cisco 1841 ISR. </p> <p>The three basic steps for powering up a switch include:</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Check the components.</p> <p><b>Step 2. </b>Connect the cables to the switch.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Power up the switch.</p> <p>When the switch is on, the power-on self-test (POST) begins. During POST, the LEDs blink while a series of tests determine that the switch is functioning properly. </p> <p>POST is completed when the SYST LED rapidly blinks green. If the switch fails POST, the SYST LED turns amber. When a switch fails POST, it is necessary to return the switch for repairs.</p> <p>When all startup procedures are finished, the Cisco 2960 switch is ready to configure.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5659886474">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050200/en0505050202/cm5659886474/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050200/en0505050202/cm5659886474/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Lab Activity</head></b></p> <p>Power up a Cisco 2960 switch.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505050300">
<title><content-text>Initial Switch Configuration</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1355192429">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050301/cm1355192429.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050301/cm1355192429text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are several ways to configure and manage a Cisco LAN switch. </p> <p><ul><li> Cisco Network Assistant</li><li> Cisco Device Manager</li><li> Cisco IOS CLI</li><li> CiscoView Management Software</li><li> <content-link target="{A0CCF8AD-0F88-418D-AD3C-8052237FBB15}" type="glossary">SNMP</content-link> Network Management Products</li></ul></p> <p>Some of these methods use IP connectivity or a web browser to connect to the switch, which requires an IP address. Unlike router interfaces, switch ports are not assigned IP addresses. To use an IP-based management product or Telnet session to manage a Cisco switch, it is necessary to configure a management IP address on the switch. </p> <p>If the switch does not have an IP address, it is necessary to connect directly to the console port and use a terminal emulation program to perform configuration tasks.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5486016691">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050302/cm5486016691.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050302/cm5486016691text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Catalyst 2960 switch comes preconfigured and only needs to be assigned basic security information before being connected to the network.</p>  <p>The commands to configure the host name and passwords on the switch are the same commands used to configure the ISR. To use an IP-based management product or Telnet with a Cisco switch, configure a management IP address.</p> <p>To assign an address to a switch, the address must be assigned to a virtual local area network <content-link target="{8C4BE291-AB98-44FF-9DF2-CE7963AE2C8A}" type="glossary">VLAN</content-link> interface. A VLAN allows multiple physical ports to be grouped together logically. By default, there is one VLAN, preconfigured in the switch, VLAN1, that provides access to management functions. </p> <p>To configure the IP address assigned to the management interface on VLAN 1, enter global configuration mode.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch><b>enable</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch#<b>configure terminal</b></span></p> <p>Next, enter the interface configuration mode for VLAN 1.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch(config)#<b>interface vlan 1</b></span></p> <p>Set the IP address, subnet mask, and default gateway for the management interface. The IP address must be valid for the local network where the switch is installed.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch(config-if)#<b>ip address 192.168.1.2 255.255.255.0</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch(config-if)#<b>exit</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch(config)#<b>ip default-gateway 192.168.1.1</b></span></p> <p><span class="cmd">Switch(config)#<b>end</b></span></p> <p>Save the configuration by using the <span class="cmd"><b>copy running-configuration startup-configuration</b></span> command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050303">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm6088387638">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050303/cm6088387638.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050303/cm6088387638text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>E-Lab Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure the basic settings on a Cisco Catalyst switch.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050304">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1691898299">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050304/cm1691898299/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050300/en0505050304/cm1691898299/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Perform a basic switch configuration.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505050400">
<title><content-text>Connecting the LAN Switch to the Router</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4422026210">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050401/cm4422026210.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050401/cm4422026210text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Connect the Switch to the Network</b></p> <p>To connect the switch to a router, use a straight-through cable. LED lights on the switch and router indicate that the connection is successful.</p> <p>After the switch and router are connected, determine if the two devices are able to exchange messages. </p> <p>First, check the IP address configuration. Use the <span class="cmd"><b>show running-configuration</b></span> command to verify that the IP address of the management interface on the switch VLAN 1 and the IP address of the directly connected router interface are on the same local network.</p> <p>Then test the connection using the <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command. From the switch, ping the IP address of the directly connected router interface. Repeat the process from the router by pinging the management interface IP address assigned to the switch VLAN 1.</p> <p>If the ping is not successful, verify the connections and configurations again. Check to ensure that all the cables are correct and that the connections are seated.</p> <p>After the switch and router are successfully communicating, individual PCs can be connected to the switch using straight-through cables. These cables can be directly connected to the PCs, or can be used as part of the structured cabling leading to wall outlets.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2770023501">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050402/cm2770023501.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050402/cm2770023501text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Switch ports can be an entry point to the network by unauthorized users. To prevent this, switches provide a feature called port security. Port security limits the number of valid MAC addresses allowed per port. The port does not forward packets with source MAC addresses that are outside the group of defined addresses.</p> <p>There are three ways to configure port security.</p> <p><b>Static</b></p> <p>MAC addresses are manually assigned using the <span class="cmd"><b>switchport port-security mac-address <i>&lt;mac-address></i></b> </span> interface configuration command. Static MAC addresses are stored in the address table and added to the running configuration.</p> <p><b>Dynamic</b></p> <p>MAC addresses are dynamically learned and stored in the address table. The number of addresses learned can be controlled. By default, the maximum number of MAC addresses learned per port is one. Addresses that are learned are cleared from the table if the port is shutdown or if the switch is restarted.</p> <p><b>Sticky</b></p> <p>Similar to dynamic, except that the addresses are also saved to the running configuration. </p> <p>Port security is disabled by default. If port security is enabled, a violation will result in the port being shutdown. For example, if dynamic port security is enabled and the maximum number of MAC addresses per port is one, the first address learned becomes the secure address. If another workstation attempts to access the port with a different MAC address, a security violation occurs. </p> <p>There is a security violation when either of these situations occurs: </p> <p><ul><li> The maximum number of secure MAC addresses has been added to the address table, and a device with a MAC address that is not in the address table attempts to access the interface. </li><li> An address learned or configured on one secure interface is seen on another secure interface in the same VLAN.</li></ul></p> <p>Before port security can be activated, the port must be set to access mode with the <span class="cmd"><b>switchport mode access</b></span> command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050403">
﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3649155349">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050403/cm3649155349.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050403/cm3649155349text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To verify port security settings for the switch or the specified interface, use the <span class="cmd"><b>show port-security interface <i>interface-id</i></b></span> command. The output displays the following:</p> <p><ul><li> Maximum allowed number of secure MAC addresses for each interface</li><li> Number of secure MAC addresses on the interface</li><li> Number of security violations that have occurred</li><li> Violation mode</li></ul></p> <p>Additionally, the show port-security address command displays the secure MAC addresses for all ports, and the show port-security command displays the port security settings for the switch. </p> <p>If static port security or sticky port security is enabled, the show running-config command can be used to view the MAC address associated with a specific port. There are three ways to clear a learned MAC address that is saved in the running configuration: </p> <p><ul><li> Use the <span class="cmd"><b>clear port-security sticky interface <i>&lt;port#></i> access</b></span> to clear any learned addresses. Next, shutdown the port using the <span class="cmd"><b>shutdown</b></span> command. Finally, re-enable the port using the <span class="cmd"><b>no shutdown</b></span> command. </li><li> Disable port security using the <span class="cmd"><b>no switchport port-security</b></span> interface command. Once disabled, re-enable port security. </li><li> Reboot the switch.</li></ul></p> <p>Rebooting the switch will only work if the running configuration is not saved to the startup configuration file. If the running configuration is saved to the startup configuration file, that will eliminate the need for the switch to relearn addresses when the system reboots. However, the learned MAC address will always be associated with a particular port unless the port is cleared using the <span class="cmd"><b>clear port-security</b></span> command or disabling port security. If this is done, be sure to re-save the running configuration to the startup configuration file to prevent the switch from reverting to the original associated MAC address upon reboot.</p> <p>If there are any ports on a switch that are unused, best practice is to disable them. It is simple to disable ports on a switch. Navigate to each unused port and issue the <span class="cmd"><b>shutdown</b></span> command. If a port needs to be activated, enter the <span class="cmd"><b>no shutdown</b></span> command on that interface.</p> <p>In addition to enabling port security and shutting down unused ports, other security configurations on a switch include setting passwords on vty ports, enabling login banners, and encrypting passwords with the <span class="cmd"><b>service password-encryption</b></span> command. For these configurations, use the same Cisco IOS CLI commands as those used to configure a router.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050404">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9331533957">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050404/cm9331533957/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050404/cm9331533957/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Packet Tracer Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure and connect the switch to the LAN using a configuration checklist.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050405">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm8572509551">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050405/cm8572509551/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050400/en0505050405/cm8572509551/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b><head>Lab Activity</head></b></p> <p>Configure and connect the Cisco 2960 switch.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0505050500">
<title><content-text>Cisco Discovery Protocol</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050501">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9328479410">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050500/en0505050501/cm9328479410.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050500/en0505050501/cm9328479410text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Cisco Discovery Protocol (CDP) is an information-gathering tool used on a switch, ISR, or router to share information with other directly connected Cisco devices. By default, CDP begins running when the device boots up. It then sends periodic messages, known as CDP advertisements, onto its directly connected networks. </p> <p>CDP operates at Layer 2 only and can be used on many different types of local networks, including Ethernet and serial networks. Because it is a Layer 2 protocol, it can be used to determine the status of a directly connected link when no IP address has been configured, or if the IP address is incorrect. </p> <p>Two Cisco devices that are directly connected on the same local network are referred to as being neighbors. The concept of neighbor devices is important to understand when interpreting the output of CDP commands.</p> <p>Information gathered by CDP includes:</p> <p><ul><li> Device identifiers - Configured host name</li><li> Address list - Layer 3 address, if configured</li><li> Port identifier - Directly connected port; for example, serial 0/0/0</li><li> Capabilities list - Function or functions provided by the device </li><li> Platform - Hardware platform of the device; for example, Cisco 1841</li></ul></p> <p>The output from the <span class="cmd"><b>show cdp neighbors</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>show cdp neighbors detail</b></span> commands displays the information that a Cisco device collects from its directly connected neighbors.</p> <p>Viewing CDP information does not require logging in to the remote devices. Because CDP collects and displays a lot of information about directly connected neighbors, and no login is required, it is usually disabled in production networks for security purposes. Additionally, CDP consumes bandwidth and can impact network performance. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505050502">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm4586112658">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050500/en0505050502/cm4586112658/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0505000000/en0505050000/en0505050500/en0505050502/cm4586112658/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Use the CDP show commands to discover information about devices in the network.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en0505060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505060100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0505060101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm2595629277">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505060000/en0505060100/en0505060101/cm2595629277.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0505000000/en0505060000/en0505060100/en0505060101/cm2595629277text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en0505070000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0505070100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0505070101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm7813855914">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en0505000000/en0505070000/en0505070100/en0505070101/cm7813855914/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en0505000000/en0505070000/en0505070100/en0505070101/cm7813855914/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
