<textcomponents>

<component id="restart">
<text><![CDATA[Restart]]></text>
</component>
<component id="fastforward">
<text><![CDATA[Fast Forward]]></text>
</component>
<component id="rewind">
<text><![CDATA[Rewind]]></text>
</component>
<component id="end">
<text><![CDATA[End]]></text>
</component>
<component id="pause">
<text><![CDATA[Pause]]></text>
</component>
<component id="play">
<text><![CDATA[Play]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_instructions">
 <text><![CDATA[<b>Click Play to view the introduction.</b>]]></text>
 </component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b><p>The globalization of the<font color="#006699" size="+14"> Internet </font>has succeeded faster than anyone could have imagined.</p></b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b><p>The manner in which social, commercial, political and personal<font color="#006699" size="+14"> interactions </font>occur is rapidly changing to keep up with the<font color="#006699" size="+14"> evolution </font>of the Internet.</p></b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b><p>This<font color="#006699" size="+14"> expansion </font>has created a wider audience and a larger consumer base for whatever message, product or service can be<font color="#006699"size="+14"> delivered. </font></p></b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b><p>Today, there are millions of individuals<font color="#006699" size="+14"> connected </font>to this<font color="#006699" size="+14"> global network </font>and the number is growing.</p></b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>After completion of this chapter, you should be able to:<br/> </b><ul><li>Describe how the Internet is evolving and the various ways that businesses are using the Internet.</li><br/><li>Describe the importance of standards in the continuing growth of the Internet.</li><br/><li>Describe the purpose of an Internet Service Provider (ISP) and the services that it offers.</li><br/><li>Describe the hierarchical structure of the Internet and the purpose of the Point of Presence (POP) and the Internet Exchange Point (IXP).</li><br/><li>Identify the types of devices used by the ISP to provide services and describe the importance of scalability in the ISP network.</li><br/><li>Describe the various network support teams that work at an ISP and the roles and responsibilities of each one.</li></ul></p>]]></text>
</component>



</textcomponents>



