<transcript lastedited="01.09.09 11:01:50">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.7.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.	Which frame field is created by a source node and used by a destination node to ensure that a transmitted data signal has not been altered by interference, distortion, or signal loss?<br>A.	Transport Layer error check field<br>B.	Frame Check Sequence field<br>C.	User Datagram Protocol field<br>D.	Error correction<br>E.	Flow control field<br><br>2.	Which Data Link Layer addressing scheme is used in a point-to-point logical topology?<br>A.	IPv4 addressing<br>B.	IPv6 addressing<br>C.	Ring addressing<br>D.	Multilayer addressing<br>E.	Layer 2 addressing not required for this topology<br><br>3.	What do network hosts use Data Link Layer addresses for?<br>A.	Remote delivery<br>B.	Local and remote delivery<br>C.	Local delivery<br>D.	Remote delivery using routers<br><br>4.	Which three basic parts are common to all frame types supported by the Data Link Layer? (Choose three.)<br>A.	header<br>B.	type field<br>C.	MTU size<br>D.	data <br>E.	trailer<br>F.	CRC value<br><br>5.	What are two characteristics of the controlled media access method? (Choose two.)<br>A.	It is known as a deterministic access method.<br>B.	There are no collisions when this type of method is in use. <br>C.	Any station can transmit at any time.<br>D.	Bandwidth is more efficiently utilized than in a contention-based access method.<br>E.	Stations must determine if the media is carrying a signal before they can transmit. <br><br>6.	Which of the following are sublayers of the Data Link Layer?<br>A.	ACL, LMC<br>B.	MAC, LAC<br>C.	MAC, LLC<br>D.	O S I, LLC<br><br>7.	Which two of the following are Data Link Layer encapsulation details? (Choose two.)<br>A.	A header and trailer are added.<br>B.	Data is converted into packets.<br>C.	Packets are packaged into frames.<br>D.	Frames are divided into segments.<br>E.	Packets are changed into bits for Internet travel.<br><br>8.	What is achieved by the encapsulation process at the Data Link Layer?<br>A.	Packets are put into frames.<br>B.	Data is packaged into a packet.<br>C.	Packets are divided into segments.<br>D.	Data is converted for Internet transmission.<br><br>9.	Match the characteristic to the associated media access control method. (Not all characteristics are used.)<br>Characteristics:<br>Deterministic<br>Ethernet<br>Physical ring topology<br>No collisions<br>Non-deterministic<br>Only one station can transmit at a time<br>Stations can transmit at any time<br>Token passing<br>More efficient use of bandwidth<br><br>Media access control methods:<br>Controlled access<br>Contention-based access<br><br>10.	Match the characteristic to the topology type. (Not all characteristics are used.)<br>Characteristics:<br>Connects two nodes directly<br>CSMA/CD<br>Deterministic<br>Logical virtual circuit<br>Frame header not required<br>Token passing<br>Shared media<br><br>Topology types:<br>Point-to-Point<br>Multi-access<br>Ring]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
