<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 10:10:42">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.2.3 Portable Devices]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 2, Interactive<br><br>The diagram gives a brief description of the following devices: tablet PC, pocket PC, personal digital assistant, gaming device, and cellular phone.<br><br>Tablet PC <br>A tablet PC is typically a wireless device with a special stylus type pen that is used to write on an LCD touch screen. The notes or handwritten text can be digitized using built in handwriting recognition software. Tablet PC's can have comparable power and functionality to desktops and laptops. Some tablet PC's have a convertible screen that functions like a laptop, or can be rotated and folded down over the integrated keyboard. A tablet PC runs a special OS such as Microsoft Windows XP Tablet Edition.<br><br>Pocket PC <br>A pocket PC is a scaled down version of a laptop, with a less powerful CPU, less RAM, and no hard disk. Most pocket PC's have a small QWERTY style keyboard and color display screen with fairly good resolution. They use memory cards to store user documents and photographs. They run a special OS, such as Microsoft Mobile. They are typically about the size of a candy bar and weigh less than 7 ounces. The following features may be included: mini applications such as PowerPoint Viewer and Mobile Excel, cellular phone, email, wireless networking, persistent storage, memory card storage, touch screen, megapixel camera, camcorder, voice recorder, and high speed Internet capability.<br><br>Personal Digital Assistant<br>A PDA is also known as a handheld or palmtop. These are generic terms that are often applied to any small portable device that provides storage for personal information, such as calendars and contacts. They use primarily touch screen technology, although some also have a small keyboard. The distinction between these devices and the pocket PC is blurred. The PDA is increasingly being combined with cell phones and PC like functionality. A PDA can run an open source OS, such as Linux, or a proprietary OS, such as  Microsoft Windows CE, Palm OS, or Blackberry OS.<br><br>Gaming Device<br>A portable gaming device is a small computer that is dedicated to playing computer games. It has a good quality display and is increasingly more powerful. Some have wireless capabilities to allow multi person gaming. Examples of gaming devices include Sony PlayStation Portable (PSP) and Nintendo Dual Screen (DS). Gaming devices run a proprietary OS. Games are written for a specific OS and device.<br><br>Cellular Phone<br>Cell phones are in use everywhere and are replacing regular land line phones in some areas. They are becoming increasingly powerful but most do not have a keyboard and lack a large enough screen to display quality graphics. A newer cell phone has many features of a more advanced  P D A or pocket PC, including calendars, contact information, memory card storage, digital camera, camcorder, MP3 player, games, wireless networking capabilities, email, and Internet access.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
