<textcomponents>
<component id="titletxt1">
<text><![CDATA[Tablet PC]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt1">
<text><![CDATA[A Tablet PC is typically a wireless device with an LCD touch screen that allows a user to write on it using a special stylus type pen. The notes or handwritten text can be digitized using built-in handwriting recognition software. Tablet PCs can have comparable power and functionality to desktops and laptops. Some tablet PCs have a convertible screen that allows it to function like a laptop or the screen can be rotated and folded down over the integrated keyboard. Tablet PCs run a special OS such as Microsoft's Windows XP Tablet Edition.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt2">
<text><![CDATA[A Pocket PC is a scaled down version of a laptop, with a less powerful CPU, less RAM and no hard disk. Most Pocket PCs have small QWERTY-style keyboards and color display screens with fairly good resolution. They use memory cards to store user documents and photographs. They run a special OS such as Microsoft Mobile. They are typically about the size of a candy bar and weigh less than 7 ounces. Features can include: mini-applications such as PowerPoint viewer and Mobile Excel, Cellular phone, Wireless networking, persistent storage, memory card storage, touch screen, megapixel camera, camcorder, voice recorder and High-speed Internet capability. ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt2">
<text><![CDATA[Pocket PC ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt3">
<text><![CDATA[PDAs (personal digital assistant) are also known as handhelds or Palmtops. These are generic terms that are often applied to any small portable device that provides storage for personal information, such as calendars and contacts. They use primarily touch screen technology although some also have a small keyboard. The distinction between these devices and the Pocket PC is blurred. PDAs are increasingly being combined with cell phones and PC-like functionality. Some PDAs use Microsoft Windows CE and others use a proprietary OS such as Palm OS or Blackberry OS.  ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt3">
<text><![CDATA[PDA ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt4">
<text><![CDATA[Portable gaming devices are small computers that are dedicated to playing various computer games. They have good quality displays and are increasingly more powerful, with some having wireless capabilities to allow multi-person gaming. Examples include Sony PlayStation Portable (PSP) and Nintendo DS (dual screen). Gaming devices run a proprietary OS and games are written for this specific OS and device. ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt4">
<text><![CDATA[Game device]]></text>
</component>
<component id="txt5">
<text><![CDATA[Cellular phones (cell phones) are in use everywhere and are replacing regular land line phones in some areas. They are becoming increasingly powerful but they do not have a keyboard and lack a large enough screen to display quality graphics. Newer cell phones have many features of more advanced handheld PDAs and pocket PCs, including: calendars, contact information, memory card storage, digital camera, camcorder, MP3 player, games, wireless networking capabilities and Internet access. ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="titletxt5">
<text><![CDATA[Cell Phone]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each portable device for a description.</b>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>