<transcript lastedited="10.15.08 11:10:05">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.4.2 Using a Firewall]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Four Diagrams<br><br>Diagram 1, Animation<br><br>The diagram depicts the use of a firewall to allow and block traffic. There are three parts to the network: Internal, External, and DMZ.<br><br>Internal<br>The internal network has two hosts and one FTP server, which are connected to a switch. The switch is connected to a router, which is acting as a firewall.<br><br>External<br>The external network has a router, which is acting as a firewall. The router connects to the Internet.<br><br>DMZ<br>The DMZ is the area between the internal router and external router. There is a switch, which connects the two routers. There is a web server connected to the switch. <br><br>A web request is sent from one of the hosts within the internal network. The web request is sent to the switch and forwarded to the internal router. There are speech bubbles in the diagram, as follows:<br><br>The router says, "This request is permitted."<br><br>The web request is then forwarded to the switch within the DMZ, and then to the web server.<br><br>The web server says, "Got the request. I will send a response."<br><br>The response is then forwarded back to the source host.<br><br>An FTP request is sent from one of the hosts within the internal network. The FTP request is sent to the switch, and then forwarded to the internal FTP server. There is a speech bubble in the diagram, as follows:<br><br>The FTP server says, "Got the request. I will send a response." <br><br>A response is then sent from the FTP server to the source host.<br><br>A web request is sent from a host on the Internet. The request is forwarded to the external router. There are speech bubbles in the diagram, as follows:<br><br>The external router says, "This request is permitted."<br><br>The packet is then forwarded to the web server. <br><br>The web server says, "Got the request. I will send a response."<br><br>A response is then sent from the web server to the source host.<br><br>A FTP request is sent from a host on the Internet. The request is forwarded to the external router. There are speech bubbles in the diagram, as follows:<br><br>The External Router says, "The request is permitted."<br><br>The packet is then forwarded through the switch to the internal router. <br><br>The internal router says, "This request is denied."<br><br>The packet is then dropped.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
