<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">
<text>
<![CDATA[<b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b>]]>
</text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Computers are used all over the world and in all types of environments including: government, medical, education, manufacturing, legal and leisure.</b><br/><br/><ul><li>Special purpose customized computers can be integrated into devices such as televisions, cash registers, sound systems, and other electronic devices.</li><br/><li>In order to perform useful functions, computers require hardware, operating software and applications.</li><br/><li>A network application has two components, one that runs on the local computer (client) and one that runs on a remote computer (server).</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>


<!-- slide 1 graphic text -->
<component id="s1_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Local and Network Applications</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="s1_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Business/Industry</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="s1_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>General Use</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Word Processor</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Spreadsheet</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Accounting</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[<b>Medical</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[<b>Educational</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[<b>CAD</b>]]></text></component>







<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>There are many different types of computers available.</b><br/>
<ul><li>Servers provide services to many end users. Server hardware is optimized for quick response time to multiple network requests.</li><br/><li>Workstations are high-powered devices, designed to run specialty applications found in the work place.</li><br/><li>Desktops are stationary devices configured for home or business to support applications such as word processing, spreadsheets, e-mail and games.</li><br/><li>Laptops are comparable to desktops in usage and power, except they are built to be small, lightweight, with a built-in mouse, monitor and keyboard.</li><br/><li>Portable devices vary in size, power, graphic capability and sometimes provide multifunction capabilities, and include:</li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='20'>Laptop or notebook PC</li><li>Tablet or pocket PC</li><li>Personal Digital Assistant (PDA)</li><li>Gaming device</li><li>Cell Phones</li></TEXTFORMAT></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Mainframe</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Server</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Workstation</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Desktop</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Laptop</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Handheld</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s2_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Classes of Computers</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each icon to see the actual device.</b>]]></text>
</component>




<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Computers use binary digits to represent and interpret letters, numbers and special characters. Today, computer data as well as graphics, photos, voice, video and music are represented by patterns of bits.</b><br/><br/><ul><li>Bits are grouped into bytes.  Each byte contains eight bits.</li><br/><li>Bytes are used represent quantities of disk storage capacity and computer memory (RAM), common measurements of bytes are: kilobytes (KB), megabytes (MB), gigabytes (GB), and terabytes (TB).</li><br/><li>Bits per second is used as a measurement of access speed. Common Internet access speeds include kbps (kilobits per second), Mbps (megabits per second) or Gbps (gigabits per second).</li><br/><li>Megabytes per second (MBps) is the measurement of hard disk transfer speeds.</li><br/><li>Pixels are the unit of measure for graphics and image resolution.  In digital cameras, resolution is measured by the number of megapixels.</li><br/><li>Hertz are used to measure both the speed of the computer processor and wireless transmission and radio frequencies.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s3_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Measuring Data Storage Capacity</b>]]></text>
</component>






<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Data moves between system components on the bus, located on the computer motherboard.  Key system components include:</b><br/><br/><ul><li>A CPU is characterized by its processor speed and bus speed. The CPU processes all data, operating software and applications within the machine.</li><br/><li>RAM is used to store programs and data while being processed by the CPU.</li><br/><li>Adapter card functions include video and sound cards, network interface cards, modems, interface and controller cards.</li><br/><li>Hard Drives (Magnetic Storage) are the main storage medium found in servers, desktops and laptops.</li></ul>
<b>Additional devices provide functionality such as:</b><br/><br/><ul><li>Peripherals are external and are input, output, storage or networking devices.</li><br/><li>Surge suppressors and Uninterruptible Power Supply (UPS) protect the computer system from power fluctuations.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Computer System</b>]]></text>
</component>



<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Computers are a collection of very complex components and peripherals. Occasionally, one of these components fails or must be upgraded, which requires opening the computer and working inside the case. It is very important to follow proper safety and installation procedures whenever performing maintenance on a computer.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s5_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Safety and Best Practices</b>]]></text>
</component>



</textcomponents>