<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 08:10:32">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.6.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Five Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br><br>Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts two shaded bubbles that overlap each other. The larger of the two bubbles is labeled the General Use sector. The second smaller bubble is labeled the Business/Industry sector. Connected to the General Use sector are the following boxes: Spreadsheet, Accounting, and Word Processing applications. Attached to the Business/Industry sector are the following boxes: Medical, Educational, and CAD, meant to indicate that they are enterprise derived.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>Computers are used all over the world and in all types of environments, including government, medical, education, manufacturing, legal, and leisure.<br><br>Special purpose customized computers can be integrated into devices, such as televisions, cash registers, sound systems, and other electronic devices. To perform use functions, computers require hardware, operating software, and applications.<br>A network application has two components: one that runs on the local computer (client) and one that runs on a remote computer (server).<br><br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the different classes of computers, as follows:<br><br>Mainframe computer<br>Server computer<br>Workstation computer<br>Desktop computer<br>Laptop computer<br>Handheld computer<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>There are many different types of computers available.<br>A server provides services to end users. Server hardware is optimized for quick response time to multiple network requests.<br>A workstation is a high powered device designed to run specialty applications found in the work place.<br>A desktop is a stationary device that is configured for home or business to support applications, such as word processing, spreadsheets, email, and games.<br>A laptop is comparable to a desktop in usage and power, except it is designed to be small, lightweight, with a built in mouse, monitor, and keyboard.<br>Portable devices vary in size, power, graphic capability, and multifunction capabilities. The following are types of portable devices:<br>Laptop or notebook PC<br>Tablet or pocket PC<br>Personal digital assistant<br>Gaming device<br>Cell phone<br><br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts and image of a desktop PC.  The image has been zoomed into to accentuate the keyboard and LCD screen. It appears to be in a multi PC environment.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>Computers use binary digits to represent and interpret letters, numbers, and special characters. Today, computer data, graphics, photos, voice, video, and music are represented by patterns of bits.<br>Bits are grouped into bytes. Each byte contains eight bits.<br>Bytes are used to represent quantities of disk storage capacity and computer memory (RAM). Common measurements of bytes are kilobyte, megabyte, gigabyte, and terabyte.<br>Bits per second is used as a measurement of access speed. Common Internet access speeds include kilobits per second, megabits per second, or gigabits per second.<br>Megabytes per second is used to measure hard disk transfer speeds.<br>Pixels are the unit of measure for graphics and image resolution. In digital cameras, resolution is measured by the number of megapixels. <br>Hertz is used to measure the speed of wireless transmission and radio frequencies, and the speed of the computer processor.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a desktop computer broken down into separate components prior to build. The components are as follows:<br><br>Adapter cards, such as video, sound, network<br>RAM<br>Hard disk drives<br>Floppy drive<br>CPU<br>Main Board<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>Data moves between system components on the bus that is located on the computer motherboard. The following are the main system components:<br>A CPU is characterized by the processor speed and bus speed. The CPU processes the data, operational software, and computer applications.<br>RAM is used to store programs and data that is being processed by the CPU.<br>Adapter card functions include video and sound cards, network interface cards, modems, interface, and controller cards.<br>A magnetic storage hard drive is the main storage medium found in servers, desktops, and laptops.<br>Additional devices provide other types of functionality:<br>Input, output, storage, and networking devices that are external peripheral devices.<br>Surge suppressors and uninterruptible power supply devices that protect the computer system from power fluctuations.<br><br>Diagram 5, Image<br><br>The image depicts a woman sitting in front of a desktop PC indicating that Safety and Best Practices should be implemented whenever maintenance or  trouble shooting is being attempted on a desktop PC.<br><br>Diagram 5 text<br><br>A computer is a collection of complex components and peripherals. Occasionally, a component fails or must be upgraded, which requires opening the computer and working inside the case. It is very important to follow proper safety and installation procedures when performing maintenance on a computer.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
