<transcript lastedited="12.16.08 15:12:30">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.7.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Eight Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br><br>Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts voice, video, and data converged networks.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>This chapter discussed basic concepts and benefits of networking, and the characteristics of local Ethernet networks.<br><br>Information networks can carry voice, video, and data.<br>Information networks consist of peripherals, hosts, network devices, and media.<br>Topology diagrams used to depict both logical and physical network design.<br>Hosts can play the role of client, server, or both.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts protocol characteristics.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>All communication has a source, a destination, and a channel.<br>Computer communications operate under special rules, called protocols.<br>Protocols define the characteristics of a message including: encoding, formatting, encapsulation, size, timing, and patterns.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the network protocol evolution.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>To communicate on a local network requires the computers share a common protocol.<br>The most common protocol used on local wired networks is industry standard Ethernet.<br>Each local host in an Ethernet network is identified by a physical MAC address, which is pre configured into a hosts NIC.<br>Proprietary Vendor Protocols (1970's) IBM, NCR, Xerox, D E C, HP<br>Limited Number of standards (1980's and 1990's) Ethernet (IEEE 8 0 2 dot 3), ARCnet (IEEE 8 0 2 dot 4), Token Ring (IEEE 8 0 2 dot 5)<br>And the winner is Ethernet (2000)<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts hierarchical network design.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>It is common to divide larger networks into smaller, more manageable ones using a layered hierarchical design, which can include the following layers:<br>Access<br>Distribution<br>Core<br><br>Each of these layers has a primary function and associated devices.<br><br>Diagram 5, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts routed network using logical and physical addressing.<br><br>Diagram 5 text<br><br>Logical IP addresses are used to identify the location of a host within this hierarchical design.<br>To deliver a packet to an individual host requires both a physical MAC address and a logical IP address.<br>ARP is used to resolve an IP address to a MAC address for local delivery.<br><br>Diagram 6, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts hierarchical network design.<br><br>Diagram 6 text<br><br>Access Layer<br>The Access Layer is the first point of entry into the network for all hosts.<br>Hosts are usually directly connected using Ethernet cables to an Access Layer device, such as a hub or switch.<br>MAC address and IP addresses are used on the local network at the Access Layer.<br>Distribution Layer<br>The Distribution Layer connects independent local networks and controls traffic between them.<br>Individual hosts are not usually connected directly to the Distribution Layer devices.<br>Routers are the main networking device within the Distribution Layer and use IP addresses to move packets between networks.<br><br>Diagram 7, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts network planning.<br><br>Diagram 7 text<br><br>A network plan starts with the gathering of information about how the network will be used. This information includes the following parameters:<br>The number and type of hosts to be connected to the network.<br>The applications to be used.<br>Sharing and Internet connectivity requirements.<br>Security and privacy considerations.<br>Reliability and up time expectations.<br>Connectivity requirements, including wired and wireless.<br><br>Diagram 8, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a WRT300N wireless router multifunction device.<br><br>Diagram 8 text<br><br>Cisco ISR's, and other multifunction networking devices connect home and small business networks in order for multiple hosts to share resources and to connect to the Internet.<br>A home networking device is a simplified low cost device commonly used in small networks.<br>These devices typically provide the functionality of a switch, router, and wireless access point in one device.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
