<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 17:01:32">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.7.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Match the wireless standard to the appropriate description.<br>Standards:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b.<br>8 0 2 dot 11g.<br>8 0 2 dot 11a.<br>8 0 2 dot 11n.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>Specifies data rates of 1, 2, 5.5, and 11 Megabits per second due to differently sized spreading sequences specified in the DSSS modulation technique.<br><br>Uses the 5.7 Gigahertz band with less interference, but obstructions can affect performance and limit range.<br><br>Uses multiple radios and antennae at endpoints, each broadcasting on the same frequency to establish multiple streams.<br><br>Uses the 8 0 2 dot 11 MAC address, but with higher data rates in the 2.4 Gigahertz I SM band by using the OFDM modulation technique.<br><br>2.Match the wireless device to the appropriate description.<br>Devices:<br>Wireless NIC.<br>Access point.<br>Wireless router.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>Connects multiple wireless clients or stations to the wired LAN.<br><br>Connects two separated, isolated wired networks together.<br><br>Encodes a data stream onto an RF signal using the configured modulation technique.<br><br>3.At which layer of the O S I model do wireless access points operate?<br>A.Physical.<br>B.Data link.<br>C.Network.<br>D.Application.<br><br>4.Which two steps are required for a wireless client to associate with an access point? (Choose two.)<br>A.IP addressing.<br>B.Wireless address translation.<br>C.Wireless client authentication.<br>D.Channel identification.<br>E.Wireless client association.<br><br>5.Which three W LAN client authentication types require a preprogrammed network key to be set on the client? (Choose three.)<br>A.Open with data encryption disabled.<br>B.Shared with data encryption algorithm WEP.<br>C.WPA with data encryption algorithm TKIP.<br>D.WPA-PSK with data encryption algorithm TKIP<br>E.WPA2 with data encryption algorithm A E S.<br>F.WPA2-PSK with data encryption algorithm A E S.<br><br>6.Which two items contribute to the security of a W LAN? (Choose two.)<br>A.WPA2.<br>B.Use of multiple channels.<br>C.Hiding the SSID.<br>D.Open authentication.<br>E.A E S.<br><br>7.Which term is used for products that are tested to be interoperable in both PSK and 8 0 2 dot 1x / Extensible Authentication Protocol (E AP) operation for authentication?<br>A.Personal mode.<br>B.WPA2 compatible.<br>C.RADIUS authenticated.<br>D.Enterprise mode.<br>E.Pre-shared key authenticated.<br><br>8.To help ensure a secure wireless network, most enterprise networks should follow which i e e e standard?<br>A.8 0 2 dot 11a<br>B.8 0 2 dot 11b<br>C.8 0 2 dot 11c<br>D.8 0 2 dot 11i<br><br>9.Refer to the diagram description to answer the question.<br>A screenshot of the Linksys G U I shows the wireless security screen and the network authentication entry area with Open as the default. Other options are listed as potential answers.<br><br>Which method of network authentication provides the highest level of security?<br>A.Open<br>B.Shared<br>C.WPA<br>D.WPA-PSK<br><br>10.Which two combinations of 8 0 2 dot 11b RF channels would allow two wireless AP's to operate simultaneously in the same room with no channel overlap? (Choose two.)<br>A.Channels 10 and 6.<br>B.Channels 9 and 6.<br>C.Channels 8 and 5.<br>D.Channels 7 and 2.<br>E.Channels 6 and 2.<br>F.Channels 6 and 11.<br><br>11.Why do cordless devices, such as telephones, sometimes interfere with wireless access points?<br>A.These devices operate at similar frequencies.<br>B.These devices operate at the same frequencies and have higher RF power settings.<br>C.These devices flood the entire frequency spectrum with low power noise, which may cause loss of signal for wireless devices trying to connect with an access point.<br>D.The signal from the cordless device is non-polarized and combines with the access point polarized signal, thus reducing overall signal strength.<br><br>12.Refer to the diagram description to answer the question.<br>A laptop computer is positioned at the intersection of two AP range areas that overlap.<br><br>What is the recommended overlap between the two wireless access points to provide proper connectivity for users?<br>A.5 to 10 percent<br>B.10 to15 percent<br>C.15 to 20 percent<br>D.20 to 25 percent<br><br>13.Match the authentication method to the correct encryption algorithm or security protocol it would use.<br>Authentication Methods:<br>Open.<br>WEP.<br>WPA.<br>WPA2.<br><br>Protocols:<br>A E S.<br>Disabled.<br>RC4.<br>TKIP.<br><br>14.Which W LAN client settings would be reviewed to resolve encryption problems with the access point?<br>A.Wireless mode (8 0 2 dot 11a, 8 0 2 dot 11b, 8 0 2 dot 11g).<br>B.Wireless network card drivers.<br>C.Channel selection for ad hoc network.<br>D.TCP/IP properties.<br>E.Wireless association properties.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
