<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 18:01:52">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.6.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question One. Refer to the following diagram description when answering this question: There is one switch, S1 with two PC's attached. PC1 is attached to S1 Port 1, and PC2 is attached to S1 Port 3. A cable is attached to S1 Port 2, but no PC is attached.<br><br>There are six steps in the process of a switch learning a MAC address for the purposes of forwarding Ethernet frames. Put the following six steps in order by placing the appropriate number in the blank.<br>Answer:<br>One. The switch receives a broadcast frame from PC1 on Port 1.<br>Two. The switch enters the source MAC address and the switch port that received the frame into the address table.<br>Three. Because the destination address is a broadcast, the switch floods the frame to all ports, except the port on which it received the frame.<br>Four. The destination device replies to the broadcast with a unicast frame addressed to PC1.<br>Five. The switch enters the source MAC address of PC2 and the port number of the switch port that received the frame into the address table. The destination address of the frame and its associated port is found in the MAC address table.<br>Six. The switch can now forward frames between source and destination devices without flooding, because it has entries in the address table that identify the associated ports.<br><br><br>Question Two. List the two principal switch-forwarding methods and the two primary methods of memory buffering in switches.<br>Answer:<br>Store and forward switching and cut-through switching.<br>Port-based memory buffering and shared memory buffering.<br><br>Question Three. Refer to the following command output to answer the question. What is the likely reason for interface V LAN 99 displaying up /down as its status?<br><br>S1# show running config<br><br>Interface FastEthernet0/18<br>Switchport access v lan 99<br>Switchport mode access<br><br>Interface V LAN 99<br>i p address 172.17.99.11 255.255.255.0<br>No i p route cache<br><br>S1# show i p interface brief<br>InterfaceIP AddressOK?MethodStatus<br>V LAN 99172.17.99.11YESmanualup<br><br>FastEthernet0/18unassignedYESunsetdown<br>FastEthernet0/19unassignedYESunsetdown<br><br>Gigabit Ethernet 0/2 unassigned              YES  unsetdown<br><br>Answer: There are no active physical interfaces associated with V LAN 99.<br><br>Question Four. Refer to the following commands to answer the question. Which two commands are unnecessary for a basic SSH configuration providing remote network connectivity for SSH clients? (Choose two.)<br><br>Switch (config)#i p domain name my domain dot com<br>Switch (config)#crypto key generate r s a<br>Switch (config)#i p ssh version 2<br>Switch (config)#line v t y 0 15<br>Switch (config-line)#transport input SSH<br><br>Answer: The i p ssh version 2 and transport input SSH commands are not required to provide remote access.<br><br>Question Five. List and describe the three port security violation modes.<br>Answer: <br>Protect: When the number of secure MAC addresses reaches the limit allowed on the port, packets with unknown source addresses are dropped until you remove a sufficient number of secure MAC addresses or increase the number of maximum allowable addresses. You are not notified that a security violation has occurred.<br><br>Restrict: When the number of secure MAC addresses reaches the limit allowed on the port, packets with unknown source addresses are dropped until you remove a sufficient number of secure MAC addresses or increase the number of maximum allowable addresses. In this mode, you are notified that a security violation has occurred. Specifically, an SNMP trap is sent, a syslog message is logged, and the violation counter increments.<br><br>Shutdown: In this mode, a port security violation causes the interface to immediately become error disabled and turns off the port L E D. It also sends an SNMP trap, logs a syslog message, and increments the violation counter. When a secure port is in the error disabled state, you can bring it out of this state by entering the err disable recovery cause p secure violation global configuration command, or you can manually re-enable it by entering the shutdown and no shutdown interface configuration commands. This is the default mode.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
