<transcript lastedited="10.14.08 17:10:01">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[11 Questions ]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.A technician is setting up equipment. Which three devices will need IP addresses? (Choose three)<br><br>a printer with an Ethernet card<br>a web camera attached directly to a host<br>a server with two NIC's<br>an IP phone<br>a standalone workstation<br>a PDA attached to a networked workstation<br><br>2.Which three statements are true about binary octets? (Choose three)<br><br>if a bit is a zero (0), its column value is not counted.<br>The value of each bit in an octet is twice that of the bit to its right.<br>The rightmost bit in an octet has a value of 0 when it is turned on.<br>A host looks at every bit of an IP address as it is received by the host NIC.<br>If all of the bits in an octet are set to one (1), the value of the octet is 256.<br>There are 32 value positions in an octet.<br><br>3.Match the number of the first octet to the corresponding  address Class: A, B, C (Not all terms will be used)<br><br>first octet number of 0<br>first octet number of 126<br>first octet number of 130<br>first octet number of 200<br>first octet number of 224<br>first octet number of 240<br><br>4.Which statement is true concerning private network addresses?<br><br>They are always routed on the Internet.<br>They can be used by only one company at a time.<br>They enable Internet web servers to be easily accessed by outside users.<br>They are more secure as they are visible only to the local network.<br><br>5.How many Class C networks are reserved for private address space?<br><br>1<br>16<br>128<br>256<br><br>6.What is the destination MAC address of a broadcast Ethernet frame?<br><br>255.255.255.255<br>1.1.1.1<br>AA-AA-AA-AA-AA-AA<br>FF-FF-FF-FF-FF-FF<br><br>7.Match the statement to the Category (4 statements per category)<br><br>Categories:<br>Static IP addressing<br>Dynamic IP Addressing<br><br>Statements:<br>useful for printers and servers<br>provides more control of network resources<br>possibility of input errors<br>useful for mobile users<br>limited in time period<br>addresses provided by a server<br>draws addresses automatically from a pool<br>addresses are not reassigned to another devices<br><br>8.Place these DHCP messages in the correct order for a host to obtain an IP address from a DHCP server.<br><br>DHCP Request<br>DHCP Discover<br>DHCP Offer<br>DHCP Acknowledge<br><br>9.An ISR has a public IP address issued by the ISP. What is the purpose of the public IP address?<br><br>allows internal hosts to communicate with each other on the local network<br>allows internal hosts to communicate with other hosts on the Internet<br>allows internal the ISR to communicate with the local hosts on the network<br>allows the ISR to communicate with the local servers on the network<br><br>10.What function does NAT perform in an ISR?<br><br>NAT takes a source IP address and translates it to a default gateway address.<br>NAT takes a local IP address and translates it to an internal source IP address.<br>NAT takes an internal global IP address and translates it to a local source IP address.<br>NAT takes an internal source IP address and translates it to a global IP address.<br><br>11.Refer to the graphic, What two types of IP address should be used on the ISR at interfaces A and B? (Choose two)<br><br>Graphic: Linksys WRT300N Router(R1)<br>R1 is connected to the ISP Router on Interface B (Public Network)<br>R1 is connected to the local switch on interface A (Local Network)<br>The Local Network has three Hosts (H1, H2, H3) which are connected via Switch<br><br>Interface A should use a private IP address.<br>Interface A should use a public IP address.<br>Interface A should use a source IP address.<br>Interface B should use a private IP address.<br>Interface B should use a public IP address.<br>Interface B should use a destination IP address.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
