<transcript lastedited="12.18.08 08:12:24">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.6.1 Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[12 Questions<br><br>1. Why is IEEE 8 0 2 dot 11 wireless technology able to transmit further distances than Bluetooth technology?<br>Transmits at much lower frequencies<br>Has higher power output<br>Transmits at much higher frequencies<br>Uses better encryption methods<br><br>2. What are three advantages of wireless over wired LAN technology? (Choose three)<br>Lower ongoing costs<br>Longer transmission distance<br>Ease of installation<br>Easily expandable<br>Higher level of security<br>Cheaper host adapters<br><br>3. In which scenario would wireless security be most important? <br>Your wireless mouse uses the I rDA port on your desktop PC.<br>The local coffee shop provides free internet access as a wireless hotspot.<br>A real estate agent sends information on the sale of a house through a cell phone.<br>Two users create a wireless peer to peer network in order to share a music file.<br><br>4. Which wireless technology standard provides the most compatibility with older wireless standards, but has greater performance?<br>8 0 2 dot 11a<br>8 0 2 dot 11b<br>8 0 2 dot 11g<br>8 0 2 dot 11n<br><br>5. Match the characteristic to the W LAN component. Each component has two characteristics.<br>Characteristic:<br>Allows long range point to point connections between networks<br>Acts as a media converter<br>Participates as a host device in a wireless network<br>Connects two wireless network as a wireless link<br>Controls access between a wired and wireless network<br>Referred to as a S T A<br><br>Component:<br>Wireless Client<br>Access Point<br>Wireless Bridge<br><br>6. Match the characteristic to the installation type.<br><br>Characteristic:<br>An AP controls who talks and when<br>Two or more wireless clients in a peer to peer network<br>Individual S T A's do not communicate directly with each other<br>Usually a less expensive network<br>Larger networks require this type of installation <br>Does not include an AP<br><br>Installation type:<br>Ad hoc <br>Infrastructure Mode<br><br>7. What is CSMA/CA on a network?<br>An access method used by wireless technology to avoid duplicate SSID's.<br>An access method used by any technology that has excess collisions.<br>An access method used by wired Ethernet technology to avoid collisions.<br>An access method used by wireless technology to avoid collisions.<br><br>8. Match the statement to the category. There are two statements per category.<br>Statement:<br>A wireless attacker needs physical access to your network in order to launch an attack.<br>As wireless hacker within radio range of any access point could launch an attack.<br>If someone you don't know gains access to your wireless network, they can use your internet connection.<br>The purpose of war chalking is to attack a wireless network and deny access to the internet to the wireless network owner.<br><br>Category:<br>True<br>False<br><br>9. What statement is true about authentication using pre shared keys when E AP is enabled?<br>Use a key to encrypt an random string of bytes sent by a AP.<br>Requires a backend authentication server such as RADIUS.<br>Performs one way authentication only.<br>Allows clients to associate based on MAC address.<br><br>10. When is a client considered to be "authenticated" when only MAC address filtering is enabled on the access point?<br>When the client gives the access point the correct secret key.<br>When the client sends the MAC address to the access point.<br>When the access point verifies that the MAC address is in the MAC table and sends a confirmation message to the client. <br>When the access point sends the MAC address to the server and receives notification that the MAC address is a valid one.<br><br>11. Match the statement to the category. There are two statements per category.<br>Statement:<br>The MAC address filtering feature requires E AP to be enabled.<br>A MAC address of a PC can be used by another PC controlled by an attacker.<br>The MAC address filtering feature requires manual entry of approved MAC addresses.<br>A wireless access point with MAC filtering configured disables non authorized wireless NIC's.<br><br>Category:<br>True<br>False<br><br>12. Match the term to the category. Note that not all terms will be used.<br>Term:<br>E AP<br>WEP<br>WPA<br>Open<br>SSID<br>Wifi<br>Pre shared keys<br><br>Category:<br>Authentication<br>Encryption<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
