<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 10:09:32">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.4.1 - Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 1, Image <br><br>The diagram depicts a network with three buildings, Building A, Building B, and Building C.<br>Building A is connected to Building B via fiber-optic cable.<br>Building A is connected to Building C via fiber optic cable.<br>Building A has an MDF which is connected to two switches (I DF-A2, I DF-A1) via fiber-optic or U T P Cable. I DF-A1 has four hosts connected, I DF-A2 has 3 hosts connected.<br>Building B has an I DF (I DF-B1) with three hosts connected.<br>Building C has an I DF (I DF-C1) with three hosts connected.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>Network infrastructure diagrams document devices in a network. Network documentation includes the Business Continuity plan, Business Security plan, Network Maintenance plan, and Service Level Agreements. <br>The enterprise NOC manages and monitors all network resources. <br>End-users connect to the network via Access Layer switches and wireless A P's in the IDF. <br>P o E provides power to devices over the same U T P cable that carries data. <br><br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a network of four buildings, HQ, Site A, Site B, and Site C. The network is exposed to outside attacks. These attacks include F W, I D S, A C L, D M Z, VPN, and I P S attacks.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>The enterprise edge provides Internet access and service for users inside the organization. <br>The POP provides a direct link to an I S P and connects remote sites. <br>The POP contains a de-marc line of responsibility, between the service provider and customer. <br>Edge devices provide security against attacks. <br>Services are brought to the enterprise by copper wires or fiber-optic cable. <br><br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a 48 port 10 /100 /1000 Cisco Gigabit Ethernet switch, which has had the two 10 Gigabit fiber-optic uplink ports removed from the switch.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>Access Layer switches provide connectivity to end users. <br>Distribution Layer routers move packets between locations and the Internet. <br>Routers and switches use in-band and out-of-band management. <br>Routers can control broadcasts.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
