<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_title1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Backup Media</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each type of data loss for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="pop_title01">
<text><![CDATA[Hardware Failure]]></text>
</component>

<component id="Poptext01">
<text><![CDATA[As hardware ages the probability of hardware failure and data loss increases. Hardware failure usually means a lot of lost data. Recovering from hardware failure requires replacing the failed hardware and restoring all the data from a current backup.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="pop_title02">
<text><![CDATA[User Error]]></text>
</component>

<component id="Poptext02">
<text><![CDATA[User error includes accidentally overwriting a file, deleting an important file, editing a file incorrectly, or deleting important information within the file. This type of data loss often represents a higher impact to the user than to the company. The company will typically lose productivity time while the user recreates or retrieves the lost data. With user error, generally a specific file or folder must be retrieved from a backup source.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="pop_title03">
<text><![CDATA[Theft]]></text>
</component>

<component id="Poptext03">
<text><![CDATA[Thieves target laptops, memory sticks, CDs and DVDs, tapes, or other data storage devices. When taking company data off site, create backup copies of all data. Keep careful track of portable data sources. It is also a good idea to encrypt all data on portable devices so that it is of no use to the thief.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="pop_title04">
<text><![CDATA[Malicious Activity]]></text>
</component>

<component id="Poptext04">
<text><![CDATA[Viruses and hackers can destroy data. Some viruses target specific types of files to corrupt. Some viruses can affect the hard drive that the data is stored on and can cause the drive to be inaccessible. Additionally, hackers can manipulate data, such as defacing a web site to gain exposure.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="pop_title05">
<text><![CDATA[Operating System Failure]]></text>
</component>

<component id="Poptext05">
<text><![CDATA[A bad patch or driver update could result in serious operating system failure, preventing access to needed data. With backed up operating system files, the operating system can often be restored at a functional level. However, a reinstallation may be necessary and possibly a full restore of all the missing data.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_cap01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Hardware Failure<b/>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_cap02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>User Error</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_cap03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Theft</b>]]></text>
</component>
 
<component id="ID_cap04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Malicious Activity</b>]]></text>
</component>
 
<component id="ID_cap05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Operating System Failure</b>]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>


