<transcript lastedited="12.17.08 12:12:37">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.4.3 - A Scalable Network Architecture]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the structure of the Internet with Tier 1, 2, and 3 ISP's, along with the hierarchical, distributed, and peer features of the Internet. <br><br>Tier 1 - At the center of the Internet, Tier 1 ISP's provide national and international connections. These ISP's treat each other as equals. Examples are Verizon, Sprint, AT&T, NTT, cable systems, and wide area wireless networks. This is the backbone of the Internet.<br><br>Tier 2 - Tier 2 ISP's are smaller and often provide regional service. Tier 2 ISP's usually pay Tier 1 ISP's for connectivity to the rest of the Internet. The point where ISP's interconnect is often called a border.<br><br>Tier 3 - Tier 3 ISP's provide local service directly to end users. Tier 3 ISP's are usually connected to Tier 2 ISP's and pay Tier 2 providers for Internet access.<br><br>Hierarchical - The Domain Name System (DNS) provides a hierarchical directory of addresses so that one server does not have to hold the entire list of millions of addresses. The DNS servers update each other with the top level addresses, so local devices can search the closest server and be confident that the information is up to date. The DNS servers contain lower level addresses only for the networks that are directly connected. This keeps the directories from getting too large.<br><br>Distributed - The distributed nature of connections and directories allows communication to bypass bottlenecks and outages. Originally designed to protect against military attack, the system has also proved to be the best way to offer a scalable, reliable civilian network. If one DNS server is down, local devices can get in touch with another one. If one route is congested or broken, communication is automatically directed along another route. <br><br>Peers - Peer connections between networks at the same level provide direct connections, bypassing longer routes and preventing congestion on the backbone. <br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
