<transcript lastedited="10.31.08 08:10:19">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.4.6  - Configuring Port Security]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts multiple images including port security, secure MAC address types and security violation modes.<br><br>Port Security:<br>Implement security on all switch ports to:<br>- Specify a group of valid MAC addresses allowed on a port.<br>- Allow only one MAC address to access the port.<br>- Specify that the port automatically shuts down if unauthorized MAC addresses are detected.<br><br>Secure MAC Address Types:<br>Secure MAC addresses are the following types:<br>- Static secure.<br>- Dynamic secure.<br>- Sticky secure. <br><br>Sticky secure MAC addresses have these characteristics:<br>- Learned dynamically and converted to sticky secure MAC addresses stored in the running configuration.<br>- Disabling sticky learning removes MAC addresses from the running configuration, but not from the MAC table.<br>- Sticky secure MAC addresses are lost when the switch restarts.<br>- Saving sticky secure MAC addresses in the startup configuration file enables the switch to have them when it restarts.<br>- Disabling sticky learning converts sticky MAC addresses to dynamic secure addresses and removes them from the running configuration.<br><br>Security Violation Modes:<br>Security violations occur in these situations:<br>- A station whose MAC address is not in the address table attempts to access the interface when the table is full.<br>- An address is being used on two secure interfaces in the same V LAN.<br><br>Security violation modes include protect, restrict, and shutdown.<br><br>Protect Violation Mode:<br>- Forwards Traffic: No.<br>- Sends Syslog Message: No.<br>- Displays Error Message: No.<br>- Increases Violation Counter: No.<br>- Shuts Down Port: No.<br><br>Restrict Violation Mode:<br>- Forwards Traffic: No.<br>- Sends Syslog Message: Yes.<br>- Displays Error Message: No.<br>- Increases Violation Counter: Yes.<br>- Shuts Down Port: No.<br><br>Shutdown Violation Mode:<br>- Forwards Traffic: No.<br>- Sends Syslog Message: Yes.<br>- Displays Error Message: No.<br>- Increases Violation Counter: Yes.<br>- Shuts Down Port: Yes.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
