<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[Virtual Network]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[Tunneling]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[Private Network]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[Encryption]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[Encrypt]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[Encrypted Message]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[Decrypt]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[Virtual Private Network = Tunneling + Encryption]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt09"><text><![CDATA[Click the highlighted areas to learn more about tunneling options.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt10"><text><![CDATA[ ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt11"><text><![CDATA[ ]]></text></component><component id="TextBox1"><text><![CDATA[<b>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) </b>tunnels provide a specific pathway across the shared WAN. They  encapsulate traffic with new packet headers to ensure delivery to specific destinations. The network is private. This is because traffic can enter a tunnel only at an endpoint and can leave only at the other endpoint. Tunnels do not provide true confidentiality (like encryption does) but can carry encrypted traffic.<b>IP Security (IPSec)</b> acts at the Network Layer, protecting and authenticating IP packets between participating IPSec devices (peers). IPSec is not bound to any specific encryption, authentication, security algorithms, or keying technology. IPSec is a framework of open standards.<b>Layer 2 Forwarding Protocol (L2F)</b> is a protocol developed by Cisco that supports the creation of secure virtual private dialup networks over the Internet by tunneling Layer 2 frames. <b>Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol (PPTP)</b> was developed by Microsoft. It is described in RFC2637. PPTP is widely deployed in Windows client software to create VPNs across TCP/IP networks. <b>Layer 2 Tunneling Protocol (L2TP)</b> is an IETF standard that incorporates the best attributes of PPTP and L2F.  L2TP is used to tunnel Point-Point Protocol (PPP) through a public network, such as the Internet, using IP. Since the tunnel occurs on Layer 2, the upper layer protocols are unaware of the tunnel. Like GRE, L2TP can also encapsulate any Layer 3 protocol.]]></text></component><component id="TextBox2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Encryption algorithms</b><b>Data Encryption Standard (DES) algorithm</b>- DES was developed by IBM. DES uses a 56-bit key, ensuring high-performance encryption. 3DES is a symmetric key cryptosystem. <b>Triple DES (3DES) algorithm</b>- 3DES is a variant of the 56-bit DES. 3DES operates similarly to DES, in that data is broken into 64-bit blocks. 3DES then processes each block three times, each time with an independent 56-bit key. 3DES provides significant encryption strength over 56-bit DES. DES is a symmetric key cryptosystem.<b>Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) :</b> The National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) have recently adopted AES to replace the existing DES encryption in cryptographic devices. AES provides stronger security than DES. It is computationally more efficient than 3DES. AES offers three different key lengths: 128-, 192-, and 256-bit keys.<b>Rivest, Shamir, and Adleman (RSA) :</b> RSA is an asymmetrical key cryptosystem. It uses a key length of 512, 768, 1024, or larger. IPSec does not use RSA for data encryption. IKE only uses RSA encryption during the peer authentication phase.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody"><text><![CDATA[IP Address. . : 192.168.1.1<br>Subnet Mask . . : 255.255.255.0<br>Default Gateway . . : 192.168.1.254 ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle2"><text><![CDATA["Host2 Says:"]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody2"><text><![CDATA[IP Address. . : 192.168.1.2<br>Subnet Mask . . : 255.255.255.0<br>Default Gateway . . : 192.168.1.254 ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle3"><text><![CDATA["Host3 Says:"]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody3"><text><![CDATA[IP Address. . : 192.168.1.3<br>Subnet Mask . . : 255.255.255.0<br>Default Gateway . . : 192.168.1.254 ]]></text></component></textcomponents>