<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 13:01:10">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.3.1  - Switch Configuration Issues]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts switch configuration issues. <br><br>Topology One:<br>Switch S1 has two PC's. PC1 is connected to Port F0/11, and PC3 is connected to F0/6. The PC1 IP address is 172.17.10.21. The PC3 IP address is 172.17.30.23. PC1 is in V LAN 10, and PC3 is in V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using two links and two router interfaces. Switch S1 port F0/4 is connected to router R1 interface F0/0 with IP address 172.17.10.1 /24. Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/1 with IP address 172.17.30.1 /24. This allows the router to route between V LAN 10 and V LAN 30. Switch S1 ports F0/4 and F0/11 are in V LAN 10. Switch S1 ports F0/5 and F0/6 are in V LAN 30.<br><br>Topology One illustrates an issue with traditional inter-V LAN routing. If the switch port F0/4 is in the default V LAN, it must be configured to be in V LAN 10 so that PC1 can communicate with the router R1 interface F0/0 and allow routing to occur.<br><br>Topology Two:<br>Same as Topology One, except that switch S1 F0/5 has only one link to router R1 interface F0/0. The single router physical interface F0/0 has two logical subinterfaces defined: <br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 10, IP address 172.17.10.1<br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 30, IP address 172.17.30.1<br><br>Topology Two illustrates an issue with router-on-a-stick routing. If the switch port F0/5 is not configured as a trunk and then left in the default V LAN for the port, the router does not function correctly because its configured subinterfaces cannot send or receive V LAN tagged traffic. This situation prevents all configured V LAN's from routing through router R1 to reach the other V LAN's.<br><br>Topology Three:<br>Two switches, S1 and S2, are connected using a trunk. Switch S2 has PC1 and PC3 connected. Switch S1 has PC3 connected. The PC1 IP address is 172.17.10.21. The PC3 IP address is 172.17.30.23. PC1 is in V LAN 10, and PC3 is in V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using a single link and one router interface. Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/0. The single router physical interface F0/0 has two logical subinterfaces defined: <br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 10, IP address 172.17.10.1<br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 30, IP address 172.17.30.1<br><br>This allows the router to route between V LAN 10 and V LAN 30. Switch S1 ports F0/4 and F0/11 are in V LAN 10. Switch S1 port F0/2 is a trunk link to S2 F0/2. The S2 link to PC1 is in V LAN 10.<br><br>Topology Three illustrates what occurs when the trunk link between switch S1 and switch S2 is down. Because there is no redundant connection or path between the devices, all devices connected to switch S2 are unable to reach router R1. As a result, all devices connected to switch S2 cannot route to other V LAN's through router R1.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
