<transcript lastedited="10.07.08 08:10:12">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.5.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 1 Quiz: Networking in the Enterprise<br><br>1.What are two benefits of using VPN? (Choose two.)<br>A.They allow precise configuration of which ports are forwarded to the internal office servers.<br>B.They allow a remote worker to have access to network resources as if they were physically located in the office.<br>C.They provide a faster connection to the office by providing direct access to the internal network.<br>D.They encrypt all communications between the remote worker and internal network resources.<br>E.They block unsolicited traffic that does not have the proper tunneling protocol.<br>F.They reduce malicious attacks by identifying them when they hit the VPN.<br><br>2.When planning to identify traffic flows and network applications that run on an enterprise network, why is it best for a network engineer to sample traffic during times of peak utilization?<br>A.During peak utilization times, most traffic is localized in a single segment and can be more easily analyzed.<br>B.The network engineer does not want to confuse traffic from network backups done at night with normal business traffic.<br>C.The network is busiest and the most critical business applications are in use, providing an accurate sampling of network activities.<br>D.The network is slowest during this time and the sampling will not interfere with the normal business traffic<br><br>3.What are two resources to analyze multiple network segments when identifying network traffic? (Choose two.)<br>A.Network segments may have varying traffic patterns exclusive to that segment.<br>B.Network traffic should always be monitored on a core device because all network traffic needs to pass through it.<br>C.Network traffic that passes between segments may be reduced if a server accessed primarily by on segment is relocated to that segment.<br>D.Network traffic on a single segment is not important because traffic on a local segment does not affect the network traffic as a whole.<br>E.Network traffic on a single segment does not consume much bandwidth within that segment and can be overloaded.<br><br>4.Why do V o IP and video network traffic use UDP instead of TCP?<br>A.Voice and video applications require receipt of all packets regardless of delay.<br>B.The three-way handshake used in UDP speeds up the voice and video streams.<br>C.Voice and video applications cannot tolerate the delay caused by retransmissions.<br>D.UDP allows for segment receipt and acknowledgement, ensuring guaranteed segment delivery.<br><br>5.This question depicts a network topology as explained below:<br>One Router, RTA, is connected to two Switches, SW1 and SW2.<br>RTA connects to SW1 and SW2.  SW1 has Hosts A and B connected to it.  SW2 has Hosts C, D and a server connected to it.<br>Based on this topology, if SW1 stops working, which statement will be true?<br>A.Hosts A and B will not be able to reach each other or hosts C, D, and the server.<br>B.Hosts A and B will be able to reach each other, but not hosts C, D, or the server.<br>C.Hosts A, B, C, and D will be able to reach each other, but not the server.<br>D.All hosts will still be able to reach each other.<br><br>6.Match each Cisco Enterprise Architecture to its corresponding definition (Not all definitions will be uses)<br>Cisco Enterprise Architectures<br>Enterprise Campus<br>Enterprise Edge<br>Service Provider Edge<br>Definitions<br>consists of Internet, VPN, and WAN modules<br>consists of remote users and branch offices<br>consists of the campus infrastructure with server farms<br>provides Internet, WAN, and PSTN services<br><br>7.Which two technologies enhance the ability of remote workers to connect securely to internal company resources?  (Choose two.)<br>A.Telnet<br>B.SSH<br>C.VPN<br>D.FTP<br>E.HTTP<br><br>8.A company has hired a new employee who will be working remotely.  What should the I T administrator do so that the employee can connect to the internal network using the existing VPN infrastructure of the company?<br>A.Configure the WAN router to allow incoming connections.<br>B.Allow tunnelling within the Intrusion Prevention System (I P S).<br>C.Add the credentials of the user to the DMZ.<br>D.Configure the VPN client application on the laptop of the remote employee.<br><br>9.A remote I T engineer needs to simultaneously demonstrate how to operate a software application to multiple people.  Which tool can be used to perform the task?<br>A.FTP<br>B.e-mail<br>C.Telnet<br>D.desktop sharing<br><br>10.Match the network types with their corresponding description.<br>Network Types<br>LAN <br>WAN<br>intranet<br>extranet<br>Internet<br>Descriptions<br>provides Internet-like services for company employees only<br>global public network that operates using a common set of communication protocols<br>private network that allows access by specified external users like contractors and suppliers<br>private network that connects geographically dispensed sites using public or private services<br>private network controlled by a single organization usually limited to a single campus<br><br>11.Which statement is true about the three-layer hierarchical design mode?<br>A.Core and access layer functions can be combined.<br>B.Smaller networks can use the core layer services offered by their ISP.<br>C.The distribution layer consists of high-end routers that interconnect geographically dispensed locations.<br>D.The access layer can be spread across multiple geographical locations.<br><br>12.When designing a network based on the Cisco Enterprise Architecture, which two items would be included in the enterprise edge functional component?  (Choose two.)<br>A.internal web servers <br>B.core layer routers<br>C.VPN servers<br>D.server farm<br>E.intrusion detection system<br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
