<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 18:10:00">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.5.6 Adding Hosts to Local and Remote Networks]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Single Diagram<br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br>The diagram depicts two network topologies: a LAN consisting of a single local network, and a LAN consisting of multiple local networks connected by a central router. The conditions and characteristics for each of these networks are as follows:<br>LAN with all hosts on a single local network<br>In the diagram of a LAN with all hosts on a single local network topology, two switches directly connected to each other. Each switch is connected to five clients. Switch 1 has clients H1 through H5, and Switch 2 has clients H6 through H10.<br>ADVANTAGES<br>Appropriate for simpler networks. <br>Less complexity and lower network cost.<br>Allows devices to be "seen" by other devices.<br>Faster data transfer because of more direct communication.<br>Ease of device access. <br><br>DISADVANTAGES<br>All hosts are in one broadcast domain which causes more traffic on the segment and may slow network performance. <br>LAN with hosts on different networks.<br>In the diagram of a LAN with hosts on different networks, a single router has its two Fast Ethernet ports directly connected to two Layer 2 switches. Switch 1 has three hosts, H4 through H6, and Switch 2 has three hosts, H10 through H12.<br>ADVANTAGES<br>Appropriate for larger, more complex networks.<br>Splits up broadcast domains and decreases traffic.<br>Can improve performance on each segment. <br>Makes the machines invisible to those on other local network segments.<br>Can provide increased security.<br>Can improve network organization. <br><br>DISADVANTAGES<br>Requires the use of routing (Distribution Layer). <br>Router can slow traffic between segments.<br>More complexity and expense (requires router).<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
