<transcript lastedited="01.09.09 11:01:11">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.1.1 - Data Link Layer - Supporting and Connecting to Upper Layer Services]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts the movement of a frame and the protocols of the Data Link Layer as a frame travels over various link types.<br><br>Data Link Layer protocols govern how to format a frame for different media. <br><br>As the animation progresses, a frame travels over the following links:<br>1. From PC to router R1 over a copper wired link.<br>2. From router R1 to satellite Dish1 over a fiber-optic link.<br>3. From satellite Dish1 to a satellite over a wireless link.<br>4. From satellite to satellite Dish2 over a wireless link.<br>5. From satellite Dish2 to wireless router R2 over a fiber-optic link.<br>6. From wireless router R2 to a wireless laptop over a wireless link.<br><br>At each hop along the path, an intermediary device accepts frames from one medium, decapsulates the frame, and then forwards the packets in a new frame. The headers of each frame are formatted for the specific medium that it crosses.<br><br>A More Information popup displays the following text: <br>It is important to understand the meaning of the words medium and media within the context of this chapter. Here, these words refer to material that actually carries the signals representing the transmitted data. Media is the physical copper cable, optical fiber, or atmosphere through which the signals travel. In this chapter, media does not refer to content programming, such as audio, animation, television, and video, as used when referring to digital content and multimedia.<br><br>A physical network has a separate connotation than a logical network. Logical networks are structures defined at the Network Layer by the arrangement of the hierarchical addressing scheme. Physical networks represent the interconnection of devices on a common media. Sometimes, a physical network is also referred to as a network segment.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
