<transcript lastedited="10.08.08 11:10:21">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.6.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 5 Quiz: Routing with a Distance Vector Protocol<br><br>1.How do RIP v1 and RIP v2 differ?<br>A.Only RIP v1 provides authentication in its updates.<br>B.Only RIP v1 uses spilt horizon to prevent routing loops.<br>C.Only RIP v2 uses 16 hops as the metric value for infinite distance.<br>D.Only RIP v2 sends subnet mask information with its routing updates.<br><br>2.RouterA and RouterB are exchanging RIP v2 updates.  RouterB has not received an update from RouterA in the prescribed time.  Assuming default timer settings, how many second will RouterB wait before it marks the routes served by RouterA as invalid?<br>A.90 seconds<br>B.120 seconds<br>C.150 seconds<br>D.180 seconds<br>E.240 seconds<br><br>3.What are three advantages of using EIGRP instead of RIP v1?  (Choose three.)<br>A.EIGRP supports VLSM and CIDR.<br>B.EIGRP requires less memory and CPU time.<br>C.EIGRP supports a higher hop count.<br>D.EIGRP has no hop count limit because it is based on path cost.<br>E.EIGRP is a link-state protocol which has faster convergence than distance-vector protocols.<br>F.EIGRP uses RTP, a protocol independent transport layer to guarantee delivery of routing information.<br><br>4.According to the router output from the show ip route command, which of the following statements are true?  (Choose two.)<br><br>labb#show ip route<br>Codes:<br>C - connected, S - static, I - IGRP, R - RIP, M - Mobile, B - BGP<br>D - EIGRP, EX - EIGRP, external, O - OSPF, IA - OPSF inter area<br>N1 OSPF NSSA external true 1, N2 - OSPF NSSA external type 2<br>E1 - OSPF external type 1, E2 - OSPF external type 2, E - EGP<br>i - I S-I S, L1 - I S-I S level-1, L2 - I S-I S level-2, * - candidate default, <br>U - per-user static route, o - ODR<br><br>Gateway of last resort is not set<br><br>R192.168.8.0/24 [120/2] via 192.168.5.2, 00:00:24, Serial0<br>R192.168.2.0/24 [120/1] via 192.168.3.1, 00:00:03, Serial1<br>C192.168.4.0/24 is directly connected, Ethernet0<br>C192.168.5.0/24 is directly connected, Serial0<br>R192.168.7.0/24 [120/1] via 192.168.5.2, 00:00:24, Serial0<br>R192.168.1.0/24 [120/1] via 192.168.3.1, 00:00:03, Serial1<br>R192.168.6.0/24 [120/1] via 192.168.5.2, 00:00:24, Serial0<br>C192.168.3.0/24 is directly connected, Serial1<br><br>A.The metric to network 192.168.8.0 is 24.<br>B.The hop count to a device on network 192.168.8.0 is 2.<br>C.The total path cost to network 192.168.4.0 is the default value of 16.<br>D.The logical address of the next router for network 192.168.1.0 is 192.168.3.1.<br>E.The devices on network 192.168.5.0 cannot be reached as indicated by the 'C' label.<br><br>5.If EIGRP routing is employed and the successor route to a destination becomes unreachable or unreliable, which of the following would be used as a replacement?<br>A.the route flagged as active in the topology table<br>B.the feasible successor route in the topology table<br>C.the default gateway in the neighbor table<br>D.the primary designated route in the topology table<br>E.the backup designated router in the routing table<br><br>6.If an EIGRP route goes down and a feasible successor is not found in the topology table, how does DUAL flag the route that has failed?<br>A.recomputed<br>B.passive<br>C.active<br>D.down<br>E.unreachable<br>F.successor <br><br>7.Which of the following tables does DUAL use to calculate the lowest cost routes to each destination? <br>A.routing table and topology table<br>B.neighbor table and routing table<br>C.neighbor table and topology table<br>D.neighbor table and adjacency table<br><br>8.What is the advantage of routers forming adjacencies when using EIGRP?  (Choose three.)<br>A.Neighbor routers can quickly take over for a router that is in passive mode.<br>B.New routers and their routes can quickly be discovered by neighbor routers.<br>C.A router can share routing loads with neighbor routers.<br>D.A router can quickly discover when a neighbor router is no longer available.<br>E.Changes in network topology can quickly be shared with neighbor routers.<br>F.Neighbor routers can save overhead by sharing the DUAL database.<br><br>9.You have configured EIGRP route summarization on a serial interface to summarize routes learned from an ethernet interface.  What route will show in the routing table?<br>A.A summary route pointing to a Serial0 interface.<br>B.A summary route pointing to the Loopback0 interface.<br>C.A summary route pointing to an Ethernet interface.<br>D.A summary route pointing to the Null0 interface.<br><br>10.What are two attributes of EIGRP?  (Choose two.)<br>A.It uses link-state advertisements.<br>B.It is a distance-vector routing protocol.<br>C.It supports CIDR.<br>D.It is link-state routing protocol.<br>E.It is a classful routing protocol. <br><br>11.What are two advantaged of static routing over dynamic routing?  (Choose two.)<br>A.The static route configuration is less prone to errors.<br>B.Static routing is more secure because routers do not advertise routes.<br>C.Static routing keeps the network scalable.<br>D.CPU utilization is lower with static routes.<br>E.Administration of the configuration is easier.<br><br>12.Examine the following router configuration:<br><br>interface Serial0/0<br>ip address 10.10.1.2 255.255.255.0<br>interface Serial0/1<br>ip address 10.11.1.2 255.255.255.0<br>router eigrp 75<br>network 10.0.0.0<br>no auto-summary<br><br>Which command set would summarize the 10.10.0.0/16 network when it is sent out interface S0/1?<br>A.router eigrp 75<br>ip summary-address S0/1 10.10.0.0 255.255.0.0<br>B.router eigrp 75<br>ip summary-address 10.10.0.0 255.255.0.0 S0/1<br>C.interface S0/1<br>ip summary-address eigrp 10.10.0.0 255.255.0.0<br>D.interface S0/1<br>ip summary-address eigrp 75 10.10.0.0 255.255.0.0<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
