<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[Availability]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[Scalability]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[Security]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[Manageability]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[<b>Click each host to see the IP configuration and default gateway address.</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[<b>Remote<br>Network</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle"><text><![CDATA[<b>Availability</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody"><text><![CDATA[A network designed for availability is one that delivers consistent, reliable performance, 24 hours a day, 7 days a week. Additionally, the failure of a single link or piece of equipment should not significantly impact network performance.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Scalability</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody2"><text><![CDATA[Scalable network designs are able to grow to include new user groups and remote sites and can support new applications without impacting the level of service delivered to existing users.  ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle3"><text><![CDATA[<b>Security</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody3"><text><![CDATA[Security is a feature that must be designed into the network, not added on after the network is complete. Planning the location of security devices, filters, and firewall features is critical to safeguarding network resources.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle4"><text><![CDATA[<b>Manageability</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody4"><text><![CDATA[No matter how good the initial network design is, the available network staff must be able to manage and support the network. A network that is too complex or difficult to maintain cannot function effectively and efficiently.]]></text></component><component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[Click the terms to view more information about the network requirements.]]></text></component></textcomponents>