<transcript lastedited="12.18.08 08:12:55">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.6.1 Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[10 Questions<br><br>1. A small office uses a wireless ISR to connect to a cable modem for Internet access. The network administrator receives a call that one office computer cannot access external websites. The first trouble shooting step that the network administrator performs is to ping the ISR. Which trouble shooting technique does this represent?<br>Top-down<br>Bottom-up<br>Substitution<br>Divide-and-conquer<br><br>2. Select three items that should be documented after trouble shooting an internal web server crash? (Choose three)<br>When the problem occurred.<br>The dialogue with the user.<br>The configuration of all networking devices on the LAN at the time of the crash.<br>The configuration of all hosts on the LAN at the time of the crash.<br>Steps that were performed to identify the cause of the problem.<br>Steps that were performed that failed to identify the cause of the problem.<br><br>3. A user calls the help desk to report a workstation problem. Which three questions would produce the most helpful information for troubleshooting? (Choose three)<br>If you received an error message, what was it?<br>Have there been any changes to your workstation recently?<br>Do you have the warranty for you workstation?<br>What version of operating system is running on your workstation?<br>Have you used a network-monitoring tool on your workstation?<br>When did you last perform a backup?<br><br>4. A user wants to test connectivity between host three and host eight on a network. Which command can be used to verify a connection?<br>i p config<br>ping<br>netstat<br>n s lookup<br><br>5. Match the utility to the purpose.<br><br>Utility:<br>ping<br>netstat<br>trace rt<br>i p config<br>n s lookup<br><br>Purpose:<br>Displays IP settings on host.<br>Displays network connections.<br>Tests connections to other IP hosts.<br>Displays route taken to destination.<br>Asks name server for info on destination domain.<br><br>6. Which three pieces of information are revealed by the i p config command? (Choose three)<br>Physical address<br>IP address<br>DHCP server<br>DNS Server<br>Subnet mask<br>Default gateway<br><br>7. How does an activity L E D indicate that traffic is moving through a port?<br>By flashing.<br>By staying turned off.<br>By staying a solid green color.<br>By staying a solid amber color.<br><br>8. What is one of the most common reasons why hosts could not be unable to connect?<br>Operator error<br>Cabling problems<br>Equipment failure<br>Addressing problems<br><br>9. Which three factors can affect the ability of hosts to connect to an AP using radio frequency signals? (Choose three)<br>The RF signal strength increases with distance.<br>The 8 0 2 dot 11a is not compatible with the 8 0 2 dot 11b/g standards.<br>The available bandwidth between devices is shared with AP's.<br>A wireless conversation must occur on multiple, overlapping channels.<br>Multiple devices running on the same frequency causes interference.<br>Equipment that conforms to one standard will work with all other standards.<br><br>10. What step should be taken once a problem is resolved?<br>Consult an FAQ.<br>Escalate the problem.<br>Update the documentation.<br>Run remote access software.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
