<textcomponents><component id="ID_title"><text><![CDATA[<b>The Internet and Standards</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[<b>Employees</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Business</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[<b>Home Office</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Internet</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[<b>E-Commerce</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[<b>Collaboration and Training</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[<b>Communications</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[<b>Customers</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each business use for more information. </b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt09"><text><![CDATA[<b>Intranet</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle"><text><![CDATA[E-Commerce]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody"><text><![CDATA[Refers to any business that can be conducted over the web. This includes the use of webspace for advertisements, brochures, catalogs, as well as ordering and distribution services. Companies can sell products and services over the Internet from their own websites, through auction sites, or through affiliated websites. ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle2"><text><![CDATA[Communication]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody2"><text><![CDATA[Refers to any electronic method of communication, such as the use of email, instant messaging, and online chat. In addition, many businesses use  internal phone systems that operate over the Internet using IP phones and Voice over IP (VoIP) technology to reduce phone costs.  ]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle3"><text><![CDATA[Collaboration and Training]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody3"><text><![CDATA[Refers to creating environments that allow for sharing of documents, presentations and spreadsheets.  Allows for virtual teams of people to work together from remote locations for business and training purposes.   Examples include: video conferencing, virtual meeting places, virtual classrooms, online learning, online bulletin boards, FTP sites and password protected databases and applications.]]></text></component></textcomponents>