<transcript lastedited="01.07.09 08:01:58">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.6.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Match the properties associated with interfaces to the appropriate interface type.<br>Properties:<br>A. One physical interface for many V LAN's.<br>B. Bandwidth contention.<br>C. Access mode switch port connection.<br>D. Complex cable configuration.<br>E. Trunk mode switch port connection.<br>F. One physical interface per V LAN.<br><br>Interface Types:<br>One. Physical.<br>Two. Subinterface.<br><br>2.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 interface FA0/0 as an 8 0 2 dot 1 Q trunk. PC1 is connected to switch S1 port FA0/1 and is in V LAN 10. PC2 is connected to switch S1 port FA0/2 and is in V LAN 20.<br><br>The logical subinterfaces defined on R1 interface FA0/0 are: <br>FA0/0 dot 10 - V LAN 10<br>FA0/0 dot 20 - V LAN 20<br><br>PC1 wants to send data to PC2, but does not know the MAC address of PC2. When PC1 sends an ARP request, which interface returns a MAC address?<br>A.Because PC1 and PC2 are connected to the same switch, PC2 supplies its MAC address.<br>B.The switch provides the MAC address of the FA0/1 interface.<br>C.Because the subinterfaces on the router have unique MAC addresses, subinterface FA0/0.10 supplies its MAC address.<br>D.The router supplies the MAC address of physical interface FA0/0.<br><br>3.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using three interfaces: FA0/0 (V LAN 2), FA0/1 (V LAN 3), and FA0/2 (V LAN 4). Host A in V LAN 2 is connected to the switch. Host B in V LAN 3 is connected to the switch, and Host C in V LAN 4 is connected to the switch.<br><br>What are three advantages of replacing the individual V LAN links between the switches and the router with a trunk line and subinterfaces? (Choose three.)<br>A.It would free up two switch and router ports.<br>B.It would reduce the complexity of the cabling runs.<br>C.It would increase the amount of bandwidth available for inter-V LAN routing.<br>D.It would allow for less complex troubleshooting of inter-V LAN routing issues.<br>E.It would allow adding more V LAN's without requiring more cabling or switch ports.<br>F.It would allow for a less complex configuration of inter-V LAN routing.<br><br>4.What condition is required to enable Layer 3 switching?<br>A.The Layer 3 switch must have IP routing enabled.<br>B.All participating switches must have unique V LAN numbers.<br>C.All routed subnets must be on the same V LAN.<br>D.Inter-V LAN portions of Layer 3 switching must use router-on-a-stick.<br><br>5.When implementing router-on-a-stick, what is necessary for establishing communication between V LAN's?<br>A.Multiple switch port to connect to a single router interface.<br>B.Native V LAN IP address that is configured on the router physical interface.<br>C.All trunk ports configured in access mode.<br>D.Router subinterfaces.<br><br>6.Which two methodologies could be employed to reduce the risk of a failed inter-switch link disrupting inter-V LAN routing? (Choose two.)<br>A.Configure and enable EtherChannel.<br>B.Disable trunking on all switch ports.<br>C.Configure and enable alternate paths between switches.<br>D.Assign all switch ports to separate V LAN's.<br>E.Configure and enable Dynamic Tree Protocol.<br><br>7.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using three interfaces: FA0/0 (V LAN 2), FA0/1 (V LAN 3), and FA0/2 (V LAN 4). Host A in V LAN 2 is connected to the switch. Host B in V LAN 3 is connected to the switch, and Host C in V LAN 4 is connected to the switch.<br><br>Which three statements are true regarding this configuration? (Choose three.)<br>A.This configuration will not scale easily.<br>B.This configuration limits the number of V LAN's because the router can support only a fixed number of physical interfaces.<br>C.The connections between the switch and router are trunk links.<br>D.All traffic between the router and the switch must be tagged with its V LAN ID.<br>E.This configuration is not the most cost-effective.<br>F.The switch serves as the gateway for the hosts. <br><br>8.How does the router-on-a-stick model for inter-V LAN routing differ from traditional routing?<br>A.It uses multiple physical interfaces on the router, each configured with a different Layer 3 address.<br>B.It uses a single physical interface on the switch with only the no shutdown command issued.<br>C.It uses the subinterfaces on the router with only the no shutdown command issued on the physical interface.<br>D.It uses the subinterfaces on the switch with only the no shutdown command issued on the physical interface.<br><br>9.Which command does the network administrator use to determine whether inter-V LAN communication is functioning?<br>A.show v lan.<br>B.ping.<br>C.i p config.<br>D.show interface.<br><br>10.Refer to the following command output to answer the question.<br><br>R1#show interfaces fastEthernet 0/0.1<br>FastEthernet 0 /0.1 is up, line protocol is up<br>Hardware is AmdFE, address is 0003.e36f.41e0 (bia 0003.e36f.41e0).<br>Internet address is 10.10.10.1 /24<br>MTU 1500 bytes, BW 100000 Kbit, DLY 100 usec, reliability 255/255, txload 1/255, rxload 1/255<br><br>R1#show interfaces fastEthernet 0/0.2<br>FastEthernet 0 /0.2 is up, line protocol is up<br>Hardware is AmdFE, address is 0003.e36f.41e0 (bia 0003.e36f.41e0).<br>Internet address is 10.10.11.1 /24<br>MTU 1500 bytes, BW 100000 Kbit, DLY 100 usec, reliability 255/255, txload 1/255, rxload 1/255<br><br>What statement is true regarding the output?<br>A.Each subinterface returns a unique address in response to ARP requests.<br>B.This inter-V LAN routing configuration is not the most cost-effective or scalable.<br>C.The router is properly configured for router-on-a-stick inter-V LAN routing between the 10.10.10.0.24 and 10.10.11.0/24 subnetworks.<br>D.The trunk link was dynamically negotiated.<br>E.Layer 3 addressing is not properly configured.<br><br>11.In a router-on-a-stick configuration, which two items are required to support connectivity between the router and the switch? (Choose two.)<br>A.All ports on the switch must be configured as access ports.<br>B.The router-to-switch physical interface must be configured with an IP address.<br>C.Router subinterfaces must be configured with unique addresses in different subnets.<br>D.The switch port that connects to the router must be configured as a trunk.<br>E.Each subinterface must be configured with the no shutdown command.<br><br>12.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using three interfaces: FA0/0 (V LAN 2), FA0/1 (V LAN 3), and FA0/2 (V LAN 4). Host A in V LAN 2 is connected to the switch. Host B in V LAN 3 is connected to the switch, and Host C in V LAN 4 is connected to the switch.<br><br>Which three statements are true regarding this configuration? (Choose three.)<br>A.The links between the router and switch are access mode links.<br>B.Each router interface requires a unique IP address on separate subnets for each V LAN.<br>C.Each switch interface requires a unique IP address on separate subnets for each V LAN.<br>D.Each router interface requires the no shutdown command.<br>E.A routing protocol must be configured on the router.<br>F.The router is configured with the interface fast ethernet 0 /0.2 command.<br><br>13.Which of the following are valid inter-V LAN routing types?<br><br>A. Traditional routing.<br>B. Spanning-tree routing.<br>C. Router-on-a-stick.<br>D. 8 0 2 dot 1 Q routing.<br>E. Switch-based routing.<br><br>14.A network technician is configuring a router to support inter-V LAN routing. After entering C L I global configuration mode on R1 and selecting Fast Ethernet interface F0 /0/1, the network administrator attempts to enter the command encapsulation dot 1q 10. The router refuses to accept this command. What could account for this failure?<br>A.Router port F0/0/1 is not physically connected to the switch.<br>B.V LAN 0001 has been renamed.<br>C.The R1 interface F0/0/1 was configured for subinterface operation.<br>D.This command can only be configured on router subinterfaces.<br>E.Interface F0/0/1 on the switch is shutdown.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
