<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[This CCNA Discovery course is the fourth and last course in the Cisco Networking Academy Discovery curriculum. This series of courses has provided you with an opportunity to gain the knowledge, skills, and abilities that you will need to take the Cisco Certified Network Associate certification exam.
To successfully pass the certification exam, you need to review the material presented in all four Discovery courses. The Cisco certification exams include a hands-on component that is presented throughout the exam as simulations. These simulations are similar to the remote labs that may have been used in your class. Practicing all of the Hands-on labs and Packet Tracer activities will help you prepare for this part of the exam. To help ensure your success, Cisco provides an on-line certification preparation center. There are several vendors who sell practice test exams to help prepare to take the certification exam.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[As you have seen, a career in IT involves an ongoing commitment to developing your skills and knowledge. To further your networking education, several advanced Cisco Networking Academy curricula are available, including:<br/><br/><li><b>CCNP</b> -The Cisco Certified Network Professional (CCNP) curriculum builds on the CCNA curricula with more complex network configurations, diagnosis, and troubleshooting. The courses map to the four CCNP exams: Building Scalable Internetworks, Implementing Secure Converged Wide-Area Networks, Building Multilayer Switched Networks, and Optimizing Converged Networks.</li><br/><li><b>Fundamentals of Network Security</b>- The security course teaches students to design and implement security solutions that will reduce the risk of revenue loss and vulnerability.</li><br/><li><b>Fundamentals of Wireless LANs</b> -The wireless course focuses on the design, planning, implementation, operation, and troubleshooting of wireless networks.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Visit the Academy Connection website for more information:]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>The Cisco CCNA Prep center can be found at:</b>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>



