<transcript lastedited="03.27.09 10:03:34">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.6.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Which three layers of the O S I model make up the Application Layer of the TCP/IP model? (Choose three.)<br>A.data link<br>B.network<br>C.transport<br>D.session<br>E.presentation<br>F.application<br><br>2.What protocol is used to transfer web pages from server to client?<br>A.HTML<br>B.SMTP<br>C.HTTP<br>D.SSH<br>E.Telnet<br>F.POP<br><br>3.The diagram depicts a client and server with an arrow pointing from the client to the server representing data transfer. Based on the diagram description, which term applies to a data transfer in the direction indicated by the arrow?<br>A.download<br>B.data read<br>C.data write<br>D.upload<br><br>4.Which protocols use authentication and encryption to secure data traveling between the client and server? (Choose two.)<br>A.HTTP<br>B.DNS<br>C.HTTPS<br>D.SMTP<br>E.SSH<br><br>5.The diagram depicts an Internet Explorer browser window with the following URL entered: http://www.cisco.com/web/learning/netacad/index.html. What is the top-level domain of the this URL?<br>A.cisco dot com<br>B.dot com<br>C.www dot cisco dot com<br>D.www<br>E.netacad<br>F.http://<br><br>6.Match each DNS resource record type to the resource it identifies.<br>Resource Record Types:<br>A: NS<br>B: CNAME<br>C: MX<br>D: A<br>Resource It Identifies:<br>One.End device address.<br>Two.Authoritative name server.<br>Three.Canonical or fully qualified domain name for an alias.<br>Four.Domain name mapped to a list of mail exchange servers for that domain.<br><br>7.Match the functions to the appropriate e-mail component.<br>Functions:<br>A: Resolves final delivery issues.<br>B: Forwards mail between servers using SMTP.<br>C: Retrieves mail using POP.<br>D: Delivers mail to the user's mailbox.<br>E: Receives mail from client.<br>F: Accesses and reads mail.<br><br>E-mail Component:<br>One.MTA<br>Two.MDA<br>Three.M UA<br><br>8.A network administrator is troubleshooting failed access to www.cisco.com. Typing the IP address of the web server into the browser successfully brings up the web page. What Application Layer protocol is responsible for the failure?<br>A.DHCP<br>B.DNS<br>C.CDP<br>D.HTTP<br>E.HTTPS<br>F.SSL]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
