<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[1]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[2]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[3]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[4]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[5]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[6]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt12"><text><![CDATA[Selecting the Correct Cisco IOS Software Using the CCO Feature Navigator.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt13"><text><![CDATA[1. From the Cisco.com Homepage select Tools & Resources.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt14"><text><![CDATA[2. Select Tool by Category.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt15"><text><![CDATA[3. NOTE: Software downloads are available only to registered Cisco.com users with a Cisco service contract.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt16"><text><![CDATA[Click the buttons to view the steps to access Feature Navigator on Cisco.com.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt17"><text><![CDATA[NOTE: This page changes frequently. If you cannot find Feature Navigator using these directions, please use the Search Function to find the Feature Navigator. ]]></text></component><component id="tipTitle"><text><![CDATA[<b>More Information</b>]]></text></component><component id="tipBody"><text><![CDATA[Cisco IOS Release Codes:<BR><BR><b>Early Deployment (ED)</b><br>Early Deployment (ED) relates to software releases that provide new features and new platform support. The releases also provide bug fixes.<br><br><b>Limited Deployment (LD)</b><br>A Major Release of Cisco IOS or a Release Train of Catalyst OS (CatOS) software is said to be in the "Limited Deployment" phase of its life cycle during the period between Early Deployment (ED) and the General Deployment (GD) milestone. No new features or new platform support is added in this phase, only bug fixes.<br><br><b>General Deployment (GD)</b><br>Date at which this software release reached the "General Deployment" milestone in its life cycle. A Major Release of Cisco IOS or a Release Train of CatOS software reaches the "General Deployment" milestone when Cisco feels it is suitable for deployment anywhere in customer networks where the features and functionality of the release are required. An example of a Cisco IOS Major Release that has reached GD is 12.2. An example of a CatOS Release Train that has reached GD is 7.x. Criteria for reaching the "General Deployment" milestone are based on, but not limited to, customer feedback surveys from production and test networks using the releases, CE bug reports, and reported field experience.]]></text></component><component id="TipText"><text><![CDATA[More Information]]></text></component></textcomponents>