<transcript lastedited="12.17.08 12:12:48">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.8.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.	Which form of communication is a real-time, text-based communication type used between two or more people who use mostly text to communicate with each other?<br>A.	Weblogs<br>B.	Wikis<br>C.	Instant messaging<br>D.	Podcasting<br>E.	Collaboration tools<br><br>2.	Which type of network provides customers limited access to corporate data such as inventory, parts lists and orders?<br>A.	intranet<br>B.	extranet<br>C.	internetwork<br>D.	Internet<br><br>3.	What balances the importance of traffic and its characteristics in order to manage data?<br>A.	network administration<br>B.	network traffic<br>C.	Q o S strategy<br>D.	network evaluation<br><br>4.	Which processes occur to network traffic so that quality of service strategies work correctly? (Choose two.)<br>A.	Traffic is classified based on quality of service requirements.<br>B.	Priorities are assigned to each classification of application data.<br>C.	Web traffic is always assigned to a high priority queue for processing.<br>D.	Digital movies are always assigned to the high-priority queue for processing.<br>E.	E-mail traffic is always assigned to the low priority queue.<br><br>5.	What are two components of network architecture? (Choose two.)<br>A.	people that comprise the human network.<br>B.	programmed services and protocols that move the messages across the network.<br>C.	data transferred across the network.<br>D.	technologies that support network communications.<br>E.	corporations that operate and maintain the data network.<br><br>6.	For which three reasons were circuit-switched, connection-oriented technologies rejected when the Internet was being developed? (Choose three.)<br>A.	Circuit-switched technologies required that a single message be broken up into multiple message blocks that contain addressing information.<br>B.	Early circuit-switched networks did not automatically establish alternative circuits in the event of circuit failure.<br>C.	Circuit-switched technologies required that an open circuit between network endpoints be established, even if data was not actively being transferred between locations.<br>D.	The quality and consistency of messages transmitted across a connection-oriented, circuit-switched network could not be guaranteed.<br>E.	The establishment of multiple, simultaneous open circuits for fault tolerance was costly.<br><br>7.	For which three reasons was a packet-switched, connectionless data communications technology used when developing the Internet? (Choose three.)<br>A.	It can rapidly adapt to the loss of data transmission facilities.<br>B.	It efficiently utilizes the network infrastructure to transfer data.<br>C.	Data packets can travel multiple paths through the network simultaneously.<br>D.	It allows for billing of network use by the amount of time a connection is established.<br>E.	It requires that a data circuit between the source and destination be established before the data can be transferred.<br><br>8.	What is the role of Q o S in a converged network?<br>A.	Ensures that all traffic above available bandwidth levels is dropped.<br>B.	Establishes delivery priorities for different communication types in a network.<br>C.	Determines precise priorities for all network communication.<br>D.	Allows unused bandwidth to be shared by other organizations within the network.<br><br>9.	Match the characteristics of a network architecture with their definitions (Not all options are used.)<br>Characteristics: <br>Convergence<br>Scalability<br>Security<br>Fault tolerance<br>Quality of service<br>Definitions:<br>Limits the impact of hardware or software failures and provides failure recovery mechanisms.<br>Supports expansion of the network infrastructure to support new users and applications.<br>Provides a level of consistent and uninterrupted data delivery to support expectations of users.<br>Protects confidential and business critical information from theft or alteration.<br><br>10.	Network security threats can be classified as relating to either network infrastructure security or content security. Classify the security threats according to the appropriate category. <br>Security threats:<br>A custodian unplugs an essential network device.<br>A disgruntled employee alters information in a customer database.<br>Builders accidentally cut a network cable while digging.<br>A competitor accesses sensitive information through an unsecured wireless network.<br>A secretary sends confidential information in reply to an e-mail that falsely appears to come from her boss.<br>A hacker connects to a network device and changes settings in its management software.<br>Categories:<br>Network infrastructure security<br>Content security]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
