<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_title">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Message to Students</b>]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_page1">
         <text><![CDATA[page 1 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page2">
         <text><![CDATA[page 2 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page3">
         <text><![CDATA[page 3 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page4">
         <text><![CDATA[page 4 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page5">
         <text><![CDATA[page 5 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page6">
         <text><![CDATA[page 6 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page7">
         <text><![CDATA[page 7 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page8">
         <text><![CDATA[page 8 of 9]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page9">
         <text><![CDATA[page 9 of 9]]></text>
</component>
   

<component id="ID_txt01">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Welcome</b><br/>Welcome to the CCNA Exploration Accessing the WAN course. The goal of this course is to introduce you to fundamental networking concepts and technologies. These online course materials will assist you in developing the skills necessary to plan and implement small networks across a range of applications. The specific skills covered in each chapter are described at the start of each chapter. ]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_txt02">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>More than just information</b><br/>This computer-based learning environment is an important part of the overall course experience for students and instructors in the Networking Academy. These online course materials are designed to be used along with several other instructional tools and activities. These include:<br/><br/><ul><li>Class presentation, discussion, and practice with your instructor </li><li>Hands-on labs that use networking equipment within the Networking Academy classroom</li><li>Online scored assessments and a matching grade book</li><li>Packet Tracer 4.1 simulation tool</li><li>Additional software for classroom activities</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>A global community</b><br/>When you participate in the Networking Academy, you are joining a global community linked by common goals and technologies. Schools, colleges, universities and other entities in over 160 countries participate in the program. A visualization of the global Networking Academy community at <a href="javascript:openExternal('http://www.academynetspace.com');"><font color="#0000FF">http://www.academynetspace.com</font></a>. <br/><br/>The material in this course encompasses a broad range of technologies that facilitate how people work, live, play, and learn by communicating with voice, video, and other data. Networking and the Internet affect people differently in different parts of the world. Although we have worked with instructors from around the world to create these materials, it is important that you work with your instructor and fellow students to make the material in this course applicable to your local situation.<br/><br/><b>Keep in Touch</b><br/>These online instructional materials, as well as the rest of the course tools, are part of the larger Networking Academy. The student, instructor, and administrator portal for the program is located at <a href="javascript:openExternal('http://www.cisco.com/web/learning/netacad/index.html');"><font color="#0000FF">http://www.cisco.com/web/learning/netacad/index.html</font></a>. There you will obtain access to the other tools in the program such as the assessment server and student grade book), as well as informational updates and other relevant links.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Mind Wide Open™</b><br/>An important goal in education is to enrich you, the student, by expanding what you know and can do. It is important to realize, however, that the instructional materials and the instructor can only <i>facilitate</i> the process. <i>You</i> must make the commitment yourself to learn new skills. Below are a few suggestions to help you learn and grow.<br/><br/>1.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Take notes.</b> Professionals in the networking field often keep Engineering Journals in which they write down the things they observe and learn. Taking notes is an important way to help your understanding grow over time.</textformat><br/><br/>2.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Think about it.</b> The course provides information both to change what you know and what you can do. As you go through the course, ask yourself what makes sense and what doesn’t. Stop and ask questions when you are confused. Try to find out more about topics that interest you. If you are not sure why something is being taught, consider asking your instructor or a friend. Think about how the different parts of the course fit together.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
         <text><![CDATA[3.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Practice.</b> Learning new skills requires practice. We believe this is so important to e-learning that we have a special name for it. We call it e-Doing. It is very important that you complete the activities in the online instructional materials and that you also complete the hands-on labs and Packet Tracer activities. </textformat><br/><br/>4.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Practice again.</b> Have you ever thought that you knew how to do something and then, when it was time to show it on a test or at work, you discovered that you really hadn’t mastered it? Just like learning any new skill like a sport, game, or language, learning a professional skill requires patience and repeated practice before you can say you have truly learned it. The online instructional materials in this course provide opportunities for repeated practice for many skills. Take full advantage of them. You can also work with your instructor to extend Packet Tracer, and other tools, for additional practice as needed.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
         <text><![CDATA[5.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Teach it.</b> Teaching a friend or colleague is often a good way to reinforce your own learning. To teach well, you will have to work through details that you may have overlooked on your first reading. Conversations about the course material with fellow students, colleagues, and the instructor can help solidify your understanding of networking concepts.</textformat><br/><br/>6.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Make changes as you go.</b> The course is designed to provide feedback through interactive activities and quizzes, the online assessment system, and through structured interactions with your instructor. You can use this feedback to better understand where your strengths and weaknesses are. If there is an area that you are having trouble with, focus on studying or practicing more in that area. Seek additional feedback from your instructor and other students.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt07">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Explore the world of networking</b><br/>This version of the course includes a special tool called Packet Tracer 4.1. Packet Tracer is a networking learning tool that supports a wide range of physical and logical simulations. It also provides visualization tools to help you to understand the internal workings of a network.<br/><br/>The pre-made Packet Tracer activities consist of network simulations, games, activities, and challenges that provide a broad range of learning experiences. <br/><br/><b>Create your own worlds</b><br/>You can also use Packet Tracer to create your own experiments and networking scenarios. We hope that, over time, you consider using Packet Tracer – not only for experiencing the pre-built activities, but also to become an author, explorer, and experimenter.<br/><br/>The online course materials have embedded Packet Tracer activities that will launch on computers running Windows® operating systems, if Packet Tracer is installed. This integration may also work on other operating systems using Windows emulation.]]></text>
</component>
 
<component id="ID_txt08">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Course Overview</b><br/><br/>The primary focus of this course is on accessing wide area networks (WAN). The goal is to develop an understanding of various WAN technologies to connect small- to medium-sized business networks.<br/><br/>The course introduces WAN converged applications and quality of service (QoS). It focuses on WAN technologies including PPP, Frame Relay, and broadband links. WAN security concepts are discussed in detail, including types of threats, how to analyze network vulnerabilities, general methods for mitigating common security threats and types of security appliances and applications.  The course then explains the principles of traffic control and access control lists (ACLs) and describes how to implement IP addressing services for an Enterprise network, including how to configure NAT and DHCP. IPv6 addressing concepts are also discussed. During the course, you will learn how to use Cisco Router and Security Device Manager (SDM) to secure a router and implement IP addressing services. Finally, students learn how to detect, troubleshoot and correct common Enterprise network implementation issues.<br/><br/>The labs and Packet Tracer activities used in this course are designed to help you develop an understanding of how to configure routing operations while reinforcing the concepts learned in each chapter.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 1 Introduction to WANs</b> - In Chapter 1, you will learn the fundamentals enterprise WANs, the technologies available to implement them, and the terminology used to discuss them. You will learn how the Cisco enterprise architecture provides integrated services over an enterprise network and how to select the appropriate WAN technology to meet different enterprise business requirements.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 2 PPP</b> - Chapter 2 focuses on serial point-to-point communications and the Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP). Understanding how point-to-point communication links function to provide access to a WAN is important to an overall understanding of how WANs function. Various aspects of PPP are discussed including securing PPP using either Password Authentication Protocol (PAP) or the more effective Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol (CHAP).<br/><br/><b>Chapter 3 Frame Relay</b> - Chapter 3 focuses on the high-performance Frame Relay WAN protocol. You will learn how to implement Frame Relay for use between LANs over a WAN.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 4 Network Security</b> - Chapter 4 introduces network security which has moved to the forefront of network management and implementation. The overall security challenge is to find a balance between two important requirements: the need to open networks to support evolving business opportunities, and the need to protect private, personal, and strategic business information. You will learn to identify security threats to enterprise networks and mitigation techniques. You will also learn how to configure basic router security, disable unused resources and interfaces. Finally you will learn to manage configurations and IOS files.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 5 ACLs</b> - Chapter 5 builds on the concepts introduced in Chapter 4 and focuses on the application of ACLs. One of the most important skills a network administrator needs is mastery of access control lists (ACLs). You will learn how to create firewalls using standard and extended ACLs. Finally, you learn about advanced ACL features including dynamic, reflexive and timed ACLs.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt09">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Course Overview Continued</b><br/><br/><b>Chapter 6 Teleworker Services</b> - Chapter 6 discusses broadband technologies from a telecommuter’s perspective. Specifically, you will learn about cable, DSL, and wireless broadband options. You will also explore how VPNs are utilized to secure broadband connections.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 7 IP Addressing Services</b> - Chapter 7 discusses how a branch site can provide IP addressing services to users. You will identify teleworker requirements and recommend architectures for providing teleworking services. Specifically, you will learn how to configure a router to be a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) server and how to integrate private addresses and Network Address Translation (NAT).  You will finish with an overview of IPv6 and how to configure routers to exchange IPv6 routes using RIPng.<br/><br/><b>Chapter 8 Network Troubleshooting</b> - Chapter 8 is the capstone chapter for this course. You will learn how to establish a network baseline and develop network documentation to help in network troubleshooting. You will also develop your network troubleshooting skills by reviewing troubleshooting methodology. You will learn to identify and troubleshoot common enterprise network implementation issues using a layered model approach.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_page1_text">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Welcome to CCNA Exploration Accessing the WAN</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_page2_text">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Mind Wide Open™<br/><br/>Use the course material and then use it again. Talk about the concepts to deepen your understanding.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_page3_text">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Mind Wide Open®</b><br/><br/>Welcome to CCNA Exploration Routing Protocols and Concepts</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_page4_text">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Welcome to CCNA Exploration Network Fundamentals</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_page5_text">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Welcome to CCNA Exploration Network Fundamentals</b>]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>


