<transcript lastedited="09.26.08 09:09:03">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.4.4 - Analyzing Network ACL's and Placement]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the placement and use of ACL's to filter traffic to and from specific parts of a network.<br> <br>Network Topology<br>There are four routers, Main, Sales, HQ, and R1. <br>HQ is attached to Main and Sales via Serial link. Main is attached to Sales via Serial link.<br>HQ is attached to R1 via Serial link, HQ: S0/0/0.<br>HQ has Network 192.168.1.0 /24 connected to interface FA0/0.<br>Network 192.168.1.0 /24 has a Server Farm with three servers, IP: 192.168.1.3 - .15, as well as two hosts, Net Admin, 192.168.1.2, and H1, 192.168.1.30.<br><br><br><br>Main has Network 192.168.5.0 /24 connected to interface FA0/0, attached to the Payroll Server, server IP: 192.168.5.57.<br>Sales has Network 192.168.3.0 /24 attached on Interface FA0/0, attached to the File Server, server IP: 192.168.3.39.<br><br>There are ACL's on the FA0/0 interface of the HQ, Main, and Sales Routers. There is an ACL on the S0/0/0 interface of HQ.<br><br>The ACL's and the functions of each are as follows:<br><br>HQ S0/0/0 ACL<br>HQ - Extended ACL 105 - Interface S0/0/0 IN<br>Access-list 105 permit icmp any any echo-reply - allow pings from inside to return from Internet<br>Access-list 105 permit icmp any any unreachable - Allow error messages to return from Internet<br>Access-list 105 permit tcp any any established - Allow established TCP sessions from Internet<br><br>HQ F A 0 /0 ACL<br>HQ - Extended ACL 100 - Interface FA0/0 IN<br>Access-list 100 permit IP 192.168.1.0 0.0.0.15 any - Allow Net Admin and Server Farm full access<br>Access-list 100 deny tcp 192.168.1.0 0.0.0.255 eq 23 - Deny user PC's Telnet access<br>Access-list 100 permit IP any any - Allow all other traffic<br><br>Sales F A 0 /0 ACL<br>Sales - Extended ACL 122 - Interface FA0/0 IN<br>Access-list 122 deny IP 192.168.3.0 0.0.0.255 host 192.168.5.57 - Deny access from this net to Payroll Server<br>Access-list 122 permit udp 192.168.3.0 0.0.0.255 any range 20 21 - Allow all users on this net access to FTP Data and FTP session control<br>Access-list 122 permit udp 192.168.3.0 0.0.0.255 any eq 53 - Allow all users on this net access to remote DNS<br>Access-list 122 permit tcp 192.168.3.0 0.0.0.255 any eq 80 - Allow all users on this net access to Web services<br><br>Main F A 0 /0 ACL<br>Main - Extended ACL 111 - Interface FA0/0 IN<br>Access-list 111 permit IP host 192.168.5.57 any - Allow Payroll server access to anywhere<br>Access-list 111 permit udp 192.168.5.0 0.0.0.255 any eq 53 - Allow all users on this net access to remote DNS<br>Access-list 111 permit tcp 192.168.5.0 0.0.0.255 any eq 80 - Allow all users on this net access to Web services<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
