<textcomponents><component id="ID_but01"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Client</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_but02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Distributed Server</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_but03"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Server Farm</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_but04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Enterprise Edge</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-client</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_body01"><text><![CDATA[<b>Typical client-client applications include the following:</b><br>IP telephony - Two peers establish communication with the help of a telephone manager workstation; however, the conversation occurs directly between the two peers when the connection is established.<br><br>File sharing - Some operating systems (or even applications) require direct access to data on other workstations.<br><br>Videoconference systems - This application is similar to IP telephony. However, the network requirements for this type of application are usually higher, particularly bandwidth consumption and QoS requirements.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-distributed server</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_body02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Typical client-distributed server applications include the following:</b><br>Servers and users are located in the same virtual LAN (VLAN). Department administrators manage and control the servers. The majority of department traffic occurs in the same segment, but some traffic passes to different segments.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[<b>Management services</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Vendor Services</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[<b>Team Support</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[<b>Stadium</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Server Farm</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_body03"><text><![CDATA[<b>Typical client-server farm applications include the following:</b><br>Organizational mail servers (such as Lotus Notes and Microsoft Exchange)<br><br>Common file servers (such as Novell, Microsoft, and Sun)<br><br>Common database servers for organizational applications (such as Sybase, Oracle, and IBM)]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[<b>Application Server</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt09"><text><![CDATA[<b>Active Directory Server</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt10"><text><![CDATA[<b>DHCP/DNS Server</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt11"><text><![CDATA[<b>Stadium</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt12"><text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Enterprise Edge</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_body04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Typical client-enterprise edge applications include the following:</b><br>Applications installed on the Enterprise Edge can be crucial to organizational process flow; therefore, any outages can increase costs. Typical Enterprise Edge applications are based on web technologies. Some examples of these application types are external mail servers and public web servers. Organizations that support e-commerce applications also place their e-commerce servers into the Enterprise Edge. Client traffic to the Internet goes out the Enterprise Edge with less bandwidth than traffic to local servers.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt13"><text><![CDATA[<b>Team Support</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[<b>Click the buttons to view the different types of application communication.</b>]]>/text></component></textcomponents>