<transcript lastedited="10.14.08 14:10:33">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.1.5 ISP Levels of Service]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Three Diagrams<br><br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br><br>The diagram identifies the following services that may be offered by an ISP.<br><br>Content Filtering<br>ISP's can provide software that prevents specific material from being downloaded based on user specifications. This software is often used to block objectionable and/or offensive websites.<br><br>Video on Demand<br>Real-time downloading of movies allows users to watch movies over the Internet. This is known as streaming video.<br><br>Connection Speed<br>Download speeds can vary from 56kbps for dialup, to 1.5Mbps or higher for technologies such as DSL and cable modem. A high-speed connection is recommended for individuals who download a lot of large programs, perform gaming, or run their own servers.<br><br>Email Accounts<br>ISP's generally provide multiple user emails on one account. These email addresses can be distributed among individuals, or used to separate business mail from personal mail. Webmail allows users to access their mail from any computer connected to the Internet using any Web browser. No special/dedicated email client is required.<br><br>Personal Home Pages<br>Personal web page space is frequently provided with service. Usually both the size of the web space and the traffic generated are limited. Design and maintenance of the website is maintained by the individual author.<br><br>Web Hosting Services<br>Organizations that do not have web servers can use the ISP's servers for their website. This often comes with design and maintenance services. Web hosting services are usually purchased based on the size of the website and anticipated monthly volume.<br><br>File Storage<br>Organizations can use the ISP's online storage and file management systems to provide 24/7 access to important files. File storage can range from a few megabytes to terabytes of online storage. Online file storage is usually password protected.<br><br>IP Telephone<br>ISP's may provide IP telephone service that allow users to make and receive voice calls over the Internet. When using the Internet, regular long distance tolls do not normally apply.<br><br>Virus Scanning<br>ISP's often include virus scanning and anti-spam services as part of their connection package. Most ISP's scan for malicious code, both on the files that have been uploaded from the end user, and those arriving for delivery to the end user.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
