<textcomponents>
<component id="connectionSpeedTitle">
	<text>Connection Speed</text>
</component>
<component id="connectionSpeedBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>Download speeds can vary from 56 Kbps for dialup to 1.5 Mbps or higher for technologies such as DSL and Cable modem.</li><li>A high speed connection is recommended for individuals who download a lot of large programs, perform gaming, or run their own servers.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="emailAccountsTitle">
	<text>Email Accounts</text>
</component>
<component id="emailAccountsBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>ISPs generally provide multiple user emails on one account. These email addresses can be distributed among individuals or used to separate business mail from personal mail.</li><li>Webmail allows users to access their mail from any computer connected to the Internet using any Web browser. No special/dedicated email client is required.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="personalHomePagesTitle">
	<text>Personal Home Pages</text>
</component>
<component id="personalHomePagesBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>Personal web page space is frequently provided with service. Usually both the size of the web space and the traffic generated are limited.</li><li>Design and maintenance of the website is maintained by the individual author.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="webHostingServicesTitle">
	<text>Web Hosting Services</text>
</component>
<component id="webHostingServicesBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>Organizations that do not have web servers can use the ISPs servers for their web site. This often comes with design and maintenance services.</li><li>Web hosting services are usually purchased based on the size of the web site and the anticipated monthly volume. </li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="fileStorageTitle">
	<text>File Storage</text>
</component>
<component id="fileStorageBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>Organizations can use the ISPs online storage and file management systems to provide 24/7 access to important files.</li><li>File storage can range from a few megabytes to terabytes of online storage.</li><li>Online file storage is usually password protected.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ipTelephoneTitle">
	<text>IP Telephone</text>
</component>
<component id="ipTelephoneBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>ISPs may provide IP telephone services that allow users to make and receive voice calls over the Internet.</li><li>When using the Internet, regular long distance tolls do not normally apply.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="virusScanningTitle">
	<text>Virus Scanning</text>
</component>
<component id="virusScanningBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>ISPs often include virus scanning and anti-spam services as part of their connection package.</li><li>Most ISPs scan for malicious code both on files that have been uploaded from the end user and those arriving for delivery to the end user.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="contentFilteringTitle">
	<text>Content Filtering</text>
</component>
<component id="contentFilteringBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>ISPs can provide software that prevents specific material from being downloaded based on user specifications.</li><li>This software is often used to block objectionable and/or offensive web sites.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="videoOnDemandTitle">
	<text>Video on Demand</text>
</component>
<component id="videoOnDemandBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<li>Real-time downloading of movies allows users to watch movies over the Internet. This is known as streaming video.</li>]]></text>
</component>

    <component id="ID_txt01">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Connection Speed</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt02">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Email Accounts</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt03">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Personal Home Pages</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt04">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Web Hosting Services</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt05">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>File Storage</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt06">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>IP Telephone</b>]]></text>
	</component>
		<component id="ID_txt07">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Virus Scanning</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt08">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Content Filtering</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="ID_txt09">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Video on Demand</b>]]></text>
	</component>
	    <component id="ID_txt10">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>ISP Services</b>]]></text>
	</component>
	<component id="ID_txt11">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each of the ISP services for information on that service.</b>]]></text>
	</component>
	
</textcomponents>