<transcript lastedited="10.15.08 11:10:07">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.6.1 Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[10 Questions:<br><br>Basic Security<br><br>1. Match the network threat to the definition.<br><br>Network threat:<br>Data loss<br>Identity theft<br>Information theft<br>Data manipulation <br>Disruption of service.<br><br>Definition:<br>Destroying data on a hard drive.<br>Changing data for personal gain.<br>Overloading a server to reduce its performance.<br>Stealing data on a hard drive to gain a competitive advantage.<br>Stealing information to impersonate someone and usually to obtain credit.<br><br>2. How does a phisher typically contact a victim?<br>by email<br>by telephone<br>by voice over IP phone<br>through a person they know in common<br><br>3. A file is downloaded from the Internet. After the user opens the downloaded file, the user's hard drive crashes and all information on the computer is lost. What type of attack occurred?<br>Worm<br>Virus<br>Trojan horse<br>Denial of Service<br><br>4. In rapid succession, an intruder tries a large number of possibilities to guess passwords. As a result, other users on the network are locked out. What type of attack occurred?<br>DD o S<br>brute force<br>ping of death<br>SYN flooding<br><br>5. What type of program installs and gathers personal information, including password and account information, from a computer without permission or knowledge of the user?<br>ad ware<br>popups<br>spyware<br>popunders<br><br>6. A network administrator is trouble shooting a computer that is operating strangely. It boots slowly programs will not load and the keyboard responds very slowly. What is the best action for the administrator to take?<br>Attach a different keyboard.<br>Attach the PC to the Internet to check the operating system website for patches.<br>Add the PC to your network to see if it can communicate with other PC's.<br>Boot the PC and run antivirus and antispyware applications from an external drive.<br><br>7. Match the term to the best description.<br><br>Term:<br>NAT<br>Stateful packet inspection<br>Simple packet filtering<br>Website filtering<br><br>Description:<br>Can look inside the packet up through layer 7.<br>Allows or denies access base on a URL.<br>Allows or denies access based on an IP or MAC address.<br>Keeps external users from knowing the IP address used inside the network.<br><br>8. Match the term to the definition.<br>Term:<br>Personal firewall<br>integrated firewall<br>server based firewall<br>appliance based firewall<br><br>Definition:<br>A feature of a network device such as a router.<br>An application designed to protect a home PC.<br>A device that has the sole function of being a firewall.<br>An application designed to protect the enterprise network.<br><br>9. What are three security features commonly found on an ISR? (Choose three)<br>DMZ<br>NAT<br>SP I<br>HTTP<br>POP3<br>Server based firewall<br><br>10. What are two purposes of a DMZ? (Choose two)<br>To translate internal private addresses into outside public addresses.<br>To create a software based firewall on a server that performs other functions.<br>To prevent or deny access to a network device based on the type of application being used.<br>To create a network area that allows internal resources, such as a web server, To be accessed by external users.<br>To establish a network area where network resources can be shared by both internal and external users.<br>To create a safe network area that allows a corporate web server to be accessed by internal users only.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
