<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">

<text><![CDATA[<font size="+2">Practice Scenario</font><br /><br />Use the information contained in the scenario to answer the four questions shown on the question tab. 
]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_scenario">

<text><![CDATA[<<B>Scenario</B>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_text1">

<text><![CDATA[The XYZ insurance company has 350 agent offices around the United States. Each agent office has a Frame Relay link to corporate headquarters. Because of corporate policy, the bandwidth of the agent links is determined by and paid for by the agents working in the offices. The agents use the network connection primarily to access various database systems at headquarters and also for e-mail and Internet access.<BR><BR>XYZ has budgeted $5 million to upgrade their outdated network infrastructure at headquarters to a fully redundant Gigabit and Fast Ethernet LAN. The management believes the upgrade will reduce long-term network costs and improve the scalability, availability, security and manageability of the LAN infrastructure. The company is starting a recruiting effort that it hopes will result in the addition of 200 new agent offices in the next three years. The company needs higher capacity to meet the potential demand of the new agents. The project must be completed in three months because of the anticipated demands of a new E-Commerce system, which will increase revenue, and a new customer service system, which will improve customer satisfaction.<BR><BR>The existing LAN equipment is from a non-Cisco vendor although the WAN infrastructure is a complete Cisco solution. The company wants the LAN to be a complete Cisco solution as well, in part because they hope to save costs of operating the LAN with a single vendor solution. The company outsources its IT staff. The Cisco WAN is managed remotely. The IT staff that work on-site have limited training in Cisco networking. The company's web site is also outsourced. Even though the management is outsourced, the servers are located at headquarters and connect directly to the LAN because of XYZ company's policy is that all company data must be physically stored in company facilities. The insurance database systems use Oracle on Unix servers with custom-developed client software. The e-mail system is based on Eudora email client software.]]></text>

</component>



</textcomponents>
