<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 13:01:14">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.3.3  - IP Addressing Issues]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts router and PC IP addressing issues. <br><br>Topology One:<br>Switch S1 has two PC's. PC1 is connected to Port F0/11, and PC3 is connected to F0/6 The PC1 IP address is 172.17.10.21. The PC3 IP address is 172.17.30.23. PC1 is in V LAN 10, and PC3 is in V LAN 30.<br><br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using two links and two router interfaces. Switch S1 port F0/4 is connected to router R1 interface F0/0 with IP address 172.17.10.1 /24. Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/1 with IP address 172.17.30.1 /24. This allows the router to route between V LAN 10 and V LAN 30. Switch S1 ports F0/4 and F0/11 are in V LAN 10. Switch S1 ports F0/5 and F0/6 are in V LAN 30.<br><br>Topology One illustrates an issue with traditional inter-V LAN routing. The IP address for router R1 interface F0/0 is configured incorrectly as 172.17.100.1/24. This prevents PC1 from communicating with router R1 on V LAN 10.<br><br>Topology Two:<br>Same as Topology One, except that the router R1 IP address is 172.17.10.1, and the PC1 IP address is 172.17.20.21.<br><br>Topology Two illustrates an issue with traditional inter-V LAN routing. The IP address for PC1 is configured incorrectly as 172.17.20.21/24. This places PC1 on a different network and prevents it from communicating with router R1 on V LAN 10.<br><br>Topology Three:<br>Same as Topology One, except that the router R1 IP address is 172.17.10.1/24, and the PC1 IP address is 172.17.10.21/16.<br><br>Topology Three illustrates what happens if PC1 has been configured with the incorrect subnet mask. According to the subnet mask configured for PC1 (/16), PC1 is on the 172.17.0.0 network. This causes PC1 to determine that PC3, with IP address 172.17.30.23, is on the local subnet. As a result, PC1 does not forward traffic destined for PC3 to router R1 interface F0/0. Therefore, the traffic never reaches PC3.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
