<transcript lastedited="01.05.09 13:01:11">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.6.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question 1. Where do Transport Layer processes occur?<br>Answer: Transport Layer processes occur between the Application Layer and Internet Layer of the TCP/IP model, and between the Session Layer and Network Layer of the O S I model.<br><br>Question 2. What are the responsibilities of the Transport Layer?<br>Answer: The Transport Layer is responsible for:<br>- Keeping track of the individual conversations taking place between applications on the source and destination hosts.<br>- Segmenting data and adding a header to identify and manage each segment.<br>- Using the header information to reassemble the segments back into application data.<br>- Passing the assembled data to the correct application.<br><br>Question 3. What does segmentation provide to communications?<br>Answer: Segmentation of the data, in accordance with Transport Layer protocols, provides the means to both send and receive data when running multiple applications concurrently on a computer.<br><br>Question 4. What are the primary functions specified by all Transport Layer protocols?<br>Answer: The primary functions specified by all Transport Layer protocols include:<br>-	Conversation Multiplexing: There are many applications or services running on each host in the network. Each of these applications or services is assigned an address known as a port so that the Transport Layer can determine with which application or service the data is identified.<br>-	Segmentation and Reassembly: Most networks have a limitation on the amount of data that can be included in a single PDU. The Transport Layer divides application data into blocks of data that are an appropriate size. At the destination, the Transport Layer reassembles the data before sending it to the destination application or service.<br>-	Error Checking: Basic error checking can be performed on the data in the segment to determine if the data was changed during transmission.<br> <br>Question 5. In networking terms, what is reliability?<br>Answer: In networking terms, reliability means ensuring that each segment that the source sends arrives at the destination.<br><br>Question 6. List three applications that use TCP.<br>Answer: Applications that use TCP are:<br>- Web browsing<br>- E-mail<br>- File transfers<br><br>Question 7. List three applications that use UDP.<br>Answer: Applications that use UDP include:<br>- Domain Name Resolution<br>- Video streaming<br>- Voice over IP (V o IP)<br><br>Question 8. What are the different types of port numbers?<br>Answer: <br>The different types of port numbers are:<br>Well Known Ports (Numbers 0 to 1023): These numbers are reserved for services and applications. They are commonly used for applications such as HTTP (web server) POP3 and SMTP (e-mail server), and Telnet. By defining these well-known ports for server applications, client applications can be programmed to request a connection to that specific port and its associated service.<br>Registered Ports (Numbers 1024 to 49151): These port numbers are assigned to user processes or applications. They are primarily individual applications that a user has chosen to install rather than common, universal applications that would receive a well-known port.<br>Dynamic or Private Ports (Numbers 49152 to 65535): Also known as ephemeral ports, these ports are usually assigned dynamically to client applications when initiating a connection. It is not very common for a client to connect to a service using a dynamic or private port, although some peer-to-peer file-sharing programs do.<br><br>Question 9. What is contained in the header of each segment or datagram?<br>Answer: The source and destination port numbers.<br><br>Question 10. What is the purpose of a sequence number?<br>Answer: A sequence number allows the Transport Layer functions on the destination host to reassemble segments in the order in which they were transmitted.<br><br>Question 11. What is one way to improve security on a server?<br>Answer: One way to improve security on a server is to restrict server access to only those ports associated with the services and applications that should be accessible to authorized requestors.<br><br>Question 12. Describe the TCP three-way handshake:<br>Answer: The three-way handshake does the following:<br>- Establishes that the destination device is present on the network.<br>- Verifies that the destination device has an active service and is accepting requests on the destination port number that the initiating client intends to use for the session.<br>- Informs the destination device that the source client intends to establish a communication session on that port number.<br><br>Question 13. What are TCP sequence numbers used for?<br>Answer: For the original message to be understood by the recipient, the data in these segments is reassembled in the original order.<br><br>Question 14. Explain an expectational acknowledgement.<br>Answer: TCP uses the acknowledgement number in segments sent back to the source to indicate the next byte in this session that the receiver expects to receive.<br><br>Question 15. After a predetermined amount of time, what does TCP do when it has not received an acknowledgement?<br>Answer: When TCP at the source host has not received an acknowledgement after a predetermined amount of time, it goes back to the last acknowledgement number that it received and retransmits data from that point forward.<br><br>Question 16. What term is used to refer to the amount of data that can be transmitted before a TCP acknowledgement must be received?<br>Answer: Window size.<br><br>Question 17. List key Application Layer protocols that use UDP.<br>Answer: Application Layer protocols that use UDP include:<br>-	Domain Name System (DNS)<br>-	Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)<br>-	Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP)<br>-	Routing Information Protocol (RIP)<br>-	Trivial File Transfer Protocol (TFTP)<br>-	Online games]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
