<transcript lastedited="10.08.08 08:10:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.4.2 - Configuring ACL's to Support Established Traffic]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation shows how an ACL is used to filter specific traffic from entering an internal network, but allow the same traffic access from the internal network.<br><br>Network Topology<br>An internal network has hosts, H1 and H2, connected by a switch to router, R1. R1 is connected to router, R2, via a serial connection. R2 is part of the ISP cloud, which also includes a web server. A foreign network with host, H3, is also connected to the ISP .<br><br>H1 sends a request to the web server. The packet successfully travels across the network to the web server. The web server sends a response. When the response reaches the F A 0 /0 of R1, the following ACL command is matched and the packet is allowed access to H1.<br><br>access-list 101 permit tcp any any established<br><br>Next, H2 sends a ping, also known as an echo request, to R2. R2 sends a ping, echo reply, back to H2. When the ping reaches the F A 0 /0 of R1, the following ACL command is matched and the packet is allowed access to H2. <br><br>access-list 101 permit icmp any any echo-reply<br><br>Finally, H3, located on the foreign network, sends a ping, echo request, to the internal network. When the ping reaches the F A 0 /0 of R1, the following ACL command is matched and the packet is denied.<br><br>access-list 101 deny any any<br><br>The output of R1's command prompt is as follows:<br><br>R1 (config) # access-list 101 permit tcp any any established<br>R1 (config) # access-list 101 permit icmp any any echo-reply<br>R1 (config) # access-list 101 permit icmp any any unreachable<br>R1 (config) # access-list 101 deny any any<br><br>R1 (config) # interface F A 0 /0<br>R1 (config-if) # ip access-group 101 out<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
