<transcript lastedited="10.29.08 14:10:53">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.5.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.	Which three options correctly associate a layer of the hierarchical design model with its function? (Choose three.)<br>A.	Core - interface for end devices.<br>B.	Distribution - traffic control and security policies.<br>C.	Access - interface for end devices.<br>D.	Distribution - high-speed backbone.<br>E.	Core - high-speed backbone.<br>F.	Access - implementation of security policies.<br><br>2.	With respect to network design, what is convergence?<br>A.	Implementation of standard equipment sets for LAN design.<br>B.	Implementation of a core-distribution-access design model for all sites in an enterprise.<br>C.	A point in the network where all traffic converges before transmission to the destination, normally the core switch.<br>D.	Combining conventional data with voice and video on a common network.<br><br>3.	Identify the potential benefits of a converged network. (Choose three.)<br>A.	Simplified data network configuration.<br>B.	Simplified network changes.<br>C.	Combines voice, video, and applications in one computer.<br>D.	Conventional voice equipment can be used for new V o IP implementations.<br>E.	Combines voice and data network staffs.<br>F.	Simpler maintenance than hierarchical networks.<br>G.	Lower quality of service configuration requirements.<br><br>4.	Match the analysis action to the correct analysis type.<br>Analysis Actions:<br>A.	Workstation ports required for a department.<br>B.	Amount of server-to-server traffic.<br>C.	Intensity of use of a department application server.<br>D.	Amount of traffic for a SAN.<br>E.	Anticipated department port growth.<br>F.	Data backed up to tape.<br>G.	Network attached storage.<br><br>Analysis Type:<br>One.	User communities.<br>Two.	Data stores and data servers.<br><br>5.	What factor may complicate user communities analysis?<br>A.	Application changes may radically affect predicted data growth.<br>B.	Server-to-server traffic may skew user port usage data.<br>C.	Application usage is not always bound by department or physical location.<br>D.	Different organization applications may share data stores.<br><br>6.	Match the term to the associated definition.<br>Terms:<br>A. Port density.<br>B. Forwarding rates.<br>C. Link aggregation.<br>D. Wire speed.<br><br>Definitions:<br>One.	Data rate that each port on the switch is capable of attaining.<br>Two.	Number of ports available on a single switch.<br>Three.	Processing capabilities of a switch by quantifying performance of the switch by how much data it can process per second.<br>Four.	Ability to utilize multiple switch ports concurrently for higher throughput data communication.<br><br>7.	What would be the port capability of a single port on a 48-port Gigabit Ethernet switch?<br>A.	48 Gigabits per second.<br>B.	10 Megabits per second.<br>C.	1000 Megabits per second.<br>D.	100 Megabits per second.<br><br>8.	A switch that uses MAC addresses to forward frames operates at which layer of the O S I model?<br>A.	Layer 1.<br>B.	Layer 2.<br>C.	Layer 3.<br>D.	Layer 4.<br><br>9.	What is a feature offered by all stackable switches?<br>A.	Predetermined number of ports.<br>B.	Fully redundant backplane.<br>C.	Support for Gigabit connectivity.<br>D.	Low bandwidth for inter-switch communications.<br>E.	P o E capability.<br><br>10.	What function is performed by a Cisco access level switch?<br>A.	Inter-V LAN support.<br>B.	Routing.<br>C.	Providing P o E.<br>D.	Link aggregation.<br><br>11.	Match the feature listed to the Cisco layer to which it is associated.<br>Features:<br>A.	Port security.<br>B.	Layer 3 support.<br>C.	Redundant components.<br>D.	V LAN's.<br>E.	10 Gigabit Ethernet.<br>F.	P o E.<br><br>Layers:<br>One.	Core Layer.<br>Two.	Access Layer.<br><br>12.	Which two characteristics describe the Core Layer of the hierarchical network design model? (Choose two.)<br>A.	Redundant paths.<br>B.	High-level policy enforcement.<br>C.	P o E.<br>D.	Controls access of end devices to network.<br>E.	Rapid forwarding of traffic.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
