<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 10:09:45">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.3.5 - Basic Switch C L I Commands]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts a table of the basic switch commands. The table headings include Full Command, Abbreviation, and Purpose / Information Displayed, listed below from left to right. The commands are categorized by General Use, Interface/Port Related, and Connectivity Related.<br><br>Full CommandAbbreviationPurpose/Information Displayed<br>General Use<br>show running-configsh runDisplays current config running in RAM.  Includes hostname, passwords, interface IP addresses, routing protocol activated, DHCP and NAT configuration.  Must be issued in EXEC mode.<br>show startup-configsh starDisplays backup config in NV RAM.  May be different if running config has not been copied to backup.  Must be issued in EXEC mode.<br>show versionsh veDisplays I O S version, ROM version, router uptime system image file name, boot method, number and type of interfaces installed, amount of RAM, NV RAM and flash, and configuration register value.<br>Interface/Port Related<br>show interfaces (type#)sh int f 0 /0 Displays one or all interfaces with line (protocol) status, bandwidth, delay, reliability, encapsulation, duplex, and I / O statistics.<br>show ip interface briefsh ip int br Displays all interfaces with IP address with interface status (up/down/admin down) and line protocol status (up/down)<br>show port-security sh por Show any ports where security has been activated along with max address allowed, current count, security violation count, and action to take (usually shutdown).<br>show mac-address-table sh mac-a Displays all MAC addresses the switch has learned, how learned (dynamic or static) the port number and the V LAN the port is in.<br>Connectivity Related<br>show cdp neighbors (detail)sh cdp ne Displays information on directly connected devices including Device ID (host name). Local interface where device is connected, capability (R=router), S=switch), platform (eg.2620XM), and port ID or remote device.  The details option provides the I P address of the other device as well as the I O S version.<br>show sessionssh sesDisplays telnet sessions (V T Y) with remote hosts. Displays session number, host name, and address.<br>show s s h sh s s h Displays s s h server connections with remote hosts.<br>ping (ip or hostname)PSends 5 ICMP echo requests to an IP address or host name (if DNS is available) and displays min and max and average time to respond.<br>traceroute (ip or hostname)TrSends echo request with varying T T L. Lists routes (hops) in path and time to respond.<br><br>Note that router interfaces start numbering at 0, while switch interfaces start at 1. For example, a fast Ethernet interface on a router would start at fa 0 /0, whereas the first port on a switch would be referenced as fa 0 /1.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
