<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.2.5  - VTP Pruning]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts an activity in which you must perform a VTP operation testlet.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S1 port F0/1 is connected to S2 port F0/1. Switch S3 is not currently connected. Three PC's, PC1, PC2, and PC3, are connected to switch S2 on ports F0/11, F0/18, and F0/6, respectively. Switch S2 has failed and is being replaced with switch S3. <br><br>PC1:<br>IP address 172.17.10.21<br>V LAN 10<br><br>PC2:<br>IP address 172.17.20.22<br>V LAN 20<br><br>PC3:<br>IP address 172.17.30.23<br>V LAN 30<br><br>Switch S1:<br>VTP Domain Name = CCNA<br>VTP Mode = Server<br>Config Revision = 4<br>V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99<br><br>Switch S2:<br>VTP Domain Name = CCNA<br>VTP Mode = Client<br>Config Revision = 4<br>V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99<br><br>Switch S3:<br>VTP Domain Name = CCNA<br>VTP Mode = Client<br>Config Revision = 6<br>V LAN's = 1, 99-104<br><br>Scenario:<br>In the topology, S2 failed and is being replaced. The network administrator acquired the S3 switch from another area of the network where it was no longer in use. The administrator erased the configuration of the S3 device and applied the configuration from the old S2 device so that V LAN port assignments would be reapplied. The administrator also added the VTP domain name and set the VTP mode to client. However, when the S3 device was connected to S1 and trunking was restored, all the ports in V LAN's 10, 20, and 30 transitioned to the inactive state.<br><br>Question One.<br>After the S2 device was replaced with the S3 device and the trunk links were established, which represents the configuration revision number and V LAN information for switches S1 and S3?<br><br>A.	Config Revision = 4, V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99 to 104<br>B.	Config Revision = 6, V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99 to 104<br>C.	Config Revision = 4, V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99<br>D.	Config Revision = 6, V LAN's = 1, 10, 20, 30, 99<br>E.	Config Revision = 6, V LAN's = 1, 99 to 104<br><br>Question Two.<br>Which two of the following is true about the configuration revision number? (Choose two.)<br><br>A.	Only subset advertisements contain the configuration revision number.<br>B.	Only summary advertisements contain the configuration revision number.<br>C.	All VTP messages contain the configuration revision number.<br>D.	Higher configuration revision numbers take precedence over lower configuration revision numbers.<br>E.	Lower configuration revision numbers take precedence over higher configuration revision numbers.<br><br>Question Three.<br>Which solution is appropriate to resolve the V LAN configuration discrepancies for the VTP domain and connectivity for the PC1, PC2, and PC3 devices?<br><br>A.	Add the missing V LAN's to the VTP server S1.<br>B.	Delete the V LAN's from the new S3.<br>C.	Delete all possible V LAN's from the VTP server S1.<br>D.	Add the missing V LAN's to switches S1 and S3.<br><br>Question Four.<br>Which two methods avoid unintentional V LAN database corruption when adding a new switch? (Choose two.)<br><br>A.	Reset the configuration revision number on the new switch by temporarily changing the VTP domain name.<br>B.	Increase the configuration revision number on an existing VTP server so that it is lower than the switch being added.<br>C.	Temporarily change the mode of the new switch to transparent.<br>D.	Delete the V LAN database of the VTP server before connecting the new device to the network.<br>E.	Change the configuration register number on the new switch using the config-reg command.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
