<chapter type="" id="en1102000000">
<title><content-text>Exploring the Enterprise Network Infrastructure</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1102000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm7756428292">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102000000/en1102000100/en1102000101/cm7756428292.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102000000/en1102000100/en1102000101/cm7756428292text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1102010000">
<title><content-text>Describing the Current Network</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102010100">
<title><content-text>Enterprise Network Documentation</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8464686263">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010101/cm8464686263.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010101/cm8464686263text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the first tasks for a new network technician is to become familiar with the current network structure. Enterprise networks can have thousands of hosts and hundreds of networking devices, all of which are interconnected by copper, fiber-optic, and wireless technologies. End-user workstations, servers, and networking devices, such as switches and routers, must all be documented. Various types of documentation show different aspects of the network. </p> <p><content-link target="{0622AEF4-D62B-47FE-ADB9-2DE7FC53E24D}" type="glossary">Network infrastructure diagram</content-link>s, or topology diagrams, keep track of the location, function, and status of devices. Topology diagrams represent either the physical or logical network.</p> <p>A <content-link target="{C3060A80-5C7B-47C8-A0D8-7A70B73980FE}" type="glossary">physical topology</content-link> map uses icons to document the location of hosts, networking devices, and media. It is important to maintain and update physical topology maps to aid future installation and troubleshooting efforts. </p> <p>A <content-link target="{E3CE5221-BAE0-4F26-90ED-605DC40B99FF}" type="glossary">logical topology</content-link> map groups hosts by network usage, regardless of physical location. Host names, addresses, group information, and applications can be recorded on the logical topology map. Connections between multiple sites may be shown but do not represent actual physical locations.</p> <p>Enterprise network diagrams may also include control plane information. Control plane information describes failure domains and defines the interfaces where different network technologies intersect.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6149848687">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010102/cm6149848687.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010102/cm6149848687text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is crucial that network documentation remain current and accurate. Network documentation is usually accurate at the installation of a network. As the network grows or changes however, the documentation is not always updated.</p> <p>Network topology maps are frequently based on original floor plans. The current floor plans may have changed since the construction of the building. Blueprints can be marked up, or <content-link target="{CF19846A-538B-46D2-89AC-8B57CAE4C4D3}" type="glossary">redlined</content-link>, to show the changes. The modified diagram is known as an <content-link target="{F4586B1B-21DF-42ED-9256-5FF28C07EA59}" type="glossary">as-built</content-link>. An as-built diagram documents how a network was actually constructed which may differ from the original plans. Always ensure that the current documentation reflects the as-built floor plan and all network topology changes.</p> <p>Network diagrams are commonly created using graphical drawing software. In addition to being a drawing tool, many network diagramming tools are linked to a database. This feature allows the network support staff to develop detailed documentation by recording information about hosts and networking devices, including manufacturer, model number, purchase date, warranty period, and more. Clicking a device in the diagram opens an entry form with device data listed. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010103">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1961993319">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010103/cm1961993319.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010103/cm1961993319text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to network diagrams, several other important types of documentation are used in the enterprise network. </p> <p>Business Continuity Plan: </p> <p>The Business Continuity Plan (<content-link target="{03E5C3DE-6AD6-4CAF-BBAB-3B07D4308224}" type="glossary">BCP</content-link>) identifies the steps to be taken to continue business operation in the event of a natural or man-made disaster. </p> <p>Business Security Plan: </p> <p>The Business Security Plan (<content-link target="{B7626E3E-8186-4DB9-8EF3-6A0925B5F4D5}" type="glossary">BSP</content-link>) includes physical, system, and organizational control measures. The overall security plan must include an IT portion that describes how an organization protects its network and information assets. </p> <p>Network Maintenance Plan: </p> <p>The Network Maintenance Plan (<content-link target="{B461806A-6E26-43B4-B018-6E5E54AA028F}" type="glossary">NMP</content-link>) ensures business continuity by keeping the network up and running efficiently. Network maintenance must be scheduled during specific time periods, usually nights and weekends, to minimize the impact on business operations.</p> <p>Service Level Agreement: </p> <p>A Service Level Agreement (<content-link target="{B364C92F-7ECA-4968-897E-806F0CA816DF}" type="glossary">SLA</content-link>) is a contractual agreement between the customer and a service provider or ISP, specifying items such as network availability and service response time. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102010104">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm2373765204">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010104/cm2373765204.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010100/en1102010104/cm2373765204text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102010200">
<title><content-text>Network Operations Center (NOC)</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2620244139">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010201/cm2620244139.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010201/cm2620244139text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most enterprise networks have a Network Operations Center (<content-link target="{361F7327-C99B-4E95-90A8-EECED36F94AA}" type="glossary">NOC</content-link>) that allows for central management and monitoring of all network resources. The NOC is sometimes referred to as a <content-link target="{56601A71-2EB1-4076-BBFE-883176F5DFA6}" type="glossary">Data Center</content-link>.</p> <p>Employees in a typical enterprise NOC provide support for both local and remote locations, often managing both local and wide area networking issues. Larger NOCs may be multi-room areas of a building where network equipment and support staff are concentrated.</p> <p>The NOC usually has:</p> <p><ul><li> Raised floors to allow for cabling and power to run under the floor to the equipment</li><li> High performance UPS systems and air conditioning equipment to provide a safe operating environment for equipment</li><li> Fire suppression systems integrated into the ceiling</li><li> Network monitoring stations, servers, backup systems, and data storage</li><li> Access layer switches and distribution layer routers, if it serves as a Main Distribution Facility (MDF) for the building or campus where it is located</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8969510093">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010202/cm8969510093.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010202/cm8969510093text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to providing network support and management, many NOCs also provide centralized resources such as servers and data storage. </p> <p>Servers in the NOC are usually clustered together, creating a server farm. The <content-link target="{07EC5785-6F7F-4E79-BCC7-55BFB89DCB67}" type="glossary">server farm</content-link> is frequently considered as a single resource but, in fact, provides two functions: backup and <content-link target="{D8D1836E-0E88-491B-B056-09BEA313FA21}" type="glossary">load balancing</content-link>. If one server fails or becomes overloaded, another server takes over. </p> <p>The servers in the farm may be rack-mounted and interconnected by very high-speed switches (Gigabit Ethernet or higher). They may also be blade servers mounted in a chassis and connected by a high-speed backplane within the chassis. </p> <p>Another important aspect of the enterprise NOC is high-speed, high-capacity data storage. This data storage, or network attached storage (<content-link target="{8961D438-F0E1-4941-96C6-9F6937B31DB0}" type="glossary">NAS</content-link>), groups large numbers of disk drives that are directly attached to the network and can be used by any server. A NAS device is typically attached to an Ethernet network and is assigned its own IP address.</p> <p>A more sophisticated version of NAS is Storage Area Network (<content-link target="{3D08EA37-4F7B-4614-977C-30C98BB2BFAE}" type="glossary">SAN</content-link>). A SAN is a high-speed network that interconnects different types of data storage devices over a LAN or WAN.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3156878548">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010203/cm3156878548.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010203/cm3156878548text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Equipment in the enterprise NOC is usually mounted in racks. In large NOCs, racks are usually floor-to-ceiling mounted and may be attached to each other. When mounting equipment in a rack, ensure there is adequate ventilation and access from front and back. Equipment must also be attached to a known good ground.</p> <p>The most common rack width is 19 inches (48.26 cm). Most equipment is designed to fit this width. The vertical space that the equipment occupies is measured in Rack Units (<content-link target="{C40A95E3-6AE8-4D9C-A44A-F75FB62F5DDB}" type="glossary">RU</content-link>s). A Unit equals 1.75 inches (4.4cm). For example, a 2U chassis is 3.5 inches (8.9 cm) high. The lower the RU number the less space a device needs therefore more devices can fit into the rack. </p> <p>Another consideration is equipment with many connections, like switches. They may need to be positioned near patch panels and close to where the cabling is gathered into cable trays.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2341406892">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010204/cm2341406892.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010200/en1102010204/cm2341406892text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In an enterprise NOC, thousands of cables may enter and exit the facility. <content-link target="{97E8EF9B-D486-4E52-A7E5-915B3822E487}" type="glossary">Structured cabling</content-link> creates an organized cabling system that is easily understood by installers, network administrators, and any other technicians who work with cables. </p> <p>Cable management serves many purposes. First, it presents a neat and organized system that aids in isolating cabling problems. Second, best cabling practices protect the cables from physical damage and <content-link target="{171E4F4C-6F7C-4B5A-8A81-7C11336831BE}" type="glossary">EMI</content-link>, which greatly reduces the number of problems experienced. </p> <p>To assist in troubleshooting: </p> <p><ul><li> All cables should be labelled at both ends, using a standard convention that indicates source and destination. </li><li> All cable runs should be documented on the physical network topology diagram. </li><li> All cable runs, both copper and fiber, should be tested end-to-end by sending a signal down the cable and measuring loss. </li></ul></p> <p>Cabling standards specify a maximum distance for all cable types and network technologies. For example, the IEEE specifies that, for Fast Ethernet over unshielded twisted pair (UTP), the cable run from switch to host cannot be greater than 100 meters (approximately 328 ft). If the cable run is greater than the recommended length problems could occur with data communications, especially if the terminations at the ends of the cable are poorly completed. </p> <p>Documentation of the cable plan and testing are critical to network operations.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102010300">
<title><content-text>Telecommunication Room Design and Considerations</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9077792282">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010301/cm9077792282.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010301/cm9077792282text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The NOC is the central nervous system of the enterprise. In practice, however, most users connect to a switch in a <content-link target="{18E4D630-64B2-4E96-8517-8B1E0C1CDA2D}" type="glossary">telecommunications room</content-link>, which is some distance from the NOC. The telecommunications room is also referred to as a wiring closet or intermediate distribution facility (<content-link target="{23EAE882-7EB4-4667-8EAD-85DBE857B21C}" type="glossary">IDF</content-link>). It contains the Access Layer networking devices and ideally maintains environmental conditions similar to the NOC, such as air conditioning and UPS.</p> <p>Users working with wired technology connect to the network through Ethernet switches or hubs. Users working with wireless technology connect through an access point (<content-link target="{1B2AEE74-142A-499C-B8C2-3944ADCB0C69}" type="glossary">AP</content-link>). Access Layer devices such as switches and APs are a potential vulnerability in network security. Physical and remote access to this equipment should be limited to authorized personnel only. Network personnel can also implement port security and other measures on switches, as well as various wireless security measures on APs. </p> <p>Securing the telecommunications room has become even more important because of the increasing occurrence of identity theft. New privacy legislation results in severe penalties if confidential data from a network falls into the wrong hands. Modern networking devices offer capabilities to help prevent these attacks and protect data and user integrity.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010302">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm4987950390">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010302/cm4987950390.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010302/cm4987950390text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Many IDFs connect to a Main Distribution Facility (<content-link target="{74E879D1-CEC5-47FB-BAB1-7B6D5614375E}" type="glossary">MDF</content-link>) using an <content-link target="{FC84287D-6AD0-49C5-824F-86F9C8DEF920}" type="glossary">extended star</content-link> design. The MDF is usually located in the NOC or centrally located within the building. </p> <p>MDFs are typically larger than IDFs. They house high-speed switches, routers, and server farms. The central MDF switches may have enterprise servers and disk drives connected using gigabit copper links. </p> <p>IDFs contain lower-speed switches, APs, and hubs. The switches in the IDFs typically have large numbers of Fast Ethernet ports for users to connect at the Access Layer.</p> <p>The switches in the IDF usually connect to the switches in the MDF with Gigabit interfaces. This arrangement creates backbone connections, or uplinks. These backbone links, also called vertical cabling, may be copper or fiber-optic. Copper Gigabit or Fast Ethernet links are limited to a maximum of 100 meters and should use CAT5e or CAT6 UTP cable. Fiber-optic links can run much greater distances. Fiber-optic links commonly interconnect buildings and because they do not conduct electricity, they are immune to lightning strikes, EMI, RFI, and differential grounds.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102010303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7303580080">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010303/cm7303580080.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010303/cm7303580080text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to providing basic network access connectivity, it is becoming more common to provide power to end-user devices directly from the Ethernet switches in the telecommunications room. These devices include IP phones, access points, and surveillance cameras.</p> <p>These devices are powered using the IEEE 802.3af standard, Power over Ethernet, or <content-link target="{176D9E0A-C215-48B2-958E-388799AB8F66}" type="glossary">PoE</content-link>. PoE provides power to a device over the same twisted pair cable that carries data. This allows an IP phone, for instance, to be located on a desk without the need for a separate power cord or a power outlet. In order to support PoE devices such as the IP phone, the connecting switch must have PoE capability. </p> <p>PoE can also be provided by power injectors or PoE patch panels for those switches which do not support PoE. Panduit and other suppliers produce PoE patch panels that allow non PoE capable switches to participate in PoE environments. Legacy switches connect into the PoE patch panel which then connects to the PoE capable device.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102010304">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm7938580441">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010304/cm7938580441.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102010000/en1102010300/en1102010304/cm7938580441text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Place the MDF and IDFs in an appropriate location in the campus diagram and identify appropriate cables to connect them.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1102020000">
<title><content-text>Supporting the Enterprise Edge</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102020100">
<title><content-text>Service Delivery at the Point-of-Presence</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1306915068">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020100/en1102020101/cm1306915068.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020100/en1102020101/cm1306915068text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At the outer edge of the enterprise network is the Point-of-Presence (<content-link target="{611160C5-1AC2-4991-A510-62B18F4BC9E4}" type="glossary">POP</content-link>) which provides an entry point for services to the enterprise network. Externally-provided services coming in through the POP include Internet access, wide area connections, and telephone services (PSTN).</p> <p>The POP contains a point of demarcation, or the <content-link target="{CF8B47DC-3885-4911-8B57-E0C1AED3D19B}" type="glossary">demarc</content-link>. The demarc provides a boundary that designates responsibility for equipment maintenance and troubleshooting between the service provider (<content-link target="{3D3626CA-0ADD-4833-B8A1-6695346AF3ED}" type="glossary">SP</content-link>) and customer. Equipment from the service provider up to the point of demarcation is the responsibility of the provider; anything past the demarc point is the responsibility of the customer.</p> <p>In an enterprise, the POP provides links to outside services and sites. The POP may provide a direct link to one or more ISPs, which allows internal users the required access to the Internet. The remote sites of an enterprise are also interconnected through the POPs. The service provider establishes the wide area links between these remote sites.</p>  <p>The location of the POP and the point of demarcation vary in different countries. While they are often located within the MDF of the customer, they may also be located at the ISP.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102020200">
<title><content-text>Security Considerations at the Enterprise Edge</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1051366788">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020200/en1102020201/cm1051366788.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020200/en1102020201/cm1051366788text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Large enterprises usually consist of multiple sites that interconnect. Multiple locations may have edge connections at each site connecting the enterprise to other individuals and organizations. </p> <p>The edge is the point of entry for outside attacks and is a point of vulnerability. Attacks at the edge can affect thousands of users. For example, Denial of Service (<content-link target="{2B0C9762-0134-428E-B96F-79517BCF3F0B}" type="glossary">DoS</content-link>) attacks prevent access to resources for legitimate users inside or outside the network, affecting productivity for the entire enterprise.</p> <p>All traffic in or out of the organization goes through the edge. Edge devices must be configured to defend against attacks and provide filtering based on website, IP address, traffic pattern, application, and protocol. </p> <p>An organization can deploy a <content-link target="{564B89C3-454B-42BC-A659-43A45DA02994}" type="glossary">firewall</content-link>, and security appliances with intrusion detection system (IDS) and intrusion prevention system (IPS) at the edge to protect the network. </p> <p>External network administrators require access for internal maintenance and software installation. Virtual private networks (VPNs), access control lists (ACLs), user IDs, and passwords provide that access. VPNs also allow remote workers access to internal resources.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102020300">
<title><content-text>Connecting the Enterprise Network to External Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102020301">
﻿<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8872605694">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020300/en1102020301/cm8872605694.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020300/en1102020301/cm8872605694text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The network connection services commonly purchased by an enterprise include leased lines, <content-link target="{8AAFFD5A-54B5-4E04-B895-BBC84805C9EF}" type="glossary">T1</content-link>/<content-link target="{2E155B75-D6F2-41F2-A999-DD6B4FAC65BE}" type="glossary">E1</content-link> or business class, Frame Relay, and ATM. Physical cabling brings these services to the enterprise using copper wires, as in the case of T1/E1, or fiber-optic cable for higher-speed services.</p> <p>The POP must contain certain pieces of equipment to obtain whichever WAN service is required. For example, to obtain T1/E1 service, the customer may require a <content-link target="{FEBF4429-D926-4611-BBB0-2FA02966157F}" type="glossary">punchdown block</content-link> to terminate the T1/E1 circuit, as well as a Channel Service Unit / Data Service Unit (<content-link target="{3AFA299C-FB8D-4251-9EB2-C0C29182AAA2}" type="glossary">CSU/DSU</content-link>) to provide the proper electrical interface and signaling for the service provider. This equipment may be owned and maintained by the service provider or may be owned and maintained by the customer. Regardless of ownership, all equipment located within the POP at the customer site is referred to as Customer Premise Equipment (<content-link target="{C17C5F37-79BE-41B8-9A53-854CEA0687D2}" type="glossary">CPE</content-link>).</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102020302">
﻿<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm2593917078">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020300/en1102020302/cm2593917078.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102020000/en1102020300/en1102020302/cm2593917078text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Specify the components, in the correct sequence needed to connect a service from the edge to the internal network.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1102030000">
<title><content-text>Reviewing Routing and Switching</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102030100">
<title><content-text>Router Hardware</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8950273924">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030101/cm8950273924.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030101/cm8950273924text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One important device in the <content-link target="{52F050C6-D879-4B3E-B191-5C5DE81DD44A}" type="glossary">Distribution Layer</content-link> of an enterprise network is a router. Without the routing process, packets could not leave the local network.</p> <p>The router provides access to other private networks as well as to the Internet. All hosts on a local network specify the IP address of the local router <content-link target="{5633B51D-631B-4D82-ABD5-C6141D5B4C64}" type="glossary">interface</content-link> in their IP configuration. This router interface is the <content-link target="{E903D41C-107E-4A06-847C-5DC19FCF9AC3}" type="glossary">default gateway</content-link>. </p> <p>Routers play a critical role in networking by interconnecting multiple sites within an enterprise network, providing redundant paths, and connecting ISPs on the Internet. Routers can also act as a translator between different media types and protocols. For example, a router can re-encapsulate packets from an Ethernet to a Serial encapsulation.</p> <p>Routers use the network portion of the destination IP address to route packets to the proper destination. They select an alternate path if a link goes down or traffic is congested. </p> <p>Routers also serve other beneficial functions:</p> <p><ul><li> Provide broadcast containment </li><li> Connect remote locations</li><li> Group users logically by application or department</li><li> Provide enhanced security (using NAT and ACLs)</li></ul></p> <p>With the enterprise and the ISP, the ability to route efficiently and recover from network link failures is critical to delivering packets to their destination.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6531068543">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030102/cm6531068543.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030102/cm6531068543text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Routers come in many shapes and sizes called <content-link target="{F1E11605-C3B7-4041-93F7-7682D934F866}" type="glossary">form factor</content-link>s. Network administrators in an enterprise environment should be able to support a variety of routers and switches, from a small desktop to a rack-mounted or blade model. </p> <p>Routers can also be categorized as fixed configuration or modular. With the fixed configuration, the desired router interfaces are built-in. Modular routers come with multiple slots that allow a network administrator to change the interfaces on the router. As an example, a Cisco 1841 router comes with two Fast Ethernet RJ-45 interfaces built-in, and two slots that can accommodate many different network interface modules.</p> <p>Routers come with a variety of different interfaces, such as Fast Ethernet, Gigabit Ethernet, Serial, and Fiber-Optic. Router interfaces use the controller/interface or controller/slot/interface conventions. For example, using the controller/interface convention, the first Fast Ethernet interface on a router is numbered as Fa0/0 (controller 0 and interface 0). The second is Fa0/1. The first serial interface on a router uses controller/slot/interface is S0/0/0.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9843226732">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030103/cm9843226732.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030100/en1102030103/cm9843226732text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Two methods exist for connecting a PC to a network device for configuration and monitoring tasks: <content-link target="{55F465CF-CAC8-4004-A635-7C52234A3E17}" type="glossary">out-of-band</content-link> and <content-link target="{8D24423B-7245-44A7-AA41-A03B679D98F9}" type="glossary">in-band</content-link> management. </p> <p>Out-of-band management is used for initial configuration or when a network connection is unavailable. Configuration using out-of-band management requires:</p> <p><ul><li> Direct connection to console or AUX port</li><li> Terminal emulation client</li></ul></p>  <p>In-band management is used to monitor and make configuration changes to a network device over a network connection. Configuration using in-band management requires:</p>  <p><ul><li> At least one network interface on the device to be connected and operational </li><li> Telnet, SSH, or HTTP to access a Cisco device </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102030200">
<title><content-text>Basic Router CLI Show Commands</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3723886041">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030201/cm3723886041.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030201/cm3723886041text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Here are some of the most commonly used IOS commands to display and verify the operational status of the router and related network functionality. These commands are divided into several categories. </p> <p><b>General Use:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show version</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Routing Related:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show ip protocols</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show ip route</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Interface Related:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show interfaces</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show ip interface brief</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show protocols</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Connectivity Related:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show cdp neighbors</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show sessions</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>show ssh</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>ping</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b> traceroute</b></span></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102030202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm1319237903">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030202/cm1319237903.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030202/cm1319237903text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102030203">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm8529877271">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030203/cm8529877271.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030200/en1102030203/cm8529877271text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activty</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102030300">
<title><content-text>Basic Router Configuration Using CLI</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9228983908">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030300/en1102030301/cm9228983908.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030300/en1102030301/cm9228983908text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A basic router configuration includes the hostname for identification, passwords for security, and assignment of IP addresses to interfaces for connectivity. Verify and save configuration changes using the <span class="cmd"><b>copy running-config startup-config</b></span> command. To clear the router configuration, use the <span class="cmd"><b>erase startup-config</b></span> command and then the <span class="cmd"><b>reload </b></span>command.</p> <p><b>Configuration Management:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>enable</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>configure terminal</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>copy running-config startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>erase startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>reload</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Global Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>hostname</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>banner motd</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>enable password</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>enable secret</b></span></li></ul></p>  <p><b>Line Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>line con</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>line aux</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>line vty </b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>login and password</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Interface Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>interface type/number</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>description</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>ip address</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>no shutdown</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>clock rate</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>encapsulation</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Routing Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>router </b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>network</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b> ip route</b></span></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030302">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2343719075">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030300/en1102030302/cm2343719075/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030300/en1102030302/cm2343719075/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Practice basic router configuration and verification commands.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102030400">
<title><content-text>Switch Hardware</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2526044375">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030400/en1102030401/cm2526044375.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030400/en1102030401/cm2526044375text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although all three layers of the hierarchical design model contain switches and routers, the Access Layer generally has more switches. The main function of switches is to connect hosts such as end user workstations, servers, IP phones, web cameras, access points and routers. This means that there are many more switches in an organization than routers.</p> <p>Switches come in many form factors: </p> <p><ul><li> Small standalone models sit on a desk or mount on a wall.</li><li> Integrated routers include a switch built into the chassis that is rack mounted. </li><li> High-end switches mount into a rack and are often a chassis and blade design to allow more blades to be added as the number of users increases.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1747226927">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030400/en1102030402/cm1747226927.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030400/en1102030402/cm1747226927text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>High-end enterprise and service provider switches support ports of varying speeds, from 100 MB to 10 GB. </p> <p>An enterprise switch in an MDF connects other switches from IDFs using Gigabit fiber or copper cable. An IDF switch typically needs both RJ-45 Fast Ethernet ports for device connectivity and at least one Gigabit Ethernet port (copper or fiber) to uplink to the MDF switch. Some high-end switches have modular ports that can be changed if needed. For example, it might be necessary to switch from multimode fiber to single mode fiber, which would require a different port. </p> <p>Like routers, switch ports are also designated using the controller/port or controller/slot/port conventions. For example, using the controller/port convention, the first Fast Ethernet port on a switch is numbered as Fa0/1 (controller 0 and port 1). The second is Fa0/2. The first port on a switch that uses controller/slot/port is Fa0/0/1. Gigabit ports are designated as Gi0/1, Gi0/2 etc. </p> <p><content-link target="{F5481900-02CF-4D2E-AAD5-7EA1B7F1D303}" type="glossary">Port density</content-link> on a switch is an important factor. In an enterprise environment where hundreds or thousands of users need switch connections, a switch with a 1RU height and 48-ports has a higher port density than a 1RU 24-port switch. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1102030500">
<title><content-text>Basic Switch CLI Commands</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2065376753">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030501/cm2065376753.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030501/cm2065376753text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Switches make use of common IOS commands for configuration, to check for connectivity and to display current switch status. These commands can be divided into several categories, as follows: </p> <p><b>General Use:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show version</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Interface / Port Related:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show interfaces</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show ip interface brief</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show port-security</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show mac-address-table</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Connectivity Related:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>show cdp neighbors</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show sessions</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>show ssh</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd">t<b>raceroute</b></span></li></ul></p> <p>The same in-band and out-of-band management techniques that apply to routers also applies to switch configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102030502">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm5006580221">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030502/cm5006580221.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030502/cm5006580221text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full screen activity</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030503">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9718688624">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030503/cm9718688624.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030503/cm9718688624text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A basic switch configuration includes the hostname for identification, passwords for security, and assignment of IP addresses for connectivity. In-band access requires the switch to have an IP address.</p> <p>Verify and save the switch configuration using the <span class="cmd"><b>copy running-config startup-config</b></span> command. To clear the switch configuration, use the <span class="cmd"><b>erase startup-config</b></span> command and then the <span class="cmd"><b>reload</b></span> command. It may also be necessary to erase any VLAN information using the command <span class="cmd"><b>delete flash:vlan.dat</b></span>. </p> <p><b>Configuration Management:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>enable</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>configure terminal</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>copy running-config startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>erase startup-config</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>delete flash:vlan.dat</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>reload</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Global Settings: </b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>hostname</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>banner motd</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>enable password</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>enable secret</b> </span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>ip default-gateway</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Line Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>line con</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>line vty </b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>login and password</b></span></li></ul></p> <p><b>Interface Settings:</b></p> <p><ul><li><span class="cmd"><b>interface type/number (vlan1)</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>ip address</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"><b>speed / duplex</b></span></li><li><span class="cmd"> <b>switchport port-security</b></span></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030504">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm3962401739">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030504/cm3962401739/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030504/cm3962401739/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Configure a switch in a switching environment.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102030505">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1798872402">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030505/cm1798872402/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1102000000/en1102030000/en1102030500/en1102030505/cm1798872402/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Connect and configure a multi-router network. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1102040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1102040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm2498053257">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102040000/en1102040100/en1102040101/cm2498053257.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1102000000/en1102040000/en1102040100/en1102040101/cm2498053257text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1102050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1102050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1102050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm2288710726">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1102000000/en1102050000/en1102050100/en1102050101/cm2288710726/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1102000000/en1102050000/en1102050100/en1102050101/cm2288710726/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge. </p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
