<chapter type="" id="en1101000000">
<title><content-text>Networking in the Enterprise</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1101000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm3598923728">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101000000/en1101000100/en1101000101/cm3598923728.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101000000/en1101000100/en1101000101/cm3598923728text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1101010000">
<title><content-text>Describing the Enterprise Network</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101010100">
<title><content-text>Supporting the Business Enterprise</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4420816535">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010100/en1101010101/cm4420816535.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010100/en1101010101/cm4420816535text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As businesses grow and evolve, so do their networking requirements. A large business environment with many users and locations, or with many systems, is referred to as an <content-link target="{48A8CB3B-90EB-48F2-9B9F-CEAD6E019AE0}" type="glossary">enterprise</content-link>. Common examples of enterprise environments include:</p> <p><ul><li> Manufacturers</li><li> Large retail stores</li><li> Restaurant and service franchises</li><li> Utilities and government agencies </li><li> Hospitals</li><li> School systems </li></ul></p> <p>The network that is used to support the <content-link target="{79EF110E-E114-4E35-9A33-39D119259537}" type="glossary">business enterprise</content-link> is called an <content-link target="{52359368-1354-4E1B-B1DE-5EF6F559B961}" type="glossary">enterprise network</content-link>. Enterprise networks have many common characteristics, some of which are:</p> <p><ul><li> Support for critical applications </li><li> Support for <content-link target="{201F867E-4EFB-43DF-82EF-17E2C53D856A}" type="glossary">converged network</content-link> traffic</li><li> Need for centralized control</li><li> Support for diverse business requirements</li></ul></p> <p>An enterprise network must support the exchange of various types of network traffic, including data files, email, <content-link target="{BEB8DA37-A642-4B2B-B69D-2415334F801A}" type="glossary">IP telephony</content-link>, and video applications for multiple business units.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9671667117">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010100/en1101010102/cm9671667117.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010100/en1101010102/cm9671667117text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Businesses increasingly rely on their network infrastructure to provide <content-link target="{29C14AFC-5DA0-484E-AF7C-AF2AC00A5C8A}" type="glossary">mission-critical </content-link>services. Outages in the enterprise network prevent the business from performing its normal activities, which can cause lost revenue and lost customers. Users expect enterprise networks to be up 99.999% of the time.</p> <p>To obtain this level of reliability , high-end equipment is commonly installed in the enterprise network. Enterprise class equipment is designed for reliability, with features such as redundant power supplies and <content-link target="{379AE309-06C6-4942-8764-B9C6D0EF823F}" type="glossary">failover</content-link> capabilities. Designed and manufactured to more stringent standards than lower end devices, enterprise equipment moves large volumes of network traffic.</p> <p>Purchasing and installing enterprise class equipment does not eliminate the need for proper network design. One objective of good network design is to prevent any single point of failure. This is accomplished by building redundancy into the network. </p> <p>Other key factors in network design include optimizing bandwidth utilization, ensuring security and network performance.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101010200">
<title><content-text>Traffic Flow in the Enterprise Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4640961999">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010201/cm4640961999.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010201/cm4640961999text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To optimize bandwidth on an enterprise network, the network must be organized so that traffic stays localized and is not propagated onto unnecessary portions of the network. Using the three-layer <content-link target="{D097A13F-689A-4924-85F4-9C25243B7F86}" type="glossary">hierarchical design model</content-link> helps organize the network. This model divides the network functionality into three distinct layers: <content-link target="{815A98E5-F76B-429C-9824-79B7F0437E0D}" type="glossary">Access Layer</content-link>, <content-link target="{52F050C6-D879-4B3E-B191-5C5DE81DD44A}" type="glossary">Distribution Layer</content-link>, and <content-link target="{E3C66B97-AE29-494F-85EF-9F2D0BBB3223}" type="glossary">Core Layer</content-link>. Each layer is designed to meet specific functions. </p> <p>The access layer provides connectivity for the users. The distribution layer is used to forward traffic from one local network to another. Finally, the core layer represents a high-speed backbone layer between dispersed end networks. User traffic is initiated at the access layer and passes through the other layers if the functionality of those layers is required.</p> <p>Even though the hierarchical model has three layers, some enterprise networks use the Core Layer services offered by an ISP to reduce costs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8525740962">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010202/cm8525740962.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010202/cm8525740962text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Enterprise Architectures divides the network into functional components while still maintaining the concept of Core, Distribution, and Access layers. The functional components are:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Enterprise Campus:</b> Consists of the campus infrastructure with server farms and network management</li><li> <b>Enterprise Edge:</b> Consists of the Internet, VPN, and WAN modules connecting the enterprise with the service provider's network</li><li> <b>Service Provider Edge:</b> Provides Internet, Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN), and WAN services</li></ul></p> <p>All data that enters or exits the Enterprise Composite Network Model (<content-link target="{0647B036-ED21-47F8-BA71-E549E7952FE2}" type="glossary">ECNM</content-link>) passes through an <content-link target="{9026D794-C4ED-49F0-BD68-2803705044A4}" type="glossary">edge device</content-link>. This is the point that all packets can be examined and a decision made if the packet should be allowed on the enterprise network. Intrusion detection systems (<content-link target="{48C10A36-67C3-4377-B190-6DEE95A8137E}" type="glossary">IDS</content-link>) and intrusion prevention systems (<content-link target="{A467BD33-D360-4AE4-BDBF-EF787B81BD5D}" type="glossary">IPS</content-link>) can also be configured at the enterprise edge to prevent against malicious activity.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010203">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm4210448457">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010203/cm4210448457.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010203/cm4210448457text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A well-designed network not only controls traffic but also limits the size of failure domains. A <content-link target="{9CE68322-BEDA-4835-99AD-DAA012B8A114}" type="glossary">failure domain</content-link> is the area of a network impacted when a key device or service experiences problems. </p> <p>The function of the device that initially fails determines the impact of a failure domain. For example, a malfunctioning switch on a network segment normally impacts only hosts on that segment. However, if the router that connects this segment to others fails, the impact is much greater. </p> <p>The use of redundant links and reliable enterprise-class equipment minimize the chance of disruption in a network. Smaller failure domains reduce the impact of a failure on company productivity. They also simplify the troubleshooting process, thereby shortening the <content-link target="{3F3DEDAD-F094-48AD-A10C-BAAB7BB62719}" type="glossary">downtime</content-link> for all users.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010204">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2973013664">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010204/cm2973013664/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010200/en1101010204/cm2973013664/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Observe the flow of traffic through an enterprise network.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101010300">
<title><content-text>Enterprise LANs and WAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7577756021">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010301/cm7577756021.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010301/cm7577756021text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Enterprise networks incorporate both traditional LAN and WAN technologies. In a typical enterprise network, multiple local networks at a single campus interconnect at either the Distribution Layer or the Core Layer to form a LAN. These local LANs interconnect with other sites which are more geographically dispersed to form a WAN.</p> <p>LANs are private and under the control of a single person or organization. The organization installs, manages, and maintains the wiring and devices that are the functional building blocks of the LAN.</p> <p>Some WANs are privately owned; however, because the development and maintenance of a private WAN is expensive, only very large organizations can afford to maintain a private WAN. Most companies purchase WAN connections from a service provider or ISP. The ISP is then responsible for maintaining the <content-link target="{1D6052FB-80F2-4396-8A24-CC2101ADD14E}" type="glossary">back end</content-link> network connections and network services between the LANs.</p> <p>When an organization has many global sites, establishing WAN connections and service can be complex. For example, the major ISP for the organization may not offer service in every location or country in which the organization has an office. As a result, the organization must purchase services from multiple ISPs. Using multiple ISPs often leads to differences in the quality of services provided. In many emerging countries, for example, network designers will find differences in equipment availability, WAN services offered, and encryption technology for security. To support an enterprise network, it is important to have uniform standards for equipment, configuration, and services. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6470958614">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010302/cm6470958614.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010302/cm6470958614text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Features of a LAN:</p> <p><ul><li> The organization has the responsibility of installing and managing the infrastructure. </li><li> Ethernet is the most common technology used. </li><li> The focus of the network is in the Access and Distribution Layers.</li><li> The LAN connects users, provides support for localized applications and server farms. </li><li> Connected devices are usually in the same local area, such as a building or a campus.</li></ul></p>  <p>Features of a WAN:</p> <p><ul><li> Connected sites are usually geographically dispersed.</li><li> Connectivity to the WAN requires a device such as a modem or CSU/DSU to put the data in a form acceptable to the network of the service provider.</li><li> Services are provided by an ISP. WAN services include T1/T3, E1/E3, DSL, Cable, Frame Relay, and ATM. </li><li> The ISP has the responsibility of installing and managing the infrastructure.</li><li> The edge devices modify the Ethernet encapsulation to a serial WAN encapsulation.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101010303">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm6407205757">	<title><content-text>Drag each term into the correct LAN or WAN area.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010303/cm6407205757.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010300/en1101010303/cm6407205757text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full screen activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101010400">
<title><content-text>Intranets and Extranets</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5414429175">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010400/en1101010401/cm5414429175.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010400/en1101010401/cm5414429175text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Enterprise networks contain both WAN and LAN technologies. These networks provide many of the services associated with the Internet, including:</p> <p><ul><li> Email</li><li> Web </li><li> FTP </li><li> Telnet/SSH </li><li> Discussion forums</li></ul></p> <p>Many companies use this private network or <content-link target="{A7EDF9DE-D2B4-435E-9CDD-AF537BE624D3}" type="glossary">intranet</content-link> to provide access for local and remote employees using LAN and WAN technologies.</p> <p>Intranets may have links to the Internet. If connected to the Internet, firewalls control the traffic that enters and exits the intranet.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101010402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9383849097">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010400/en1101010402/cm9383849097.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101010000/en1101010400/en1101010402/cm9383849097text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Intranets contain confidential information and are designed for company employees only. The intranet should be protected by a firewall. Remote employees who are not connected to the enterprise LAN must authenticate before gaining access.</p> <p>In some situations, businesses extend privileged access to their network to key suppliers and customers. Common methods for doing this are: </p> <p><ul><li> Direct WAN connectivity</li><li> Remote logins to key application systems</li><li> VPN access into a protected network</li></ul></p> <p>An intranet that allows external connections to suppliers and contractors is an <content-link target="{D7E0367B-247E-4464-8161-101729063EA9}" type="glossary">extranet</content-link>. An extranet is a private network (intranet) that allows controlled access to individuals and companies outside the organization. An extranet is not a public network.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1101020000">
<title><content-text>Identifying Enterprise Applications</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101020100">
<title><content-text>Traffic Flow Patterns</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020101">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm3526580432">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020100/en1101020101/cm3526580432.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020100/en1101020101/cm3526580432text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A properly designed enterprise network has defined and predictable traffic flow patterns. In some circumstances traffic stays on the LAN portion of the enterprise network and at other times it traverses the WAN links.</p> <p>When determining how to design the network it is important to consider the amount of traffic destined for a specific location and where that traffic most often originates. For example, traffic that should typically remain local to users on the network includes: </p> <p><ul><li> File sharing</li><li> Printing</li><li> Internal backup and mirroring</li><li> Intra-campus voice</li></ul></p> <p>Traffic types which are typically seen on the local network but are also commonly sent across the WAN include:</p> <p><ul><li> System updates</li><li> Company email</li><li> Transaction processing</li></ul></p> <p>In addition to WAN traffic, external traffic is traffic that originates from or is destined to the Internet. VPN and Internet traffic is considered external traffic flow. </p> <p>Controlling the flow of traffic on a network optimizes bandwidth and introduces a level of security through monitoring. By understanding traffic patterns and flows, the network administrator can predict the types and amount of traffic to expect. When traffic is detected in an area of the network where it is unexpected, that traffic can be filtered and the source of the traffic investigated.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101020102">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6339543202">	<title><content-text>Drag the traffic type to the appropriate flow pattern. If traffic has more than one flow pattern, select the one with the largest coverage.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020100/en1101020102/cm6339543202.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020100/en1101020102/cm6339543202text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full screen</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101020200">
<title><content-text>Applications and Traffic on an Enterprise Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1067911095">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020201/cm1067911095.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020201/cm1067911095text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At one time, voice, video, and data each traveled on separate networks. Now technology supports a converged network, where voice, video, and data flow across the same medium. </p> <p>This convergence presents many design and bandwidth management challenges. Enterprise networks must support the business enterprise by allowing traffic from a variety of applications, including:</p> <p><ul><li> Database transaction processing</li><li> Mainframe or data center access</li><li> File and print sharing</li><li> Authentication</li><li> Web services</li><li> Email and other communications</li><li> VPN services</li><li> Voice calls and voicemail</li><li> Video and video conferencing</li></ul></p> <p>Network management and the control processes required for the underlying operation of the network also need support.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4378983747">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020202/cm4378983747.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020202/cm4378983747text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When trying to determine how to manage network traffic, it is important to understand the type of traffic that is crossing the network as well as the current traffic flow. If the types of traffic are unknown, a <content-link target="{4E4AFC2F-B0D0-445F-B68E-920E44EEF66C}" type="glossary">packet sniffer</content-link> can be used to capture traffic for analysis.</p> <p>To determine traffic flow patterns, it is important to:</p> <p><ul><li> Capture traffic during peak utilization times to get a good representation of the different traffic types.</li><li> Perform the capture on different network segments, because some traffic will be local to a particular segment.</li></ul></p> <p>Using the information obtained from the packet sniffer, network technicians can determine traffic flows. Technicians analyze this information based on the source and destination of the traffic as well as the type of traffic being sent. This analysis can be used to make decisions on how to manage the traffic more efficiently. This can be done by reducing unnecessary traffic flows or changing flow patterns altogether by moving a server.</p> <p>Sometimes, simply relocating a server or service to another network segment improves network performance. At other times, optimizing the network performance requires major redesign and intervention.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3174013293">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020203/cm3174013293/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020200/en1101020203/cm3174013293/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use a packet capture program to analyze network traffic.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101020300">
<title><content-text>Network Traffic Prioritization</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8200537971">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020301/cm8200537971.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020301/cm8200537971text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Not all types of network traffic have the same requirements or behave in the same manner. </p> <p><b>Data Traffic</b></p> <p>Most network applications utilize data traffic. Some types of online applications transmit data that is sporadic. Other types, such as data storage applications, transmit high volumes of traffic for a sustained period of time. </p> <p>Some data applications are more concerned about time-sensitivity than reliability, and most data applications can tolerate delays. For this reason, data traffic usually employs Transmission Control Protocol (TCP). TCP uses acknowledgments to determine when lost packets must be retransmitted and therefore guarantees delivery. While the use of acknowledgements makes TCP a more reliable delivery protocol, it also incurs a delay. </p> <p><b>Voice and Video Traffic</b></p> <p>Voice traffic and video traffic are different from data traffic. Voice and video applications require an uninterrupted stream of data to ensure high quality conversations and images. The acknowledgement process in TCP introduces delays, which break these streams and degrade the quality of the application. Therefore, voice and video applications employ User Datagram Protocol (<content-link target="{AB1D5C78-B5CE-48E9-A747-58E830382215}" type="glossary">UDP</content-link>) instead of TCP. Since UDP does not have mechanisms for retransmitting lost packets, it minimizes delays.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101020302">
﻿<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1503210555">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020302/cm1503210555.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020302/cm1503210555text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to understanding the delays of TCP versus UDP, it is also necessary to understand the delay, or <content-link target="{3D1BB055-A954-453C-8706-CB9F968E5ADB}" type="glossary">latency</content-link>, caused by the networking devices that must process the traffic on its path to the destination. OSI Layer 3 devices create more delay than Layer 2 devices due to the number of headers they have to process. Therefore, routers introduce a longer delay than switches.</p>  <p><content-link target="{7CFCC7F7-4A10-4AAF-A8C1-6DAE6B99C2BB}" type="glossary">Jitter</content-link>, caused by network congestion, is the variation in time of the packets arriving at their destination. </p> <p>It is important to reduce the impact of delay, latency, and jitter on time-sensitive traffic.</p> <p>Quality of Service (<content-link target="{C80E9D95-981B-46E2-B274-F1459EBDAF10}" type="glossary">QoS</content-link>) is a process used to guarantee a specified data flow. QoS mechanisms sort traffic into queues, based on priority. For example, voice traffic has priority over ordinary data.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101020303">
﻿<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4873584199">	<title><content-text>Drag the term displayed to the correct definition.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020303/cm4873584199.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101020000/en1101020300/en1101020303/cm4873584199text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full screen activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1101030000">
<title><content-text>Supporting Remote Workers</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101030100">
<title><content-text>Teleworking</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4666358293">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030101/cm4666358293.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030101/cm4666358293text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The development of enterprise networks and remote connection technology has changed the way we work. </p> <p><content-link target="{98D8087F-9E67-4356-83C0-3FDD0AFE99C5}" type="glossary">Teleworking</content-link>, also referred to as <content-link target="{2F8495D2-71DE-44BC-8F5C-FBE3749604A4}" type="glossary">telecommuting</content-link> and e-commuting, allows employees to use telecommunications technology to work from their homes or other remote locations. The remote worker using the technology is called a <content-link target="{965D1E8E-DCE0-46C5-B06B-1DC2E6EFAB1C}" type="glossary">teleworker</content-link> or telecommuter. </p> <p>An increasing number of companies encourage their employees to consider teleworking. Teleworking provides many advantages and opportunities for both employer and employee. From the employer perspective, when employees work from home, the company does not have to provide them with dedicated physical office space. A single office space can be set up for shared use by employees who need to spend time in the physical office. This arrangement reduces real estate costs and the associated support services. </p> <p>Some companies have even reduced the expense of air travel and hotel accommodations to bring their employees together by using <content-link target="{C8896F6F-844D-4FB5-8D66-1733E12F587F}" type="glossary">teleconferencing</content-link> and collaboration tools. People from all over the world can work together as if they were in the same physical location.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1911014670">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030102/cm1911014670.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030102/cm1911014670text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Both the employer and the employee benefit from teleworking. </p> <p>Employees save time and money, and reduce stress, by eliminating the daily travel to and from the office. Employees can dress casually at home, therefore saving money on business attire. Working from home allows employees to spend more time with their families.</p> <p>Reduced travel for employees also has a very favorable effect on the environment. Less airplane and automobile traffic means less pollution.</p> <p>Teleworkers need to be self-directed and disciplined. Some teleworkers miss the social environment of an office setting and find it difficult to work in physical isolation. </p> <p>Not all jobs can take advantage of teleworking. Some positions require a physical presence in the office during a set period of time. However, more enterprises are taking advantage of technology to increase the frequency of telecommuting. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030103">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4407584368">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030103/cm4407584368.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030103/cm4407584368text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Telecommuters need various tools to work efficiently. Some available teleworker tools include:</p> <p><ul><li> Email</li><li> Chat </li><li> Desktop and application sharing </li><li> FTP</li><li> Telnet</li><li> VoIP</li><li> Video conferencing </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5272054064">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030104/cm5272054064.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030104/cm5272054064text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Application and screen sharing tools have improved, and it is now possible to integrate both voice and video into these applications.</p> <p>New technology has enabled more sophisticated levels of online collaboration. Using the enterprise network, this technology creates an environment in which individuals from remote locations meet as though they were in the same room. By combining large video displays and high quality audio in specially-designed rooms, it appears as if all participants, regardless of their physical location, are sitting across the boardroom table from each other. </p> <p>In the graphic, only the five people in the foreground are physically in the room. The other four people displayed on the screens are located in three other locations.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101030105">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm7319999657">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030105/cm7319999657.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030100/en1101030105/cm7319999657text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1101030200">
<title><content-text>Virtual Private Networks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9412925358">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030200/en1101030201/cm9412925358.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030200/en1101030201/cm9412925358text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One obstacle that teleworkers must overcome is the fact that most of the tools available for working remotely are not secure. Using nonsecure tools allows data to be intercepted or altered during transmission.</p> <p>One solution is to always use the secure forms of applications, if they exist. For example, instead of using Telnet, use SSH. Unfortunately, secure forms of all applications may not be available. A much easier choice is to encrypt all traffic moving between the remote site and the enterprise network using Virtual Private Networks (<content-link target="{304B9119-D073-4F9F-8DF2-456DACFA55D4}" type="glossary">VPN</content-link>s).</p> <p>VPNs are often described as tunnels. Consider the analogy of an underground tunnel versus an open road way between two points. Anything that uses the underground tunnel to travel between the two points is surrounded and protected from view. The underground tunnel represents the VPN encapsulation and virtual tunnel.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101030202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7197903943">	<title><content-text>Click Play to view a VPN encapsulation protocol.</content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030200/en1101030202/cm7197903943.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101030000/en1101030200/en1101030202/cm7197903943text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When using a VPN, a virtual tunnel is created by linking the source and destination addresses. All data flow between the source and destination is encrypted and encapsulated using a secure protocol. This secure packet is transmitted across the network. When it arrives at the receiving end, it is de-encapsulated and unencrypted. </p> <p>VPNs are a client/server application; therefore, telecommuters must install the VPN client on their computers in order to form a secure connection with the enterprise network.</p> <p>When telecommuters are connected to the enterprise network through a VPN, they become part of that network and have access to all services and resources that they would have if they were physically attached to the LAN.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1101040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1101040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm5726590190">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101040000/en1101040100/en1101040101/cm5726590190.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1101000000/en1101040000/en1101040100/en1101040101/cm5726590190text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1101050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1101050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1101050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm1540069334">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1101000000/en1101050000/en1101050100/en1101050101/cm1540069334/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1101000000/en1101050000/en1101050100/en1101050101/cm1540069334/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
