<chapter type="" id="en1105000000">
<title><content-text>Routing with a Distance Vector Protocol</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1105000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm5951619559">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105000000/en1105000100/en1105000101/cm5951619559.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105000000/en1105000100/en1105000101/cm5951619559text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1105010000">
<title><content-text>Managing Enterprise Networks</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105010100">
<title><content-text>Enterprise Networks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6958045061">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010100/en1105010101/cm6958045061.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010100/en1105010101/cm6958045061text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Hierarchical enterprise networks facilitate the flow of information. Information flows between mobile workers and branch offices. These branch offices connect to corporate offices in cities and countries around the world. The organization must create a hierarchy to meet the different network requirements of each part of the company.</p> <p>Crucial information and services typically reside near the top of the hierarchy, in secured server farms or on storage area networks. The structure expands into many different departments that are spread across the lower part of the hierarchy. </p> <p>Communication between different levels of the hierarchy requires a combination of LAN and WAN technologies. As the company grows or adds e-commerce operations, a DMZ may be required to house the various servers.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4039653224">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010100/en1105010102/cm4039653224.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010100/en1105010102/cm4039653224text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Traffic control is essential in an enterprise network. Without it, these networks could not function. </p> <p>Routers forward traffic and prevent broadcasts from clogging the main channels to crucial services. They control the flow of traffic between LANs, allowing only the required traffic to pass through the network. </p> <p>Enterprise networks provide a high level of reliability and services. To ensure this, network professionals:</p> <p><ul><li> Design networks to provide redundant links to use in case a primary data path fails. </li><li> Deploy Quality of Service (QoS) to ensure critical data receives priority treatment.</li><li> Use packet filtering to deny certain types of packets, maximize available bandwidth, and protect the network from attacks.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105010200">
<title><content-text>Enterprise Topologies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6616703998">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010201/cm6616703998.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010201/cm6616703998text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Choosing the right physical topology allows a company to expand its networked services without losing reliability and efficiency. Network designers base their topology decisions upon the enterprise requirements for performance and reliability. The <content-link target="{D12D7612-C744-4CA1-9DBD-DCDA73CC345B}" type="glossary">star</content-link> and <content-link target="{BC31987E-2E8C-4A37-BAA9-E7A3F22446D2}" type="glossary">mesh</content-link> topologies are normally deployed in enterprise environments. </p> <p><b>Star Topology</b></p> <p>One popular physical topology is the star. The center of the star corresponds to the top of the hierarchy, which could be the corporate headquarters or head office. Branch offices at multiple locations connect to the center, or hub, of the star.</p> <p>A star topology provides centralized control of the network. All crucial services and technical staff can be located in one place. Star topologies are scalable. Adding a new branch office simply requires one more connection to the central point of the star. If an office adds several branches to its territory, each branch office can connect to a center hub in its own area, which then connects back to the main central point at the central office. In this way, a simple star can grow into an <content-link target="{FC84287D-6AD0-49C5-824F-86F9C8DEF920}" type="glossary">extended star</content-link>, with smaller stars radiating out from the main branch offices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2736060521">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010202/cm2736060521.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010202/cm2736060521text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The star and extended star topologies create a single point of failure. Mesh topologies eliminate this problem. </p> <p><b>Mesh Topologies</b></p> <p>Each additional link provides an alternate pathway for data and adds reliability to the network. With the addition of links, the topology becomes a mesh of interconnected nodes. Each additional link adds cost and overhead. It also adds to the complexity of managing the network.</p> <p><b>Partial Mesh</b></p> <p>Adding redundant links only to a specific area of an enterprise creates a <content-link target="{6D656554-1FB1-4C00-ADB3-39592A87636C}" type="glossary">partial mesh</content-link>. This topology meets uptime and reliability requirements for critical areas like server farms and SANs, while minimizing additional expenses. The other areas of the network are still vulnerable to failures. Therefore, it is essential to place the mesh where it provides the most benefit.</p> <p><b>Full Mesh</b></p> <p>When no downtime is acceptable, the network requires a <content-link target="{1C6EC88C-C8E3-45EE-9FD1-6D8129D28B89}" type="glossary">full mesh</content-link>. Each node in a full mesh topology connects to every other node in the enterprise. This is the most failure-proof topology, but it is also the most expensive to implement.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010203">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8043345138">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010203/cm8043345138.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010203/cm8043345138text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Internet is an excellent example of a meshed network. Devices on the Internet are not under the control of any one individual or organization. As a result, the topology of the Internet is constantly changing, with some links going down and others coming online. Redundant connections balance the traffic and ensure that there is a reliable path to the destination.</p>  <p>Enterprise networks face some of the same issues as the Internet. Therefore, processes are put in place that allow devices to adapt to these constantly changing conditions and reroute traffic as appropriate.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010204">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3021894960">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010204/cm3021894960/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010200/en1105010204/cm3021894960/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Interconnect network nodes with redundant links to provide reliability at minimal cost.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105010300">
<title><content-text>Static and Dynamic Routing</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6730807990">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010301/cm6730807990.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010301/cm6730807990text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The physical topology of an enterprise network provides the structure for forwarding data. Routing provides the mechanism that makes it work. Finding the best path to the destination becomes very difficult in an enterprise network, because a router can have many sources of information from which to build its <content-link target="{60627C13-D5ED-4D8D-A27D-27392E63E6FF}" type="glossary">routing table</content-link>. </p> <p>A routing table is a data file that exists in RAM and stores information about directly connected and remote networks. The routing table associates each network with either an <content-link target="{963BAF5F-534B-4059-9D57-A7127A45929B}" type="glossary">exit interface</content-link> or a <content-link target="{F736D147-213B-421E-9559-FE23B03D09C3}" type="glossary">next hop</content-link>. </p> <p>The exit interface is the physical path that the router uses to move the data closer to the destination. The next hop is an interface on a connected router that moves the data closer to the final destination. </p> <p>The table also attaches a number to each route that represents the trustworthiness or accuracy of the source of the routing information. This value is the <content-link target="{A92F5DAB-1C7C-4E2A-8FAA-05DA39C95F7E}" type="glossary">administrative distance</content-link>. Routers maintain information about directly connected, static, and dynamic routes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010302">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8331385894">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010302/cm8331385894.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010302/cm8331385894text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Directly Connected Routes</b></p> <p>A directly connected network attaches to a router interface. Configuring the interface with an IP address and subnet mask allows the interface to become a host on the attached network. The network address and subnet mask of the interface, along with the interface type and number, appear in the routing table as a directly connected network. The routing table designates directly connected networks with a <b>C</b>.</p> <p><b>Static Routes</b></p> <p>Static routes are routes that a network administrator manually configures. A static route includes the network address and subnet mask of the destination network, along with the exit interface or the IP address of the next hop router. The routing table designates static routes with an S. Static routes are more stable and reliable than routes learned dynamically which results in a lower administrative distance compared to the dynamic routes.</p> <p><b>Dynamic Routes</b></p> <p>Dynamic routing protocols also add remote networks to the routing table. Dynamic routing protocols enable routers to share information about the reachability and status of remote networks through <content-link target="{01BF71C0-D710-4400-BFA9-B144B3A80E3D}" type="glossary">network discovery</content-link>. Each protocol sends and receives data packets while locating other routers and updating and maintaining routing tables. Routes learned through a dynamic routing protocol are identified by the protocol used. For example, <b>R</b> for RIP and <b>D</b> for EIGRP. They are assigned the administrative distance of the protocol.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010303">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm7518028521">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010303/cm7518028521/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010303/cm7518028521/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity </b></p> <p> </p> <p>Investigate a fully-converged network with connected, static, and dynamic routing.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010304">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4139409920">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010304/cm4139409920.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010304/cm4139409920text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Typically, both static and dynamic routes are employed in an enterprise network. Static routing addresses specific network needs. Depending on the physical topology, a static route can be used to control the traffic flow. </p> <p>Limiting traffic to a single point of entrance/exit creates a <content-link target="{1170F7CC-91B9-4A08-98BC-43569BC7C8E4}" type="glossary">stub network</content-link>. In some enterprise networks, small branch offices have only one possible path to reach the rest of the network. In this situation, It is not necessary to burden the stub router with routing updates and increased overhead by running a dynamic routing protocol, therefore static routing is beneficial</p> <p>Based on their placement and function, specific enterprise routers may also require static routes. Border routers use static routes to provide secure, stable paths to the ISP. Other routers within the enterprise use either static routing or dynamic routing protocols as necessary to meet their needs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010305">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2358463471">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010305/cm2358463471.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010300/en1105010305/cm2358463471text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Routers in an enterprise network use bandwidth, memory, and processing resources to provide NAT/PAT, packet filtering, and other services. Static routing provides forwarding services without the overhead associated with most dynamic routing protocols. </p> <p>Static routing provides more security than dynamic routing, because no routing updates are required. A hacker could intercept a dynamic routing update to gain information about a network. </p>  <p>However, static routing is not without problems. It requires time and accuracy from the network administrator, who must manually enter routing information. A simple typographical error in a static route can result in network downtime and packet loss. When a static route changes, the network may experience routing errors and problems during manual reconfiguration. For these reasons, static routing is impractical for general use in a large enterprise environment.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105010400">
<title><content-text>Configuring Static Routes</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4110288434">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010401/cm4110288434.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010401/cm4110288434text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The global command for configuring most static routes is <span class="cmd"><b>ip route</b></span>, followed by the destination network, the subnet mask, and the path used to reach it. The command is:</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)#<b>ip route </b>[<i>network-address</i>] [<i>subnet mask</i>] [<i>address of next hop</i> OR <i>exit interface</i>]</span></p> <p>Using the next-hop address or the exit interface forwards traffic to the proper destination. However, these two parameters behave very differently. </p> <p>Before a router forwards any packet, the routing table process determines which exit interface to use. Static routes configured with exit interfaces require a single routing table lookup. Static routes configured with the next-hop parameter must reference the routing table twice to determine the exit interface. </p> <p>In an enterprise network, static routes configured with exit interfaces are ideal for point-to-point connections like those between a border router and the ISP. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010402">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm3287580917">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010402/cm3287580917.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010402/cm3287580917text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Static routes configured with a next hop interface require two steps to determine the exit interface. This is called a <content-link target="{5AC35118-CED5-4C7A-85E3-3C888F65D602}" type="glossary">recursive lookup</content-link>. In a recursive loopkup:</p> <p><ul><li> The router matches the destination IP address of a packet to the static route. </li><li> It matches the next hop IP address of the static route to entries in its routing table to determine which interface to use.</li></ul></p> <p>If an exit interface is disabled, static routes disappear from the routing table. The routing table reinstalls the routes when the interface is re-enabled. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7733505461">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010403/cm7733505461.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010403/cm7733505461text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Summarizing several static routes as a single entry reduces the size of the routing table and makes the lookup process more efficient. This process is called <content-link target="{4A657CE9-C663-4147-858D-1AE05546D1F0}" type="glossary">route summarization</content-link>.</p> <p>A single static route summarizes multiple static routes if:</p> <p><ul><li> The destination networks summarize into a single network address.</li><li> All of the static routes use the same exit interface or next-hop IP address.</li></ul></p> <p>Without summary routes, routing tables within Internet <content-link target="{F0A32870-C10C-466B-A1BB-10DBF1A05A81}" type="glossary">core router</content-link>s become unmanageable. Enterprise networks encounter the same problem. Summary static routes are an indispensable solution for managing routing table size.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010404">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm8637592058">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010404/cm8637592058/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010404/cm8637592058/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Create static routes.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010405">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6362956957">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010405/cm6362956957.swf" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010400/en1105010405/cm6362956957text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Depending on the WAN services used in the enterprise, static routes provide a backup service when the primary WAN link fails. A feature called floating static routes can be used to provide this backup service. </p> <p>By default, a static route has a lower administrative distance than the route learned from a dynamic routing protocol. A <content-link target="{487A07AB-8B78-400A-9FD1-084FF252C526}" type="glossary">floating static route</content-link> has a higher administrative distance than the route learned from a dynamic routing protocol. For that reason, a floating static route does not display in the routing table. The floating static route entry appears in the routing table only if the dynamic information is lost. </p> <p>To create a floating static route, add an administrative distance value to the end of the <span class="cmd"><b>ip route</b></span> command:</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)<b>#ip route 192.168.4.0 255.255.255.0 192.168.9.1 200</b></span></p> <p>The administrative distance specified must be greater than the AD assigned to the dynamic routing protocol. The router uses the primary route as long as it is active. If the primary route is down, the table installs the floating static route.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105010500">
<title><content-text>Default Routes</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1170878721">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010500/en1105010501/cm1170878721.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010500/en1105010501/cm1170878721text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Routing tables cannot contain routes to every possible Internet site. As routing tables grow in size, they require more RAM and processing power. A special type of static route, called a <content-link target="{604D1507-A0A7-4587-8338-7E55701C42B1}" type="glossary">default route</content-link>, specifies a gateway to use when the routing table does not contain a path to a destination. It is common for default routes to point to the next router in the path toward the ISP. In a complex enterprise, default routes funnel Internet traffic out of the network.</p>  <p>The command to create a default route is similar to the command used to create either an ordinary or a floating static route. The network address and subnet mask are both specified as 0.0.0.0, making it a <content-link target="{95811E04-BAA9-4E76-A1C4-0675DF5DDA6E}" type="glossary">quad zero route</content-link>. The command uses either the next-hop address or the exit interface parameters. </p> <p>The zeroes indicate to the router that no bits need to match in order to use this route. As long as a better match does not exist, the router uses the default static route.</p> <p>The final default route, located on the border router, sends the traffic to the ISP. This route identifies the last stop within the enterprise as the <content-link target="{5E8F0E31-D031-4A71-A788-8FD129C706BB}" type="glossary">Gateway of Last Resort</content-link> for packets that cannot be matched. This information appears in the routing tables of all routers.</p> <p>If the enterprise uses a dynamic routing protocol, the border router can send a default route to the other routers as part of a dynamic routing update.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105010502">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2397779188">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010500/en1105010502/cm2397779188/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105010000/en1105010500/en1105010502/cm2397779188/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Configure a default route to forward traffic from the enterprise routers to the ISP. </p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1105020000">
<title><content-text>Routing Using the RIP Protocol</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105020100">
<title><content-text>Distance Vector Routing Protocols</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5612362930">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020100/en1105020101/cm5612362930.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020100/en1105020101/cm5612362930text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Dynamic routing protocols are classified into two major categories: <content-link target="{DFED579B-3777-4AD7-9E74-5E146ED686C9}" type="glossary">distance vector protocol</content-link>s and <content-link target="{50FE76C8-754F-470C-9F0F-6B735C421E17}" type="glossary">link-state protocol</content-link>s.</p> <p>Routers running distance vector routing protocols share network information with directly connected neighbors. The neighbor routers then advertise the information to their neighbors, until all routers in the enterprise learn the information. </p> <p>A router running a distance vector protocol does not know the entire path to a destination; it only knows the distance to the remote network and the direction, or <content-link target="{2D9C0A74-AA38-4C95-AC71-24AA7455D887}" type="glossary">vector</content-link>. Its knowledge comes through information from directly connected neighbors. </p> <p>Like all routing protocols, distance vector protocols use a <content-link target="{EA76D67D-0C29-4B09-90CE-F0206B7F986B}" type="glossary">metric</content-link> to determine the best route. Distance vector protocols calculate the best route based on the distance from a router to a network. An example of a metric used is hop count, which is the number of routers, or hops, between the router and the destination.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6154958893">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020100/en1105020102/cm6154958893.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020100/en1105020102/cm6154958893text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Distance vector protocols usually require less complicated configurations and management than link-state protocols. They can run on older, less powerful routers and require lower amounts of memory and processing. </p> <p>Routers using distance vector protocols broadcast or <content-link target="{9B3DF37C-01A9-4C63-BDAD-D93623A2C020}" type="glossary">multicast</content-link> their entire routing table to their neighbors at regular intervals. If a router learns more than one route to a destination, it calculates and advertises the route with the lowest metric. </p> <p>This method of moving routing information through large networks is slow. At any given moment, some routers may not have the most current information about the network. This limits the scalability of the protocols and causes issues such as routing loops.</p> <p>RIP versions 1 and 2 are true distance vector protocols, whereas EIGRP is actually a distance vector protocol with advanced capabilities. <content-link target="{A039F0A7-1903-48E1-99E4-E4EC913244A1}" type="glossary">RIPng</content-link>, the newest version of RIP was specifically designed to support IPv6.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105020200">
<title><content-text>Routing Information Protocol (RIP)</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2617567082">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020201/cm2617567082.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020201/cm2617567082text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Routing Information Protocol (RIP) was the first IP distance vector routing protocol to be standardized in a RFC (RFC1058 in 1988). The first version of RIP is now often called RIPv1 to distinguish it from the later improved version, RIPv2; and from the IPv6 version, RIPng.</p>  <p>By default RIPv1 broadcasts its routing updates out all active interfaces every 30 seconds.</p>  <p>RIPv1 is a classful routing protocol. It automatically summarizes subnets to the <content-link target="{1F4C2534-0D2B-4F61-B0D2-AA6A1625F669}" type="glossary">classful boundary</content-link> and does not send subnet mask information in the update. Therefore RIPv1 does not support VLSM and CIDR. A router configured with RIPv1 either uses the subnet mask configured on a local interface, or applies the default subnet mask based on the address class. Due to this limitation, the subnets of the networks that RIPv1 advertises should not be <content-link target="{E08D0328-2356-44EE-9951-4D9FCD3195ED}" type="glossary">discontiguous</content-link> if correct routing is to occur.</p>  <p>For example, a router configured with interfaces as the gateways for the 172.16.1.0/24 and 172.16.4.0/24 subnets will advertise only the 172.16.0.0 Class B network with RIPv1. Another router receiving this update will therefore list the 172.16.0.0 network in its routing table. This means packets with an actual destination subnet address of 172.16.3.0 could mistakenly be forwarded to the advertising router and therefore not arrive at the correct destination subnet.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7696774716">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020202/cm7696774716.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020202/cm7696774716text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>RIP v2 has many of the features of RIPv1. It also includes important enhancements. RIPv2 is a <content-link target="{31037DE4-EF97-40B7-B5E4-02ECF9F7CA8C}" type="glossary">classless routing</content-link> protocol that supports VLSM and CIDR. A subnet mask field is included in v2 updates, which allows the use of discontiguous networks. RIPv2 also has the ability to turn off automatic summarization of routes.</p> <p>Both versions of RIP send their entire routing table out all participating interfaces in updates. RIP v1 broadcasts these updates to 255.255.255.255. This requires all devices on a broadcast network like Ethernet to process the data. RIP v2 multicasts its updates to 224.0.0.9. Multicasts take up less network bandwidth than broadcasts. Devices that are not configured for RIPv2 discard multicasts at the Data Link Layer.</p> <p>Attackers often introduce invalid updates to trick a router into sending data to the wrong destination or to seriously degrade network performance. Invalid information can also end up in the routing table due to poor configuration or a malfunctioning router. Encrypting routing information hides the content of the routing table from any routers that do not possess the password or authentication data. RIPv2 has an authentication mechanism, whereas RIPv1 does not.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020203">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4824617069">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020203/cm4824617069.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020203/cm4824617069text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although RIPv2 provides many enhancements, it is not an entirely different protocol. RIPv2 shares many of the features found in RIPv1, such as:</p> <p><ul><li> Hop-count metric</li><li> 15-hop maximum</li><li> TTL equals 16 hops</li><li> Default 30-second update interval</li><li> <content-link target="{C5E4F912-CB6F-48B9-A12F-D5F9AE5885D0}" type="glossary">Route poisoning</content-link>, <content-link target="{9C337FAF-A260-4EA1-A4B8-06B83CB50D31}" type="glossary">poisoned reverse</content-link>, <content-link target="{DCCD39A0-17C3-4F3E-8FDB-F36524EEE22A}" type="glossary">split horizon</content-link>, and <content-link target="{0EA8912F-A97F-47E3-B4AC-5235FEE4A544}" type="glossary">holddown</content-link>s to avoid loops</li><li> Updates using UDP port 520</li><li> Administrative distance of 120</li><li> Message header containing up to 25 routes without authentication </li></ul></p> <p>When a router starts up, each RIP-configured interface sends out a <content-link target="{E99486A3-343B-4560-A98B-140E728816F9}" type="glossary">request message</content-link>. This message requests that all RIP neighbors send their complete routing tables. RIP-enabled neighbors send a <content-link target="{933F0311-7851-4A54-B1E5-F484795B2DA4}" type="glossary">response message</content-link> that includes known network entries. The receiving router evaluates each route entry based on the following criteria: </p> <p><ul><li> If a route entry is new, the receiving router installs the route in the routing table. </li><li> If the route is already in the table and the entry comes from a different source, the routing table replaces the existing entry if the new entry has a better hop count.</li><li> If the route is already in the table and the entry comes from the same source, it replaces the existing entry even if the metric is not better.</li></ul></p> <p>The startup router then sends a <content-link target="{04939990-4E84-4C29-B02D-8578F83011CC}" type="glossary">triggered update</content-link> out all RIP-enabled interfaces containing its own routing table. RIP neighbors are informed of any new routes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2554045620">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020204/cm2554045620.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020204/cm2554045620text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As long as routers send and process the correct versions of routing updates, RIPv1 and RIPv2 are completely compatible. By default, RIPv2 sends and receives only version 2 updates. If a network must use both versions of RIP, the network administrator configures RIPv2 to send and receive both versions 1 and 2. By default, RIPv1 sends version 1 updates, but receives both versions 1 and 2. </p> <p>Within an enterprise, it may be necessary to use both versions of RIP. For example, part of the network may be migrating to RIPv2, whereas another part may be staying with RIPv1. Overriding the global RIP configuration with interface-specific behavior allows routers to support both versions of RIP.</p> <p>To customize the global configuration of an interface, use the following interface configuration commands:</p> <span class="cmd"><p><b>ip rip send version &lt;1 | 2 | 1 2></b></p></span> <span class="cmd"><p><b>ip rip receive version &lt;1 | 2 | 1 2></b></p></span></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105020205">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm7249170433">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020205/cm7249170433.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020200/en1105020205/cm7249170433text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Select the version of RIP that is most appropriate for the situation given.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105020300">
<title><content-text>Configuring RIPv2</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5708083601">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020300/en1105020301/cm5708083601.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020300/en1105020301/cm5708083601text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Before configuring RIPv2, assign IP addresses and masks to all interfaces that participate in routing. Set the clock rate where necessary on serial links. After the basic configurations are complete, configure RIPv2.</p> <p>The basic RIPv2 configuration consists of three commands:</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)<b>#router rip</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Enables the routing protocol</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config)<b>#version 2</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Specifies the version</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config-router)<b>#network </b>[<i>network address</i>] </span></p> <p><ul><li> Identify each directly connected network that should be advertised by RIP</li></ul></p> <p>By default, RIPv2 will summarize each network to be advertised to its classful boundary as the graphic shows. </p> <p>RIPv2 updates can be configured to be authenticated.</p> <p>RIPv2 propagates a default route to its neighbor routers as part of its routing updates. To accomplish this, create the default route and then add <span class="cmd"><b>redistribute static</b></span> to the RIPv2 configuration.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1822422898">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020300/en1105020302/cm1822422898/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020300/en1105020302/cm1822422898/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Configuring RIPv2 with VLSM addressing scheme and a default route.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105020400">
<title><content-text>Problems with RIP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4920618248">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020401/cm4920618248.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020401/cm4920618248text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Various performance and security issues arise when using RIP. The first issue concerns routing table accuracy.</p> <p>Both versions of RIP automatically summarize subnets on the classful boundary. This means that RIP recognizes subnets as a single Class A, B, or C network. Enterprise networks typically use classless IP addressing and a variety of subnets, some of which are not directly connected to each other, which creates discontiguous subnets.</p> <p>Unlike RIPv1, with RIPv2 the automatic summarization feature can be disabled. When disabled, RIPv2 will report all subnets with subnet mask information. This is done to ensure a more accurate routing table. To accomplish this, add the <span class="cmd"><b>no auto-summary</b></span> command to the RIPv2 configuration.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config-router)<b>#no auto-summary</b></span></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5917696306">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020402/cm5917696306.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020402/cm5917696306text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another issue to consider is the broadcast nature of RIP updates. As soon as the RIP configuration lists a <span class="cmd"><b>network</b></span> command for a given network, RIP immediately begins to send advertisements out all interfaces that belong to that network. These updates may not be needed on all portions of a network. For example, an Ethernet LAN interface passes these updates to every device on its network segment, which produces unnecessary traffic. The routing update could also be intercepted by any device. This makes the network less secure.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>passive-interface</b></span> command, issued in interface mode, disables routing updates on specified interfaces.</p> <p><span class="cmd">Router(config-router)#<b>passive-interface </b><i>interface-type interface-number</i></span></p> <p>In complex enterprise networks running more than one routing protocol, the <span class="cmd"><b>passive-interface</b></span> command defines which routers learn RIP routes. When the number of interfaces advertising RIP routes is limited, security and traffic control increase.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020403">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm8611101416">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020403/cm8611101416.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020403/cm8611101416text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A network running RIP needs time to converge. Some routers may contain incorrect routes in their routing tables until all routers have updated and have the same view of the network. </p> <p>Erroneous network information may cause routing updates and traffic to loop endlessly as they <content-link target="{A63FCAE5-BE1B-47C8-BFFB-D9777C7551E0}" type="glossary">count to infinity</content-link>. In the RIP routing protocol, infinity occurs when the hop count is 16.</p> <p>Routing loops negatively affect network performance. RIP contains several features designed to combat this impact. These features are often used in combination:</p> <p><ul><li> <content-link target="{9C337FAF-A260-4EA1-A4B8-06B83CB50D31}" type="glossary">Poisoned reverse</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{DCCD39A0-17C3-4F3E-8FDB-F36524EEE22A}" type="glossary">Split horizon</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{C07D09F0-2E68-4D38-8D1A-5A484FB31493}" type="glossary">Holddown timer</content-link></li><li> Triggered updates</li></ul></p> <p>Poisoned reverse sets the metric for a route to 16, making it unreachable. Because RIP defines infinity as 16 hops, any network further away than 15 hops is unreachable. If a network is down, a router changes the metric for that route to 16 so that all other routers see it as unreachable. This feature prevents the routing protocol from sending information via poisoned routes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020404">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm1511400560">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020404/cm1511400560.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020404/cm1511400560text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The anti-loop features of RIP add stability to the protocol, but also add to convergence time.</p> <p>Split horizon prevents the formation of loops. When multiple routers advertise the same network routes to each other, routing loops may form. Split horizon dictates that a router receiving routing information on an interface cannot send an update about that same network back out the same interface. </p> <p>The holddown timer stabilizes routes. The holddown timer refuses to accept route updates with a higher metric to the same destination network for a period after a route goes down. If, during the <content-link target="{95E9D862-C834-42BB-8D5D-FADD14D24D5C}" type="glossary">holddown period</content-link>, the original route comes back up or the router receives route information with a lower metric, the router installs the route in the routing table and immediately begins to use it.</p> <p>The default holddown time is 180 seconds, six times the regular update period. The default can be changed. However, any holddown period increases the convergence time and has a negative impact on network performance.</p> <p>When a route fails, RIP does not wait for the next periodic update. Instead, RIP sends an immediate update, called a triggered update. It advertises the failed route by increasing the metric to 16, effectively poisoning the route. This update places the route in holddown status while RIP attempts to locate an alternate route with a better metric.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020405">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1686497491">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020405/cm1686497491/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020400/en1105020405/cm1686497491/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Route between discontiguous networks with RIP.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105020500">
<title><content-text>Verifying RIP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5651389320">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020500/en1105020501/cm5651389320.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020500/en1105020501/cm5651389320text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>RIPv2 is a simple protocol to configure. However, errors and inconsistencies can occur on any network. There are many <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> commands to assist the technician in verifying a RIP configuration and troubleshooting RIP functionality.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>show ip protocols</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span> commands are important for verification and troubleshooting on any routing protocol. </p> <p>The following commands specifically verify and troubleshoot RIP: </p> <p><ul><li> <span class="cmd"><b>show ip rip database</b></span>: Lists all the routes known by RIP</li><li> <span class="cmd"><b>debug ip rip</b></span> or <span class="cmd"><b>debug ip rip {events}</b></span>: Displays RIP routing updates as sent and received in real time </li></ul></p> <p>The output of this debug command displays the source address and interface of each update, as well as the version and the metric.</p> <p>Do not use the <span class="cmd"><b>debug</b></span> commands more than necessary. Debugging consumes bandwidth and processing power, which slows network performance.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> command can be used to test for end-to-end connectivity. The <span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span> command provides a convenient method of verifying that all commands were entered correctly.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105020502">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2994270914">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020500/en1105020502/cm2994270914/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105020000/en1105020500/en1105020502/cm2994270914/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Troubleshoot and correct RIPv2 problems.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1105030000">
<title><content-text>Routing Using the EIGRP Protocol</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105030100">
<title><content-text>Limitations of RIP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm3754563930">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030100/en1105030101/cm3754563930.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030100/en1105030101/cm3754563930text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The RIP distance vector routing protocol is easy to configure and requires minimal amounts of router resources in order to function. </p> <p>However, the simple hop count metric used by RIP is not an accurate way to determine the best path in complex networks. Additionally, the RIP limitation of 15 hops can mark distant networks as unreachable. </p> <p>RIP issues periodic updates of its routing table, which consumes bandwidth, even when no network changes have occurred. Routers must accept these updates and process them to see if they contain updated route information. </p> <p>Updates passed from router to router take time to reach all areas of the network. As a result, routers may not have an accurate picture of the network. Routing loops can develop due to slow convergence time, which wastes valuable bandwidth.</p> <p>These characteristics limit the usefulness of the RIP routing protocol within the enterprise environment.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105030200">
<title><content-text>Enhanced Interior Gateway Routing Protocol (EIGRP)</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2196395923">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030201/cm2196395923.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030201/cm2196395923text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The limitations of RIP led to the development of more advanced protocols. Networking professionals required a protocol that would support VLSM and CIDR, scale easily, and provide faster convergence in complex enterprise networks. </p> <p>Cisco developed EIGRP as a <content-link target="{AC88BCA1-4CE0-4BC5-AAF6-BDB1043EB9EE}" type="glossary">proprietary</content-link> distance vector routing protocol. It has enhanced capabilities that address many of the limitations of other distance vector protocols. EIGRP shares some of features of RIP, while employing many advanced features.</p> <p>Although configuring EIGRP is relatively simple, the underlying features and options are complex. EIGRP contains many features that are not found in any other routing protocols. All of these factors makes EIGRP an excellent choice for large, multi-protocol networks that employ primarily Cisco devices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5409833060">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030202/cm5409833060.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030202/cm5409833060text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The two main goals of EIGRP are to provide a loop-free routing environment and rapid convergence. To achieve these goals, EIGRP uses a different method than RIP for calculating the best route. The metric used is a <content-link target="{EC664880-869E-4FA4-9F7C-FBC43ACFD0A1}" type="glossary">composite metric</content-link> that primarily considers bandwidth and delay. This metric is more accurate than hop count in determining the distance to a destination network. </p> <p>The Diffusing Update Algorithm (<content-link target="{5A441925-A689-4FD8-B18B-D5443C6182F5}" type="glossary">DUAL</content-link>) used by EIGRP guarantees loop-free operation while it calculates routes. When a change occurs in the network topology, DUAL synchronizes all affected routers simultaneously. For these reasons, the administrative distance of EIGRP is 90, whereas the administrative distance of RIP is 120. The lower number reflects the increased reliability of EIGRP and the increased accuracy of the metric. If a router learns routes to the same destination from both RIP and EIGRP, it chooses the EIGRP route over the route learned through RIP.</p> <p>EIGRP tags routes learned from another routing protocol as external. Because the information used to calculate these routes is not as reliable as the metric of EIGRP, it attaches a higher administrative distance to the routes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030203">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2546868838">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030203/cm2546868838.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030203/cm2546868838text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>EIGRP is a good choice for complex enterprise networks that are composed primarily of Cisco routers. Its maximum hop count of 255 supports large networks. EIGRP can display more than one routing table because it can collect and maintain routing information for a variety of routed protocols, such as IP and IPX. The EIGRP routing table reports routes learned both inside and outside the local system. </p> <p>Unlike other distance vector protocols, EIGRP does not send complete tables in its updates. EIGRP multicasts partial updates about specific changes to only those routers that need the information, not to all routers in the area. These are called <content-link target="{C55F55D9-D002-4A58-A35B-F9EEEA20FD96}" type="glossary">bounded update</content-link>s because they reflect specific parameters. </p> <p>Instead of sending periodic routing updates, EIGRP sends small <content-link target="{DEF0681A-25FA-4BAA-9796-4B723D98F88B}" type="glossary">hello packet</content-link>s to maintain knowledge of its neighbors. Since they are limited in size, both bounded updates and hello packets save bandwidth while keeping network information fresh.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105030204">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6356142619">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030204/cm6356142619.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030200/en1105030204/cm6356142619text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Identify the features appropriate to each routing protocol. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105030300">
<title><content-text>EIGRP Terminology and Tables</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5705251436">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030301/cm5705251436.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030301/cm5705251436text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To store network information from the updates and support rapid convergence, EIGRP maintains multiple tables. EIGRP routers keep route and topology information readily available in RAM so that they can react quickly to changes. EIGRP maintains three interconnected tables:</p> <p><ul><li> <content-link target="{36DBE1B8-C514-43C1-B6DE-37484D9D100C}" type="glossary">Neighbor table</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{A6E071D5-2314-44F5-81D1-BD8D6B1C799F}" type="glossary">Topology table</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{60627C13-D5ED-4D8D-A27D-27392E63E6FF}" type="glossary">Routing table</content-link></li></ul></p> <p><b>Neighbor Table</b></p> <p> </p> <p>The neighbor table lists information about directly connected neighbor routers. EIGRP records the address of a newly discovered neighbor and the interface that connects to it. </p> <p>When a neighbor sends a hello packet, it advertises a <content-link target="{2B605FC8-07D2-4397-BF60-EB374E982110}" type="glossary">hold time</content-link>. The hold time is the length of time that a router treats a neighbor as reachable. If a hello packet is not received within the hold time, the timer expires and DUAL recalculates the topology. </p> <p>Since fast convergence depends on accurate neighbor information, this table is crucial to EIGRP operation.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030302">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm1293946033">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030302/cm1293946033.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030302/cm1293946033text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Topology table</b></p> <p> </p> <p>The topology table lists all routes learned from each EIGRP neighbor. DUAL takes the information from the neighbor and topology tables and calculates the lowest cost routes to each network. </p> <p>The topology table identifies up to four primary loop-free routes for any one destination. These <content-link target="{A0040096-64A2-45FF-926E-353EA2D31859}" type="glossary">successor route</content-link>s appear in the routing table. EIGRP <content-link target="{209039C8-BCA2-43D5-9555-61B9885BC1EC}" type="glossary">load balances</content-link>, or sends packets to a destination using more than one path. It load balances using successor routes that are both <content-link target="{14E50CBE-8A77-4A3B-80D1-A3F6F6B2DEBB}" type="glossary">equal cost</content-link> and <content-link target="{FF3E019F-F7D5-4DF6-ABFF-B72312B7CF50}" type="glossary">unequal cost</content-link>. This feature avoids overloading any one route with packets.</p> <p>Backup routes, called <content-link target="{B66DB5F8-B2C7-492B-8B12-F3E51C5EDC4A}" type="glossary">feasible successor</content-link>s, appear in the topology table but not in the routing table. If a primary route fails, a feasible successor becomes a successor route. This backup occurs as long as the feasible successor has a lower reported distance than the feasible distance of the current successor distance to the destination. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030303">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7166534146">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030303/cm7166534146.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030303/cm7166534146text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Routing Table</b></p> <p>Whereas the topology table contains information about many possible paths to a network destination, the routing table displays only the best paths called the successor routes. </p> <p>EIGRP displays information about routes in two ways: </p> <p><ul><li> The routing table designates routes learned through EIGRP with a D. </li><li> EIGRP tags dynamic or static routes learned from other routing protocols or from outside the EIGRP network as D EX or external, because they did not originate from EIGRP routers within the same AS.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105030304">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSA" id="cm9531557176">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030304/cm9531557176.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030300/en1105030304/cm9531557176text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Determine which EIGRP table would be the most appropriate to find the specified information.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105030400">
<title><content-text>EIGRP Neighbors and Adjacencies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1983540343">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030401/cm1983540343.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030401/cm1983540343text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Before EIGRP can exchange packets between routers, it must first discover its neighbors. EIGRP neighbors are other routers running EIGRP on shared, directly connected networks.</p> <p>EIGRP routers use hello packets to discover neighbors and establish <content-link target="{07B361EF-E992-42EF-BED4-DA11412A4E87}" type="glossary">adjacencies</content-link> with neighbor routers. By default, hello packets are multicast every 5 seconds on links greater than a T1 and every 60 seconds on T1 or slower links. </p> <p>On <content-link target="{FE6104D2-85A3-4199-A5A4-E4A23F962BFE}" type="glossary">IP networks</content-link>, the multicast address is 224.0.0.10. The hello packet contains information about the router interfaces and the interface addresses. An EIGRP router assumes that as long as it is receiving hello packets from a neighbor, the neighbor and its routes are reachable. </p> <p>The hold time is the period that EIGRP waits to receive a hello packet. Generally, the hold time is three times the duration of the <content-link target="{68C220F3-C9DD-44BB-B9C6-399E5A85B89C}" type="glossary">hello interval</content-link>. When the hold time expires and EIGRP declares the route as down, DUAL re-evaluates the topology and refreshes the routing table.</p> <p>Information discovered through the hello protocol provides the information for the neighbor table. A sequence number records the number of the last received hello from each neighbor and time-stamps the time that the packet arrived.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030402">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm7556189782">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030402/cm7556189782.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030402/cm7556189782text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a neighbor adjacency is established, EIGRP uses various types of packets to exchange and update routing table information. Neighbors learn about new routes, unreachable routes, and rediscovered routes through exchange of these packets:</p> <p><ul><li> Acknowledgement</li><li> Update</li><li> Query</li><li> Reply</li></ul></p> <p>When a route is lost, it moves to an active state and DUAL searches for a new route to the destination. When a route is found, it is moved to the routing table and placed in a passive state.</p> <p>These various packets help DUAL gather the information it requires to calculate the best route to the destination network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030403">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7307149661">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030403/cm7307149661.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030403/cm7307149661text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>An acknowledgement packet indicates the receipt of an update, query, or reply packet. Acknowledgement packets are small hello packets without any data. These types of packets are always unicast.</p> <p>An <content-link target="{744C33BC-27E7-445E-8FA0-68FA78425D44}" type="glossary">update packet</content-link> sends information about the network topology to its neighbor. That neighbor then updates its topology table. Several updates are often required to send all the topology information to the new neighbor.</p> <p>Whenever DUAL places a route in the active state, the router must send a <content-link target="{4E5540E1-3968-4098-B3CA-3F386C6C1983}" type="glossary">query packet</content-link> to each neighbor. Neighbors must send replies, even if the reply states that no information on the destination is available. The information contained in each <content-link target="{BFFAEFAD-04B0-4286-911A-AEA3B5D72677}" type="glossary">reply packet</content-link> helps DUAL to locate a successor route to the destination network. Queries can be multicast or unicast. Replies are always unicast. </p> <p>EIGRP packet types use either a connection-oriented service similar to TCP or a connectionless service similar to UDP. Update, query, and reply packets use the TCP-like service. Acknowledgements and hello packets use the UDP-like service.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030404">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8696678839">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030404/cm8696678839.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030404/cm8696678839text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As a routing protocol, EIGRP operates independently of the Network Layer. Cisco designed Reliable Transport Protocol (<content-link target="{9FFC3795-013D-435C-8CAD-B3125A16A4DB}" type="glossary">RTP</content-link>) as a proprietary Layer 4 protocol. RTP guarantees delivery and receipt of EIGRP packets for all Network Layer protocols. Because large, complex networks may use a variety of Network Layer protocols, this protocol makes EIGRP flexible and scalable. </p> <p>RTP can be used as both a reliable and best effort transport protocol, similar to TCP and UDP. Reliable RTP requires an acknowledgement packet from the receiver to the sender. Update, query, and reply packets are sent reliably; hello and acknowledgement packets are sent best effort and do not require an acknowledgement. RTP uses both unicast and multicast packets. Multicast EIGRP packets use the reserved multicast address of 224.0.0.10.</p> <p>Each Network Layer protocol works through a Protocol Dependent Module (<content-link target="{0C1CF603-7219-4D60-8AAB-A2CAFDC3AAD2}" type="glossary">PDM</content-link>) responsible for the specific routing task. Each PDM maintains three tables. For example, a router running IP, IPX, and AppleTalk has three neighbor tables, three topology tables, and three routing tables.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105030405">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm3843342808">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030405/cm3843342808.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030400/en1105030405/cm3843342808text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the EIGRP packet type to its definition. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105030500">
<title><content-text>EIGRP Metrics and Convergence</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7104577659">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030501/cm7104577659.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030501/cm7104577659text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>EIGRP uses a composite metric value to determine the best path to a destination. This metric is determined from the following values:</p> <p><ul><li> Bandwidth</li><li> Delay</li><li> Reliability</li><li> Load</li></ul></p> <p>Maximum Transmission Unit (<content-link target="{37D2EA39-737B-416C-A2BC-C9ED0930AE73}" type="glossary">MTU</content-link>) is another value included in routing updates, but is not a routing metric. </p> <p>The composite metric formula consists of <content-link target="{4C120A3A-CC2A-4D32-8218-72B178C09B61}" type="glossary">K values</content-link>: K1 through K5. By default, K1 and K3 are set to 1. K2, K4, and K5 are set to 0. The value of 1 designates that bandwidth and delay have equal weight in the composite metric calculation.</p> <p><b>Bandwidth</b></p> <p>The bandwidth metric is a static value and is displayed in kbps. Most serial interfaces use the default bandwidth value of 1544 kbps. This metric reflects the bandwidth of a T1 connection. </p> <p>Sometimes the bandwidth value may not reflect the actual physical bandwidth of the interface. Bandwidth influences the metric calculation and, as a result, the EIGRP path selection. If a 56 kbps link is advertised with a 1544 kbps value, it could interfere with convergence as it struggles to cope with the traffic load.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2346060922">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030502/cm2346060922.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030502/cm2346060922text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The other metrics used by EIGRP to calculate the cost of a link are delay, reliability, and load.</p> <p>The delay metric is a static value that is based on the type of exit interface. The default value is 20,000 microseconds for Serial interfaces and 100 microseconds for Fast Ethernet interfaces.</p> <p>The delay metric does not represent the actual amount of time packets take to reach the destination. Changing the delay value associated with a specific interface alters the metric but does not physically affect the network.</p> <p>Reliability measures how often the link has experienced errors. Unlike delay, reliability updates automatically, depending on the link conditions. It has a value of between 0 and 255. A reliability of 255/255 represents a 100 percent reliable link. </p> <p>Load reflects the amount of traffic using the link. A lower load value is more desirable than a higher value. As an example, 1/255 would be a minimally loaded link, and 255/255 would be a link that is 100 percent utilized.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105030503">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6469563408">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030503/cm6469563408.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030503/cm6469563408text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The EIGRP topology table uses metrics to maintain values for feasible distance (<content-link target="{5C6D5D02-CB1B-4E97-86B6-12F96CC4A73D}" type="glossary">FD</content-link>) and advertised distance (<content-link target="{9CEE02B3-B818-4CEA-A634-0E03E843ABF3}" type="glossary">AD</content-link>), or reported distance (<content-link target="{5FEB4413-9FE5-4D1C-9A58-F9B0AAE177A2}" type="glossary">RD</content-link>). DUAL uses these values to determine successors and feasible successors. </p> <p>Feasible distance is the best EIGRP metric along the path to the destination from the router. </p> <p>Advertised distance is the best metric reported by a neighbor.</p> <p>The loop-free route with the lowest feasible distance becomes a successor. There can be multiple successors for a destination, depending on the actual topology. A feasible successor is a route with an advertised distance that is less than the feasible distance of a successor.</p> <p>DUAL converges quickly after a change in the topology. DUAL keeps feasible successors in the topology table and promotes the best one to the routing table as a successor route if the original . If no feasible successor exists, the original route moves into active mode, and queries are sent to find a new successor.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105030504">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm1190446869">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030504/cm1190446869.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105030000/en1105030500/en1105030504/cm1190446869text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen:</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Examine the network diagram and answer questions about the feasible distance (FD), advertised distance (AD), and the successor route for specified routes.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1105040000">
<title><content-text>Implementing EIGRP</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105040100">
<title><content-text>Configuring EIGRP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3051193259">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040101/cm3051193259.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040101/cm3051193259text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Basic EIGRP is relatively simple to configure. It has many similarities to RIPv2. </p> <p>To begin the EIGRP routing process, use two steps:</p> <p><b>Step 1</b></p> <p>Enable the EIGRP routing process.</p> <p>Enabling the EIGRP process requires an autonomous system parameter. This AS parameter can be assigned any 16-bit value and identifies all of the routers belonging to a single company or organization. Although EIGRP refers to the parameter as an autonomous system number, it actually functions as a process ID. This AS number is locally significant only and is not the same as the autonomous system number issued and controlled by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (<content-link target="{AB403027-9A96-4ED7-823C-43E1DEF6430B}" type="glossary">IANA</content-link>).</p> <p>The AS number in the command must match on all routers that work within the EIGRP routing process. </p> <p><b>Step 2</b></p> <p>Include network statements for each network to be advertised.</p> <p>The <span class="cmd"><b>network</b></span> command tells EIGRP which networks and interfaces participate in the EIGRP process.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm7032031898">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040102/cm7032031898.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040102/cm7032031898text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To configure EIGRP to advertise only certain subnets, include a <content-link target="{4D126DD0-5D77-451F-B236-166B7AE8FE2A}" type="glossary">wildcard mask</content-link> after the network number. To determine the wildcard mask, subtract the subnet mask from 255.255.255.255. </p> <p>Some versions of the Cisco IOS allow the subnet mask to be specified instead of using the wildcard mask. Even if the subnet mask is used, the <span class="cmd"><b>show running-config</b></span> command displays the wildcard mask in its output.</p> <p>Two additional commands complete the typical basic EIGRP configuration. </p> <p>Add <span class="cmd"><b>eigrp log-neighbor-changes</b></span> command to view changes in neighbor adjacencies. This feature helps the administrator monitor the stability of the EIGRP network. </p> <p>On serial links that do not match the default EIGRP bandwidth of 1.544 Mbps, add the <span class="cmd"><b>bandwidth</b></span> command followed by the actual speed of the link expressed in kbps. Inaccurate bandwidth interferes with choosing the best route.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040103">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8730350717">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040103/cm8730350717.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040103/cm8730350717text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Once EIGRP is enabled, any router configured with EIGRP and the correct autonomous system number can enter the EIGRP network. This means routers with different or conflicting route information can affect and possibly corrupt the routing tables. To prevent this, it is possible to enable authentication within the EIGRP configuration. Once neighbor authentication is configured, the router authenticates the source of all routing updates before accepting them.</p> <p>EIGRP authentication requires the use of a pre-shared key. EIGRP allows an administrator to manage the keys though a keychain. The configuration of EIGRP authentication consists of two steps: creating the key and enabling authentication to use the key.</p> <p><b>Key Creation</b></p> <p><br/> To create the key perform the following commands:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>key chain <i>name-of-chain</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Global configuration command.</li><li> Specifies the name of the keychain and enters the configuration mode for the keychain.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>key <i>key-id</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Identifies the key number and enters the configuration mode for that key-id.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>key-string <i>text</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Identifies the key string or password. This must be configured to match on all EIGRP routers.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Enabling Authentication</b></p> <p>The key is used to enable MD5 authentication for EIGRP with the following interface configuration commands:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ip authentication mode eigrp md5</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Specifies that MD5 authentication is required for the exchange of EIGRP packets.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ip authentication key-chain eigrp <i>AS name-of-chain</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> AS specifies the autonomous system of the EIGPR configuration.</li></ul></p> <p>Name-of-chain parameter specifies the keychain that was previously configured. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040104">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm6270103957">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040104/cm6270103957/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040100/en1105040104/cm6270103957/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure EIGRP with MD5 authentication.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105040200">
<title><content-text>EIGRP Route Summarization</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3597874701">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040201/cm3597874701.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040201/cm3597874701text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Like RIP, EIGRP automatically summarizes subnetted networks on the classful boundary. EIGRP creates only one entry in the routing table for the summary route. A best path or successor route is associated with the summary route. As a result, all traffic destined for the subnets travels across that one path. </p> <p>In an enterprise network, the path chosen to reach the summary route may not be the best choice for the traffic that is trying to reach each individual subnet. The only way that all routers can find the best routes for each individual subnet is for neighbors to send subnet information. </p> <p>When default summarization is disabled, updates include subnet information. The routing table installs entries for each of the subnets and also an entry for the summary route. The summary route is called the <content-link target="{A8D2FDF5-BCC0-4E27-9BC8-756CF77D9061}" type="glossary">parent route</content-link> and the subnet routes are called the <content-link target="{A2EC214E-2BCC-481B-8631-4081F8F77FB5}" type="glossary">child routes</content-link>. </p> <p>EIGRP installs a Null0 summary route in the routing table for each parent route. The <content-link target="{C8BAF121-7CEF-4A6E-B8C1-144C9A5E9C6E}" type="glossary">Null0 interface</content-link> indicates that this is not an actual path, but a summary for advertising purposes. If a packet matches one of the child routes, it forwards out the correct interface. If the packet matches the summary route but does not match one of the child routes, it is discarded. </p> <p>Using default summarization results in smaller routing tables. Turning off the summarization produces larger updates and larger tables. Consideration of the overall network performance and traffic patterns determines if auto summarization is appropriate.</p> <p>Use the <span class="cmd"><b>no auto-summary</b></span> command to disable the default summarization.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2996978298">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040202/cm2996978298.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040202/cm2996978298text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>With auto summarization disabled, all subnets are advertised. An administrator may have a situation in which some of the subnets need to be summarized and some do not. The decision to summarize depends on the placement of the subnets. As an example, four contiguous subnets terminating on the same router are good candidates for summarization.</p> <p><content-link target="{0D711544-85BB-4C72-B47B-3414DE590305}" type="glossary">Manual summarization</content-link> provides a more precise control of EIGRP routes. Using this feature, the administrator determines which subnets on which interfaces are advertised as summary routes. </p> <p>Manual summarization is done on a per-interface basis and gives the network administrator complete control. A manually summarized route appears in the routing table as an EIGRP route sourced from a logical, not physical, interface:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>D 192.168.0.0/22 is a summary, Null0</b></span></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040203">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm8858991072">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040203/cm8858991072/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040203/cm8858991072/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Configure and verify EIGRP and EIGRP summary routes.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040204">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3305947954">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040204/cm3305947954/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040200/en1105040204/cm3305947954/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure automatic and manual route summarization with EIGRP.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105040300">
<title><content-text>Verifying EIGRP Operation</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2320096342">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040301/cm2320096342.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040301/cm2320096342text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although EIGRP is a relatively simple protocol to configure, it employs sophisticated technologies to overcome the limitations of distance vector routing protocols. It is important to understand these technologies in order to properly verify and troubleshoot a network configuration that utilizes EIGRP. Some of the verification commands available include: </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip protocols</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Verifies that EIGRP is advertising the correct networks </li><li> Displays the autonomous system number and administrative distance</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Verifies that the EIGRP routes are in the routing table </li><li> Designates EIGRP routes with a <b>D</b> or a <b>D EX</b></li><li> Has a default administrative distance of 90 for internal routes</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip eigrp neighbors detail</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Verifies the adjacencies EIGRP forms </li><li> Displays the IP addresses and interfaces of neighbor routers</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip eigrp topology</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Displays successors and all feasible successors</li><li> Displays feasible distance and reported distance</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip eigrp interfaces detail</b> </span></p> <p><ul><li> Verifies the interfaces using EIGRP</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show ip eigrp traffic</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Displays the number and types of EIGRP packets sent and received</li></ul></p> <p>One of the primary uses of these show commands is to verify the successful formation of EIGRP adjacencies and the successful exchange of EIGRP packets between routers. EIGRP cannot work without forming adjacencies, therefore this should be verified prior to any other troubleshooting efforts.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040302">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7953714042">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040302/cm7953714042.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040302/cm7953714042text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If adjacencies appear normal but problems still exist, an administrator should begin troubleshooting using debug commands to view real-time information on the EIGRP activities occurring on a router. </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>debug eigrp packet</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> displays transmission and receipt of all EIGRP packets</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>debug eigrp fsm</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> displays feasible successor activity to determine whether routes are discovered, installed, or deleted by EIGRP</li></ul></p> <p>Debugging operations use large amounts of bandwidth and router processing power, particularly when debugging a very complex protocol like EIGRP. These commands provide details that can pinpoint the source of a lost EIGRP route or missing adjacency; however, the use of these commands can also degrade network performance.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105040303">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm6770932474">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040303/cm6770932474.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040303/cm6770932474text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p> <p>Match the output requirements with the appropriate command. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040304">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9476469610">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040304/cm9476469610/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040300/en1105040304/cm9476469610/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Explore the various EIGRP verification and troubleshooting commands.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105040400">
<title><content-text>Issues and Limitations of EIGRP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105040401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8862109671">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040400/en1105040401/cm8862109671.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105040000/en1105040400/en1105040401/cm8862109671text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although EIGRP is a powerful and sophisticated routing protocol, several considerations limit its use:</p> <p><ul><li> Does not work in a multi-vendor environment because it is a Cisco proprietary protocol </li><li> Works best with a flat network design</li><li> Must share the same autonomous system among routers and cannot be subdivided into groups</li><li> Can create very large routing tables, which requires large update packets and large amounts of bandwidth</li><li> Uses more memory and processor power than RIP </li><li> Works inefficiently when left on the default settings</li><li> Requires administrators with advanced technical knowledge of the protocol and the network</li></ul></p> <p>EIGRP offers the best of distance vector routing, while using additional features typically associated with link-state routing protocols, including bounded updates and neighbor adjacencies. Successful implementation of the many features of EIGRP requires careful configuration, monitoring, and troubleshooting.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1105050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105050100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105050101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm2767481061">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105050000/en1105050100/en1105050101/cm2767481061.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105050000/en1105050100/en1105050101/cm2767481061text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1105050200">
<title><content-text>Critical Thinking</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1105050201">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm3050017891">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105050000/en1105050200/en1105050201/cm3050017891.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1105000000/en1105050000/en1105050200/en1105050201/cm3050017891text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1105060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1105060100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1105060101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm7339939913">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1105000000/en1105060000/en1105060100/en1105060101/cm7339939913/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1105000000/en1105060000/en1105060100/en1105060101/cm7339939913/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
