<chapter type="" id="en1107000000">
<title><content-text>Implementing Enterprise WAN Links</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1107000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm2606486823">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107000000/en1107000100/en1107000101/cm2606486823.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107000000/en1107000100/en1107000101/cm2606486823text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1107010000">
<title><content-text>Connecting the Enterprise WAN</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107010100">
<title><content-text>WAN Devices and Technology</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6159766469">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010101/cm6159766469.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010101/cm6159766469text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As companies grow, they often expand from a single location to multiple remote locations. This expansion requires that the business network expand from a local area network (LAN) to a wide area network (WAN). </p> <p>Within a LAN, a network administrator has physical control over all cabling, devices, and services. Although some larger companies maintain their own WANs, most organizations purchase WAN services from a service provider. Service providers charge for the use of their network resources. ISPs allow users to share resources among remote locations without incurring the expense of building and maintaining their own network. </p> <p>Control of network resources is not the only difference between a LAN and a WAN. The technologies also differ. The most common LAN technology is Ethernet. WAN technologies are <content-link target="{E11F6854-BC15-4822-B526-60B5FB3BBEA7}" type="glossary">serial transmission</content-link>s. Serial transmissions enable reliable, long-range communications at slower speeds than a LAN.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9346357838">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010102/cm9346357838.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010102/cm9346357838text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When implementing a WAN, the WAN technology used determines the type of devices required by an organization. For example, a router used as a gateway to connect to the WAN translates the data into a format that is acceptable to the service provider network. A translation device, such as a modem, prepares the data for transmission across the service provider network. </p> <p>Preparing the data for transmission on the WAN using digital lines requires a channel service unit (CSU) and a data service unit (DSU). These two devices are often combined into a single piece of equipment called the CSU/DSU. This device integrates into the interface card in the router. When using an analog connection, a modem is necessary. </p> <p>When a business subscribes to WAN services through an ISP, the ISP owns and maintains most of the equipment. In certain environments, the subscriber may own and maintain some of the connection equipment. The point at which the control and responsibility of the customer ends and the control and responsibility of the service provider begins is known as the demarcation point, or demarc. For example, the demarc might exist between the router and the translating device or between the translating device and the central office (<content-link target="{CCDD6C13-8CDF-4258-A12E-1EFF15C39795}" type="glossary">CO</content-link>) of the service provider. Regardless of ownership, service providers use the term customer premise equipment (CPE), to describe equipment located at the customer site.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010103">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6768220378">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010103/cm6768220378.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010103/cm6768220378text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The CO is the location where the service provider stores equipment and accepts customer connections. The physical line from the CPE connects into a router or WAN switch at the CO using copper or fiber cabling. </p> <p>This connection is called the <content-link target="{C2AF670D-05B5-4F8D-8236-810E2D8F9AEB}" type="glossary">local loop</content-link>, or last mile. From the customer perspective, it is the <content-link target="{6458F653-0040-4485-8877-26D89CA694C8}" type="glossary">first mile</content-link>, because it is the first part of the medium leading from the location of the customer. </p> <p>The CSU/DSU or modem controls the rate at which data moves onto the local loop. It also provides the <content-link target="{FBCCE530-1C69-402B-98A3-EC3CCD960618}" type="glossary">clocking signal</content-link> to the router. The CSU/DSU is data communications equipment (<content-link target="{C8D6D667-34D5-42F9-A967-302755785430}" type="glossary">DCE</content-link>). The router, which is responsible for passing the data to the DCE, is data terminal equipment (<content-link target="{5958BD8E-9446-419C-B70F-111482F22224}" type="glossary">DTE</content-link>). </p> <p>The DTE/DCE interface uses various Physical Layer protocols, such as X.21 and <content-link target="{407AD422-D771-46B8-8D44-83C8A4F86FF4}" type="glossary">V.35</content-link>. These protocols establish the codes and electrical parameters that the router and the CSU/DSU use to communicate with each other.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9826023767">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010104/cm9826023767.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010104/cm9826023767text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Technology continuously develops and improves signaling standards that enable increased speed and traffic.</p> <p>When choosing a WAN technology, it is important to consider the link speed. The first digital networks created for WAN implementations provided support for a 64 kbps connection across a leased line. The term digital signal level 0 (<content-link target="{987DD345-0BC1-4CCD-8B6D-8A3951243583}" type="glossary">DS0</content-link>) refers to this standard.</p> <p>As technology improved, service providers supplied subscribers with specific increments of the DS0 channel. For example, in North America, a <content-link target="{B67E5B11-6A5D-4275-8383-F775989E2930}" type="glossary">DS1</content-link> standard, also called a T1 line, defines a single line that supports 24 DS0s, plus an 8 kbps overhead channel. This standard enables speeds of up to 1.544 Mbps. A T3 line uses a <content-link target="{02067BCB-099D-47A9-8D47-418F4CCCDA25}" type="glossary">DS3</content-link> standard, which supports 28 DS1s and speeds of up to 44.736 Mbps. </p> <p>Other parts of the world use different standards. For example, Europe offers lines such as E1s, which support 32 DS0s for a speed of up to 2.048 Mbps, and E3s, which support 16 E1s for a speed of up to 34.064 Mbps.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107010105">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm9800806488">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010105/cm9800806488.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010100/en1107010105/cm9800806488text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Match the WAN term to the definition. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107010200">
<title><content-text>WAN Standards</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5302550035">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010200/en1107010201/cm5302550035.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010200/en1107010201/cm5302550035text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Designing a network based on specific standards ensures that all of the different devices and technologies found in a WAN environment work together. </p> <p>WAN standards describe the Physical Layer and Data Link Layer characteristics of data transportation. Data Link Layer WAN standards include parameters such as <content-link target="{1B547BCD-B22A-4B06-B259-058119544D14}" type="glossary">physical addressing</content-link>, <content-link target="{BCEA8D9B-51B3-4A30-8364-1FF23943582E}" type="glossary">flow control</content-link>, and <content-link target="{DD3DF67D-F5E3-4FA8-8022-4484120957CA}" type="glossary">encapsulation</content-link> type, as well as how the information moves across the WAN link. The type of WAN technology employed determines the specific Data Link Layer standards used. Some examples of Layer 2 WAN protocols are: </p> <p><ul><li> Link Access Procedure for Frame Relay (LAPF)</li><li> High-level Data Link Control (<content-link target="{1985F3F1-184A-45A7-B376-5619FF54BD5C}" type="glossary">HDLC</content-link>)</li><li> Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP)</li></ul></p> <p>Several organizations are responsible for managing both the Physical Layer and Data Link Layer WAN standards. These include:</p> <p><ul><li> International Telecommunications Union Telecommunications Standardization Sector (ITU-T)</li><li> International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</li><li> Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</li><li> Electronics Industry Alliance (EIA)</li><li> Telecommunications Industry Association (TIA) </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107010202">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm4577709800">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010200/en1107010202/cm4577709800.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010200/en1107010202/cm4577709800text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Determine whether the standards are part of Layer 1 or Layer 2.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107010300">
<title><content-text>Accessing the WAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2359159581">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010301/cm2359159581.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010301/cm2359159581text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>WAN links use either digital or analog technology. With analog connections, the data is encoded, or <content-link target="{9AA487E5-5932-4001-9D44-86BD06538365}" type="glossary">modulated</content-link>, onto a <content-link target="{11880A28-6484-4911-8775-42FBE210E544}" type="glossary">carrier wave</content-link>. The modulated signal then carries the information across the medium to the remote site. At the remote site, the signal is demodulated and the receiver extracts the information.</p> <p>A modem encodes the information onto that carrier wave before transmission and then decodes it at the receiving end. The modem gets its name from its task of modulation and demodulation of the carrier signal.</p> <p>Modems enable remote sites to communicate through the plain old telephone system (<content-link target="{2D9CB870-7F79-4BED-8B56-C0109EDC7630}" type="glossary">POTS</content-link>). They also enable end users to connect to service provider networks through DSL or cable connections.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6486249756">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010302/cm6486249756.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010302/cm6486249756text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Companies often purchase connectivty using dedicated links between their location and the ISP. These services are often obtained using leased lines for which the companies pay monthly for these services. These lines carry large amounts of data. For example, a T1 link carries 1.544 Mbps of traffic and an E1 link carries 2.048 Mbps of traffic. Often this bandwidth is larger than the amount that the organization actually requires. A T1 can be split into 24 DS0s of 64 Kbps each. In this case, the customer is ordering part of a T1/E1, or a fractional T1 or <content-link target="{9339D692-9CF1-4D09-AF83-9E201A8EB1D9}" type="glossary">fractional E1</content-link>.</p> <p>High-bandwidth connections are split up into several DS0s. The ISP assigns each DS0 to a different conversation or end user. Organizations purchase one or more DS0 channels. A DS0 is not a separate physical entity but rather a <content-link target="{217D87ED-39AB-475F-B4E2-2E31DBE13ABB}" type="glossary">time slice</content-link> of the physical bandwidth on one wire. Each fractional connection enables full use of the media by the organization for part of the total time. There are two techniques in which information from multiple channels can be allocated bandwidth on a single cable based on time: Time Division Multiplexing (<content-link target="{BE91E370-77F7-4BD8-97EF-47B26D340EFE}" type="glossary">TDM</content-link>) and Statistical-Time Division Multiplexing (<content-link target="{B4AA8BC5-9FB2-486D-8AB1-85310EBECF43}" type="glossary">STDM</content-link>).</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010303">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm1101109775">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010303/cm1101109775.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010303/cm1101109775text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Time Division Multiplexing (TDM) allocates bandwidth based on pre-assigned time slots. Each of these time slices are then assigned to individual conversations. Each time slice represents a period of time during which a conversation has complete use of the physical media. Bandwidth is allocated to each channel or time slot regardless of whether the station using the channel has data to transmit. Therefore, with standard TDM, if a sender has nothing to say, its time slice goes unused, wasting valuable bandwidth. </p> <p>Statistical Time Division Multiplexing (STDM) is similar to TDM except that it keeps track of conversations that require extra bandwidth. It then dynamically reassigns unused time slices on an as-needed basis. In this way, STDM minimizes wasted bandwidth.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107010304">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm1037880077">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010304/cm1037880077.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010300/en1107010304/cm1037880077text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Full Screen Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Drag the data blocks into the correct order to show how TDM and STDM use bandwidth. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107010400">
<title><content-text>Packet and Circuit Switching</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010401">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4996942003">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010401/cm4996942003.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010401/cm4996942003text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>An enterprise connects to WAN services in various ways. </p> <p><b>Dedicated Leased Line</b></p> <p>One type of connection is a point-to-point serial link between two routers using a dedicated leased line. This enables a one-to-one connection for the basic function of data delivery across a link. Each link requires a separate physical interface and a separate CSU/DSU. As an organization grows to multiple locations, supporting a dedicated leased line between each location becomes very expensive. </p> <p><b>Circuit Switching</b></p> <p><content-link target="{B495108F-BA5A-413D-94E7-9F927F503938}" type="glossary">Circuit switching</content-link> establishes a circuit between end nodes before forwarding any data. A standard telephone call uses this type of connection. While the circuit is in place, it provides dedicated bandwidth between the two points. Completion of the conversation releases the circuit. No other organizations use the circuit until it releases. This method provides a level of security not available in <content-link target="{04F68C78-0745-4B66-AFA1-F126E31DDA51}" type="glossary">packet switching</content-link> or cell switching technology.</p> <p>With circuit switching, the service provider assigns links to different connections as the need arises. Costs are incurred for the link only when the connection is active. The cost for circuit switching varies based on usage time and can become quite expensive if the circuit is used often.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010402">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7446020661">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010402/cm7446020661.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010402/cm7446020661text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Switching</b></p> <p>Packet switching uses bandwidth more efficiently than other types of switching. The data is segmented into packets, with an identifier on each packet. The data is then released into the service provider network. The service provider accepts the data and switches the packet from one node to another until the packet reaches its final destination. The circuit, or pathway, between the source and destination is often a preconfigured link, but it is not an exclusive link. The service provider switches packets from multiple organizations over the same links. Frame Relay is an example of packet switching technology. </p> <p><b>Cell Switching</b></p> <p>Cell switching is a variation of packet switching. It is capable of transferring voice, video, and data through private and public networks at speeds in excess of 155 Mbps. Asynchronous Transfer Mode (ATM) uses fixed length, 53-byte cells that have 48-bytes of data and a 5-byte header. The small, uniform size of the cells allows them to be switched quickly and efficiently between nodes. An advantage of ATM is that it prevents small messages from being held up behind larger messages. However, for networks handling mainly <content-link target="{424CD60E-8996-4A7F-A8FD-537F18D41655}" type="glossary">segmented data</content-link>, ATM introduces a large amount of overhead and actually slows network performance.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2852280590">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010403/cm2852280590.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010403/cm2852280590text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Virtual Circuits</b></p> <p>When using packet switching technology, the service provider establishes virtual circuits (VCs). Virtual circuits share the link between devices with traffic from other sources. As a result, the medium is not private during the duration of a connection. There are two types of virtual circuits: switched and permanent.</p> <p><b>Switched Virtual Circuit</b></p> <p>A switched virtual circuit (<content-link target="{CC93532A-7746-4841-9B01-D1759DED5163}" type="glossary">SVC</content-link>) is dynamically established between two points when a router requests a transmission. The circuit is set up on demand and torn down when transmission is complete, such as after a file has been downloaded. When establishing an SVC, call set-up information must be sent before transmitting any data. Call clearing information tears down the connection after it is no longer required. This process introduces delays in the network as SVCs are built up and torn down for each conversation. </p> <p><b>Permanent Virtual Circuit</b></p> <p>A permanent virtual circuit (<content-link target="{788424BD-98DB-4BED-BB88-3C1BB4AD74AE}" type="glossary">PVC</content-link>) provides a permanent path to forward data between two points. The service provider must preconfigure the PVCs and they are very seldom broken or disconnected. This eliminates the need for call setup and clearing. They speed the flow of information across the WAN. PVCs also provide the ISP with much greater control over the data-flow patterns and management of their network. PVCs are more popular than SVCs and usually service sites with high-volume, constant flows of traffic. Frame Relay typically uses PVCs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107010404">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm4836095700">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010404/cm4836095700.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010400/en1107010404/cm4836095700text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Identify the best WAN connection technology to support the scenario.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107010500">
<title><content-text>Last Mile and Long Range WAN Technologies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5284905197">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010501/cm5284905197.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010501/cm5284905197text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>ISPs use several different WAN technologies to connect their subscribers. The connection type used on the local loop, or last mile, may not be the same as the WAN connection type employed within the ISP network or between various ISPs. </p> <p>Some common last mile technologies are:</p> <p><ul><li> Analog dialup</li><li> Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN)</li><li> Leased line</li><li> Cable </li><li> Digital Subscriber Line (DSL) </li><li> Frame Relay </li><li> Wireless</li></ul></p> <p>Each of these technologies provides advantages and disadvantages for the customer. Not all technologies are available in all locations.</p> <p>When a service provider receives data, it must forward this data to other remote sites for final delivery to the recipient. These remote sites connect either to the ISP network or pass from ISP to ISP to the recipient. Long-range communications are usually those connections between ISPs or between branch offices in very large companies. </p> <p>Many different WAN technologies exist that allow the service provider to reliably forward data over great distances. Some of these include ATM, satellite, Frame Relay, and leased lines.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107010502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3583479112">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010502/cm3583479112.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010502/cm3583479112text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Enterprises are becoming larger and more dispersed. As a result, applications require more and more bandwidth. This growth requires technologies that support high-speed and high-bandwidth transfer of data over even greater distances. </p> <p>Synchronous Optical Network (<content-link target="{727FC18E-1AE8-4192-ABD1-377C25993C5C}" type="glossary">SONET</content-link>) and Synchronous Digital Hierarchy (<content-link target="{F51481B4-E48A-49F3-9D04-A84B175026F0}" type="glossary">SDH</content-link>) are standards that allow the movement of large amounts of data over great distances through fiber-optic cables. Both SONET and SDH encapsulate earlier digital transmission standards and support either ATM or Packet over SONET/SDH (<content-link target="{D81BD8E6-0EA0-48EA-91A8-A9928759A5BA}" type="glossary">POS</content-link>) networking. SDH and SONET are used for moving both voice and data.</p> <p>One of the newer developments for extremely long-range communications is dense wavelength division multiplexing (<content-link target="{9B204B8F-93B7-441B-AC71-A158E1F25076}" type="glossary">DWDM</content-link>). DWDM assigns incoming optical signals to specific frequencies or wavelengths of light. It is also capable of amplifying these wavelengths to boost the signal strength. DWDM can multiplex more than 80 different wavelengths or channels of data onto a single piece of fiber. Each channel is capable of carrying a multiplexed signal at 2.5 Gbps. </p> <p>De-multiplexed data at the receiving end allows a single piece of fiber to carry many different formats at the same time and at different data rates. For example, DWDM can carry IP, SONET, and ATM data concurrently.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107010503">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm4862726427">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010503/cm4862726427.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107010000/en1107010500/en1107010503/cm4862726427text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Match the technology to the description. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1107020000">
<title><content-text>Comparing Common WAN Encapsulations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107020100">
<title><content-text>Ethernet and WAN Encapsulations</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4600119378">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020101/cm4600119378.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020101/cm4600119378text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Encapsulation occurs before data travels across a WAN. The encapsulation conforms to a specific format based on the technology used on the network. Before converting data into bits for transmission across the media, Layer 2 encapsulation adds addressing and control information. </p> <p>Layer 2 adds header information that is specific to the type of physical network transmission. Within a LAN environment, Ethernet is the most common technology. The Data Link Layer encapsulates the packet into Ethernet frames. The frame headers contain information such as the source and destination MAC addresses, and specific Ethernet controls, like the frame size and timing information.</p> <p>Similarly, the encapsulation of frames destined for transmission across a WAN link match the technology in use on the link. For example, if using Frame Relay on the link, the type of encapsulation required is Frame Relay-specific.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020102">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm3378266747">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020102/cm3378266747.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020102/cm3378266747text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The type of Data Link Layer encapsulation is separate from the type of Network Layer encapsulation. As data moves across a network, the Data Link Layer encapsulation may change continuously, whereas the Network Layer encapsulation will not. If this packet must move across the WAN on its way to the final destination, the Layer 2 encapsulation changes to match the technology in use.</p> <p>Packets exit the LAN by way of the default gateway router. The router strips off the Ethernet frame and then re-encapsulates that data into the correct frame type for the WAN. Conversion of frames received on the WAN interface into the Ethernet frame format occurs before placement on the local network. The router acts as a <content-link target="{D9606409-75DD-43BE-AB88-E82E5CDE5E6D}" type="glossary">media converter</content-link>, by adapting the Data Link Layer frame format to a format that is appropriate to the interface. </p> <p>The encapsulation type must match on both ends of a point-to-point connection. A Data Link Layer encapsulation includes the following fields:</p> <p><b>Flag</b></p> <p><ul><li> Marks the beginning and end of each frame</li></ul></p> <p><b>Address</b></p> <p><ul><li> Depends on the encapsulation type </li><li> Not required If the WAN link is point-to-point</li></ul></p> <p><b>Control</b></p> <p><ul><li> Used to indicate the type of frame</li></ul></p> <p><b>Protocol</b></p> <p><ul><li> Used to specify the type of encapsulated network layer protocol</li><li> Not present in all WAN encapsulations</li></ul></p> <p><b>Data</b></p> <p><ul><li> Used as Layer 3 data and IP datagram</li></ul></p> <p><b>Frame Check Sequence (FCS)</b></p> <p><ul><li> Provides a mechanism to verify that the frame was not damaged in transit</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107020103">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6548559860">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020103/cm6548559860.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020100/en1107020103/cm6548559860text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the Layer 2 encapsulation term to its definition.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107020200">
<title><content-text>HDLC and PPP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7108589323">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020201/cm7108589323.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020201/cm7108589323text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Two of the most common serial line Layer 2 encapsulations are HDLC and PPP.</p> <p>High-level Data Link Control (HDLC) is a standard <content-link target="{B7929B46-4DF4-48DA-B0EE-1F0F7DE8BEFB}" type="glossary">bit-oriented</content-link> Data Link Layer encapsulation. HDLC uses synchronous serial transmission, which provides error-free communication between two points. HDLC defines a Layer 2 framing structure that allows for flow control and error control using acknowledgments and a windowing scheme. Each frame has the same format, whether it is a data frame or a control frame. </p> <p>The standard HDLC frame does not contain a field that identifies the type of protocol carried by the frame. For that reason, standards-based HDLC cannot handle multiple protocols across a single link. </p> <p>Cisco HDLC incorporates an extra field, known as the <content-link target="{E18184DE-B53D-4FD6-9230-D3167BDF5327}" type="glossary">Type field</content-link>, which allows multiple Network Layer protocols to share the same link. Use Cisco HDLC encapsulation only when interconnecting Cisco equipment. Cisco HDLC is the default Data Link Layer encapsulation type on Cisco serial links.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4476524444">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020202/cm4476524444.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020202/cm4476524444text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Like HDLC, Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP) is a Data Link Layer encapsulation for serial links. It uses a layered architecture to encapsulate and carry multi-protocol <content-link target="{D317039E-28E9-474C-8808-2180C968A1F3}" type="glossary">datagram</content-link>s over a point-to-point link. Because PPP is standards-based, it enables communication between equipment of different vendors. </p> <p>The following interfaces can support PPP:</p> <p><ul><li> Asynchronous serial </li><li> Synchronous serial </li><li> High-Speed Serial Interface (HSSI) </li><li> Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN) </li></ul></p> <p>PPP has two sub-protocols:</p> <p><ul><li> Link Control Protocol - responsible for establishing, maintaining and terminating the point-to-point link.</li><li> Network Control Protocol - provides interaction with different Network layer protocols. </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020203">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8910578693">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020203/cm8910578693.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020203/cm8910578693text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Link Control Protocol</b></p> <p>PPP uses the Link Control Protocol (<content-link target="{3CF41EEB-CFF7-414D-B222-55CB418B162B}" type="glossary">LCP</content-link>) to establish, maintain, test, and terminate the point-to-point link. Additionally, LCP negotiates and configures control options on the WAN link. Some of the options that LCP negotiates include:</p> <p><ul><li> Authentication </li><li> Compression </li><li> Error detection </li><li> Multilink </li><li> PPP Callback</li></ul></p> <p>LCP also: </p> <p><ul><li> Handles varied packet sizes </li><li> Detects common misconfiguration errors </li><li> Determines when a link is functioning properly and when it is failing</li></ul></p> <p><b>Network Control Protocol</b></p> <p>PPP uses the Network Control Protocol (<content-link target="{735C84DF-FF67-4355-B799-00D2BD2742F9}" type="glossary">NCP</content-link>) component to encapsulate multiple Network Layer protocols, so that they operate on the same communications link. </p> <p>Every Network Layer protocol carried on the PPP link requires a separate NCP. For example, IP uses the IP Control Protocol (<content-link target="{689FA421-F54E-484F-8747-F242DE42643B}" type="glossary">IPCP</content-link>), and IPX uses the IPX Control Protocol (<content-link target="{7FBEA097-4D24-4AFE-9B4F-FAAE2EB4854A}" type="glossary">IPXCP</content-link>). NCPs include fields containing codes that indicate the Network Layer protocol. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020204">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2728321742">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020204/cm2728321742.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020204/cm2728321742text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>PPP sessions progress through three phases: link establishment, authentication (optional), and Network Layer protocol. </p> <p><b>Link-Establishment Phase</b></p> <p>PPP sends LCP frames to configure and test the data link. LCP frames contain a configuration option field that negotiates options such as maximum transmission unit (MTU), compression, and link-authentication. If a configuration option is missing, it assumes the default value. Link authentication and link-quality determination tests are optional parameters within the link-establishment phase. A link-quality determination test determines whether the link quality is good enough to bring up Network Layer protocols. Optional parameters, such as these, must be complete before the receipt of a configuration acknowledgment frame. Receipt of the configuration acknowledgement frame completes the Link-Establishment phase. </p> <p><b>Authentication Phase (optional)</b></p> <p>The authentication phase provides password protection to identify connecting routers. Authentication occurs after the two routers agree to the set parameters but before the NCP Negotiation Phase can begin. </p> <p><b>NCP Negotiation Phase</b></p> <p>PPP sends NCP packets to choose and configure one or more Network Layer protocols, such as IP or IPX. If LCP closes the link, it informs the Network Layer protocols so that they can take appropriate action. The <span class="cmd">show interfaces</span> command reveals the LCP and NCP states.</p> <p>When established, the PPP link remains active until the LCP or NCP frames close the link or until an activity timer expires. A user can also terminate the link.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107020205">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4032300171">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020205/cm4032300171.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020200/en1107020205/cm4032300171text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Identify the correct location of the PPP components.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107020300">
<title><content-text>Configuring PPP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7700272080">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020301/cm7700272080.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020301/cm7700272080text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>On Cisco routers, HDLC is the default encapsulation on serial links. To change the encapsulation and use the features and functions of PPP, use the following command:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>encapsulation ppp</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Enables PPP encapsulation on a serial interface.</li></ul></p> <p>Once PPP is enabled, optional features such as compression and load balancing can be configured. </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>compress <i>[predictor | stac]</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Enables compression on an interface using either predictor or stacker.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ppp multilink</b> </span></p> <p><ul><li> Configures load balancing across multiple links.</li></ul></p> <p>Compressing data sent across the network can improve network performance. Predictor and stacker are software compression techniques that vary in the way compression is handled. Stacker compression is more CPU-intensive and less memory-intensive. Predictor is more memory-intensive and less CPU-intensive. For this reason, generally use stacker if the bottleneck is due to line bandwidth issues and predictor if the bottleneck is due to excessive load on the router. </p> <p>Only use compression if network performance issues exist because enabling it will increase router processing times and overhead. Also, do not use compression if the majority of traffic crossing the network is already-compressed files. Compressing an already-compressed file often increases its size. </p> <p>Enabling PPP multilink allows for multiple WAN links to be aggregated into one logical channel for the transport of traffic. It enables the load-balancing of traffic from different links and allows some level of redundancy in case of a line failure on a single link.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020302">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2883070285">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020302/cm2883070285.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020302/cm2883070285text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The following commands are used to verify and troubleshoot HDLC and PPP encapsulation: </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show interfaces serial</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Displays the encapsulation and the states of the Link Control Protocol (LCP). </li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>show controllers</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Indicates the state of the interface channels and whether a cable is attached to the interface. </li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>debug serial interface</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Verifies the incrementation of keepalive packets. If packets are not incrementing, a possible timing problem exists on the interface card or in the network.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>debug ppp</b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Provides information about the various stages of the PPP process, including negotiation and authentication.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4659015899">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020303/cm4659015899/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020300/en1107020303/cm4659015899/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure and verify a PPP connection between two routers.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107020400">
<title><content-text>PPP Authentication</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4451540572">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020401/cm4451540572.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020401/cm4451540572text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Authentication on a PPP link is optional. If configured, authentication occurs after establishment of the link but before the Network Layer protocol configuration phase begins. Two possible types of authentication on a PPP link are Password Authentication Protocol (<content-link target="{20E48E1E-A04F-4084-8BF2-69A3A5773439}" type="glossary">PAP</content-link>) and Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol (<content-link target="{05B8E31F-6DEC-4C07-8E73-90BFB5E6A022}" type="glossary">CHAP</content-link>).</p> <p>PAP provides a simple method for a remote device to establish its identity. PAP uses a <content-link target="{FD2CA046-AC1C-466A-A5A2-04D404459E3A}" type="glossary">two-way handshake</content-link> to send its username and password. The called device looks up the username of the calling device and confirms that the sent password matches what it has stored in its database. If the two passwords match, authentication is successful.</p> <p>PAP sends the username/password pair across the link repeatedly in clear text until acknowledgement of the authentication or termination of the connection. This authentication method does not protect the username and password from being stolen using a packet sniffer.</p> <p>Additionally, the remote node is in control of the frequency and timing of the login attempts. Once authenticated, no further verification of the remote device occurs. Without ongoing verification, the link is vulnerable to <content-link target="{8AA551AF-BFC0-4A09-9F49-DEDD666D5DED}" type="glossary">hijacking</content-link> of the authenticated connection and the possibility of a hacker gaining illegal authorized access to the router using a <content-link target="{AF0317E4-63D0-406D-8C03-49DA11FDE589}" type="glossary">replay attack</content-link>.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020402">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6904192842">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020402/cm6904192842.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020402/cm6904192842text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another form of PPP authentication is Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol (CHAP).</p> <p><b>Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol</b></p> <p>CHAP is a more secure authentication process than PAP. CHAP does not send the password across the link. Authentication occurs both during initial link establishment and repeatedly during the time the link is active. The called device is in control of the frequency and timing of the authentication, making a hijack attack extremely unlikely.</p> <p>CHAP uses a <content-link target="{3553C5BC-0C2E-4125-AECD-AF76B2BDA9DB}" type="glossary">three-way handshake</content-link>. </p> <p>1. PPP establishes the link phase. </p> <p>2. Local router sends a <content-link target="{DC65C762-7DC7-48FF-87E0-D5571F120540}" type="glossary">challenge message</content-link> to the remote router. </p> <p>3. Remote router uses the challenge and a <content-link target="{B4AC8640-39A5-4BAB-92AB-C6DFA083255A}" type="glossary">shared secret</content-link> password to generate a one-way hash. </p> <p>4. Remote router sends back one-way hash to the local router. </p> <p>5. Local router checks the response against its own calculation, using the challenge and the same shared secret.</p> <p>6. Local router acknowledges authentication if values match. </p> <p>7. Local router immediately terminates connection if the values do not match. </p> <p>CHAP provides protection against playback attack through a variable challenge value. Because the challenge is unique and random, the resulting hash value is also unique and random. The use of repeated challenges limits the time of exposure to any single attack. The local router or a third-party <content-link target="{787C27C4-6E1F-4674-80C4-4CF6BEC2B632}" type="glossary">authentication server</content-link> is in control of the frequency and timing of the challenges.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107020403">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm4155425497">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020403/cm4155425497.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020400/en1107020403/cm4155425497text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Activity</p> <p>Sort the characteristics as belonging to either PAP or CHAP.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107020500">
<title><content-text>Configuring PAP and CHAP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020501">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8885694232">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020501/cm8885694232.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020501/cm8885694232text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To configure authentication on a PPP link, use the global configuration commands:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>username <i>name</i> password <i>password</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Global configuration command. </li><li>Creates a local database that contains the username and password of the remote device. </li><li>The username must match the hostname of the remote router exactly and is case sensitive.</li></ul></p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ppp authentication <i>{chap | chap pap | pap chap | pap}</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li> Interface configuration command. </li><li>Specifies the type of authentication on each interface, such as PAP or CHAP. </li><li>If more than one type is specified, example <span class="cmd"><b>chap pap</b></span>, the router attempts the first type listed and will only attempt the second if the remote router suggests it.</li></ul></p> <p>For CHAP authentication, no other configuration commands are required. However, in Cisco IOS version 11.1 or later, PAP is disabled on the interface by default. This means that the router will not send its own username and password combination just because PAP authentication is enable. Therefore, additional commands are required for PAP:</p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>ppp pap sent-username <i>name</i> password <i>password</i></b></span></p> <p><ul><li>Interface configuration command. </li><li>Specifies the local username and password combination that should be sent to the remote router. </li><li>This must match what the remote router has configured in the local username and password database.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020502">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm9760649123">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020502/cm9760649123.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020502/cm9760649123text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>With two-way authentication configured, each router authenticates the other. Use <span class="cmd"><b>debug</b></span> commands on both routers to display the exchange sequence as it occurs. </p> <p><span class="cmd"><b>debug ppp </b><i>{authentication | packet | error | negotiation | chap }</i></span></p> <p><b>Authentication </b></p> <p>Displays the authentication exchange sequence</p> <p><b>Packet </b></p> <p>Displays PPP packets sent and received</p> <p><b>Negotiation </b></p> <p>Displays packets transmitted during PPP startup, where PPP options are negotiated</p> <p><b>Error</b></p> <p>Displays protocol errors and statistics associated with PPP connection and negotiation</p> <p><b>Chap</b></p> <p>Displays CHAP packet exchanges</p> <p>To turn off <span class="cmd"><b>debug</b></span>, use the <span class="cmd"><b>no</b></span> format of each command.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107020503">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3838873473">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020503/cm3838873473/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1107000000/en1107020000/en1107020500/en1107020503/cm3838873473/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure and verify PAP and CHAP authentication on a PPP link.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1107030000">
<title><content-text>Using Frame Relay</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107030100">
<title><content-text>Overview of Frame Relay</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4519697436">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030100/en1107030101/cm4519697436.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030100/en1107030101/cm4519697436text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A common Layer 2 WAN encapsulation is Frame Relay. Frame Relay networks are multi-access networks similar to Ethernet except that they do not forward broadcast traffic. Frame Relay is a nonbroadcast multi-access network (NBMA).</p> <p>Frame Relay uses packet switching technology with variable length packets. It also makes use of STDM for optimum use of the available bandwidth.</p> <p>The router, or DTE device, normally connects to the service provider via a leased line. It connects via a Frame Relay switch, or DCE device, to the nearest point-of-presence of the service provider. This connection is an <content-link target="{53782D83-D1CF-4EE4-9BC0-F662199896BE}" type="glossary">access link</content-link>. </p> <p>The remote router at the destination end of the network is also a DTE device. The connection between the two DTE devices is a virtual circuit (<content-link target="{D633720B-3C01-4F3A-BA0E-AC8D005F826C}" type="glossary">VC</content-link>). </p> <p>The virtual circuit is typically established using PVCs that the service provider preconfigures. Most service providers discourage or even disallow the use of SVCs in a Frame Relay network.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1107030200">
<title><content-text>Frame Relay Functionality</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107030201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm3925491033">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030201/cm3925491033.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030201/cm3925491033text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In an NBMA network, each virtual circuit requires a Layer 2 address for identification. In Frame Relay, this address is the data-link connection identifier (<content-link target="{E4CF378D-0E65-4C6B-8E0D-9D4D93F3C6E9}" type="glossary">DLCI</content-link>). </p> <p>The DLCI identifies the VC that data uses to reach a particular destination. The DLCI is stored in the address field of every frame transmitted. The DLCI usually has only local significance and may be different at each end of a VC. </p> <p>The Layer 2 DLCI is associated with the Layer 3 address of the device at the other end of the VC. Mapping the DLCI to a remote IP address can occur manually or dynamically using a process known as <content-link target="{97D5FDEE-4068-4538-BC23-0AF99567425C}" type="glossary">Inverse ARP</content-link>.</p> <p>Establishing a mapping of DLCI to remote IP address occurs in the following steps:</p> <p>1. The local device announces its presence by sending its Layer 3 address out on the VC.</p> <p>2. The remote device receives this information and maps the Layer 3 IP address to the local Layer 2 DLCI.</p> <p>3. The remote device announces its IP address on the VC. </p> <p>4. The local device maps the Layer 3 address of the remote device to the local DLCI on which it received the information.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3160540132">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030202/cm3160540132.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030202/cm3160540132text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Local Management Interface (<content-link target="{DF1BAEB0-4279-4609-A4E6-6D10739E96A4}" type="glossary">LMI</content-link>) is a signaling standard between the DTE and the Frame Relay switch. LMI reports the status of PVCs between devices.</p> <p>LMI messages provide communication and synchronization between the network and the user device. They periodically report the existence of new PVCs and the deletion of existing PVCs. They also provide information about PVC integrity. VC status messages prevent data being sent to PVCs that no longer exist.</p> <p>LMI provides VC connection status information that appears in the Frame Relay map table: </p> <p><b>Active State</b></p> <p><ul><li> The connection is active and routers can exchange data. </li></ul></p> <p><b>Inactive State</b></p> <p><ul><li> The local connection to the FR switch is working but the remote connection to the FR switch is not. </li></ul></p> <p><b>Deleted State</b></p> <p><ul><li> The local connection receives no LMI messages from the FR switch or there is no service between the CPE router and the FR switch.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107030203">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6484542414">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030203/cm6484542414.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030203/cm6484542414text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When an end user subscribes to a Frame Relay service, the user negotiates certain service parameters with the provider.</p> <p>One parameter is the committed information rate (<content-link target="{F3392FBD-44C5-489D-BBA7-4F85E8EF07B2}" type="glossary">CIR</content-link>). The CIR is the minimum bandwidth rate guaranteed by the provider for data on a VC. </p> <p>The service provider calculates the CIR as the average amount of data transmitted over a period of time. The calculated time interval is the committed time (<content-link target="{AA7C7642-8A97-4E5D-92F6-FFAD1A734C20}" type="glossary">Tc</content-link>). The number of committed bits within the Tc is the committed burst (<content-link target="{4E3DCFB4-7303-4C4E-B882-5B8725743E3D}" type="glossary">Bc</content-link>). The cost of the Frame Relay service depends on the speed of the link and the CIR.</p> <p>The CIR defines the minimum rate provided; however, if there is no congestion on the links, the service provider boosts or bursts the bandwidth up to a second agreed-upon bandwidth. </p> <p>The excess information rate (<content-link target="{1AA66098-E966-4746-8422-5C1B8F1C434C}" type="glossary">EIR</content-link>) is the average rate above the CIR that a VC can support when no network congestion exists. Any extra bits above the committed burst, up to the maximum speed of the access link, is known as the excess burst (<content-link target="{1111CA11-0EE6-4906-88E6-84DBFD9F43A4}" type="glossary">Be</content-link>). </p> <p>Frames transmitted above the speed of the CIR are uncommitted, but are forwarded if the network supports it. These extra fames are marked as discard eligible (<content-link target="{81D2813F-0546-43C1-8FB8-6E67B1E71925}" type="glossary">DE</content-link>). If congestion occurs, the provider first drops frames with the DE bit set. </p> <p>Users often pay for a lower CIR, counting on the fact that the service provider supplies higher bandwidth and bursts their traffic when there is no congestion.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107030204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8478607137">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030204/cm8478607137.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030204/cm8478607137text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The forward explicit congestion notification (<content-link target="{9967B05F-0105-488F-BB06-F45E6A9B8806}" type="glossary">FECN</content-link>) is a single-bit field that can be set to a value of 1 by a switch. It indicates to an end DTE device that the network is congested ahead. </p> <p>The backward explicit congestion notification (<content-link target="{2C5B88B5-749D-46FE-A35E-4C1EFAA252F5}" type="glossary">BECN</content-link>) is a single-bit field that, when set to a value of 1 by a switch, indicates that the network is congested in the opposite direction. </p> <p>FECN and BECN allow higher-layer protocols to react intelligently to these congestion indicators. For example, the sending device uses BECNs to slow its transmission rate.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107030205">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm9719146212">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030205/cm9719146212.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107030000/en1107030200/en1107030205/cm9719146212text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the term to the definition.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1107040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1107040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm9541802169">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107040000/en1107040100/en1107040101/cm9541802169.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1107000000/en1107040000/en1107040100/en1107040101/cm9541802169text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1107050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1107050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1107050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm6613375260">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1107000000/en1107050000/en1107050100/en1107050101/cm6613375260/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1107000000/en1107050000/en1107050100/en1107050101/cm6613375260/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
