<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 15:11:08">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.7.1  - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.	Switch 1 and switch 2 are both configured with ports in the Marketing, Sales, Production, and Admin V LAN's. Each V LAN contains 12 users. How many different subnetworks are needed to address V LAN's?<br>A.	1<br>B.	2<br>C.	4<br>D.	8<br>E.	12<br>F.	24<br><br>2.	What mechanism is used to achieve the separation between different V LANs as they cross a trunk link?<br>A.	V LAN tagging using 8 0 2 dot 1Q protocol<br>B.	V LAN tagging using 8 0 2 dot 1p protocol<br>C.	V LAN multiplexing<br>D.	V LAN set as native V LAN<br><br>3.	What are two options to consider when configuring a trunk between two switches? (Choose two.)<br>A.	The switchport no negotiate command must be configured for trunks that use DTP.<br>B.	Port security cannot be configured on the trunk interfaces.<br>C.	The native V LAN must be the same on both ends of the trunk.<br>D.	Different encapsulation types can be configured on both ends of the trunk link.<br>E.	Trunk ports can only be configured on the Gigabit Ethernet ports.<br><br>4.	A 12-port switch has been configured to support three V LAN's named Sales, Marketing, and Finance. Each V LAN spans four ports on the switch. The network administrator has deleted the Marketing V LAN from the switch. Which two statements describe the status of the ports associated with this V LAN? (Choose two.)<br>A.	The ports are inactive.<br>B.	The ports are administratively disabled.<br>C.	The ports become trunks to carry data from all remaining V LAN's.<br>D.	The ports remain part of the Marketing V LAN until reassigned to another V LAN.<br>E.	The ports are released from the Marketing V LAN and automatically reassigned to V LAN 1.<br><br>5.	Which three statements are true about hosts configured in the same V LAN? (Choose three.)<br>A.	Hosts in the same V LAN must be on the same IP subnet.<br>B.	Hosts in different V LAN's can communicate with the aid of only the Layer 2 switch.<br>C.	Hosts in the same V LAN share the same broadcast domain.<br>D.	Hosts in the same V LAN share the same collision domain.<br>E.	Hosts in the same V LAN comply with the same security policy.<br>F.	Hosts in the same V LAN must be on the same physical segment.<br><br>6.	Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question:<br>Two switches, S1 and S2, are connected together. Each switch has two V LAN's defined. On switch S1, V LAN 1 and V LAN 2 are defined. On switch S2, V LAN 2 and V LAN 3 are defined. Host A on S1 is in V LAN 1. Host B on S1 is in V LAN 2. Host C on S2 is in V LAN 2. Host D on S2 is in V LAN 3.<br><br>Host C is unable to transfer data because it does not have the MAC address of the destination host. If Host C sends out an ARP request, which of the other hosts will see this message?<br>A.	Host A<br>B.	Host B<br>C.	Hosts A and B<br>D.	Hosts A and D<br>E.	Hosts B and D<br>F.	Hosts A, B, and D<br><br>7.	Match the characteristics listed to the type of V LAN, static or dynamic.<br>Characteristics:<br>A. Each port is associated with a specific V LAN.<br>B. Manual configuration of port assignments required.<br>C. Ports work out their own configuration.<br>D. Less administrative overheard when users are moved.<br>E. Requires administrator interaction when users move.<br>F. Configuration based on database.<br><br>V LAN Type:<br>One. Static V LAN<br>Two. Dynamic V LAN<br><br>8.	Match the V LAN related option to the appropriate category.<br>Options:<br>A. 1 to 1005<br>B. 1006 to 4094<br>C. Not learned by VT <br>D. Default management V LAN<br>E. All ports are a member by default<br>F. Contains reserved V LAN's for Token Ring and FDDI<br><br>Categories:<br>One. Normal range V LAN<br>Two: Extended range V LAN<br>Three: V LAN 1<br><br>9.	Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question:<br>Two switches, S1 and S2, are connected together using a trunk link between S1 F0/1 and S2 F0/2. Each switch has two V LAN's defined, V LAN 10 and V LAN 20. Host B and two unlabelled hosts on S1 are in V LAN 10. Host A and one unlabelled host on S1 are also in V LAN 10. There is an unlabelled host in VLAN 20 on each switch.<br><br>Brand new switches with empty CAM tables are interconnected via a trunk link. All hosts on both switches are configured with the V LAN memberships described above. How is a frame sent from Host A forwarded to Host B?<br>A.	Switch S1 floods the message from Host A to all hosts attached to S1.<br>B.	Switch S1 floods the message from Host A to all hosts attached to both switches.<br>C.	Switch S1 tags the frame with V LAN ID 10 and floods the frame to all hosts on switch S2.<br>D.	Switch S1 tags the frame with V LAN ID 10 and floods the frame to all hosts on switch S2 that are members of V LAN 10.<br><br>10.	Refer to the following configuration commands issued on Switch_A to answer the question:<br><br>Switch_A#config terminal<br>Switch_A(config)#v lan 10<br>Switch_A(config-v lan)#name Accounting<br>Switch_A(config-v lan)#exit<br>Switch_A(config)#v lan 20<br>Switch_A(config-v lan)#name Marketing<br>Switch_A(config-v lan)#exit<br>Switch_A(config)#interface fast ethernet 0/4<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport mode access<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport access v lan 10<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#interface fast ethernet 0/5<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport mode access<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport access v lan 20<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#interface fast ethernet 0/6<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport mode access<br>Switch_A(config-i f)#switchport access v lan 10<br><br>Host1 is connected to port F0/4 with an IP address of 192.168.1.22 /28. Host2 is connected to port F0/5 with an IP address of 192.168.1.33 /28. Host3 is connected to port F0/6 with an IP address of 192.168.1.30 /28.<br>Select the three statements that describe the success of pinging from one host to another. (Choose three.)<br>A.	Host1 can ping Host2.<br>B.	Host1 cannot ping Host2.<br>C.	Host1 can ping Host3.<br>D.	Host1 cannot ping Host3.<br>E.	Host2 can ping Host3.<br>F.	Host2 cannot ping Host3.<br><br>11.	Match the command to the associated description. (Not all options are used.)<br>Commands:<br>A. show v lan id<br>B. show v lan<br>C. show v lan brief<br>D. show interface F0/1 switchport<br>E. show interface F0/1<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Displays detailed information about all V LAN's on the switch.<br>Two. Displays V LAN information about a specific port.<br>Three. Displays information about a specific V LAN.<br><br>12.	Match the command to the associated description.<br>Commands:<br>A. switchport mode trunk<br>B. switchport mode dynamic desirable<br>C. switchport nonnegotiate<br>D. switchport mode access<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Configures the port to negotiate a trunk.<br>Two. Configures the trunk to not send DTP packets.<br>Three. Configures the port as a permanent 802 dot 1q trunk.<br>Four. Disables trunk mode.<br><br>13.	Match the term to the associated description.<br>Terms:<br>A. Native V LAN mismatch<br>B. Trunk mode mismatch<br>C. Incorrect V LAN list<br>D. V LAN subnet conflict<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Both switches are configured to dynamic auto and will not negotiate a link.<br>Two. Not all the V LAN's needed are allowed to transverse a trunk.<br>Three. Two V LAN's are sharing the same address space.<br>Four. The V LAN configured for untagged frames is not the same on two switches connected by a trunk.<br><br>14.	Match the V LAN port membership statement to the correct option.<br><br>Statements:<br>A. Access port attached to a PC, configured to use one V LAN for voice traffic and another V LAN for data traffic.<br>B. Port on a switch that maintains its assigned V LAN configuration until it is changed manually.<br>C. Port on a switch using VMPS and associates a port to a V LAN based on the destination MAC address.<br>D. Port on a switch that can change the manually assigned V LAN configuration dynamically.<br>E. Access port attached to an IP phone, configured to use one V LAN for voice traffic and another V LAN for data traffic.<br>F. Port on a switch using VMPS and associates a port to a V LAN based on the source MAC address.<br><br>Options:<br>One. Static V LAN port membership<br>Two. Dynamic V LAN port membership<br>Three. Voice V LAN port membership]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
