<textcomponents><component id="Button1"><text><![CDATA[<b>Optimize Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Operate Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button3"><text><![CDATA[<b>Implement Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button4"><text><![CDATA[<b>Design Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button5"><text><![CDATA[<b>Plan Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button6"><text><![CDATA[<b>Prepare Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Inst"><text><![CDATA[Click the buttons to learn more about each phase of the lifecycle.]]></text></component><component id="Title1"><text><![CDATA[<b>Optimize Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table1"><text><![CDATA[The Optimize Phase involves proactive management of the network. The goal of proactive management is to identify and resolve issues before they affect the organization. In the PPDIOO process, the Optimize Phase may prompt a recommendation for network redesign. Redesign may be necessary if too many network problems or errors arise, if performance does not meet expectations, or if new applications are identified to support organizational and technical requirements.]]></text></component><component id="Title2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Operate Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table2"><text><![CDATA[Operation is the final test of the appropriateness of the design. The Operate Phase involves maintaining network health through day-to-day operations, including maintaining high availability and reducing expenses. The fault detection, correction, and performance monitoring that occur in daily operations provide initial data for the Optimize Phase.]]></text></component><component id="Title3"><text><![CDATA[<b>Implement Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table3"><text><![CDATA[After the design has been approved, implementation (and verification) begins. The network is built, or additional components are incorporated, according to the design specifications. The goal is to integrate devices without disrupting the existing network or creating points of vulnerability.]]></text></component><component id="Title4"><text><![CDATA[<b>Design Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table4"><text><![CDATA[The initial requirements that were derived in the Plan Phase drive the activities of the network design specialists. The network design specification is a comprehensive, detailed design that meets current business and technical requirements. It incorporates specifications to support scalability, availability, security, and manageability. The design specification is the basis for the implementation activities.]]></text></component><component id="Title5"><text><![CDATA[<b>Plan Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table5"><text><![CDATA[The Plan Phase involves identifying initial network requirements based on goals, facilities, user needs, and other factors. This phase involves characterizing sites and assessing any existing networks. It also includes performing a gap analysis to determine whether the existing system infrastructure, sites, and operational environment are able to support the proposed system. A project plan is useful to help manage the tasks, responsibilities, critical milestones, and resources required to implement changes to the network. The project plan should align with the scope, cost, and resource parameters established in the original business requirements.]]></text></component><component id="Title6"><text><![CDATA[<b>Prepare Phase</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table6"><text><![CDATA[During the Prepare phase of the lifecycle, organizations create a business case for the network upgrade. This includes how the network can support the goals of the organization, as well as the financial justification for adding new technolgies and services.  The Prepare Phase can establish a financial justification for network strategy by assessing the business case for the proposed architecture.]]></text></component></textcomponents>