<transcript lastedited="11.06.08 06:11:45">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.1.1  - Introducing Inter-V LAN Routing]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts traditional inter-V LAN routing using two router interfaces. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Three switches, S1, S2 and S 3, are interconnected in a full mesh using dual trunk links between switches. Switch S1 is connected to router R1 using two links and two router interfaces. Device connections are as follows:<br>- Switch S1 Port F0/1 is connected to S2 Port F0/1 (Trunk).<br>- Switch S1 Port F0/2 is connected to S2 Port F0/2 (Trunk).<br>- Switch S1 Port F0/5 (V LAN 30) is connected to R1 Port F0/1.<br>- Switch S1 Port F0/6 (V LAN 10) is connected to R1 Port F0/0.<br>- Switch S2 Port F0/3 is connected to S 3 Port F0/1 (Trunk).<br>- Switch S2 Port F0/4 is connected to S 3 Port F0/2 (Trunk).<br>- Switch S2 Port F0/11 is connected to PC1 with IP address 172.17.10.21 (V LAN 10). <br>- Switch S2 Port F0/18 is connected to PC2 with IP address 172.17.20.22 (V LAN 20). <br>- Switch S2 Port F0/6 is connected to PC3 with IP address 172.17.30.23 (V LAN 30). <br>- Switch S 3 Port F0/4 is connected to S1 Port F0/4 (Trunk).<br>- Switch S 3 Port F0/3 is connected to S1 Port F0/3 (Trunk).<br><br>Scenario:<br>PC1 (in V LAN 10) sends a unicast frame to PC3 (in V LAN 30) via switches S2 and S1 and router R1, using two router interfaces.<br><br>Animation sequence:<br>One. PC1 sends unicast traffic destined for PC3 to switch S2 on V LAN 10. Switch S2 tags the frame with V LAN ID 10. S2 then forwards the frame through the trunk interface to switch S1. <br><br>Two. Switch S1 removes the V LAN tag and then forwards the unicast traffic to router R1 on interface F0/0. <br><br>Three. The router routes the unicast traffic to its interface F0/1, which is connected to V LAN 30. <br><br>Four. The router forwards the unicast traffic to switch S1 on V LAN 30. <br><br>Five. Switch S1 forwards the unicast traffic to switch S2 through the trunk link. S2 tags the frame with V LAN ID 30. S2 can then forward the unicast traffic to PC3 on V LAN 30.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
