<transcript lastedited="03.30.09 10:03:16">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.10.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Match the Ethernet frame field to the proper function.<br>Fields:<br>A. Preamble (7 Bytes) and Start of Frame Delimiter (1 Byte)<br>B. Frame Checksum Sequence (4 Bytes)<br>C. Destination Address (6 Bytes)<br>D. Source Address (6 Bytes)<br>E. Length/Type (2 Bytes)<br>F. 8 0 2 dot 2 Header and Data (46 to 1500 Bytes)<br><br>Functions:<br>1. Contains the encapsulated data from a higher layer.<br>2. Identifies the intended recipient.<br>3. Value equal to or greater than 0x0600 indicates the encapsulated protocol.<br>5. Used for synchronization between the sending and receiving devices.<br>6. Used to detect errors in a frame.<br>7. Identifies the frame's originating NIC or interface.<br><br>2.What is a primary function of CSMA/CD in an Ethernet network?<br>A.Assigns MAC addresses to hosts.<br>B.Defines the area in which collisions can occur.<br>C.Identifies the start and end of an Ethernet frame.<br>D.Provides a method to determine when and how hosts access the Ethernet medium.<br>E.Creates the header in the Ethernet frame as data is encapsulated.<br>F.Maps an IP address to a MAC address.<br><br>3.What technology is the IEEE 8 0 2 dot 3a c standard specifically designed to accommodate?<br>A.Simple Network Management Protocol<br>B.Address Resolution Protocol<br>C.Virtual Local Area Network<br>D.Voice over IP<br>E.Internet Control Message Protocol<br><br>4.What is the purpose of media access control?<br>A.It identifies which workstation has sent a frame.<br>B.It determines which Layer 3 protocol should handle a frame.<br>C.It identifies which Ethernet frame format to use on the network.<br>D.It determines which workstation on a shared medium LAN is allowed to transmit data.<br><br>5.How are collisions detected on an Ethernet network?<br>A.Stations identify the altered FCS field on the colliding packets.<br>B.The signal amplitude on the networking media is higher than normal.<br>C.Traffic on the network cannot be detected due to a blockage.<br>D.The signal amplitude on the networking media is lower than normal.<br><br>6.Which Layer 2 sublayer provides service to the network layer of the O S I Model?<br>A.FCS<br>B.IEEE 8 0 2 dot 3<br>C.LLC<br>D.MAC<br><br>7.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Diagram description:<br>A PC, a printer, and a router are connected to a hub. The router is also connected to the Internet. <br><br>Which devices in the diagram must have a MAC address?<br>A.Only the PC<br>B.Only the router<br>C.PC and router<br>D.PC, hub, and router<br>E.PC, printer, and router<br><br>8.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Diagram description:<br>Four PC's, Host A, Host B, Host C, and Host D, are connected to a hub. <br><br>Host A has reached 50% completion in sending a 1 KB Ethernet frame to Host D, when Host B wishes to transmit its own frame to Host C. What must Host B do?<br>A.Host B can transmit immediately since it is connected on its own cable segment.<br>B.Host B must wait to receive a CSMA transmission from the hub, to signal its turn.<br>C.Host B must send a request signal to Host A by transmitting an interframe gap.<br>D.Host B must wait until it is certain that Host A has completed sending its frame.<br><br>9.Which of the following are fields in an 8 0 2 dot 3 Ethernet frame? (Choose three.)<br>A.Source physical address<br>B.Source logical address<br>C.Media type identifier<br>D.Frame check sequence<br>E.Destination physical address<br>F.Destination logical address<br><br>10.What address type does a switch use to make selective forwarding decisions?<br>A.Source IP<br>B.Destination IP<br>C.Source MAC<br>D.Destination MAC]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
