<textcomponents>
 
					<!--<component id="title1_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b>Group 1</b>]]>
          </text>
          </component>
          <component id="title2_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b>Group 2</b>]]>
          </text>
          </component>
          <component id="title3_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b>Group 3</b>]]>
          </text>
          </component>
<component id="hub_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[192.168.0.0 /24<br/>192.168.1.0 /24<br/>192.168.2.0 /24<br/>192.168.3.0 /24]]>
          </text>
     </component>
<component id="switch1_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[172.16.0.0 /16<br/>172.17.0.0 /16]]>
          </text>
     </component>
<component id="switch2_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[10.3.5.64 /27<br/>10.3.5.96 /27<br/>10.3.5.128 /27<br/>10.3.5.160 /27<br/>10.3.5.192 /27<br/>10.3.5.224 /27]]>
          </text> 
     </component>
<component id="send_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b>Send</b>]]>
          </text>
     </component>
<component id="reset_txt">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b>Reset</b>]]>
          </text>
     </component>
     -->
     <component id="ID_more_details">
		<text><![CDATA[Show more details]]></text>
	</component>
	<component id="ID_business_goal">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Business Goal Summary:</b><br>1. Provide better atmosphere and<br>    safety<br>2. Reduce costs<br>3. Provide better customer service<br>4. Support growth]]></text>
	</component>
		<component id="ID_additional_info_title">
		<text><![CDATA[StadiumCompany Business Goals]]></text>
	</component>
	<component id="ID_additional_info">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>1. Provide better atmosphere and safety for people attending events.</b><br><li>Provide 24 hour service over the network and the web for the security video monitoring.</li><li>Automate the customer entry process with a computerized ticket scanning system.</li><li>Add additional wireless coverage to meet customer demand.</li><li>Improve the customer experience by providing customized services for different categories of customers.</li><li>Improve the vendor experience by streamlining the ordering of supplies and automating the customer order processes.</li><b>2. Reduce costs by consolidating the separate voice, video, and data networks.</b><li>Reduce telephony costs and add remote sites to the local telephone system.</li><li>Provide additional services, like voice and video, to the remote sites</li><b>3. Provide better customer service by improving the access to the website for viewing of schedules, purchasing and printing of tickets, and purchasing of merchandise.</b><li>Streamline the on-line ticket purchasing.</li><li>Improve server security and control access to network resources.</li><li>Create an on-line customer service site.</li><b>4. Support the growth of the StadiumCompany as it expands and add new types of entertainment, new partners, and new vendors.</b><li>The network design will support anticipated growth rates from 50% to 75%.</li><li>Minimize downtime as new services have new availability requirements.</li>]]></text>
	</component>
<component id="ID_activity">
          <text>
               <![CDATA[<b><font size='+2'>Activity</font></b><br><br>Based on the prioritized business goals of the StadiumCompany, make design decisions.<br><br><b>Select the higher priority design option for the StadiumCompany.</b>]]>
          </text>
     </component>
</textcomponents>