<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_setup">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Use this activity to check your understanding of the main points in this chapter.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_setup2">
<text><![CDATA[<ul><li>A series of questions will be presented. This is not a quiz and your answers are not recorded.</li><li>Click <b>Answer</b> to see the answer.</li><li>Click <b>Next Question</b> to go to the next question in the series.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="clickHere">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click Here<br/>to Begin</b>]]></text>
</component>



<!-- Question 1 -->
<component id="ID_Q1_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[1) <textformat blockindent='20'>Describe the organizational, social, and environmental benefits of teleworking.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[(from 6.1)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Organizational Benefits:</b><ul><li>Continuity of operations</li><li>Increased responsiveness </li><li>Secure, reliable, and manageable access to information </li><li>Cost effective integration of data, voice, video, and applications</li><li>Increased employee productivity, satisfaction, and retention</li></ul><b>Social Benefits:</b><ul><li>Increased employment opportunities for marginalized groups</li><li>Less traveling and commuter-related stress</li></ul><b>Environmental Benefits</b><ul><li>Reduced carbon footprints, both for individual workers and organizations</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 2 -->
<component id="ID_Q2_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[2) <textformat blockindent='20'>Describe the four main connection methods used by home and SOHO business.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[(from  6.2)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Dialup access: </b><ul><li>Dialup access is an inexpensive option that uses any phone line and a modem. </li><li>It is the slowest connection option, and is typically used in areas where higher speed connections are not available.</li></ul><b>DSL: </b><ul><li>DSL is more expensive than dialup, but provides a faster connection. </li><li>It also uses telephone lines, but unlike dialup access, DSL provides a continuous connection to the Internet. </li><li>This connection option uses a special high-speed modem that separates the DSL signal from the telephone signal and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or LAN.</li></ul><b>Cable modem: </b><ul><li>A cable modem is a connection option offered by cable television service providers. </li><li>The Internet signal is carried on the same coaxial cable that delivers cable television to homes and businesses.</li><li>A special cable modem separates the Internet signal from the other signals carried on the cable and provides an Ethernet connection to a host computer or LAN. </li></ul><b>Satellite: </b><ul><li>Satellite connection is an option offered by satellite service providers. </li><li>The user's computer connects through Ethernet to a satellite modem that transmits radio signals to the nearest POP within the satellite network.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 3 -->
<component id="ID_Q3_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[3) <textformat blockindent='20'>Describe the two types of VPN networks.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[(from  6.3)]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Site-to-Site VPNs:</b><ul><li>A site-to-site VPN is an extension of classic WAN networking and can connect a branch office network to a company headquarters network.</li><li>Hosts send and receive TCP/IP traffic through a VPN “gateway,” which could be a router, PIX firewall appliance, or an Adaptive Security Appliance (ASA). </li><li>The VPN gateway is responsible for encapsulating and encrypting outbound traffic for all of the traffic from a particular site and sending it through a VPN tunnel over the Internet to a peer VPN gateway at the target site.</li><li>On receipt, the peer VPN gateway strips the headers, decrypts the content, and relays the packet toward the target host inside its private network.</li></ul><b>Remote Access VPNs:</b><ul><li>Mobile users and telecommuters use remote access VPNs extensively.</li><li>Remote VPN connections typically take advantage of the broadband connections.</li><li>Each host typically has VPN client software that encapsulates and encrypts that traffic before sending it over the Internet to the VPN gateway at the edge of the target network.</li><li>On receipt, the VPN gateway handles the data in the same way as it would handle data from a site-to-site VPN.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_conclusion">
<text><![CDATA[<b>This concludes this chapter's Check Your Understanding questions.</b>]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>