<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">
<text>
<![CDATA[<b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b>]]>
</text>
</component> 

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Cisco Lifecycle Services is a six-phase approach to deploying and operating Cisco technologies.</li><br/><li>The six phases of the network lifecycle are:</li><br/><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='60'><li>Prepare</li><li>Plan</li><li>Design</li><li>Implement</li><li>Operate</li><li>Optimize</li></textformat><br/><li>In the Prepare phase, the business goals of the project are identified and a business case is created to justify the installation of the network upgrade.</li><br/><li>During the Plan phase, the network designer performs a comprehensive site and operations assessment of the current network.</li><br/><li>A project plan is created that includes the tasks, timelines, risks, responsibilites and the resources required to complete the network design project.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>



<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<li>In the Design phase, the designer creates a flexible design that can integrate new technologies into the current operations and existing network infrastructure.</li><br/><li>During the Implement phase, the network is built according to the approved design specifications and tested to ensure it meets the business goals and requirements.</li><br/><li>The Operate and Optimize phases of the network lifecycle are ongoing and represent the day-to-day operations of the network.</li><br/><li>Optimizing a network is a continuous process that identifies and resolves potential weaknesses before they become problems for network operations.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_TextTitle1">
<text><![CDATA[Physical Connections]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Internet]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Ticket Sales Office]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[ISP2]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[VPN<br>(over DSL)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[ISP3]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[Vendor<br>(Souvenir Shop)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[ISP1]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Edge Router]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[Stadium Switch]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[Team Switch]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[Vendor Switch]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[Luxury Suites Switch]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt13">
<text><![CDATA[VPN<br/>(over DSL)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt14">
<text><![CDATA[VPN<br/>(over DSL)]]></text>
</component>




<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Requests for Proposal (RFP) and Requests for Quotations (RFQ) solicit proposals from networking contractors to provide design services, equipment, installation and support.</li><br/><li>RFPs and RFQs provide information as to a company's business goals, requirements for new technologies and outline the process to follow to submit a proposal.</li><br/><li>Following the required format and schedule is critical to submitting a successful proposal to provide network services.</li><br/><li>A team of individuals from the networking contractor respond to the customer's request. This team includes an account manager, pre-sales system engineers, network designers and post-sales field engineers.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s3_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Websites are an additional media used for RFPs]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Account managers serve as the primary point of contact between their customers and the networking contractor.</li><br/><li>Pre-sales system engineers are responsible for assisting the account manager to determine the need for upgrades or additions to the current network.  They assist the network designers to ensure that the new equipment and services can integrate into the existing network.</li><br/><li>Network designers provide customers with a network design that meets the customer requirements for scalability, availability, security and manageability.</li><br/><li>Post-sales field engineers are responsible for the smooth installation of the network upgrade and ensure that the network functions as designed.</li><br/><li>All members of the networking contractor staff must demonstrate effective interpersonal skills in order to instill confidence in their abilities to provide the necessary network services.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Click the monitor to view the requirements for submitting and RFP.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Websites are an additional media used for RFPs]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<br><font size='12'><p align='center'><b>StadiumCompany Request for Proposal</b></p></font>

Applications will be accepted on or before December 1, 200X.  Proposals may be mailed or hand delivered.

Submit a signed original and one copy to:

Mr. Stewart
1 City Plaza, Suite 900
City, State Zip
Attn:  Stadium Improvement Project

For more information call (999) 999-9999

Formatting requirements:

1.Cover sheet on company letterhead that includes all relevant contact information, including the   
   name of the contact person, their phone number and fax number and a brief concise summary of 
   your proposed project.

2.Proposal with one-sided, single-spaced pages that include the following sections:
            A.Executive Summary Section
            B.Proposed Solution Specifications Section
                        o  Business Goals 
                        o  Project Scope 
                        o  Design Requirements 
                        o  Current Network Evaluation 
                        o  Logical Design 
                        o  Physical Design 
                        o  Implementation Plan 
                        o  Proof of Concept 
            C.Proposed Cost section
            D.Signature page
            E.Appendixes

3.Company qualifications, including background, primary mission and history
4.Appendices (include the following as attachments):
          o  Bonding and insurance information
          o  Latest financial statements, and current general operating budget
          o  Letters of reference from previous customers.
]]></text>
</component>






<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Factors that limit the ability of the business to incorporate new technology include the amount of the budget, policies, schedules and the availablility of qualified personnel.</li><br/><li>Constraints can and do affect the network design and need to be considered early in the design process.</li><br/><li>Top-down network design strategies have the best chance to succeed because the designers take into account the business goals of the customer before selecting technology solutions.</li><br/><li>Bottom-up design strategies start with the selection of equipment and technologies, and then determine how to incorporate them into the network.</li><br/><li>A primary technical requirement for any network is the availability of qualified support personnel. To simplify ongoing network operations, network monitoring and management software should be part of network design.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>