<transcript lastedited="10.15.08 12:10:11">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.1.3 Approaches to Troubleshooting]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Three Diagrams <br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br>The diagram depicts the seven layers of the O S I model in boxes. From the top down, they are listed as follows: Application, Presentation, Session, Transport, Network, Data Link, and Physical. The Application, Presentation, and Session Layers are grouped together in one box.<br>There are several different structured troubleshooting techniques identified, including top-down, bottom-up, and divide-and-conquer.<br>Bottom-up Troubleshooting Approach<br>Starts at Physical Layer.<br>How it operates: Always starts at the Physical Layer and works its way up until it finds a faulty layer.<br>Cases for which it is suitable: Best suited for complex cases.<br>Advantages/Disadvantages: It is a slow, but solid approach. When the problem is Application, or upper layer related, this approach can take a long time.<br> <br>Divide-and-Conquer Troubleshooting Approach<br>Starts at Data Link, Network, or Transport Layer.<br>How it operates: Based on the circumstances (reported issues) and troubleshooting experience, the technician might decide to start at any layer and work up or down the O S I stack.<br>Cases for which it is suitable: Most suitable when the technician is experienced and the problem has precise symptoms.<br>Advantages/Disadvantages: It approaches the layer of the culprit faster than the other approaches. The technician needs experience to use this approach effectively.<br><br>Top-down Troubleshooting Approach<br>Starts at Application Layer.<br>How it operates: Always starts at the Application Layer and works its way down until it finds a faulty layer.<br>Cases for which it is suitable: More suitable for simpler problems or those that are suspected to be application/user or upper-layer related. <br>Advantages/Disadvantages: If the problem turns out to be related to lower layers, the technician has wasted a lot of time and effort at the upper or Application Layers.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
