<transcript lastedited="10.01.08 10:10:56">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.5.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 6 Quiz: Routing with a Link-State Protocol<br><br>1.What attribute is associated with link-state routing protocols?<br>A.split horizon<br>B.poison reverse<br>C.low processor overhead<br>D.shortest-path first calculations<br><br>2.If OSPF is configured in the network using the costs, as described in the Network Topology and Table of OSPF Costs, which path will a packet taken from H1 to H2?  To answer this question refer to the description of the Network Topology and the Table of OSPF Costs.<br><br>Network Topology<br>Host H1 is connected via an Ethernet cable to router R1.  R1 is connected via Ethernet cable to router R2.  R2 is connected via a T1 serial link to router R5.  R1 is also connected via an Ethernet cable to R5.  R1 is also connected via a T1 serial link to R4.  R4 is connected via a GigEthernet link to R5.  R1 is also connected via a T3 serial link to R3.  R3 is connected via a FastEthernet link to R4.  Finally R5 is connected via an Ethernet link to host H2.  <br><br>Table of OSPF Costs<br>GigabitEthernet link = OSPF cost of 1<br>FastEthernet link = OSFP cost of 10<br>T3 link = OSFP cost of 20<br>Ethernet link= OSFP cost of 100<br>T1 link = OSFP cost of 800<br><br>A.R1 - R5<br>B.R1 - R2 - R5 <br>C.R1 - R4 - R5 <br>D.R1 - R3 - R4 - R5<br><br>3.To answer this question refer to the information regarding the Destination IP address and the Learned Routes.  <br><br>Destination IP address: 192.168.1.143<br>Learned Routes: <br>O 192.168.1.0/24 (110/65) via 192.168.2.2, 00:00:05, Serial 0/0/0<br>R 192.168.1.0/24 (120/1) via 192.168.3.2, 00:00:05, FastEthernet 0/0<br>D 192.168.1.0/24 (90/21765) via 192.168.4.2, 00:00:05, Serial 0/0/1<br><br>The router learned three different routes to the subnet 192.168.1.0.  What action will the router take to forward a packet to the destination of 192.168.1.143?<br>A.The packet will be dropped by the router.<br>B.The packet will be load-balanced across the three routes.<br>C.The packet will be forwarded to the next hop of 192.168.4.2.<br>D.The packet will exit the router through the FastEthernet 0/0 interface.<br><br>4.To answer this question refer partial output from the show running-config command on RouterA.  <br>With all interfaces on RouterA active, the network administrator modifies the configuration of the router by issuing the command no router-id 18.20.20.172.  The configuration is then saved and the router restarted.  What will be the router ID for RouterA when OSPF is re-established?<br><br>RouterA# show running-config<br><br>interface Loopback0<br> IP address 192.168.30.1 255.255.255.0<br>!<br>interface Loopback1<br> IP address 192.168.70.18 255.255.255.252<br>!<br>interface FastEthernet0/0<br> IP address 192.168.102.1 255.255.255.0<br>!<br>interface FastEthernet0/1<br> IP address 192.168.90.1 255.255.255.0<br>!<br>interface Serial0/0/0<br> IP address 172.20.20.18 255.255.255.252<br>!<br>router ospf 100<br> router-id 18.20.20.172<br><br>A.10.190.102.1<br>B.172.20.20.18<br>C.192.168.30.1<br>D.192.168.70.18<br>E.192.168.90.1<br><br>5.To answer this question refer to the Network Topology.<br>Network Topology<br>A switch at the core of a star topology is connected to routers A, B, C and D. <br>RouterA is connected to the core switch via F a 0/0 with the IP address 172.16.5.1/24.  RouterA has a Loopback0 address 172.16.4.3/32. <br>RouterB is connected to the core switch via F a 0/0 with the IP address 172.16.5.2/24.  RouterB has a Loopback0 address 172.16.4.2/32. <br>RouterC is connected to the core switch via F a 0/0 with the IP address 172.16.5.3/24.  RouterC has a Loopback0 address 172.16.4.1/32. <br>RouterD is connected to the core switch via Fa0/0 with the IP address 172.16.5.4/24.  RouterD has a Loopback0 address 172.16.4.4/32.<br><br>RouterA, RouterB, and RouterC in the network topology are running OSPF on their Ethernet interfaces.  RouterD was just added to the network.  Routers are configured with the loopback interfaces (Lo 0).  What happens to the OSPF DR/BDR after RouterD is added to the network?<br><br>A.RouterB takes over as DR and RouterD becomes the BDR.<br>B.RouterD becomes the BDR and RouterA remains the DR.<br>C.RouterD becomes the DR and RouterA remains the BDR.<br>D.RouterC acts as the DR until election process is complete.<br>E.RouterD becomes the DR and RouterB remains the BDR.<br>F.There is no change in the DR and BDR until either current DR or BDR goes down.<br><br>6.To answer this question refer to the Network Topology.<br><br>Network Topology<br>Router A is connected to a LAN addressed 192.168.10.64/26.  Router A is also connected to Router B via a serial link, IP address 192.168.10.192/30.  Router B is connected to a LAN addressed 192.168.10.128/27.  All networks from Router A and Router B are part of OSPF Area 0.<br><br>What network commands will configure Router A to properly advertise the OSPF routes?<br><br>A.network 192.168.10.0 0.0.0.63 area 0 network 192.168.10.128 0.0.0.63 area 0<br>B.network 192.168.10.64 0.0.0.63 area 0 <br>network 192.168.10.192 0.0.0.3 area 0<br>C.network 192.168.10.0 255.255.255.252 area 0 network 192.168.10.128 255.255.255.252 area 0<br>D.network 192.168.10.64 255.255.255.252 area 0 <br>network 192.168.10.192 255.255.255.252 area 0<br><br>7.Which two statements are true regarding the cost calculation for a link in OSPF?  (Choose two.)<br>A.It can be set with the IP OSPF cost command.<br>B.It is set to 1544 by default for all OSPF interfaces.<br>C.The configured loopback addresses map to link costs.<br>D.It may be calculated using the formula reference bandwidth/bandwidth.<br>E.It is calculated proportionally to observed throughput capacity of the router.<br><br>8.To answer this question refer to the Network Topology.<br><br>Network Topology<br>This network topology consists of three routers.  Router A is connected to a LAN with the IP address 192.168.10.64/26.  Router A is connected to router B via a serial link with the IP address 192.168.10.0/30.  Router B is connected to a LAN with the IP address 192.168.10.128/26.  Router B is connected to router C via a serial link with the IP address 192.168.10.4/30.  Router C is connected to a LAN with the IP address 192.168.10.192/26.<br><br>OSPF routing protocol is configured for the routers, however, router A is not receiving any OSPF routed from the other routers.  Based on the information given in the Network Topology, what is the problem with the router A configuration?<br><br>A# show IP protocols<br>Routing Protocol is "OSPF 1"<br>  Outgoing update filter list for all interfaces is not set<br>  Incoming update filter list for all interfaces is not set<br>  Router ID 192.168.10.65<br>  Number of areas in this router is 1. 1normal 0 stub 0 nssa<br>  Maximum path: 4<br>  Routing for Networks:<br>    192.168.10.64 0.0.0.63 area 0<br>    192.168.10.128 0.0.0.63 area 0<br>Routing Information Sources:<br>GatewayDistanceLast Update<br>192.168.10.6511000:00:28<br>Distance: (default is 110)<br><br>A.None of the interfaces are enabled.<br>B.OSPF has an improper process ID.<br>C.One of the network statements is wrong.<br>D.Auto-summarization needs to be disabled.<br><br>9.To answer this question refer to the Network Topology.<br><br>Network Topology<br>Router HQ has a serial link to the Internet.  HQ has serial links to routers North, South, East and West similar to a hub and spoke type network.<br>HQ(config)# IP route 0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 serial 1/0<br>HQ(config)# IP router OSPF 1<br>HQ(config-router) #default-information originate<br>HQ(config)# exit<br><br>A network administrator is implementing OSPF between headquarters and multiple branch offices.  All branch offices are connected to the Internet through the headquarters router.  What effect will the commands entered on the headquarters router have?<br><br>A.The command will only affect the local router.<br>B.The command must be applied to all routers in order for the default route to be propagated.<br>C.The default will be propagated to all routers participating in the same OSPF area.<br>D.The default route will only be learned by the OSPF adjacent neighbors.<br><br>10.For what two reasons would a network administrator choose to enable authentication for OSPF exchanges?  (Choose two.)<br>A.to prevent routing information from being falsified<br>B.to reduce OSPF information exchange overhead<br>C.to keep routing information being captured<br>D.to encrypt routing tables to prevent unauthorized viewing<br>E.to ensure the OSPF routing information takes priority over RIP and EIGRP updates.<br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
