<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[Constraint]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[Gathered Information]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[Designer's Notes]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[Budget]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[Policy]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[Schedule]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[Personnel]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[<li>No plans to fund redundancy at the access-layer. Must also reuse sixteen existing 2960-48TT switches</li><li>New cable runs are not funded, except for fiber to connect new wireless access points.</li>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt09"><text><![CDATA[<li>The management guideline was to use ISP managed VPNs across the Internet for low cost remote connectivity. (This is under review.)</li>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt10"><text><![CDATA[<li>The time frame for implementing a major change is approximately 4 months, the time until the primary sports season starts.</li>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt11"><text><![CDATA[<li>There is no plan to add additional staff.</li>]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt12"><text><![CDATA[Since the 2960s only support Layer 2 services, Layer 3 wiring closets will not be possible. The two pairs of fiber to each closet can support a connection to a pair of distribution switches.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt13"><text><![CDATA[Since the QoS and SLA support needed for the business applications is not possible through the local ISP, need to investigate alternate WAN technologies.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt14"><text><![CDATA[Need to consider the time required for the installation and turn-up of any new circuits and equipment.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt15"><text><![CDATA[Currently understaffed for the planned network expansion with only one network administrator, three network technicians, and one manager.Staff needs immediate training in wireless and IP telephony. Look to reduce complexity.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt16"><text><![CDATA[Click each constraint to display the designer's notes on how it impacts the network design.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt17"><text><![CDATA[Stadium Network Project Constraints]]></text></component></textcomponents>