<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[Click each box to view the advantage of each strategy.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[WAN link assigned 200.100.15.129 and .130]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01b">
<text><![CDATA[Apply the address to the LAN or WAN link]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[WAN link assigned 200.100.15.133 and .134]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[WAN link assigned  200.100.15.137 and .138]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title1">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody1">
<text><![CDATA[Build and test a sample Access Layer modular block to see the effect of adding devices to the network.<br><br>Use this tested design as the template to make it easier to scale the network.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title2">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody08">
<text><![CDATA[Use Layer 3 devices at the Distribution Layer to filter and reduce traffic to the network core.<br><br>With a modular Layer 3 Distribution Layer design, new Access Layer modules can be connected without requiring major reconfiguration.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title3">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody09">
<text><![CDATA[Careful IP address planning eliminates the need to re-address the network to support additional users and services.<br><br>Route summarization reduces the routing table size. Small routing tables improve network convergence time.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title4">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody11">
<text><![CDATA[Modules can be added to the existing equipment to support new features and devices without requiring major equipment upgrades.<br><br>Some devices can be integrated in a cluster to act as one device to simplify management and configuration.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title5">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody10">
<text><![CDATA[Combining multiple Ethernet links into a load-balanced EtherChannel configuration increases available bandwidth.<br><br>EtherChannel implementations can be used when budget restrictions prohibit purchasing high speed interfaces and fiber runs.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_title6">
<text><![CDATA[<font color="#333333">.</font>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody12">
<text><![CDATA[Keep VLANs local to the wiring closet to minimize the need for Spanning Tree configurations.<br><br>This design helps speed network convergence and increases scalability and stability.]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>





