<transcript lastedited="12.18.08 08:12:52">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.5.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Four Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br>Diagram 1, Image<br>The diagram depicts the electromagnetic spectrum.<br>Diagram 1 text<br>This chapter described various technologies for the transmission of information between hosts without cables. This chapter also describes the benefits and limitations of these wireless technologies and the devices that use them. <br><br>Wireless technologies use electromagnetic radiation in the form of radio signals to carry information between devices.<br>The most common wavelengths used for public wireless communications include the Infrared and part of the Radio Frequency (RF) band.<br>Remote control devices, wireless mice, and wireless keyboards use either Infrared (IR) or Blue tooth technology. <br>Devices such as microwave ovens and cordless phones can interfere with W LAN communications, because they use similar frequencies.<br>Wireless networks are grouped into three major categories: wireless personal area networks (W PAN), wireless local area networks (W LAN), and wireless wide area networks (W WAN).<br>The main organization responsible for the creation of wireless technical standards is the IEEE. Standards that govern the WLAN environment include: 8 0 2 dot 11A, 8 0 2 dot 11B, 8 0 2 dot 11G, 8 0 2 dot 11N. They are known as WiFi standards.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br>The diagram depicts wireless cells connected by a distribution system.<br>Diagram 2 text<br>Devices in a W LAN include: wireless clients, access points, wireless bridges, and antennas.<br>A small W LAN, peer to peer network, is known as an ad hoc network and does not include an AP.<br>Wireless devices use antennas to transmit and receive information. There are two types of antennas: directional and omni directional.<br>All wireless devices in a W LAN must be configured with the same SSID and operate using the same standards in order to communicate.<br>To separate conversations, the RF spectrum is divided into different channels.<br>APs and clients use an access method called Carrier Sense Multiple Access with Collision Avoidance (CSMA/CA) that creates a reservation on the channel for use by a specific conversation.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br>The diagram depicts wireless security measures.<br>Diagram 3 text<br>Because they can operate without much configuration and transmit information through the air, wireless networks are more susceptible to attacks than wired networks. <br>An attacker can access your network from any location your wireless signal reaches.<br>Attackers can use your Internet services for free, or damage files and steal private information from your network.<br>Some of the more basic security measures that should be taken include the following:<br>Change default values for the SSID, usernames, and passwords.<br>Disable broadcast SSID.<br>Configure MAC Address Filtering.<br><br>Some of the more advanced security measures that should be included in your plan would include the following:<br>Configure encryption using WEP or WPA.<br>Configure authentication.<br>Configure traffic filtering.<br>Diagram 4, Image<br>The diagram depicts people planning and using wireless networks.<br>Diagram 4 text<br>Before installing a wireless network, an installation plan should be created that includes the standards to be used, the locations of devices, a security plan, and a strategy for backing up configurations. In order to carry out this plan, the following steps are needed:<br><br>Gather user requirements to determine the appropriate standard to use, bandwidth requirements, coverage areas, existing implementations, and cost.<br>Perform a site survey to determine the optimum number and location of AP's.<br>Combine multiple security techniques to strengthen the integrity of the wireless network.<br>Perform a full configuration backup of wireless devices to provide a stored copy in case of device failure.<br>Upgrade firmware, if necessary, to take advantage of enhancements to the operating system.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
