<transcript lastedited="01.21.09 18:01:05">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.6.3 - Switches - Selective Forwarding]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts switch operation, which includes the switch learning process:<br>-	Learning - Records the MAC address and port number.<br>-	Flooding - Sends the frame to all ports, except the incoming port.<br>-	Selective Forwarding - Sends the frame only to the destination port.<br><br>A 12-port switch is shown with the following connections:<br><br>Host1 with MAC address 0A is connected to port FA1.<br>Host2 with MAC address 0C is connected to port FA6.<br>Host3 with MAC address 0B is connected to port FA3.<br>Host4 with MAC address 0D is connected to port FA8.<br><br>The following steps explain the basic switch operation.<br><br>Step 1. Upon initialization of the switch, the MAC address table is empty.<br><br>Step 2. Host1 sends data to Host2. The frame sent contains both a source MAC address and a destination MAC address.<br><br>Step 3. Learning takes place. The switch reads the source MAC address, 0A, from the frame received on port FA1 and stores it in the MAC address table for use in the forwarding of frames to Host1.<br><br>Step 4. Flooding takes place. The destination MAC address, 0C, is not in the MAC table. The switch floods the frame out all ports except port FA1, the port of the sender. Host3 and Host4 receive the frame, but the address in the frame does not match their MAC address. They drop the frame. The destination MAC address in the frame matches Host2, and it accepts the frame.<br><br>Step 5: Host2 sends a frame to Host1 containing a reply. The source address in the frame is the MAC address of Host2. The destination address in the frame matches the MAC address for Host1.<br><br>Step 6: Learning takes place. The switch reads the source MAC address, 0C, from the frame received on port FA6 and stores it in the MAC address table for use in the forwarding of frames to Host2.<br><br>Step 7: Selective forwarding takes place. The destination MAC address, 0A, is in the MAC address table. The switch selectively forwards the frame out port FA1 only. The destination MAC address in the frame matches the MAC address for Host1. Host1 accepts the frame.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
