<transcript lastedited="01.20.09 11:01:33">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.5.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question 1. Name two ways in which bits are encoded as voltages. How do they differ?<br>Answer: In NRZ (non-return to zero) encoding, a zero might be represented by one voltage level on the media during the bit time, and a one might be represented by a different voltage on the media during the bit time.<br><br>Manchester Encoding uses transitions, or the absence of transitions, to indicate a logic level. For example, a zero is indicated by a high-to-low transition in the middle of the bit time. For a one, there is a low-to-high transition in the middle of the bit time.<br><br>Question 2. Why might bits be encoded as symbols before transmission?<br>Answer: One encoding technique is the use of symbols. The Physical Layer might use a set of encoded symbols to represent encoded data or control information called code groups. A code group is a consecutive sequence of code bits interpreted and mapped as data-bit patterns. For example, code bits 10101 can represent the data bits 0011.<br><br>While code groups introduce overhead in the form of extra bits to transmit, they improve the robustness of a communications link. This is particularly true for higher speed data transmission.<br><br>By transmitting symbols, the error detection capabilities and timing synchronization between transmitting and receiving devices are enhanced. These are important considerations in supporting high-speed transmission over the media.<br><br>Some of these advantages are:<br>-	Reduced bit-level error.<br>-	Limiting the effective energy transmitted into the media.<br>-	Distinguishing data bits from control bits.<br>-	Better media error detection.<br><br>Question 3. What safety issues must be considered when using copper cabling?<br>Answer: Electrical hazards<br>Copper wires can conduct electricity in undesirable ways. This could subject personnel and equipment to a range of electrical hazards. A defective network device can conduct currents to the chassis of another network device. Additionally, network cabling could present undesirable voltage levels when used to connect devices that have power sources with different ground potentials. Also copper cabling can conduct voltages caused by lightning strikes to network devices. Undesirable voltages and currents can damage network devices and connected computers or injure personnel.<br><br>Fire hazards<br>Cable insulation and sheaths might be flammable or produce toxic fumes when heated or burned. Building authorities or organizations might also stipulate related safety standards for cabling and hardware installations.<br><br>Question 4. In what situations is fiber-optic cabling preferred over copper cabling?<br>Answer: Given that the glass fibers used in fiber-optic media are not electrical conductors, the media is immune to electromagnetic interference and does not conduct unwanted electrical currents due to grounding issues. In addition, because optical fibers have relatively low signal loss, they can be operated at much greater lengths than copper media, without the need for signal regeneration.<br><br>Question 5. Name several copper and fiber-optic connecter types.<br>Answer: Copper: RJ-45, RJ-11<br>Fiber: Straight-Tip (ST), Subscriber Connector (SC), Lucent Connector (LC)]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
