<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.2.4  - VTP Modes]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts VTP in action.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switches S1, S2, and S3 are not connected initially. All switches have default settings.<br>VTP Domain Name - null<br>VTP Mode - server<br>Config Revision - 0<br>V LAN's - 1<br><br>Animation Sequence:<br>All switches have default settings.<br><br>S1 VTP mode set to server.<br>S2 VTP mode set to client.<br>S3 VTP mode set to transparent.<br><br>Switch S1 is configured as a VTP server, switch S2 is configured as a VTP client, and switch S3 as VTP transparent. After V LAN's are configured on S1, the switches are connected so that VTP advertisements can pass between them.<br><br>The S1 VTP domain name is set to cisco1.<br><br>S1 V LAN 2 is added.<br>S1 Revision = 1.<br><br>S1 V LAN 3 is added.<br>S1 Revision = 2.<br><br>Switch S1 is now configured and ready to be trunked to the other VTP-enabled switches.<br><br>Switch S1 sends the following summary advertisement to S2 and S3:<br>Domain Name - cisco1.<br>Configuration Revision Number - 2.<br><br>Switch S2 updates its VTP domain name to cisco1.<br>Switch S3 does not respond to the summary advertisement.<br><br>Switch S2 sends a request advertisement for V LAN configuration details to S1.<br><br>Switch S1 sends a summary advertisement to S2.<br><br>Switch S1 sends the following subset advertisement to S2 with V LAN configuration details:<br>V LAN's - 1, 2, 3.<br><br>Switch S2 updates its V LAN configuration.<br><br>Switch S3 in VTP transparent mode remains configured the same. In this example, it does not participate in VTP.<br><br>After VTP has sent all the advertisements, the VTP information in the switches is as follows:<br><br>Switch S1:<br>VTP Domain Name = Cisco1<br>VTP Mode = Server<br>Config Revision = 2<br>V LAN's = 1, 2, 3 <br><br>Switch S2:<br>VTP Domain Name = Cisco1<br>VTP Mode = Client<br>Config Revision = 2<br>V LAN's = 1, 2, 3<br><br>Switch S3:<br>VTP Domain Name = null<br>VTP Mode = Transparent<br>Config Revision = 0<br>V LAN's = 1]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
