<transcript lastedited="01.05.09 13:01:58">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.7.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Match the TCP port numbers with the correct protocol. (Not all options are used.)<br>Port Numbers:<br>20<br>23<br>25<br>27<br>63<br>80<br>110<br><br>Protocols:<br>HTTP<br>Telnet<br>FTP<br>SMTP<br><br>2.Categorize the options based on whether they describe TCP or UDP.<br>Options:<br>A.Reliable<br>B.No flow control<br>C.Reassembles messages at destination host<br>D.Resends anything not received<br>E.Does not reassemble incoming messages<br>F.Unreliable<br>G.Connectionless<br>H.Connection-oriented<br><br>Categories:<br>TCP - Transmission Control Protocol<br>UDP - User Datagram Protocol<br><br>3.At the Transport Layer, which of the following controls is used to avoid a transmitting host overflowing the buffers of a receiving host?<br>A.Best effort<br>B.Encryption<br>C.Flow control<br>D.Compression<br>E.Congestion avoidance<br><br>4.End systems use port numbers to select the proper application. What is the lowest port number that can be dynamically assigned by a host system?<br>A.1<br>B.64<br>C.128<br>D.256<br>E.512<br>F.1024<br><br>5.During data transfer, what are the main responsibilities of the receiving host? (Choose two.)<br>A.Throughput<br>B.Encapsulation<br>C.Acknowledgement<br>D.Bandwidth<br>E.Segmentation<br>F.Reassembly<br><br>6.At which layer of the TCP/IP model does TCP operate?<br>A.Session<br>B.Transport<br>C.Network<br>D.Data Link<br><br>7.What determines how much data a sending station running TCP/IP can transmit before it must receive an acknowledgement?<br>A.Segment size<br>B.Transmission rate<br>C.Bandwidth<br>D.Window size<br>E.Sequence number<br><br>8.What is the purpose of the sequence number in the TCP header?<br>A.Reassembles the segments into data.<br>B.Identifies the Application Layer protocol.<br>C.Indicates the number of the next expected byte.<br>D.Shows the maximum number of bytes allowed during a session.<br><br>9.Refer to the diagram description to answer the question. <br>Diagram description: <br>The sender is sending TCP segments to the receiver, three at a time, and has sent the sixth segment. The receiver is sending an ACK back to the sender. Which acknowledgement number is sent by the receiver?<br>A.3<br>B.4<br>C.6<br>D.7<br>E.9<br>F.12<br><br>10. What is the purpose of TCP/UDP port numbers?<br>A.Indicates the beginning of a three-way handshake.<br>B.Reassembles the segments into the correct order.<br>C.Identifies the number of data packets that may be sent without acknowledgement.<br>D.Tracks different conversations crossing the network at the same time.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
