<transcript lastedited="09.30.08 21:09:12">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.7.1 Quiz<br><br>]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[10 Questions <br><br>1.A company requires a high end computer that can store a significant amount of files and process applications quickly and simultaneously.  Which two components are the most critical for the computer performance (choose two)?<br>RAM<br>CPU<br>video card<br>sound card<br>modem<br><br>2.Which peripheral is a storage device that connects to the USB interface and allows files to be saved and moved between computers?<br>modem<br>scanner<br>printer <br>flash drive<br>network interface card<br><br>3.Which component provides backup power to a computer system for a short period of time?<br>CPU <br>modem<br>surge suppressor<br>uninterruptable power supply<br><br>4.Which term describes static electricity that can be transferred from your body to electronic components in the computer?<br>voltage surge<br>voltage spike<br>grounding <br>surge suppressor<br>electrostatic discharge<br><br>5.What are two examples of input only peripheral devices (choose two)?<br>printer <br>scanner<br>joystick <br>flash drive<br>external NIC<br>monitor<br><br>6.A small real estate company with one office wants to purchase a computer to use for file storage.  What type of computer would be the best choice?<br>mainframe server<br>standalone server<br>rack mount server<br>workstation <br>blade server<br><br>7.A user opens an application and sends a message to a friend in another country.  What type of application has been used?<br>local <br>graphics <br>network<br>standalone<br><br>8.Decipher whether the statements that are listed below are workstation statements or server statements:<br>used for virtual reality simulation<br>normally secured in a room<br>powerful graphic capabilities<br>usually has redundant components such as hard drives<br>runs high end applications like engineering programs<br>provides services to multiple clients<br><br>9.What measurement is commonly associated with graphics resolution?<br>Hz<br>MB<br>GB<br>bps<br>pixels<br><br>10.Match the value with its definition.<br>Value<br>Bit<br>Byte<br>Kilobyte <br>Megabyte<br>Gigabyte<br>Terabyte<br>Definition<br>approximately one thousand bytes<br>approximately one trillion bytes<br>approximately one million bytes<br>approximately one billion bytes<br>a one or a zero<br>eight bits<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
