<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 08:10:23">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.4.5 Peripheral Devices]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Single Diagram<br><br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br><br>The diagram gives a brief description of the following peripheral devices.<br><br>Disk Drives<br>A disk drive that is external to a computer and is not required for the computer to function is considered a peripheral device. Types of disk drives include floppy disks (FD), hard disks (HD), compact discs (CD), and digital video discs (DVD). A disk drive can be used to increase the available storage capacity of a computer and also to move large amounts of data between different computers.<br><br>Scanner<br>A scanner is used to convert printed pages, handwriting, diagrams, and pictures into digital format for storage on a computer. Scanners are considered peripheral devices.<br><br>Mouse<br>The mouse is used to select items displayed on the monitor. The selection process can also be carried out using the keyboard, so the mouse is not a required device and is considered a peripheral.<br><br>Flash Drive<br>A flash drive is a storage device that connects to the USB interface and allows files to be saved and moved between computers. The optional storage device functions similarly to a floppy disk and is considered a peripheral.<br><br>Network Interface Card<br>An external NIC is used to allow communications between computers. Since the NIC is not required for the individual computer to function, it is considered a peripheral.<br><br>Printer<br>A printer converts the digital information stored in a computer to a printed page. Many different types of printers exist and can have either black or color output. Printers are considered peripheral devices.<br><br>Modem<br>An external modem is used to allow communication between computers. Since the modem is not required for the individual computer to function it is considered a peripheral device.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
