<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_inst">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over the various peripherals for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>
   	
<component id="ID_txt01">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Disk Drives </b>]]></text>
</component>
  	
<component id="ID_txt03">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Mouse</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Flash drive</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Network Interface Card </b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Printer</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt08">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Modem</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt09">
   	<text><![CDATA[<b>Scanner</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt10">
   	<text><![CDATA[A disk drive which is external to a computer and is not required for the computer to function is considered a peripheral device. Different types of disk drives exist including floppy disks (FD), hard disks (HD), compact disks (CD) and Digital Video Disks (DVD). These devices allow a user to easily increase the available storage capacity of a computer and also move large amounts of data between different computers.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt12">
   	<text><![CDATA[The mouse allows the user to select items displayed on the monitor. The selection process can also be carried out using the keyboard so the mouse is not a required device and is considered a peripheral.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt13">
   	<text><![CDATA[A flash drive is a storage device that connects to the USB interface and allows files to be saved and moved between computers. This optional storage device functions similarly to an external floppy disk drive and is considered a peripheral.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt14">
   	<text><![CDATA[An external NIC is used to allow communications between computers. Since the NIC is not required for the individual computer to function, it is considered a peripheral device.]]></text>
</component>
   	
<component id="ID_txt15">
   	<text><![CDATA[A printer converts the digital information stored in a computer to a printed page. Many different types of printers exist and can have either monochrome or color output. Printers are considered peripheral devices.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt17">
   	<text><![CDATA[An external modem is used to allow communications between computers. Since the modem is not required for the individual computer to function it is considered a peripheral device.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt18">
   	<text><![CDATA[A scanner allows printed pages, handwriting, diagrams and pictures to be converted into digital format for storage on a computer. Scanners are considered peripheral devices.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle01">
<text><![CDATA[Disk Drives]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle03">
	<text><![CDATA[Mouse]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle04">
<text><![CDATA[Flash drive]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle05">
<text><![CDATA[Network Interface Card]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle06">
<text><![CDATA[Printer]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle08">
<text><![CDATA[Modem]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle09">
	<text><![CDATA[Scanner]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>