<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 11:09:12">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.6.1 - Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the use of Store-and-Forward and Cut-Through Switching. The diagram also shows how using Store-and-Forward Switching is a better solution because there will be a decrease in the number of errors.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>Switches use microsegmentation to create single port collision domains <br>Layer 3 switching takes place in special A S I C hardware. <br>Switches forward traffic using store-and-forward or cut-through techniques. Basic security features should be applied to switches to ensure that only authorized personnel access the devices. <br><br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a network where there are four looped switches. The last switch connects to first. One port has been blocked by S T P to eliminate the loop.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br>Spanning Tree Protocol shuts down redundant links to prevent switching loops.<br>A root bridge is at the top of the spanning tree and it is elected based on the lowest bridge I D.<br>Spanning Tree recalculation can take up to 50 seconds to complete during which time the network has limited functionality.<br>Rapid Spanning Tree has evolved to shorten the convergence time.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a building with a network on three floors. There are three different colored ovals which represent three V LAN's. The V LAN's are spread over three floors.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>A V LAN is a collection of hosts that are on the same local area network even though they may be physically separated from each other.<br>V LAN 1 is the management V LAN by default.<br>Frame tagging applies the V LAN I D to the Ethernet frame so the switch can identify the source V LAN.<br>IEEE 802.1 Q is the open standard frame tagging protocol that inserts a 4-byte tag into the Ethernet frame.<br><br><br>Diagram 4, Image <br><br>The diagram depicts the use of a subinterface to establish communication between multiple V LAN's. There are three V LAN's each represented by a different colored circle. All three V LAN's connect to the router via a single link (subinterface) on the F A 0 / 0 Interface.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>An access port connects a device to a switch and is a member of one V LAN. <br>A trunk port connects two switches or a switch and a router, and forwards tagged frames from multiple V LAN's. <br>Untagged frames are forwarded using the native V LAN. <br>A Layer 3 device is required to move traffic between different V LAN's. <br>A router interface is configured using subinterfaces to support multiple V LAN's. <br><br><br>Diagram 5, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a network shown with three different colored circles. Each circle represents a different V LAN. <br><br>Diagram 5 text<br><br>V LAN Trunking Protocol provides a method for the centralized control, distribution, and maintenance of the enterprise V LAN database. <br>Switches are either servers, clients, or transparent. <br>A server issues a VTP update by having a higher revision number than the other switches. <br>V LAN's are suit-ed for time sensitive traffic such as voice. <br>Best practices, such as consistent VTP domain name and revision number control increase network efficiency.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
