<transcript lastedited="10.10.08 14:10:42">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.5.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 2 Quiz: Exploring the Enterprise Network Infrastructure<br><br>1.Match each term to its correct description.  (Not all options are used.)<br>Terms<br>POP <br>VPN<br>D o S<br>C P E<br>DMZ<br>demarc<br><br>Descriptions<br>maliciously prevents access to network resources by legitimate users<br>boundary that designates responsibility for equipment maintenance and troubleshooting<br>physical link to outside networks at the enterprise edge <br>equipment located at the customer facilityallows remote workers to access the internal network securely <br>allows remote workers to access the internal network securely <br><br>2.What information can be found by using the command show mac-address-table on a Cisco Catalyst switch? <br>A.The MAC addresses of the ports on the Catalyst switch<br>B.The port the switch will use to forward frames to a host<br>C.The IP addresses of directly connected network devices<br>D.The mapping between MAC address and IP address for network hosts<br><br>3.While trouble shooting a network problem, the network administrator issues the show version command on a router.  What information can be found using this command?<br>A.the amount of NV RAM, DRAM, and flash memory installed on the router<br>B.bandwidth, encapsulation, and I/O statistics on the interfaces<br>C.differences between the backup configuration and the current running configuration<br>D.the version of the routing protocols running on the router<br><br>4.After gathering a thorough list of network applications, the traffic generated by these applications, and the priority of this traffic, a network engineer wishes to integrate this information into a single document for analysis.  How can this be accomplished?<br>A.Create a physical topology map of the network and annotate it with the network application data.<br>B.Create a logical topology map of the network and annotate it with the network application data.<br>C.Create a blueprint of the facility, including network cabling and telecommunication rooms and annotate it with the network application data.<br>D.Take a photograph of the facility and annotate it with the network application data.<br><br>5.One evening a network administrator attempted to access a recently deployed website and received a "page not found" error.  The next day the administrator checked the web server logs and noticed that during the same hour that the site failed to load, there were hundreds of requests for the website home page.  All of the requests originated from the same IP address.  Given this information, what might the network administrator conclude?<br>A.It is normal web surfing activity.<br>B.It is likely that someone attempted a D o S attack.<br>C.The link to the website does not have enough capacity and needs to be increased.<br>D.The web server was turned off and not able to service requests.<br><br>6.What type of media typically connects a MDF switch to an IDF switch in another building?<br>A.fiber-optic<br>B.coaxial-cable<br>C.unshielded twisted pair<br>D.shielded twisted pair<br><br>7.Which three devices can receive power over the same twisted pair Ethernet cable that carries data?  (Choose three)<br>A.wireless access point<br>B.monitors<br>C.web camera<br>D.IP Phone<br>E.network switches<br>F.laptops<br><br>8.Match the hardware characteristics to the hardware type.  Identify if each characteristic relates to a router or a switch.  (Three characteristics relate to a router and three characteristics relate to a switch.)<br>Hardware Characteristics<br>define broadcast domains<br>connect IP Phones and access points to the network<br>enhance security with ACL's<br>interconnect networks<br>appear more commonly at the access layer<br>connect hosts to the network<br><br>Hardware Type<br>router<br>switch<br><br>9.Which two protocols can be used to access a Cisco router for in-band management?  (Choose two)<br>A.ARP<br>B.S S H<br>C.FTP<br>D.SMTP<br>E.Telnet<br><br>10.A network analyst is documenting the existing network at ABC Corporation.  The analyst decides to start at the core router to identify and document the Cisco network devices attached to the core.  Which command executed on the core router provides the required information?<br>A.show version<br>B.show ip route<br>C.show tech-support<br>D.show running-config<br>E.show C D P neighbors detail<br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
