<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_but01">
<text><![CDATA[Open Guest Access]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_but02">
<text><![CDATA[Secured Employee Access]]></text>
</component><component id="ID_but03">
<text><![CDATA[More Information ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Access Point]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Access Layer Switch</br>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Data VLAN]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[Voice VLAN]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[Guest VLAN]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[Data SSID]]></text>
</component><component id="ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[Voice SSID]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Guest SSID]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[Data]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[Voice]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[Guest]]></text>
</component><component id="ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[Click the buttons to view Open Guest Access and Secured Employee Access.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt13">
<text><![CDATA[More Information]]></text>
</component>
<component id="tipTitle">
<text>More Information</text>
</component>

<component id="tipBody">
<text><![CDATA[One of the primary benefits of wireless networking is ease and convenience of connecting devices. Unfortunately that ease of connectivity and the fact that the information is transmitted through the air makes a wireless network vulnerable to interception and attacks.<br><br>Standard best practices for securing a wireless Access Point and the associated wireless transmissions include the following procedures: <br>• Modify the default SSID, and do not broadcast it unless necessary. <br>• Use strong encryption. <br>• Deploy mutual authentication between the client and the network using pre-shared keys or an implementation of Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP). <br>• Use VPNs or WPA combined with MAC address control lists to secure business-specific devices. <br>• Use VLANs to restrict access to network resources. <br>• Ensure that management ports are secured. <br>• Deploy lightweight Access Points because they do not store security information locally. <br>• Physically hide or secure Access Points to prevent tampering. <br>• Monitor the exterior building and site for suspicious activity. <br><br>Some of these factors affect network design; for example, the location and type of authentication servers and VPN end-points, as well as the choice of lightweight Access Points. <br><br>Other factors to consider when deciding on the WLAN design include:<br>• Determining the secure physical locations for wireless equipment <br>• Securing the wired network WLANs connect to]]></text>
</component>
<component id="TipText">
<text><![CDATA[More Information]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>

