<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:38">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.2.3  - VTP Advertising]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the details for the three types of VTP advertisements used to communicate between VTP-enabled switches.<br><br>Summary Advertisement Details:<br>Version - This field displays the VTP version used. On Cisco 2960 switches, the version is either VTP V1 or VTP V2.<br>Code - A code that identifies the type of advertisement.<br>Followers - This field indicates that the packet is followed by a subset advertisement packet.<br>MgmtD Len - Indicates the length of the management domain name.<br>Management Domain Name (zero-padded to 32 bytes) - The name of the VTP domain.<br>Configuration Revision Number - The revision number of the VTP server sending the message.<br>Updater Identity - The IP address of the switch that last incremented the configuration revision.<br>Update Timestamp (12 bytes) - The date and time of the last increment of the configuration revision.<br>MD5 Digest (16 bytes) - Message Digest 5 (MD5) carries the VTP password, if MD5 is configured and used to authenticate the validation of a VTP update.<br><br>Subset Advertisement Details:<br>Version - This field displays the VTP version used. On Cisco 2960 switches, the version is either VTP V1 or VTP V2.<br>Code - The format is 0x02 for a subset advertisement.<br>Seq-Number - Sequence of the packet in the stream of packets that follow a summary advertisement. The sequence starts with 1.<br>MgmtD Len - Indicates the length of the management domain name.<br>Management Domain Name (zero-padded to 32 bytes) - The name of the VTP domain.<br>Configuration Revision Number - The revision number of the VTP server sending the message.<br>V LAN-info Field 1 through V LAN-info Field N<br><br>V LAN-Info contains information for each V LAN and is formatted as follows:<br>- Info Length <br>- Status<br>- V LAN-Type<br>- V LAN-name Len<br>- ISL V LAN-id <br>- MTU Size<br>- 802 dot 10 Index<br>- V LAN name (Padded with zeroes to multiples of 4 bytes)<br><br>Request Advertisement Details:<br>Version - This field displays the VTP version used. On Cisco 2960 switches, the version is either VTP V1 or VTP V2.<br>Code - The format is 0x03 for an advertisement request.<br>Rsvd - Reserved field.<br>MgmtD Len - Indicates the length of the management domain name.<br>Management Domain Name (zero-padded to 32 bytes) - The name of the VTP domain.<br>Start Value - This field is used when there are several subset advertisements. If the first (n) subset advertisement has been received and the subsequent advertisement (n+1) has not been received, the VTP-enabled switch only requests advertisements from the (n+1) one.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
