<transcript lastedited="01.09.09 09:01:59">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.8.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question 1: What defines a network in terms of an IPv4 address?<br>Answer: For each IPv4 address, some portion of the high-order bits represents the network address. At Layer 3, we define a network as a group of hosts that have identical bit patterns in the network address portion of their addresses.<br><br>Question 2: Name and state the purpose of the three types of IPv4 addresses.<br>Answer: <br>-	Network address: The address by which we refer to the network.<br>-	Broadcast address: A special address used to send data to all hosts in the network.<br>-	Host addresses: The addresses assigned to the end devices in the network.<br><br>Question 3: What distinguishes each of the three types of IPv4 addresses?<br>Answer: Within the IPv4 address range of a network, the lowest address is reserved for the network address. This address has a 0 for each host bit in the host portion of the address.<br><br>Host address - Host bits are a unique mix of ones and zeros within a network. The broadcast address uses the highest address in the network range. This is the address in which the bits in the host portion are all ones. For the network 10.0.0.0 with 24 network bits, the broadcast address would be 10.0.0.255. This address is also referred to as the directed broadcast.<br><br>Question 4: List the three forms of IPv4 communication.<br>Answer: <br>-	Unicast: Sending a packet from one host to an individual host.<br>-	Broadcast: Sending a packet from one host to all hosts in the network.<br>-	Multicast: Sending a packet from one host to a selected group of hosts.<br><br>Question 5: List the purpose of having specified ranges of IPv4 addresses for public and private use.<br>Answer: Specified private addresses allow network administrators to allocate addresses to those hosts that they know never need direct access to the public Internet.<br><br>Question 6: Where are reserved and special IPv4 addresses used?<br>Answer:<br>Multicast Addresses:<br>The IPv4 multicast address range 224.0.0.0 to 239.255.255.255 is reserved for special purposes.<br><br>Private Addresses:<br><br>The private address blocks are:<br>10.0.0.0 to 10.255.255.255 (10.0.0.0/8)<br>172.16.0.0 to 172.31.255.255 (172.16.0.0/12)<br>192.168.0.0 to 192.168.255.255 (192.168.0.0/16)<br><br>Private space address blocks are set aside for private networks.  Hosts that do not require access to the Internet at large can make unrestricted use of private addresses because these addresses do not need to be unique among outside networks. Many hosts in different networks can use the same private space addresses. Packets using these addresses as the source or destination must not appear on the public Internet. The router or firewall device at the perimeter of these private networks must block or translate these addresses.<br><br>Default Route:<br>The IPv4 default route is 0.0.0.0. The use of this address also reserves all addresses in the 0.0.0.0 to 0.255.255.255 (0.0.0.0 /8) address block.<br><br>Loopback:<br>One reserved address is the IPv4 loopback address 127.0.0.1. Addresses 127.0.0.0 to 127.255.255.255 are reserved for loopback where hosts direct traffic to themselves.<br><br>Link-Local Link Addresses:<br>IPv4 addresses in the address block 169.254.0.0 to 169.254.255.255 (169.254.0.0/16) are designated as link-local addresses. These addresses can be automatically assigned to the local host by the operating system in environments where no IP configuration is available. These might be used in a small peer-to-peer network or for a host that could not automatically obtain an address from a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) server.<br><br>TEST-NET Addresses:<br>The address block 192.0.2.0 to 192.0.2.255 (192.0.2.0/24) is set aside for teaching and learning purposes. These addresses can be used in documentation and network examples. Unlike the experimental addresses, network devices accept these addresses in their configurations.<br><br>Question 7: List three reasons for planning and documenting IPv4 addresses.<br>Answer: The allocation of addresses inside the networks should be planned and documented for the purpose of:<br>-	Preventing duplication of addresses.<br>-	Providing and controlling access.<br>-	Monitoring security and performance.<br><br>Question 8: Give examples where network administrators statically and dynamically assign IPv4 addresses.<br>Answer: Static assigned addresses - servers, printers, LAN gateway addresses on routers, management addresses on network devices such as switches, and wireless access points.<br><br>Dynamically assigned addresses - large numbers of general-purpose computers and end devices such as IP phones.<br><br>Question 9: List the features of IPv6 that distinguish it from IPv4.<br>Answer: IPv6 has these features compared to IPv4:<br>-	Improved packet handling<br>-	Increased scalability and longevity<br>-	Q o S mechanisms<br>-	Integrated security<br><br>To provide these features, IPv6 offers:<br>-	128-bit hierarchical addressing to expand addressing capabilities.<br>-	Header format simplification to improve packet handling.<br>-	Improved support for extensions and options for increased scalability and longevity and improved packet handling.<br>-	Flow labeling capability as Q o S mechanisms.<br>-	Authentication and privacy capabilities to integrate security.<br><br>Question 10: State the purpose of the subnet mask in IPv4 addressing.<br>Answer: Network devices use the subnet mask to determine the network or subnet address of an IP address that the device is processing.<br><br>Question 11: List factors that should be considered when planning an IPv4 addressing scheme.<br>Answer: Networks are subnetted to overcome issues with location, size, and control. In designing the addressing, consider these factors for grouping the hosts:<br>-	Grouping based on common geographic location.<br>-	Grouping hosts used for specific purposes.<br>-	Grouping based on ownership.<br><br>Question 12: State three possible levels at which to use the ping utility to test and verify a host's network connectivity.<br>Answer: <br>-	Ping 127.0.0.1 loopback test.<br>-	Ping the host's gateway address or another host on the same network.<br>-	Ping a host on a remote network.<br><br>Question 13: When would using a trace route utility be more useful than ping?<br>Answer: When a remote address cannot be accessed and ping fails. Using trace route shows how many hops toward the destination that the source host could successfully reach. This can help determine where the network is failing or where security restrictions are.<br><br>Question 14: List the reasons why ICMPv4 is an important protocol to have operating with IPv4. <br>Answer: IPv4 is an unreliable best-effort protocol. ICMPv4 provides a means for network problems, such as dropped packets or congestion, to be reported back to the source network or host. Messages include:<br>-	Host conformation<br>-	Unreachable destination or service<br>-	Time exceeded<br>-	Route redirection<br>-	Source quench<br>Note: ICMP does not make IP reliable.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
