<textcomponents>
<component id="play"><text><![CDATA[Play]]></text></component>
<component id="pause"><text><![CDATA[Pause]]></text></component>
<component id="rewind"><text><![CDATA[Rewind]]></text></component>
<component id="forward"><text><![CDATA[Fast Forward]]></text></component>
<component id="mute"><text><![CDATA[Mute]]></text></component>
<component id="unmute"><text><![CDATA[UnMute]]></text></component>
<component id="previous"><text><![CDATA[Restart]]></text></component>
<component id="next"><text><![CDATA[End]]></text></component>
<component id="transcript"><text><![CDATA[Transcript]]></text></component>
<component id="ID_title"><text><![CDATA[<b>Interacting with Customers</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_customer">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Customer</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_technician">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Technician</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[<b>Click Play to view how to handle a customer call.</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[<b>Good morning. This is the ZYX help desk. I am Mark. How can I help you today?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt01inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Be prepared to answer the customer call in accordance with the company customer service policies. Answer the call in a courteous manner and immediately identify yourself and the company.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Hello Mark, I am having trouble getting to the Internet to get my email this morning.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[<b>May I have your name and contract number? I will need to retrieve your information to open a trouble ticket.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt03inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Ask for the customer contact information. Keep the customer informed of what you are doing and why you need the information.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[<b>Sure, Mark, I am Mary Davis and my contract number is M345-678.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt05"><text><![CDATA[<b>Ms. Davis, is your company still located at 2356 West 14th Street? Our records show that you connect to us through a Linksys router.</b> ]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt05inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Follow the help desk script, begin by verifying the information in the customer record.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06"><text><![CDATA[<b>Yes, the information is correct. Will this take very long? We really need access to the email.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[<b>Ms. Davis, I understand that email is critical to your company. I will try to resolve this as quickly as possible. First, I need some additional information to get started. When did this problem first begin?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt07inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Show empathy for the customer. Make sure the customer understands that you will do everything necessary to solve the problem as quickly as possible.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt08"><text><![CDATA[<b>We first noticed it when we came in this morning. The power was out for a short time last night, the time on our clocks is off by an hour.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt09"><text><![CDATA[<b>Are you able to reach any web sites or other Internet services?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt09inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Continue following the script, recording all of the information on the trouble ticket.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt10"><text><![CDATA[<b>No, it appears that we are unable to reach the Internet.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt11"><text><![CDATA[<b>Ms. Davis, may I put you on hold for a short time, while I check the status of the connection from our site to your company router?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt11inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Always ask for permission to place the customer on hold. Keep the customer informed as to what you are doing and why.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt12"><text><![CDATA[<b>Yes, I will wait.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt13"><text><![CDATA[<b>Ms. Davis, it looks like the connection is functioning. Are you near the Linksys router? Are you or someone at your location able to reset the router?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt13inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Avoid using technical terms or jargon, unless the customer does. Always ask if the customer is comfortable performing a task before instructing them to do so.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt14"><text><![CDATA[<b>Yes, what do I need to do?</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt15"><text><![CDATA[<b>Locate the power cord. Unplug the cord and wait a few seconds. Plug the cord back in and wait for the router to power up. The lights on the front indicate when it is ready. It may take a minute for the router to fully power up. Then try your computer to see if you can get your email.</b> ]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt15inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Communicate what to do in plain language, including all of the necessary steps.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt16"><text><![CDATA[<b>Thank you! That seems to have fixed the problem.</b>]]></text></component>
<component id="ID_txt17"><text><![CDATA[<b>Is there anything else that I can do for you today? If not, I will close this trouble ticket.</b>]]></text></component>

<component id="ID_txt17inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Verify that the customer is satisfied and close the trouble ticket.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt18"><text><![CDATA[<b>No, everything seems to be working now. Thank you.</b>]]></text></component>

</textcomponents>