<transcript lastedited="03.27.09 10:03:19">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.9.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.What are the differences between binary and decimal numbers? (Choose two.)<br>A.Decimal numbers are based on powers of 1, and binary numbers are based on powers of 2.<br>B.Binary numbers are based on powers of 2, and decimal numbers are based on powers of 10.<br>C.Computers use binary numbers, and people normally use decimal numbers.<br>D.Numbers typed on a keyboard are entered as binary and converted to decimal by the computer.<br>E.Binary numbers consist of three states: on, off, null. Decimal numbers do not have states.<br><br>2.Refer to the topology description below and current PC and server configurations to answer the question. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Clerical LAN:<br>PC A, PC B, and Clerical server are attached to the Clerical switch, which is connected to interface FA0/0 of the New York router.<br>-PC A IP address: 192.168.100.105/26<br>-PC B IP address: 192.168.100.99/27<br>-Clerical server IP address: 192.168.100.98/27<br>-New York router FA0/0 IP address: 192.168.100.97/27<br><br>Admin LAN:<br>PC C, PC D, and Admin server are attached to the Admin switch, which is connected to interface FA0/1 of the New York router.<br>-PC C IP address: 192.168.100.85/27<br>-PC D IP address: 192.168.100.75/27<br>-Admin server IP address: 192.168.100.66/27<br>-New York router FA0/1 IP address: 192.168.100.65/27<br><br>Host A in the Clerical office failed and was replaced. Although a ping to 127.0.0.1 was successful, the replacement computer cannot access the company network. With proxy ARP disabled on the FA0/0 interface of the New York router, what is the likely cause of the problem?<br>A.Network card failure<br>B.Network cables unplugged<br>C.IP address incorrectly entered<br>D.Subnet mask incorrectly entered<br><br>3.Refer to the following output from the ping commands to answer the question. <br><br>C:\>ping 127.0.0.1<br><br>Pinging 127.0.0.1 with 32 bytes of data:<br><br>Reply from 127.0.0.1: bytes=32 time<1ms TTL 128<br>Reply from 127.0.0.1: bytes=32 time<1ms TTL 128<br>Reply from 127.0.0.1: bytes=32 time<1ms TTL 128<br>Reply from 127.0.0.1: bytes=32 time<1ms TTL 128<br><br>Ping statistics for 127.0.0.1:<br>    Packets: Sent = 4, Received = 4, Lost = 0 (0% loss),<br>Approximate round trip times in milli-seconds:<br>    Minimum = 0ms, Maximum = 0ms, Average = 0ms<br><br>A network administrator is testing the configuration on a host computer. What type of address is 127.0.0.1?<br>A.Link-local<br>B.Loopback<br>C.Public<br>D.Default route<br><br>4.What portion of the IP address does the prefix represent?<br>A.Broadcast<br>B.Host<br>C.Network<br>D.Unicast<br><br>5.Which is true regarding IP network addresses?<br>A.All host bits are set to 0.<br>B.All host bits are set to 1.<br>C.They are assigned the highest address in a range.<br>D.All network bits are set to 1.<br><br>6.Which address type has all host bits set to 1?<br>A.Network<br>B.Broadcast<br>C.Host<br>D.Unicast<br><br>7.How many binary digits (bits) are in an IPv6 address?<br>A.64 bits<br>B.48 bits<br>C.128 bits<br>D.32 bits<br><br>8.What is the primary reason for development of IPv6?<br>A.Security<br>B.Header format simplification<br>C.Expanded addressing capabilities<br>D.Addressing simplification<br><br>9.Refer to the IP addresses listed below:<br>192.168.223.99   192.168.223.107   192.168.223.117   192.168.223.127<br><br>These addresses are part of a single subnet. Which three statements are true regarding these addresses? (Choose three.)<br>A.Their final octet has 4 of the most significant bits in common.<br>B.They have 5 low-order bits in common.<br>C.They have 27 high-order bits in common.<br>D.192.168.223.99 is a feasible network number for their range.<br>E.255.255.255.224 is an appropriate mask for their range.<br>F.192.168.223.127 is the broadcast address for their range.<br><br>10.Match the options with the correct statement.<br>Options:<br>A. 192.168.12.192/30<br>B. 172.27.64.98/23<br>C. 172.18.125.6/20<br>D. 10.1.167.36/13<br>E. 192.168.87.212/24<br>F. 172.31.16.128/19<br><br>Statements:<br>Four bits borrowed from classful network subnets.<br>Eight subnets from the classful network.<br>Two usable hosts per subnet.<br>A classful network.<br>512 addresses per subnet.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
