<transcript lastedited="10.29.08 14:10:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.2.4  - Switches for Small and Medium Sized Business (SMB)]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts photographs and features of Cisco Catalyst Switch product lines. The product lines are grouped according to features, scalability, and longevity, as well by organization, size, and density (small, medium, or large).<br><br>The Cisco switch product lines are as follows:<br><br>The Catalyst Express 500 access level switch is geared toward small businesses with 20 to 250 employees. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates of 8.8 Gigabits per second to 24 Gigabits per second.<br>-	Web-based management only.<br>-	Fast Ethernet and Gigabit Ethernet connectivity.<br>-	Port densities to 24 10 100 ports (P o E optional) or 12 10 100 1000 ports.<br><br>The Catalyst 2960 access level switch is geared toward entry-level enterprise, medium-sized, and branch office networks. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates of 16 Gigabits per second to 32 Gigabits per second.<br>-	Cisco C L I and web-based management.<br>-	Advanced LAN features, including multilayered switching, Q o S, and access control lists (or ACL's).<br>-	Fast Ethernet and Gigabit Ethernet connectivity.<br>-	Up to 48 10 100 ports or 10 100 1000 ports, but does not support P o E.<br>-	Dual purpose gigabit uplinks.<br><br>The Catalyst 3560 access level switch is geared toward small enterprise LAN access or branch-office converged network environments. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates between 32 Gigabits per second to 128 Gigabits per second Cisco C L I and web-based management.<br>-	Advanced LAN features, including Q o S and ACL's.<br>-	Fast Ethernet and Gigabit Ethernet connectivity.<br>-	Up to 48 10 100 1000 ports plus 4 SFP ports.<br>-	10 Gigabit Ethernet connectivity through the Catalyst 3560-E.<br>-	24 15.4 watt P o E ports or 48 7.3 watt P o E ports.<br><br>The Catalyst 3750 access level switch is geared toward midsize organizations and enterprise branch offices. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates between 32 Gigabits per second to 128 Gigabits per second.<br>-	Cisco StackWise technology.<br>-	Cisco C L I and web-based management.<br>-	Advanced LAN features, including Q o S and ACL's.<br>-	Fast Ethernet and Gigabit Ethernet connectivity.<br>-	Up to 48 10 100 1000 ports plus 4 SFP ports.<br>-	10 Gigabit Ethernet connectivity through the Catalyst 3750-E.<br>-	24 15.4 watt P o E ports or 48 7.3 watt P o E ports.<br><br>The Catalyst 4500 access, distribution, and core level switch is geared toward midsize organizations and enterprise branch offices. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates up to 136 gigabits per second.<br>-	Modular 3, 6, 7, and 10 slot chassis.<br>-	Cisco C L I web-based management.<br>-	Advanced LAN features, including multilayer switching, hardware-assisted IP routing, Q o S, and ACL's.<br>-	384 Fast Ethernet, Gigabit with 10 Gigabit Ethernet fiber uplink ports, with P o E as an optional feature.<br>-	Dual, hot-swappable internal power supplies.<br><br>The Catalyst 4948 specialty access level switch is optimized for data centers. It supports the following:<br>-	96 Gigabits per second with a forwarding rate of 72 million packets per second.<br>-	Cisco C L I and web-based management.<br>-	Adanced LAN features, including multilayer switching, Q o S, and ACL's.<br>-	48 10 100 1000 ports with 4 SFP ports or 48 10 100 1000 ports with 2 10 Gigabit Ethernet ports.<br>-	Dual, hot-swappable internal power supplies and hot-swappable fan trays.<br><br>The Catalyst 6500 access, distribution, and core level switch is geared toward midsize organizations and enterprise branch offices. It supports the following:<br>-	Forwarding rates up to 720 Gigabits per second.<br>-	Modular 3, 4, 6, 9, and 13 slot chassis.<br>-	Cisco C L I and web-based management.<br>-	Advanced LAN features, including LAN WAN service modules, multilayer switching, hardware-assisted IP routing, Q o S, and ACL's. <br>-	1152 10 100 ports, 577 10 100 1000 ports, 410 SFP Gigabit Ethernet ports, or 64 10 Gigabit Ethernet ports.<br>-	420 15.4 watt P o E devices<br>-	Dual, hot-swappable internal power supplies.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
