<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Service Level Agreement</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Service Description</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Availability, Performance and Reliability</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Tracking and Reporting</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Problem Management</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Security</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Termination</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Penalties for Service Outages</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Costs</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle">
<text><![CDATA[Service Description]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Defines the range of services that an ISP will provide. </li><li>Includes the service amount or service volume and the times when the service is and is not covered by the SLA. </li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle2">
<text><![CDATA[Availability, Performance and Reliability]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody2">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Availability - hours and days per month per year that service is available. </li><li>Performance - a measure of service capability expectations during peak data volumes. </li><li>An example of this is the rule of five-9s, which states that the system should be operational 99.999% of the time.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle3">
<text><![CDATA[Tracking and Reporting]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody3">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Defines how often reports, such as performance reports, will be provided to the customer.</li><li>Includes a written explanation of what level of network service users are experiencing.</li> ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody4">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Response time – A measure of how fast an ISP can respond to unexpected events that cause the service to stop. </li><li>Defines the process that will be used to handle and resolve unplanned incidents</li><li>Defines what the different levels of a problem are and who should be called for each problem level.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle4">
<text><![CDATA[Problem Management]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody5">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Define security measures that are ISP responsibilities versus customer responsibilities.</li><li>Determines how network services that the ISP offers fit within the security policies of the customer and the ISP.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle5">
<text><![CDATA[Security]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody6">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Defines termination agreement and costs if services are terminated early.  Typically SLAs are renegotiated annually and coincide with the budget cycle of the customer.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle6">
<text><![CDATA[Termination]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody7">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Describe the penalties for a network service failure. This is especially important if the ISP is providing services critical for business operation.</li> ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle7">
<text><![CDATA[Penalties for Service Outages]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtBody8">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Describes the charges to the customer by defining services rather than equipment. The ISP is able to cost out the services needed and the customer only pays for the services used.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_txtTitle8">
<text><![CDATA[Costs]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over the parts of the SLA for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>