<transcript lastedited="06.13.08 05:06:48">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.2.4 Email Clients and Servers]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts two images. The first is the POP3/SMTP email client and server interaction. The second is the I MAP4/SMTP email and client interaction. The two images are described in further detail below:<br><br>POP3/SMTP Email Client and Server<br>The diagram depicts a PC and an email server positioned next to each other. The PC has the labels POP3 Client and SMTP Client. The server has been identified as the POP3 server. Its destination port is 110. It also has the SMTP protocol active. The SMTP server has a destination port of 25. The source PC sends email using the SMTP protocol to the email server. The mail server forwards email to the destination host PC with the POP3 protocol. The SMTP protocol is used to contact the server and send a message. Email servers also use SMTP to transfer mail between themselves. The POP3 protocol is used to download messages to the client from the server. The following are descriptions given in the diagram:<br><br>POP3<br>Used by the client to contact the server and download mail. <br>Mail is deleted off the server.<br><br>SMTP<br>Used by the client to forward mail to the server. <br>Server accepts and stores the mail in the proper queue.<br><br>I MAP4/SMTP Email Client and Server<br>The diagram depicts a PC and an email server positioned next to each other. The PC has the labels I MAP4 Client and SMTP Client. The server has been identified as the I MAP4 server. Its destination port is 143. It also has the SMTP protocol active. The SMTP server has a destination port of 25. The source PC sends email using the SMTP protocol to the email server. The mail server allows the host PC to access mail on the server using the I MAP4 protocol. The SMTP protocol is used to contact the server and send the message. The I MAP4 protocol is used to read messages stored on the IMAP server. The following are descriptions given in the diagram:<br><br>I MAP4<br>Used by the client to contact the server and access mail.  <br>Mail is maintained on the server.<br><br>SMTP<br>Used by the client to forward mail to the server.  <br>Server accepts and stores the mail in the proper queue.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
