<transcript lastedited="09.26.08 09:09:09">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.5.1 - Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a hierarchical network with three separate LAN's are connected to routers which converge to a single router before connecting to the network cloud.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>A single broadcast domain is a non-hierarchical or flat network. <br>A hierarchical addressing structure logically groups networks into smaller sub-networks. <br>A hierarchical network design simplifies network management and improves scalability and performance.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a network 10.3.2.0 /24 that has been subnetted using the /28 mask.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>With basic or standard subnetting, each subnet is the same size and has the same number of hosts. <br>Variable Length Subnet Masking (VLSM) enables routers to use route summarization to reduce the size of routing tables. <br>Variable Length Subnet Masking (VLSM) enables different masks for each subnet. <br>A subnet can be further subnetted, creating sub-subnets. <br>VLSM requires classless routing protocols. <br>When implementing VLSM, ensure room for growth in the number of subnets and hosts available.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts how known networks are summarized into a summary route. <br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>Classful IP addressing determines the subnet mask of a network address by the value of the first octet. <br>With C I D R, the network address is not determined by the class of the address. Instead it is determined by the prefix length. <br>Route summarization groups contiguous subnets using a single address and shorter mask to reduce the number of routes advertised. <br>Route summarization, route aggregation, or supernetting are done at network boundaries on a boundary router. <br>The use of classful routing protocols can create the issue of discontiguous networks.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts how routers use NAT translation to forward packets.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>Private addresses are used and routed internally, but are not routed on the Internet. <br>NAT translates private addresses into public addresses that route into the Internet. <br>Static NAT maps a single inside local address to a single inside global (public) address. <br>Dynamic NAT uses an available pool of public addresses and assigns them to inside local addresses. <br>PAT translates multiple local addresses to a single global IP address.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
