<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_title">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Becoming Cisco Certified</b>]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_page1">
         <text><![CDATA[page 1 of 2]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page2">
         <text><![CDATA[page 2 of 2]]></text>
</component>
   

<component id="ID_txt01">
         <text><![CDATA[This CCNA Discovery course is the first step along the journey towards becoming a valuable networking professional.  With the knowledge, skills and abilities you have acquired in this course, you can immediately begin your career in home and small business network support. Ask your instructor if your school participates in a network internship or volunteer program, where you can gain valuable experience.<br><br>Obtaining an industry recognized certification is one way to validate your networking abilities to future employers.  The Discovery series of courses offered through the Networking Academy program are an excellent way to prepare for the Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA) exam.]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_txt02">
         <text><![CDATA[The CCNA Discovery Series includes this course, as well as the next three courses in the series: 
<br/><li><b>Working at a Small-to-Medium Business or ISP</b> - Prepare to take the first in Cisco Certified Network Associate certification exam series while you learn the skills to work at an ISP or SMB as a help desk or on-site support technician.</li><br/><li><b>Introducing Routing and Switching in the Enterprise</b>- Learn how enterprise networks support critical business applications. Further refine and enhance your networking skills as you prepare for the Cisco CCNA certification.</li><br/><li><b>Designing and Supporting Computer Networks</b> - Learn the concepts that contribute to good network design. These skills prepare you for entry-level pre-sale positions with network vendors, as well as provide the fundamental knowledge necessary for students to start their own small network support businesses.</li>]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>


