<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 18:01:14">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.7.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Which are two problems associated with redundant switched Ethernet topologies? (Choose two.)<br>A.Broadcast storms.<br>B.Routing loops.<br>C.Multiple frame copies.<br>D.Load balancing.<br>E.Incorrect frame addressing.<br>F.Unicast frame flooding.<br><br>2.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Switch SW-1 and SW-2 are connected to each other using two links, Segment A and Segment B. A PC and router are also attached to Segment A.<br><br>The network described above is not running spanning-tree algorithm. What would be the result if an ARP request were sent by the workstation?<br>A.The frame will loop between SW-1 and SW-2 until the TTL field drops to zero.<br>B.The frame will loop until the TTL field reaches the default maximum value.<br>C.The frame will be prevented from traveling the network by the router.<br>D.The frame will loop between SW-1 and SW-2 repeatedly.<br><br>3.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Four switches are interconnected. Switch-A is connected to Switch-C, Switch-D, and a router. Switch-B is connected to Switch-A, Switch-C, Switch-D, and the same router. Switch-C is connected to Switch-A, Switch-B, Switch-D, and Switch-E. Switch-D is connected to Switch-A, Switch-B, Switch-C, and Switch-E.<br><br>How will spanning tree prevent switching loops in this network if all switches have only the default V LAN configured?<br>A.Traffic will be load-balanced between all switches.<br>B.A single switch will be elected as the root switch, and redundant paths to this switch will be blocked.<br>C.Two of the switches will be elected root bridges, thus blocking traffic between the other two switches.<br>D.Two of the switches will be elected designated switches, thus blocking traffic between the other two switches.<br>E.Either Switch-A or Switch-B will be elected as the root switch, and Switch-C or Switch-D will become the designated switch.<br><br>4.What must a switch running spanning tree do when it is first turned on?<br>A.Adjust its bridge priority value.<br>B.Learn the B ID's of all other switches in the network.<br>C.Request the MAC address of all connected hosts.<br>D.Select the BPDU with the greatest MAC address.<br>E.Adjust its bridge priority value to network conditions.<br><br>5.Match the spanning-tree protocol variants to the appropriate description.<br><br>Protocol Variants:<br>A. CST.<br>B. MSTP.<br>C. PVST.<br>D. PVST+.<br>E. Rapid PVST+.<br>F. RSTP.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Supports the use of ISL trunking and load balancing.<br>Two. Incorporated into i e e e 8 0 2 dot 1D-2004; supports BackboneFast, UplinkFast, and PortFast.<br>Three. Supports BackboneFast, UplinkFast, and PortFast and is based on i e e e 8 0 2 dot 1w.<br>Four. Supports BPDU guard, root guard, and i e e e 8 0 2 dot 1Q trunking.<br>Five. Reduces the number of spanning-tree instances required to support large numbers of V LAN's.<br>Six. Only one spanning-tree instance encompassing every V LAN in the network.<br><br>6.Which three port types will discard data traffic during STP operation? (Choose three.)<br>A.blocking ports.<br>B.disabled ports.<br>C.designated ports.<br>D.root ports.<br>E.forwarding ports.<br>F.listening ports.<br><br>7.Match the spanning-tree port states with their activities.<br><br>States:<br>A. Learning.<br>B. Disabled.<br>C. Forwarding.<br>D. Listening.<br>E. Blocking.<br><br>Activities:<br>One. Does not receive BPDU's.<br>Two. Receives BPDU's only.<br>Three. Receives BPDU's and processes BPDU's.<br>Four. Receives BPDU's, processes BPDU's, and fills the MAC address table.<br>Five. Receives BPDU's, processes BPDU's, fills the MAC table, and sends data.<br><br>8.Which three timers determine STP performance and state changes? (Choose three.)<br>A.blocking delay.<br>B.hello time.<br>C.port speed.<br>D.forward delay.<br>E.maximum age.<br>F.backward delay.<br><br>9.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Three switches are interconnected. Switch Cat-A is connected to switch Cat-B, Cat-C, Cat-D, and a router. Switch Cat-B is connected to switch Cat-A, Cat-C, and the same router. Switch Cat-C is connected to switch Cat-A and Cat-B.<br><br>Bridge information provided:<br>Switch Cat-A:<br>Bridge Priority: 32768<br>MAC Address: 0010.0da2.000c<br><br>Switch Cat-B:<br>Bridge Priority: 48252<br>MAC Address: 0010.0da2.0001<br><br>Switch Cat-C:<br>Bridge Priority: 32768<br>MAC Address: 0010.0da2.000a<br><br>What will be the result of the spanning-tree root bridge selection process in the network described above if each switch contains only one V LAN?<br>A.Cat-A will be the root bridge.<br>B.Cat-B will be the root bridge.<br>C.Cat-C will be the root bridge.<br>D.Cat-A and Cat-B will be the root bridges.<br>E.Cat-A and Cat-C will be the root bridges.<br><br>10.Per-V LAN Spanning Tree Protocol plus (PVST+) provides support for which i e e e standard?<br>A.8 0 2 dot 1Q<br>B.8 0 2 dot 1D<br>C.8 0 2 dot 1w<br>D.8 0 2 dot 1<br><br>11.Which two characteristics are associated with Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (RSTP)? (Choose two.)<br>A.Supports UplinkFast and BackboneFast.<br>B.Preferred protocol for preventing Layer 2 loops.<br>C.Forward delay and max-age timers are unneeded.<br>D.Lacks backward compatibility with i e e e 8 0 2 dot 1D.<br>E.Compatible with rapid PVST+.<br><br>12.What is a characteristic of an RSTP edge port?<br>A.It remains in the learning state until it receives a BPDU from the root bridge.<br>B.It goes directly from the listening state to the forwarding state.<br>C.After it is enabled, it immediately transitions to the forwarding state.<br>D.It generates and propagates topology changes when it transitions to a disabled status.<br><br>13.When implementing RSTP for non-edge ports, which two categories of link types are available? (Choose two.)<br>A.Shared.<br>B.Multipoint.<br>C.Redundant.<br>D.Point-to-point.<br>E.Dedicated.<br><br>14.What method does RSTP use to decrease the time it takes to designate a new root port when the existing root port fails?<br>A.Smaller values for forward-delay and max-age timers than STP.<br>B.Pre-negotiated alternate ports for the root port.<br>C.TCN BPDU's originating from the affected switch.<br>D.Improved spanning-tree algorithm.<br><br>15.A switch currently has only one V LAN configured and is running a single instance of RSTP. Which action will create a second RSTP instance?<br>A.Creating a second V LAN.<br>B.Entering the spanning-tree mode rapid pvst command.<br>C.Assigning a port to a V LAN other than V LAN 1.<br>D.Connecting to another switch.<br><br>16.Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>Four switches are interconnected.<br>Switch S1 port Gigabit 0/1 is connected to S2 port Gigabit 0/1.<br>Switch S1 port Gigabit 0/2 is connected to S3 port Gigabit 0/1.<br>Switch S2 port Gigabit 0/2 is connected to S4 port Gigabit 0/1.<br>Switch S3 port Gigabit 0/2 is connected to S4 port Gigabit 0/2.<br><br>Bridge information provided:<br>S1 Bridge Priority: 24576<br>MAC Address: 000A00333333<br><br>S2 Bridge Priority: 32768<br>MAC Address: 000A00222222<br><br>S3 Bridge Priority: 32768<br>MAC Address: 000A00111111<br><br>S4 Bridge Priority: 36864<br>MAC Address: 000A00111110<br><br>Spanning-tree port priorities are listed beneath each interface. S4 port Gigabit 0/2 is currently in RSTP discarding state. What action would change the state to forwarding?<br>A.Changing the physical port connections so that Gigabit 0/2 connects to S2, and Gigabit 0/1 connects to S3.<br>B.Using the spanning-tree v lan priority command to increase the priority of Gigabit 0/2 for all V LAN's.<br>C.Changing the port role for Gigabit 0/1 to non-designated, using the spanning-tree port priority command.<br>D.Making S4 the root bridge by manually configuring the MAC address to a lower value than S1. <br><br>17.Refer to the following command output to answer the question. <br>SW4#show spanning-tree<br>V LAN 0001<br>  Spanning tree enabled protocol i e e e<br>Root IDPriority 24577<br>Address0019.2f8d.d200<br>Cost 27<br>Port 16 (FastEthernet 0/14)<br>Hello Time3 sec Max Age 20 sec Forward Delay 15 sec<br><br>Bridge ID Priority28673 (priority 28672 sys-id-ext 1)<br>Address0019.2f94.a480<br>Hello Time2 sec Max Age 20 sec Forward Delay 15 sec<br>Aging Time 300<br><br>Which two statements are true regarding the V LAN 0001 spanning-tree environment that switch SW4 is participating in? (Choose two.)<br>A.Spanning tree for V LAN 0001 is using the default hello time interval.<br>B.The root bridge was selected because of its lower MAC address.<br>C.The root port on SW4 is FastEthernet 0/14.<br>D.SW4 is directly connected to port 16 on the root switch.<br>E.The root bridge does not have an aging time.<br>F.SW4 is using the timers advertised by the root switch.<br><br>18.Refer to the following command output to answer the question.<br><br>SW4(config)#interface range FA0/1 - 24<br>SW4(config-i f-range)#spanning-tree portfast<br>output omitted.<br><br>SW4#show spanning-tree interface FA0/1 portfast<br>V LAN 0001enabled<br><br>SW4#show spanning-tree interface FA0/2 portfast<br>V LAN 0001enabled<br><br>SW4#show spanning-tree interface FA0/3 portfast<br>V LAN 0001enabled<br><br>SW4#show spanning-tree interface FA0/4 portfast<br>V LAN 0001disabled<br><br>Why would interface FA0/4 have spanning-tree portfast disabled?<br>A.Interface FA0/4 is not active.<br>B.Interface FA0/4 could not transition into forwarding mode and was thus disabled.<br>C.Interface FA0/4 did not receive a BPDU, allowing PortFast to be enabled.<br>D.Interfaces FA0/1 to 3 are connected to end workstations, while interface FA0/4 is connected to another Layer 2 device.<br><br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
