<transcript lastedited="08.12.08 13:08:54">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.5.2 - Critical Thinking]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts an activity in which you must answer questions regarding routing based on an EIGRP network topology diagram.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Five routers, R1, R2, R3, R4 and R5 are connected in an EIGRP routing environment. The following connections are present:<br>Router R1. is connected to stub network LAN2 with a metric of One.<br>Router R1 is connected to Router R2 with a metric of Three.<br>Router R2 is connected to Router R3 with a metric of Two.<br>Router R2 is connected to Router R4 with a metric of One.<br>Router R3 is connected to Router R4 with a metric of One.<br>Router R3 is connected to Router R5 with a metric of One.<br>Router R4 is connected to Router R5 with a metric of Three.<br>Router R4 is connected to stub network LAN1 with a metric of One.<br><br>Questions:<br>Question One. What is the advertised distance to LAN1 from R2 via R4?<br>A.One<br>B.Two<br>C.Three<br>D.Four<br><br>Question Two. What is the feasible distance to LAN2 from R3 via R2?<br>A.Two<br>B.Three<br>C.Four<br>D.Five<br>E.Six<br><br>Question Three. What is the feasible distance to LAN2 from R5 via R4?<br>A.Three<br>B.Four<br>C.Five<br>D.Six<br>E.Seven<br>F.Eight<br><br>Question Four. What is the advertised distance to LAN1 from R5 via R4?<br>A.One<br>B.Two<br>C.Three<br>D.Four<br><br>Question Five. What is the best route to take to reach LAN2 from R5?<br>A.R4 - R2 - R1<br>B.R3 - R2 - R1<br>C.R4 - R3 - R2 - R1<br>D.R3 - R4 - R2 - R1<br><br>Question Six. Which statement is true about the path to LAN2 from R5 via R4 - R2 - R1?<br>A.This route is the successor.<br>B.This route is used as the feasible successor.<br>C.This route is placed in the routing table.<br>D.This route is placed in the neighbor table.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
