<transcript lastedited="09.26.08 09:09:38">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.4.3 - Static and Dynamic NAT]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts the addressing configuration using two processes, Static NAT and Dynamic NAT. <br><br>Host H3, within a cloud, has been configured with a public IP address 200.165.202.130.  H3 connects via a serial link in the cloud to router R1. R1 has a switch directly connected. Two computers H1 and H2 are connected to the switch. H1 and H2 have been configured with the private IP addresses 192.168.2.18 and 192.168.2.19 respectively. Also connected to R1 is the web server with the private IP address 192.168.1.200.  <br><br>In the Static NAT process, H3 sends a message out to R1 using the source IP address 209.165.202.130 and the destination IP address 209.165.200.225, which is the Inside Global address of R1. R1 references its NAT Table and changes the destination IP to the Inside Local address of 192.168.1.200 (web server). The web server responds with a destination IP address of H3, the original requester, 209.165.202.130 and a source address of the inside local address (web server) 192.168.1.200, R1 maps the Inside Local address of 192.168.1.200 to the Inside Global address 209.165.200.225, which becomes the new source address. Static NAT is configured manually and remains permanently in the table.<br><br>In the Dynamic NAT process, H2 sends a message to R1 using the source IP address 192.168.2.19 and the destination IP address for H3, which is 209.165.202.130. R1 references its NAT Table and changes the Inside Local Source IP address of 192.168.2.19 to a public address 209.165.200.226, which is derived from its pool of public IP's 209.165.200.224 /27. H3 responds to H2 using the Inside Global public IP 209.165.200.226. R1 references its NAT Table and sees that the Inside Global address 209.165.200.226 maps to the Inside Local address 192.168.2.19.  When H2 receives the response and the session is complete, the NAT entry is removed from the NAT Table of R1.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
