<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 17:01:27">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.6.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question One. Match the term with the appropriate description.<br>Answer:<br>A. Wireless router: Performs the role of a switch, a router, and an access point.<br>B. Wireless NIC: Encodes a data stream onto an RF signal.<br>C. Wireless access point: Not required for RF communication between two devices.<br><br>Question Two. What is the abbreviation for each of the wireless technologies described?<br>Answer:<br>Open Access: SSID.<br>- No encryption.<br>- Basic authentication.<br>- Not a security handle.<br><br>First Generation Encryption: WEP.<br>- No strong authentication.<br>- Static, breakable keys.<br>- Not scalable.<br><br>Interim: WPA<br>- Standardized.<br>- Improved encryption.<br>- Strong, user-based authentication (for example, LEAP, PEAP, E AP-FAST).<br><br>Present: 8 0 2 dot 11i or WPA2<br>- An E S Encryption.<br>- Authentication: 8 0 2 dot 1x.<br>- Dynamic key management.<br>- WPA2 is the WiFi Alliance implementation of 8 0 2 dot 11i.<br><br>Question Three. For the most rudimentary wireless security, which two of the displayed settings should be changed?<br><br>Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br>The Linksys G U I Wireless Tab screenshot shows the Basic Wireless Settings option selected. <br>The Linksys G U I screenshot shows the following parameter settings:<br>Wireless Network Name (SSID): linksys-n.<br>Wireless Network Mode: B / G / N Mixed.<br>Wireless Channel: 6 - 2.437 Gigahertz.<br>Wireless SSID Broadcast: Enabled.<br><br>Answer:<br>One. Change the SSID to something other than Linksys (the default).<br>Two. Change the SSID broadcast setting to disabled.<br><br><br>Question Four. The wireless laptop associated with WRS3 is unable to communicate with the rest of the network. What are three possible problems? <br>Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Three switches, S1, S2, and S3, are interconnected in a full mesh with dual trunk links. In addition:<br>Switch S1 is connected to router R1.<br>Switch S2 is connected to wired PC1 and PC2.<br>Switch S2 is connected to AP WRS2.<br>Switch S3 is connected to AP to WRS3.<br>AP WRS2 is communicating with two wireless laptops.<br>AP WRS3 is not communicating with any wireless laptop.<br><br>Situation: The laptop does not have connectivity with AP WRS3.<br><br>Possible Answers:<br>1. The SSID does not match the SSID of WRS3.<br>2. The security mode does not match that of WRS3 (for example, WEP, WPA, or WPA2).<br>3. The security key does not match that of WRS3.<br>4. The channel setting does not match that of WRS3.<br>5. There is RF interference or the distance to WRS3 is too great.<br>6. The drivers on the laptop need to be upgraded to support the appropriate wireless protocol.<br>7. The firmware on WRS3 needs to be upgraded to support the appropriate wireless protocol.<br>8. The laptop user is unable to authenticate to obtain network access.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
