<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 10:09:29">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.4.1 - Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts an enterprise network.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>A large business environment with many users and locations or many systems is referred to as an enterprise.<br>The enterprise network supports mission critical applications, network traffic, centralized control, and diverse business needs.<br><br>The enterprise network:<br><br>Provides 99.99% up time.<br>Uses both LAN and WAN components.<br>Utilizes many different types of technology.<br>Makes uses of services of ISPs.<br>Carries many types of traffic including voice, video, and data.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the Cisco Enterprise Architecture with three sub-blocks labeled Enterprise Campus, Enterprise Edge, WAN and Internet, as well as two smaller blocks labeled Enterprise Branch and Teleworker. <br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>Enterprise Campus - Consists of the campus infrastructure with server farms and network management.<br>Enterprise Edge - Consists of the Internet, VPN, and WAN modules connecting the enterprise with the service providers network.<br><br>Service Provider Edge - Provides Internet, Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN), and WAN services.<br><br>Failure Domain - Describes the devices impacted on a portion of a network when a key device or service experiences problems.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts intranets and extranets. <br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>An intranet is a private network that utilizes TCP/IP and other services to provide private services for company employees.<br>If vendors and customers, and other outside individuals, access the intranet, it is known as an extranet.<br>Confine network traffic only to the segment where it is required.<br>Some traffic moves through the enterprise WAN, and other traffic moves external to the enterprise network.<br>Q o S allows some traffic to be given preferential treatment over other traffic, such as voice and video traffic over data traffic.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a woman that is teleworking.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>Teleworking is the use of technology to replace business travel.<br>Teleworking has many advantages for the employer, the employee, and the environment.<br>As technology advances, the numbers of jobs suit-ed for telecommuting are increasing.<br>Teleworkers use tools like email, chat, desktop and application sharing, FTP, Telnet, V o IP, and video conferencing to make their jobs easier.<br>VPNs address the security needs of teleworkers by creating an encrypted tunnel between the sites.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
