<transcript lastedited="12.15.08 14:12:29">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.2.2 Wireless LAN Components]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Three Diagrams<br><br>Diagram 1, Interactive<br><br>The diagram depicts different types of wireless networks, including a Wireless Access Point Network and Wireless Bridge Network. Brief description are given for the various networks.<br><br>Wireless Access Point Network<br>The Wireless Access point network has a Linksys WRT300N router, which has three clients connected to it via WI FI.<br><br>Wireless Bridge Network<br>The Wireless Bridge Network has two wireless bridges connected to one another via WI FI. Each bridge also has four clients attached, which are also connected via WI FI.<br><br>Wireless Client<br>Any host device that can participate in a wireless network. Most devices that can be connected to a traditional wired network can be connected to a W LAN, if equipped with the proper wireless NIC and software.<br>Can either be stationary or mobile.<br>Commonly referred to as  S T A, which is short for station.<br>Examples include laptops, PDA's, printers, projectors, and storage devices.<br><br>Access Point<br>Controls access between a wired and a wireless network. For example: It allows wireless clients to gain access to a wired network, and vice versa.<br>Acts as a media converter, accepting the Ethernet frames from the wired network and converting them to 8 0 2 dot 11 compliant frames before transmitting them on the W LAN.<br>Accepts 8 0 2 dot 11 frames from the W LAN and converts them into Ethernet frames before placing them onto the wired network.<br>AP's support wireless connections within a limited area, known as a cell, or Basic Service Set (BSS).<br><br>Wireless Bridge<br>Used to connect two wired networks through a wireless link.<br>Allows long range, point to point connections between networks.<br>Using the unlicensed RF frequencies, networks 25 miles (40 km) or more apart can be connected without the use of wires.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
