<textcomponents>
<component id="clientTitle">
	<text>Wireless Clients</text>
</component>
<component id="clientBody">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Client</b><br><li>Any host device that can participate in a wireless network.  Most devices that can be connected to a traditional wired network can be connected to a WLAN if equipped with the proper wireless NIC and software.</li><li>Can either be stationary or mobile.</li><li>Commonly referred to as a STA, short for station.</li><li>Examples include: laptops, PDAs, printers, projectors and storage devices.</li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="apTitle">
	<text>Access Points</text>
</component>
<component id="apBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Access Point</b><br><li>Controls access between a wired and a wireless network.  I.E. allows wireless clients to gain access to a wired network and vice versa.</li><li>Acts as a media converter accepting the Ethernet frames from the wired network and converting them to 802.11 compliant frames before transmitting them on the WLAN.</li><li>Accepts 802.11 frames from the WLAN and converts them into Ethernet frames before placing them onto the wired network.</li><li>APs support wireless connections within a limited area, known as a <u>cell</u> or <u>Basic Service Set (BSS)</u></li>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="bridgeTitle">
	<text>Wireless Bridge</text>
</component>
<component id="bridgeBody">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Bridge</b><br><li>Used to connect two wired networks through a wireless link.</li><li>Allows long-range point-to-point connections between networks.</li><li>Using the unlicensed RF frequencies, networks 40 km (25 miles) or more apart can be connected without the use of wires.</li>]]></text>
	</component>




<component id="ID_inst">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Click each highlighted wireless component for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_ap">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Access Point</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wc1">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Client</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wc2">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Client</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wc3">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Client</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wapn">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Access Point Network</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wb">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Bridge</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wb1">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Bridge</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_wbn">
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Wireless Bridge Network</b>]]></text>
</component>




</textcomponents>