<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><textcomponents><component id="Button1"><text><![CDATA[<b>Information needed</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Possible incorrect outcomes if I do not possess the necessary knowledge</b>]]></text></component><component id="Button3"><text><![CDATA[<b>Possible symptoms of problems</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each area of analysis that should be considered when studying the RIP routing protocol.</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_header"><text><![CDATA[Task: Configure RIPv2 to route network traffic.]]></text></component><component id="Title1"><text><![CDATA[<b>Information needed:</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table1"><text><![CDATA[<font size="-4">&#8226; Steps to configure RIPv2 routing.    1. Log in to the router    2. Enter privileged mode    3. Enter configuration mode    4. Enable RIP    5. Enable version 2    6. Configure a network statement for each connected network that participates in RIP.&#8226; Cisco IOS commands to enable RIPv2 routing.    1. Config t    2. Router rip    3. Version 2    4. Network [address]    5. Copy running-config startup-confi&#8226; Network addresses for each connected network.&#8226; Methods to verify if RIPv2 is configured correctly and working.    1. Use show running-configuration command    2. Use show ip route command    3. Ping from a host to a remote IP address on another network    4. Trace the route through the router to a remote IP address    5. Use debug to verify that RIPv2 routing updates are being sent and received</font>]]></text></component><component id="Title2"><text><![CDATA[<b>Possible incorrect outcomes:</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table2"><text><![CDATA[<ul><li>I cannot enter configuration mode to begin the configuration.</li><li>I forget to configure version 2 or add the network statements.</li><li>I do not configure all the networks.</li><li>I enter the wrong IP address information.</li><li>I cannot verify if RIPv2 is operating correctly.</li></ul>]]></text></component><component id="Title3"><text><![CDATA[<b>Possible symptoms of problems:</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table3"><text><![CDATA[<ul><li>Cannot ping hosts on other networks</li><li>Cannot traceroute through the router</li><li>No routes appear in routing table of router </li></ul>]]></text></component><component id="Title4"><text><![CDATA[<b>Proposed Cost</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table4"><text><![CDATA[Section with budget details that may include but is not limited to:&#8226; Software and application components&#8226; Hardware components and interfaces&#8226; Licensing required&#8226; Fees or permit costs&#8226; Training charges&#8226; Warranty, maintenance, and support costs&#8226; Labor cost per hour or flat fees related to staff working on project&#8226; Travel expenses if applicable&#8226; Telecommunication service provider charges for changes and upgrades&#8226; Specific tools or equipment required to complete the job&#8226; Removal or disposal costs if applicable&#8226; Costs related to equipment rental such as forklifts needed for implementation&#8226; Electrician charges&#8226; Methods of payments including leasing options if appropriate&#8226; Final payment method after acceptance]]></text></component><component id="Title5"><text><![CDATA[<b>Signature Page</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table5"><text><![CDATA[Section of proposal that is signed by customer representative with authority to accept the project. ]]></text></component><component id="Title6"><text><![CDATA[<b>Appendices</b>]]></text></component><component id="Table6"><text><![CDATA[Section with additional information supporting proposal that may include:&#8226; Detailed lists of equipment and services&#8226; Diagrams and forms related to equipment and services list&#8226; Background company information which may include items such as:  - Size of company as it relates to total number of employees and revenues earned  - Services and products the company provides  - Reference list of previous customers for projects similar to the current RFP   - Brief biographies of employees who will be working on the project including their education<br>    and certifications  - The insurance and liability coverage of the company relating to projects  - Identification of outside vendors, if the company plans to use subcontractors, as part of the service and product structure]]></text></component></textcomponents>