<chapter type="" id="en1204000000">
<title><content-text>Identifying Application Impacts on Network Design</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1204000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm4049808882">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204000000/en1204000100/en1204000101/cm4049808882.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204000000/en1204000100/en1204000101/cm4049808882text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1204010000">
<title><content-text>Characterizing Network Applications</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204010100">
<title><content-text>The Importance of Application Performance</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7741533127">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010100/en1204010101/cm7741533127.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010100/en1204010101/cm7741533127text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most people who use network services know very little about the underlying network or network design. Their experience as users is based on how they interact with the applications that run on the network. </p> <p>In the case of the sports stadium, network-based applications provide essential services to the fans, the teams, and the management. These services, and the network on which they reside, are among the business-critical elements ensuring that customer and user demands are met.</p> <p>Gathering statistical information from routers, servers, and other network devices helps determine whether a system is functioning to manufacturer specifications. However, technical considerations alone do not determine success in the marketplace.</p> <p>Success depends on how the customer, the suppliers, and the vendors view the performance of the network. </p> <p>For end users, application performance is based on:</p> <p><ul><li> Availability-Is the application working when they need it?</li><li> Responsiveness-Is the application responding as quickly as expected?</li></ul></p> <p>For example, in the stadium, revenue from ticket sales, concessions, and souvenirs suffers when transaction processes are not available or are taking too long to complete.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6594568809">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010100/en1204010102/cm6594568809.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010100/en1204010102/cm6594568809text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Stadium customers rate the convenience of an application by the length of time it takes to complete the transaction. They also expect the application to be available whenever they want to use it.</p> <p>Applications for which fast response time is considered critical for the user include:</p> <p><ul><li> Interactive kiosk services </li><li> Point-of-sale ticket machines </li><li> Concession registers </li></ul></p> <p>Applications considered critical by stadium personnel include:</p> <p><ul><li>Emergency services </li><li> Voice and video monitoring and transmission</li></ul></p> <p>The measurement of application performance should combine user satisfaction with normal technical metrics, such as throughput on the network, or the number of successful transactions.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204010200">
<title><content-text>Characteristics of Different Application Categories</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8822849555">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010201/cm8822849555.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010201/cm8822849555text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In an existing network, <content-link target="{FA790631-4989-4913-AB03-9BBFD77EA276}" type="glossary">application characterization</content-link> helps the network designer to incorporate business goals and technical requirements into the network design. </p> <p>The application characterization process involves looking at the following aspects of network applications:</p> <p><ul><li> How the applications work on the network </li><li> The technical requirements of the application </li><li> How applications interact with each other on the network</li></ul></p> <p>From the information gathered during the early phases of the design process, the designer determines which applications are considered business-critical. The designer estimates how these applications will function with the proposed network. </p> <p>The characterization process provides information about network bandwidth usage and response times for specific applications. These parameters influence design decisions, including:</p> <p><ul><li> Selection of the transmission medium</li><li> Estimates of required bandwidth</li></ul></p> <p>Traffic from different types of applications results in varying network demands. The network designer recognizes four main types of application communication:</p> <p><ul><li> <content-link target="{91910FE5-D0D1-482D-AA04-8B5B54EFB94E}" type="glossary">Client-to-client</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{DC35725C-5D33-4721-8408-08F5A37C3127}" type="glossary">Client-to-distributed server</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{AA73D9EE-EB37-4C60-90D7-7B07035A39A5}" type="glossary">Client-to-server farm</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{385F947A-03FF-4101-BDD6-8177213A2AD3}" type="glossary">Client-to-enterprise edge</content-link></li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7775059007">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010202/cm7775059007.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010202/cm7775059007text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>On an existing network, the first step in characterizing applications is to gather as much information about the network as possible. This includes gathering information from:</p> <p><ul><li> Organizational input</li><li> Network audit</li><li> Traffic analysis</li></ul></p> <p> </p> <p><b>Organizational Input</b></p> <p>Organizational input consists of existing documentation about the network and verbal input from the stadium personnel. During the early phases of design, obtaining input is easy but not always reliable. For example, application changes such as upgrades or user-installed software may go undocumented or unnoticed. </p> <p><b>Network Audit</b></p> <p>A network audit gathers information about network devices, monitors traffic, and reveals details of the current network configuration.</p> <p><b>Traffic Analysis</b></p> <p>Traffic analysis provides information about how the applications and protocols use the network. It can reveal shortcomings in the network. For example, several high-bandwidth applications using the same medium can generate large amounts of traffic. This could be a potential weakness in the current design. </p> <p><b>Cisco IOS Software Embedded Tools</b></p> <p>Network-Based Application Recognition (<content-link target="{4647D7E1-9023-4E77-8F83-AB071CDAD7FC}" type="glossary">NBAR</content-link>) is a Cisco utility that conducts audits and traffic analysis. NBAR is a classification engine that recognizes a wide variety of applications. NBAR recognizes web-based and other difficult-to-classify protocols that utilize dynamic TCP and UDP port assignments. </p> <p>Another tool is Cisco IOS <content-link target="{B72369FE-1650-4D0B-AA88-6B120C6577CD}" type="glossary">NetFlow</content-link>. NetFlow efficiently provides a set of services for IP applications. Services include:</p> <p><ul><li> Network traffic accounting</li><li> Usage-based network billing</li><li> Network planning</li><li> Security</li><li> Denial of Service monitoring capabilities</li><li> Network monitoring </li></ul></p> <p>NetFlow provides valuable information about network users and applications, peak usage times, and traffic routing.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4170456953">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010203/cm4170456953/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010200/en1204010203/cm4170456953/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use NetFlow to characterize the network applications being used on a network.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204010300">
<title><content-text>How Traffic Flow Affects Network Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm9495134927">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010300/en1204010301/cm9495134927.swf" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010300/en1204010301/cm9495134927text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As part of application characterization, it is necessary to determine the internal and external traffic flows on the network. </p> <p><b>Internal Traffic </b></p> <p><content-link target="{7C811DE9-41B3-4041-8CFA-487179E08B9F}" type="glossary">Internal traffic</content-link> is generated by local hosts and is destined for other hosts within the campus network. Diagramming internal traffic flows can show areas where high bandwidth connections are needed, as well as identify possible bottlenecks where traffic might become congested. These diagrams assist the designer to select the appropriate equipment and infrastructure to support the traffic volumes. </p> <p><b>External Traffic </b></p> <p><content-link target="{09652EDE-89EB-4DF7-892F-BE8F47D74CBD}" type="glossary">External traffic</content-link> is defined as traffic that is initiated by users outside the local network as well as traffic sent to destinations located on remote networks. Some types of external traffic, such as emergency services or financial services, require redundancy and present additional security concerns. The designer diagrams this traffic in order to determine the location of firewalls and DMZ networks, as well as the Internet connectivity requirements. </p> <p>The designer analyzes internal and external traffic flows using NBAR and Netflow. To ensure that network bandwidth is used efficiently, NBAR can be used to identify and classify types of traffic in order to apply QoS mechanisms.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204010302">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4270382635">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010300/en1204010302/cm4270382635.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010300/en1204010302/cm4270382635text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>full page activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204010400">
<title><content-text>How Application Characteristics Affect Network Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204010401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm5033443112">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010400/en1204010401/cm5033443112.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010400/en1204010401/cm5033443112text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The types of hardware installed on a network affect the performance of an application. A complex network, such as the sports stadium network, contains many different types of hardware. Each of these device types can introduce delay in application response speed to user requests. Delay affects customer satisfaction with the application performance. For example, applications used for voice and video can be affected by hardware delays, causing performance to degrade. Hardware delays can be caused by:</p> <p><ul><li> Processing time that a router takes to forward traffic </li><li> Older switches that are not able to handle traffic loads generated by modern applications</li></ul></p> <p>One way to ensure high performance is to use the top-down approach. The top-down approach adapts the design of the physical infrastructure to the needs of the network applications. Network devices are chosen only after a thorough technical requirements analysis.</p> <p>Network applications on a modern network produce a range of packets. These packets are of various sizes, with distinct sets of protocols, different tolerances to delay, and other characteristics. When the service requirements of these different applications conflict with one another, performance problems can result. When adding a new application, the network designer needs to consider the impact on the performance of existing applications. The designer should consider the predicted application performance under varying configurations and network conditions.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204010402">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm6933963691">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010400/en1204010402/cm6933963691.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204010000/en1204010400/en1204010402/cm6933963691text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Page Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1204020000">
<title><content-text>Explaining Common Network Applications</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204020100">
<title><content-text>Transaction Processing</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm6799143082">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020101/cm6799143082.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020101/cm6799143082text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Networked applications are now the backbone of business activity. To meet the business goals of the client, the network designer must ensure application performance. However, each application or traffic type and each particular mix of applications has different requirements, which can result in performance issues.</p> <p>Some of the more common application types include:</p> <p><ul><li> Transaction-processing applications</li><li> Real-time streaming applications</li><li> File transfer and email applications</li><li> HTTP and web applications</li><li> Microsoft domain services</li></ul></p> <p><b>Transaction-Processing Applications </b></p> <p>Transaction-processing is a type of processing in which the computer responds immediately to user requests. Each request generated by the user is a transaction. These transactions can require additional operations to take place in response to the original request. For this reason, application transactions are a unique consideration in network design.</p> <p>As an example of a transaction process, consider what happens when a customer purchases tickets online for an event at the sports stadium.</p> <p>This single transaction generates all the following operations on the network:</p> <p><ul><li> Web traffic from the client to the network</li><li> Database transactions</li><li> Customer order transaction</li><li> Order processing transaction</li><li> Shipping/delivery transaction</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2029500738">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020102/cm2029500738.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020102/cm2029500738text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Not all traffic that enters or exits a network is considered a transaction process. A valid transaction must meet the following criteria: </p> <p><ul><li> It must be atomic.</li><li> It must be consistent.</li><li> It must be isolated.</li><li> It must be durable.</li></ul></p> <p> </p> <p><b>Atomic Transaction</b></p> <p>An <content-link target="{F1A56AA3-A27D-41F8-8574-951913E8E005}" type="glossary">atomic transaction</content-link> guarantees that either all the tasks of a transaction are performed or none of them are. If the transaction is not fully processed, then the entire transaction is void.</p> <p><b>Consistent Transaction</b></p> <p>A consistent transaction ensures that incomplete transactions are not allowed. If an incomplete transaction occurs, the system returns to the state that it was in before the transaction began. </p> <p><b>Isolated Transaction</b></p> <p>An isolated transaction is kept secure from all the other transactions on the network. Security is a major network design consideration. Security options include the addition of access control lists (<content-link target="{971E5041-12FD-4A86-A8E1-FCF688D864A0}" type="glossary">ACLs</content-link>), <content-link target="{C5892D73-1F35-471B-B5BB-D18EAD5B501E}" type="glossary">encryption</content-link>, and firewalls to the network topology.</p> <p><b>Durable Transaction</b></p> <p>A durable transaction guarantees that once the transaction is completed, the transaction will not be undone - even after a system failure. A durable design for transaction processes requires redundancy at multiple levels. These levels include the Physical Layer connections, servers, switching devices, and routers.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020103">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm3160003843">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020103/cm3160003843.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020103/cm3160003843text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The network designer evaluates redundancy and security tools that support transaction-processing applications.</p> <p><b>Redundancy</b></p> <p>Incorporating transaction applications requires the designer to consider the impact of each transaction on the network. This process is crucial, because additional cabling or devices may be needed to provide the redundancy or available throughput that these transactions require. Adding redundancy to a network brings the following advantages:</p> <p><ul><li> Reduction or elimination of network downtime</li><li> Increased availability of applications</li></ul></p> <p>Networks with redundancy eliminate the problem of single points of failure. If a path or device fails, the redundant path or device can complete the process or transaction. Servers that handle transaction processes have an alternate path to receive or deliver traffic. This helps ensure that the application is available when the customer requests it.</p> <p>Network devices can also be configured for redundancy. Two common protocols are:</p> <p><ul><li> Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (<content-link target="{88771053-CE38-4F2E-9126-4C55203BB756}" type="glossary">RSTP</content-link>)</li><li> Hot Standby Routing Protocol (<content-link target="{F354557E-446D-48EE-8309-AF95870DAE61}" type="glossary">HSRP</content-link>)</li></ul></p> <p>RSTP prevents Layer 2 switching loops that can occur with redundant switches.</p> <p>HSRP can provide Layer 3 redundancy in the network. HSRP provides immediate or link-specific failover and a recovery mechanism. </p> <p>Redundant links and devices can be implemented in the proposed stadium network design at both the Distribution and Core Layers.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020104">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7683440960">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020104/cm7683440960.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020100/en1204020104/cm7683440960text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Security</b></p> <p>Security is always a major consideration. It affects not only the transaction processes, but all applications and traffic within an internal network and an external network. Protecting the privacy and integrity of transaction information and the transaction database should be the focus of security considerations. The network designer analyzes the potential for the transaction data to be accessed inappropriately or altered.</p> <p>VPNs use a process called tunneling. Tunneling is often referred to as "port forwarding". It is the transmission of data through a public network that is intended for a private network. Tunneling is accomplished by encapsulating the private network data and protocol information within the public network transmission units. </p> <p>Intrusion detection systems (IDS) are used to monitor network traffic for suspicious activity. If suspicious activity is detected, an IDS alerts the system or administrator. An IDS can be configured to block the user source IP address from accessing the network.</p> <p>Firewalls filter traffic based on a set of criteria. The complexity of the firewall configuration can cause delays. The potential impact of delays should be considered in the design of a network. </p> <p>ACLs can filter potentially harmful traffic that is trying to enter the network and block specific traffic from exiting the network. These access controls can slow the transaction process. The time-sensitive nature of some transactions should be considered when configuring ACLs.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204020200">
<title><content-text>Real-Time Streaming and Voice</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5363254808">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020201/cm5363254808.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020201/cm5363254808text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Real-time Applications</b></p> <p>When designing the network to accommodate real-time applications, the network designer must consider how the network infrastructure will affect application performance.</p> <p>These considerations include the physical elements of the infrastructure:</p> <p><ul><li> Hardware devices and connections </li><li> Network topology</li><li> Physical redundancy</li></ul></p> <p>Logical considerations include how the configuration of QoS and security solutions affect traffic. All of these considerations affect how the designer will implement network solutions, such as <content-link target="{BEB8DA37-A642-4B2B-B69D-2415334F801A}" type="glossary">IP telephony</content-link> services.</p> <p>Real-time streaming applications present unique requirements for the network design. The only real-time application currently in use in the stadium is video surveillance. IP telephony is included in the proposed network upgrade. Traffic from these applications must be forwarded with the least latency and jitter possible.</p> <p>When determining the business goals and technical requirements for the customer, all aspects of the network should be analyzed to ensure proper implementation and support of the real-time applications.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4238927151">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020202/cm4238927151.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020202/cm4238927151text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Infrastructure</b></p> <p>To support the existing and proposed real-time applications, the infrastructure must accommodate the characteristics of each type of traffic.</p> <p>The network designer must determine whether the existing switches and cabling can support the traffic that will be added to the network. Cabling that can support gigabit transmissions should be able to carry the traffic generated and not require any changes to the infrastructure. Older switches may not support Power over Ethernet (<content-link target="{176D9E0A-C215-48B2-958E-388799AB8F66}" type="glossary">PoE</content-link>). Obsolete cabling may not support the bandwidth requirements. The switches and cabling would need to be upgraded to support these applications.</p> <p><b>VoIP</b></p> <p>When introducing <content-link target="{1C23B044-4FC0-418E-B183-5AEFEB95F2A2}" type="glossary">VoIP</content-link> to a network that uses traditional telephones, it is important to remember that VoIP uses voice-enabled routers. These routers convert analog voice from traditional telephone signals into IP packets. </p> <p>Once converted into IP packets, the router sends those packets between corresponding locations. Voice-enabled routers must be added to the design. </p> <p><b>IP Telephony</b></p> <p>In IP telephony, the IP phone itself performs voice-to-IP conversion. Voice-enabled routers are not required within the enterprise network. IP phones can use <content-link target="{D4D44D5E-ADB6-4BCE-A461-204AAB743501}" type="glossary">Cisco Unified Communications Manager</content-link> as a server for call control and signaling. The stadium network requirements include IP telephony.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7904243408">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020203/cm7904243408.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020200/en1204020203/cm7904243408text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Real-time Video Protocols</b></p> <p>To transport streaming media effectively, the network must be able to support applications that require delay-sensitive delivery. Real-Time Transport Protocol (<content-link target="{9FFC3795-013D-435C-8CAD-B3125A16A4DB}" type="glossary">RTP</content-link>) and Real-Time Transport Control Protocol (<content-link target="{C00ABCE7-8280-4E8B-9FD3-284395B20AA3}" type="glossary">RTCP</content-link>) are two protocols that support this requirement.</p> <p>RTP and RTCP enable control and scalability of the network resources by allowing QoS mechanisms to be incorporated. These QoS mechanisms provide valuable tools for minimizing latency issues for real-time streaming applications. These tools include priority queuing, custom queuing, <content-link target="{2E5AADFE-573D-4F6B-8563-A694D4081F20}" type="glossary">low latency queuing</content-link>, and class-based weighted fair queuing.</p> <p>One of the technical requirements of the stadium is to allow video of the events held in the stadium to be viewed in real-time from anywhere in the stadium. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204020300">
<title><content-text>File Transfer and Email</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7291405497">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020301/cm7291405497.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020301/cm7291405497text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>File transfers put high-volume traffic onto the network. This traffic can have a greater effect on throughput than interactive end-to-end connections. Although file transfers are throughput-intensive, they typically have low response-time requirements.</p> <p>Some of the characteristics of file transfer traffic include:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Unpredictable bandwidth usage</b> - this type of traffic is usually user initiated and therefore cannot be reliably predicted. </li><li> <b>Large packet size</b> - FTP and other file transfer traffic uses large packet sizes for efficient transfer. These large packets can cause delay for other types of traffic when the network becomes congested. </li></ul></p> <p>As part of the initial characterization of the network, it is important to identify the number of users that use file transfers on a regular basis. FTP is not the only type of file transfer traffic usually present on a LAN. Copying files from shared network drives and downloading large files using http have similar characteristics to FTP. </p> <p>From this information, the network designer can anticipate the throughput requirements. If these requirements exceed the network capacity, it is necessary to implement QoS measures to ensure the performance of delay-sensitive applications.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3068982225">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020302/cm3068982225.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020302/cm3068982225text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Email</b></p> <p>Email is one of the most popular network services. With its simplicity and speed, email has revolutionized how people communicate. Yet, to run on a computer or other end device, email requires several applications and services. Two common Application Layer protocols are Post Office Protocol (POP) and Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP).</p> <p><b>Email Client Processes</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Email users typically access their email service using an application called an email client. The email client enables users to compose and send messages, then places received messages into the user's mailbox.</p> <p><b>Email Server Processes</b></p> <p> </p> <p>The email server also transfers and delivers mail to the email client.</p> <p>Although a single email does not generate significant traffic, it is possible for mass emails to be transmitted that inundate the network or servers with traffic.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6245422539">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020303/cm6245422539.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020303/cm6245422539text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Supporting File Transfer and Email Applications </b></p> <p>Customers expect immediate access to their emails and to the files that they are sharing or updating.</p> <p>To help ensure this availability, the network designer takes the following steps:</p> <p><ul><li> Securing file and mail servers in a centralized location, such as a server farm.</li><li> Protecting the location from unauthorized access by physical and logical security measures.</li><li> Creating redundancy in the server farm that ensures that if one device fails, all files are not lost.</li><li> Configuring redundant paths to the servers.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020304">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4003614906">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020304/cm4003614906/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020300/en1204020304/cm4003614906/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Analyze network traffic using NBAR.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204020400">
<title><content-text>HTTP and Web Traffic</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4537342990">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020400/en1204020401/cm4537342990.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020400/en1204020401/cm4537342990text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>HTTP and Web Traffic</b></p> <p>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (<content-link target="{FC9FBA97-7549-4F98-B403-4CE5321D6848}" type="glossary">HTTP</content-link>) is one of the protocols in the TCP/IP suite that was originally developed to publish and retrieve web pages. It is now used for distributed collaborative information systems. HTTP is used across the World Wide Web for data transfer. It is one of the most widely used application protocols. </p> <p>HTTP specifies a request/response protocol between a client, typically a web browser, and a server.</p> <p>When a client sends a request message to a server, the HTTP protocol defines the message types used by the client. The protocol also specifies the message types that the server uses to respond.</p> <p>This process would appear to be a minor consideration in the design process. However, if the server that is being accessed is used for e-commerce or to store customer information, the security and redundancy issues become even more important. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6972503534">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020400/en1204020402/cm6972503534.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020400/en1204020402/cm6972503534text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Network Media</b></p> <p>To support HTTP and web traffic, it is necessary to have Layer 3 devices that can control the internal and external traffic flows. In a network audit, the inbound traffic should be considered part of the network baseline testing.</p> <p><b>Redundancy</b></p> <p>Servers usually have redundant components and power sources. They may be equipped with two or more NICs connected to separate switches. </p> <p><b>Security</b></p> <p>Security features such as ACLs, firewalls, and IDS, are also used to prevent unauthorized traffic from being sent in to or out of the protected networks. As with the other application servers, the HTTP server should be located at the ISP or in the centralized server farm for added physical security and redundancy.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204020500">
<title><content-text>Microsoft Domain Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204020501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2448798912">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020500/en1204020501/cm2448798912.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020500/en1204020501/cm2448798912text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The stadium uses Microsoft Active Directory Services. Therefore, the network designer must consider both server-to-server and server-to-client communications. Microsoft servers support many different types of services that rely on high speed communications between the servers themselves. These services, such as Active Directory replication, must be considered when relocating servers during a network redesign.</p> <p><b>Ports used by Microsoft Domain Services <br/> </b><br/> Microsoft servers and clients communicate with each other using a set of TCP and UDP ports. These ports are used for various Microsoft services, including authentication and authorization. Many Microsoft-specific services generate local broadcast packets on these ports, as well as unicast requests. Common TCP and UDP ports that must be open for Microsoft Domain Services to operate correctly include:</p> <p>UDP 53 - DNS Services</p> <p>UDP 67 - DHCP </p> <p>UDP 123 - Windows Time Service</p> <p>TCP 135 - Remote Procedure Call (RPC)</p> <p>UDP 137 - NetBIOS Name Resolution</p> <p>UDP 138 - NetBIOS Datagram Service</p> <p>TCP 139 - NetBIOS Session Service</p> <p>TCP 389 and UDP 389 - LDAP Service</p> <p>TCP 445 - Server Message Blocks (SMB)</p> <p>TCP 1433 - Microsoft SQL over TCP</p> <p><b>Active Directory and DNS</b></p> <p>When a Microsoft Windows 2003 Server is installed in a network, there is very tight integration between Active Directory Services and DNS. Active Directory requires DNS to locate domain controllers, which provide authentication and authorization services. Windows 2003 Domain Controllers must be DNS servers as well. This DNS service can provide the main DNS for an organization, or may be in addition to Internet DNS services located on non-Windows servers. Microsoft design guides also recommend that DCHP be integrated with DNS. This ensures that a simultaneous entry is created in the DNS file when a PC or device receives an IP address via DHCP.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204020502">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm3552498632">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020500/en1204020502/cm3552498632.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204020000/en1204020500/en1204020502/cm3552498632text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>full Screen Actiivty</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1204030000">
<title><content-text>Introducing Quality of Service (QoS)</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204030100">
<title><content-text>What Is Quality of Service and Why Is It Needed?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2689389085">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030100/en1204030101/cm2689389085.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030100/en1204030101/cm2689389085text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Quality of Service (<content-link target="{C80E9D95-981B-46E2-B274-F1459EBDAF10}" type="glossary">QoS</content-link>) refers to the capability of a network to provide preferential service to selected network traffic. The primary goal of QoS is to provide priority, including dedicated bandwidth, controlled jitter and latency, and reduced packet loss. </p> <p>When creating QoS policies for an organization, it is important to focus on which traffic needs preferential treatment. Network designers must consider how QoS issues affect not only the devices on a network but also the applications that use the network. </p> <p>Users perceive service quality based on two criteria:</p> <p><ul><li> The speed with which the network reacts to their requests</li><li> The availability of the applications they want to use </li></ul></p> <p>QoS helps to manage these issues for traffic flows within the network infrastructure and for the applications that use the network.</p> <p>Some Cisco devices, such as routers, have built-in QoS mechanisms.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4356356592">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030100/en1204030102/cm4356356592.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030100/en1204030102/cm4356356592text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Some applications are extremely sensitive to bandwidth requirements, packet delays, network jitter, and possible packet loss. These applications include real-time IP telephony and streaming video.</p> <p><b>IP Telephony Requirements</b></p> <p>The requirements of IP telephony illustrate many of the problems of real-time applications in a converged network. Voice traffic requires more than a simple connection between users. The quality of the transmissions is extremely important. When delays occur, voices break up and words become distorted. </p> <p>To avoid substandard transmission quality, IP telephony requires that QoS mechanisms be in place. Voice packets must not have a one-way delay greater than 150 ms. It is critical in the deployment of IP telephony solutions that voice packets have low latency and low jitter at each hop along a given path.</p> <p><b>Streaming Video Requirements</b></p> <p>Streaming video is a video feed that is usually sent from prerecorded files. It can be distributed in a live broadcast converting the video into a compressed digital signal and then transmitted by a special web server. This media stream is sent as a multicast so multiple users can view the stream at the same time. </p> <p>In a network without QoS, all packets receive the same treatment, and real-time applications suffer. </p> <p>QoS does not actually create more bandwidth. Instead, it prioritizes bandwidth use to support the applications, such as IP telephony, that need it most. To do this, QoS uses traffic queues to help manage priority traffic on converged networks.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204030200">
<title><content-text>Traffic Queues</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2153723417">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030200/en1204030201/cm2153723417.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030200/en1204030201/cm2153723417text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Voice and Data Traffic</b></p> <p>In a converged network, constant, small-packet voice traffic competes with larger, irregular data flows from server updates and file transfers. Although typically the packets carrying voice traffic on a converged network are small, delays that occur while they traverse the network will cause poor voice quality. </p> <p>Data from real-time applications, such as IP telephony, must be processed at the same rate as it is sent, and there is no time to retransmit packets with errors. Therefore, VoIP uses UDP as a best-effort transport protocol.</p> <p>Conversely, packets carrying file transfer data typically are large. These packets use the error-checking and retransmission features of TCP to survive delays and packet drops.</p> <p>It is possible to retransmit part of a dropped data file, but it is not feasible to retransmit part of a voice conversation. For this reason, critical, time-sensitive, voice and video traffic must have priority over data traffic. </p> <p><b>QoS Mechanisms</b></p> <p>Mechanisms must be in place to provide QoS priority. The priorities for traffic can be high, medium, normal, and low. Traffic queues are only one of the QoS mechanisms available for prioritizing traffic on the network. Traffic queues assist in providing secure, predictable, and guaranteed services. Even a brief network outage on a converged network can seriously disrupt business operations. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm6272730208">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030200/en1204030202/cm6272730208.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030200/en1204030202/cm6272730208text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Hardware and Software Queues</b></p> <p>Queues are used to manage traffic flow with QoS. Hardware queues store traffic as it is received and send packets out in the order received, on a first-come first-served basis. The hardware queue is sometimes referred to as the transmit queue, or <content-link target="{AB456A52-8A0C-41C7-9933-9D8159EF2B68}" type="glossary">TxQ</content-link>. This is the physical queue where packets wait for forwarding based on their priority.</p> <p>Software queues allow the packets to be sent out based on the priority set by the network designer or administrator. The queues are based on the QoS requirements. Priority queuing (<content-link target="{C51DE71C-2D23-4292-80E6-C5E3F8DCDC2B}" type="glossary">PQ</content-link>) and Custom Queuing (<content-link target="{65F0022A-7F40-416B-807C-A2C75A621711}" type="glossary">CQ</content-link>) are examples of software queues.</p> <p><b>Implementing QoS in Traffic Queues</b></p> <p>To implement QoS on a network, the designer follows three basic steps to ensure that traffic is properly prioritized:</p> <p><b>Step 1: Identify Traffic Requirements</b></p> <p>Determine the QoS requirements needed for the different types of traffic such as voice, mission-critical applications, and which low priority traffic can be marked as best-effort. </p> <p><b>Step 2: Define Traffic Classes</b></p> <p>After traffic has been identified, it can be placed in appropriate classes, such as voice traffic, which has the highest priority, followed by mission-critical applications. All other traffic can be prioritized as normal or low depending on the purpose of the data. Packets are marked to indicate the class to which they belong.</p> <p><b>Step 3: Define QoS Policies</b></p> <p> </p> <p>The last step is to define the <content-link target="{9127D9A2-D550-4C29-923A-EE8124D6AEC6}" type="glossary">QoS policies</content-link> to be applied to each class. These policies include scheduling traffic queues and rules for managing congestion.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204030300">
<title><content-text>Priorities and Traffic Management</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6926658741">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030301/cm6926658741.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030301/cm6926658741text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Many methods are available for managing traffic on a network. One method is Priority Queuing (<content-link target="{C51DE71C-2D23-4292-80E6-C5E3F8DCDC2B}" type="glossary">PQ</content-link>). As part of implementing QoS on a network, Priority Queuing classifies traffic as high, medium, normal, or low priority. Priority Queuing can then be applied to these QoS classes.</p> <p>Priority Queuing is useful for time-sensitive, mission-critical protocols. PQ works by establishing four output interface queues - high, medium, normal, and low - each serving a different level of priority. These queues are configurable for the following characteristics: </p> <p><ul><li> Queue type </li><li> Traffic assignment </li><li> Size </li></ul></p> <p>Incoming traffic is classified, marked to indicate its class, and forwarded. </p> <p>Traffic is assigned to the various queues based on QoS policies defined in a priority list. These policies can be based on protocol, port number, or other criteria established for the designated traffic type. They represent a set of filters that separate different traffic types into the four class-based queues.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2721408578">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030302/cm2721408578.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030302/cm2721408578text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Cisco is incorporating tools to assist with the configuration of QoS. One of those tools is AutoQoS, which is available as part of the Cisco IOS software.</p> <p>Cisco AutoQoS provides a simple, intelligent Command Line Interface (CLI). This CLI enables LAN and WAN QoS for VoIP on Cisco switches and routers. </p> <p>Auto QoS incorporates the Cisco best practices for implementing quality of service and makes it easy for customers to configure their networks to support high priority traffic, such as voice or video. </p> <p>Cisco AutoQoS can reduce the deployment cost and time frame by as much as two-thirds, when compared to a manual approach.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9320801034">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030303/cm9320801034/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030300/en1204030303/cm9320801034/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Rank traffic based on given scenarios specific to the stadium case study.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204030400">
<title><content-text>Where Can QoS Be Implemented?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7101708358">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030400/en1204030401/cm7101708358.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030400/en1204030401/cm7101708358text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When configuring QoS features, the network administrator can select the specific network traffic, prioritize it according to its relative importance, and use congestion-management techniques to provide preferential treatment. QoS can be implemented at the Access, Distribution, and Core Layers of a network. </p> <p><b>Layer 2 Devices</b></p> <p>Layer 2 switches at the Access Layer can support QoS based on IEEE 802.1p Class of Service (CoS). The Layer 2 switch QoS uses classification and scheduling to prioritize sending frames from the switch into the network.</p> <p><b>Layer 3 Devices</b></p> <p>Layer 3 devices can support QoS based on physical interface, IP addresses, logical port numbers, and QoS bits in the IP packet. QoS in Distribution and Core Layer devices must be supported in both directions of traffic flow.</p> <p><b>Classification and Marking</b></p> <p>Classification is the process by which traffic is grouped. Classifications are made based on how traffic is marked or by protocol. Traffic can be marked by Layer 2 class of service, an IP precedence, or a Differentiated Services Code Point (<content-link target="{3506D95C-6D19-4A10-BDFC-1B95A840113F}" type="glossary">DSCP</content-link>) value:</p> <p><ul><li> Class of service (CoS) is the first 3 bits of an 802.1q VLAN tag. </li><li> IP precedence is the first 3 bits of the Type of Service (<content-link target="{0D311880-2599-4CD9-B403-4BA7361DF530}" type="glossary">ToS</content-link>) byte in the IP header.</li><li> DSCP can be assigned by the router or switch. It is the first 6 bits in the ToS byte in the header.</li></ul></p> <p>Classification and marking allow the partitioning of traffic into multiple priority levels, or classes of service.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204030402">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4346720055">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030400/en1204030402/cm4346720055/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204030000/en1204030400/en1204030402/cm4346720055/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Set up a Priority Queue to mark packets. Use NetFlow to view packet markings. Create a list of possible areas for QoS and redundancy inclusion. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1204040000">
<title><content-text>Examining Voice and Video Options</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204040100">
<title><content-text>Converged Network Considerations</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5149395091">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040100/en1204040101/cm5149395091.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040100/en1204040101/cm5149395091text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Modern networks can support converged services where video and voice traffic are merged with data traffic. The network in the stadium is a typical example.</p> <p><b>Managing Converged Networks</b></p> <p>Control methods for voice and video traffic on converged networks are different from control methods for other traffic, such as web-based (HTTP) traffic. </p> <p><b>Quality of Service (QoS) on Converged Networks</b></p> <p>All networks perform better when QoS controls:</p> <p><ul><li> Delay and jitter</li><li> Bandwidth provisioning</li><li> Packet loss parameters</li></ul></p> <p>Converged networks require strong performance and security features to manage the conflicting requirements of their traffic. For this reason, QoS mechanisms are mandatory. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204040200">
<title><content-text>Requirements of an IP Telephony Solution</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5470937317">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040201/cm5470937317.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040201/cm5470937317text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the technical requirements of the stadium network is to upgrade to an IP telephony solution.</p> <p><b>IP Telephony Design Considerations</b></p> <p>The proposed network design must include:</p> <p><ul><li> Power and capacity planning</li><li> Identifying contending traffic flows</li><li> Selecting the components for the IP telephony solution</li></ul></p> <p>The components of an IP telephony solution can include:</p>  <p><ul><li> IP phones</li><li> <content-link target="{30EC46F3-A134-4B2F-B2FF-3DF4E1C0833A}" type="glossary">Gateway</content-link> </li><li> Multipoint control unit (<content-link target="{D0A34448-653E-4B73-AB78-07DE191D8971}" type="glossary">MCU</content-link>)</li><li> <content-link target="{342DD1A2-53C5-4BCE-9E1C-3C3FE496229D}" type="glossary">Call agent</content-link></li><li> Application servers</li><li> Video endpoint</li><li> Software telephone</li></ul></p> <p>Other components, such as software voice applications and interactive voice response (<content-link target="{E3886DDC-7840-450D-85D3-CB0EA2E2ECFE}" type="glossary">IVR</content-link>) systems, provide additional services to meet the needs of enterprise sites.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3744499644">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040202/cm3744499644.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040202/cm3744499644text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Isolating Traffic</b></p> <p>If both the client PC and the IP phone are on the same VLAN, each will try to use the available bandwidth without considering the other device. The simplest method to avoid a conflict is to use separate VLANs for IP telephony traffic and data traffic. </p> <p><b>Benefits of Separate VLANs</b></p> <p>Using separate VLANs provides these benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> QoS can prioritize the IP telephony traffic as it crosses the network. </li><li> Network administrators can identify and troubleshoot network problems more easily when phones are on separate IP subnets and VLANs.</li></ul></p> <p>The proposed stadium network upgrade, including the IP telephony solution, requires the development of a more efficient IP addressing scheme and a VLAN structure. The network designer should add this information to the Design Requirements document.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7329577452">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040203/cm7329577452.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040203/cm7329577452text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The stadium management wants to replace their digital telephone system with IP telephony.</p> <p><b>Traditional Telephony</b></p> <p>Traditional business telephone systems are typically built around a central control unit, called a Private Branch Exchange (<content-link target="{C38C4054-092C-4D09-A53B-7F13B396FA89}" type="glossary">PBX</content-link>). The PBX routes voice calls via analog or digital lines, depending on the type of device. For example, an analog fax machine or analog phone uses an analog line, and a digital desktop phone uses a digital line. In traditional telephony, the physical address of the phone is dependent on the wire to which it is connected. Consequently adding, moving, or changing telephones requires a significant amount of manual configuration. Most businesses have a separate wiring infrastructure to support their telephone network in addition to the infrastructure that supports their data network. </p> <p>The stadium company has a digital PBX system that operates over a separate infrastructure.</p> <p><b>VoIP</b></p> <p>Cisco uses the term VoIP when using voice-enabled routers to convert analog voice from traditional telephones into IP packets and route those packets between locations. Within the IT industry, VoIP is used interchangeably with IP telephony. With VoIP, the PBX connects to a voice-enabled router. It does not connect to a <content-link target="{D3F3F8B7-33EE-404C-B224-E91B1BFF7CA5}" type="glossary">PSTN</content-link> or to another PBX. Businesses use VoIP to reduce costs by consolidating WAN links, decreasing long distance calling charges and reducing the number of support staff. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040204">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm3022096682">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040204/cm3022096682.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040204/cm3022096682text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>IP Telephony</b></p> <p>IP telephony replaces traditional phones with IP phones and uses Cisco Unified Communications Manager, which is a server for call control and signaling. IP telephony has the following features:</p> <p><ul><li> Integrates voice and voice-messaging applications that connect via the IP network rather than via the analog or digital systems.</li><li> Uses an IP phone to perform voice-to-IP conversion. </li><li> Creates peer-to-peer relationships between the phones involved in a conversation rather than centrally routing calls as a PBX does.</li></ul></p> <p>The network designer and customer can incorporate VoIP or IP telephony onto the existing data network, creating a converged network.</p> <p>The stadium company expects to gain the following benefits of IP telephony: </p> <p><ul><li> Simplified administration of office moves, additions, and changes</li><li> Additional applications, such as directories and web pages, to the telephony system</li><li> Reduced cost to manage the separate infrastructures</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204040205">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm3615084441">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040205/cm3615084441.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040200/en1204040205/cm3615084441text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204040300">
<title><content-text>Video - Live and On-Demand</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4712358580">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040300/en1204040301/cm4712358580.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040300/en1204040301/cm4712358580text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Higher bandwidths enable network users to have audio and video on their computer systems. Video can be viewed as live video or as Video on Demand (<content-link target="{BB9BAC20-B338-4D60-9E9A-A5CD87F50013}" type="glossary">VoD</content-link>).</p> <p><br/> <b>Live Video</b> <br/> <br/> Live video, or <content-link target="{2681BC64-696B-4AD0-A7CF-F4D9C71B005E}" type="glossary">streaming video</content-link>, enables users to see content before all the media packets are inside their computer system. Streaming media files do not have a waiting period for viewing; they are available immediately as a continuous stream of data packets. Streaming video eliminates the need to store large media files or to allocate storage space for the files before playing them. A live video feed is often sent using multicast packets to many users at the same time. <br/> <br/> <b>VoD </b><br/> <br/> With VoD, users can either stream or download all of the content to their computer cache before they view it. Downloading the complete video file before viewing is also called store-and-forward. This method minimizes the load on system resources. Installing a server to direct streaming media into a computer cache allows users to retain the content and view it at a later time. VoD is sent using unicast packets to the specific user requesting the video. <br/> <br/> The stadium managment requires streaming video and VoD. This creates additional traffic on the network. Placing the servers for video storage inside the server farm makes it easier to manage troubleshooting, redundancy, and security.</p> <p> </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204040302">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm1838254615">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040300/en1204040302/cm1838254615.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040300/en1204040302/cm1838254615text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204040400">
<title><content-text>Supporting Remote Workers with Voice and Video</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2971820212">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040401/cm2971820212.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040401/cm2971820212text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Technology developments allow greater flexibility to workers in terms of how and where to work. At the stadium, for example, workers connect to the central site from several remote sites.</p> <p>To take advantage of central site resources and communications, a teleworker, branch office, or mobile user typically has at least one WAN connection to the central site. The bandwidth requirements for the WAN connection depend on the type of network resources that the users need to function in their job. If remote workers are part of the IP telephony network, a call manager system may need to be located remotely. The network designer considers whether the remote workers require access to video resources simultaneously. This access impacts bandwidth. For example, streaming video may be used for a corporate meeting. These design decisions require assessing the bandwidth at the central site WAN connection as well.</p> <p><b>Permanent Link or On Demand?</b></p> <p>The network designer decides whether it is better to use permanent or on-demand links to the central site. The designer works with the customer to consider cost, security, and availability requirements. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3621251419">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040402/cm3621251419.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040402/cm3621251419text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A high-speed Internet connection is a good solution for teleworkers. It is easy to set up in remote offices and is also available in many hotels. The stadium management plans to provide an Internet connection using wireless APs in the luxury boxes and the stadium restaurant.</p> <p>Sometimes, asynchronous dialup connections are the only remote access solution available to travelers. Employees who travel can use a PC with a modem and the existing telephone network to connect to the company. </p> <p>WAN connections at telecommuter sites can have the following features: </p> <p><ul><li> Asynchronous dialup </li><li> ISDN BRI </li><li> Cable modems </li><li> DSL </li><li> Wireless and satellite </li><li> VPN </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204040403">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2560878464">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040403/cm2560878464/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204040000/en1204040400/en1204040403/cm2560878464/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Investigate the impact of multicast streaming video traffic on a network. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1204050000">
<title><content-text>Documenting Applications and Traffic Flows</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204050100">
<title><content-text>What Is a Traffic Flow?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9610388283">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050101/cm9610388283.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050101/cm9610388283text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Traffic Flow</b></p> <p>Traffic flow on a network is similar to the traffic flow on city streets. Just as cars move from one location to another throughout the city, traffic generated from applications moves from one location in the network to another. </p> <p>A car on the street travels from a starting point to a destination. Similarly, a traffic flow created by an application travels as a unidirectional stream of packets between a source and a destination. The path is typically defined by a Network Layer IP address. Depending on the QoS and policies configured in the network, the path can be influenced by other information such as Transport Layer source and destination port numbers. For example, a host sends a request for a file to a server in one flow. The server processes the request and returns the file to the host in another flow. </p> <p><b>Traffic Control</b></p> <p>Without some form of traffic control, such as traffic signs or alternate roads to maintain the flow, traffic on the streets becomes congested. Networks also need a way to control traffic flows. QoS mechanisms are designed to ensure the smooth flow of application traffic on the network. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1781346889">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050102/cm1781346889.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050102/cm1781346889text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Application Traffic Flows</b></p> <p>The flow of application traffic in and out of a portion of the network can be minimal at times and significantly higher at others. For instance, in the sports stadium, early morning traffic may include email requests, Internet access, and file uploads to the stadium servers. Afternoon traffic might include VoIP, email, file transfers, and transaction processes from ticket sales.</p> <p>If the network designer does not correctly estimate the volume of application traffic during the initial design of the stadium network, all applications could experience network congestion and degraded performance. Customers at concession stands and ticket purchasing kiosks might encounter significant delays or even an inability to access the applications. Customer satisfaction would diminish. </p> <p> </p> <p>To aid in visualizing current and future traffic on the network, the designer creates a diagram of traffic flows. The first step is to identify the projected applications on the network. This information is gathered from the following sources:</p> <p><ul><li> Customer input</li><li> Network audit</li><li> Traffic analysis</li></ul></p> <p>The designer documents these applications and associated hardware in a network diagram.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050103">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1885195545">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050103/cm1885195545.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050103/cm1885195545text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is extremely important to identify traffic flows between hosts. The network designer uses the contents of logical or physical diagrams to plan the design to accommodate both existing and new applications traffic.</p> <p>The network designer generally uses a design program, such as <content-link target="{B1C7AB36-14D4-42CE-A88D-E2A7049A356A}" type="glossary">MS Visio</content-link>, to create a diagram that shows the identified applications and the logical topology of the network. </p> <p>After the diagram of applications, devices, and traffic flow is created, the designer analyzes the proposed design and identifies where the network can be improved. </p> <p>From the logical diagram, the designer identifies possible areas of congestion. The designer then determines the equipment needed to handle the traffic flowing from host to host and from host to server.</p> <p>In the stadium, the logical topology diagram shows the traffic flows from host to host and from host to servers. The connection of the devices also shows the applications that will be used. The traffic generated between the hosts is relatively minor when compared to the traffic generated from the hosts to the servers. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050104">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7789312928">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050104/cm7789312928/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050100/en1204050104/cm7789312928/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Identify the traffic flows for the FilmCompany. Use NetFlow to identify the applications and the destination of traffic.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204050200">
<title><content-text>Diagramming Internal (Intranet) Traffic Flows</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5950328365">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050200/en1204050201/cm8918016785.swf" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050200/en1204050201/cm8918016785text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The stadium network serves a complex organization that has many operational areas. The management offices, servers, vendors, and ticket offices are all a part of the larger network. </p> <p>Each LAN within the stadium handles traffic being sent from host to host and host to server. General file transfers from host to host and email traffic do not consume large amounts of bandwidth. However, the daily backups to the server consume large amounts of bandwidth and need to be analyzed during the design phase. </p> <p>All traffic flows, from both the internal and external networks, must be carefully assessed when designing a new network or proposing upgrades for an existing network. This assessment poses unique challenges for the network designer:</p> <p><ul><li> Traffic within the internal network is easy to identify. This traffic can be used to estimate utilization of the network. </li><li> Traffic from external sources is difficult to characterize. The designer needs to estimate the bandwidth requirements for external traffic flows.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5481920620">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050200/en1204050202/cm5481920620/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050200/en1204050202/cm5481920620/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Using NetFlow, diagram the flow of traffic from host to host and host to server within a LAN segment of the FilmCompany.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204050300">
<title><content-text>Diagramming Traffic Flows To and From Remote Sites</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5261892976">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050300/en1204050301/cm5261892976.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050300/en1204050301/cm5261892976text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After all sections of the internal LAN have been characterized and diagrammed, the network designer focuses on the remote sites and VPNs.</p> <p>The amount of traffic sent to or received from a remote site can be small. In the stadium network, the traffic flows may be small, but they are primarily transactional processes sent from the ticket office to the servers located at the stadium. Because these applications are mission-critical, it is important to identify the flows for QoS, redundancy, and security purposes.</p> <p>As with the LAN topology, the remote devices that generate traffic on the network need to be identified. All switches and routers that are used to connect the remote sites to the stadium are part of the path that the application traffic takes. </p> <p>The network designer should calculate the amount of traffic flowing from the remote sites as part of the external traffic flows into the stadium network. The designer should also determine if any ACLs or firewalls will interfere with the flow of appropriate traffic.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm8985221613">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050300/en1204050302/cm8985221613/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050300/en1204050302/cm8985221613/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Using NetFlow, diagram the flow of traffic to and from remote sites of the FilmCompany.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204050400">
<title><content-text>Diagramming External Traffic Flows</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8362909194">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050400/en1204050401/cm8362909194.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050400/en1204050401/cm8362909194text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Although most of the traffic in the existing stadium network is internal, the network designer must consider the external traffic that is destined for the Internet. </p> <p>Diagramming the Internet is impossible, considering the number of devices that are connected to it. However, it is possible to determine: </p> <p><ul><li> The outgoing traffic flows destined for the Internet. An example of outgoing traffic in the stadium network is users in the stadium who require access to external resources, such as online sports news.</li><li> The incoming traffic flows from the Internet to locally-provided services. An example of incoming traffic is customers purchasing tickets online who need access to the internal servers to process the purchases.</li></ul></p> <p>By determining the traffic flows associated with the Internet, internal or external, the designer can assess the need for redundancy and security to facilitate the traffic that is generated.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050402">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm3197628425">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050400/en1204050402/cm3197628425/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050400/en1204050402/cm3197628425/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Using NetFlow, diagram the FilmCompany External traffic flows.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1204050500">
<title><content-text>Diagramming Extranet Traffic Flows</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9466045229">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050500/en1204050501/cm9466045229.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050500/en1204050501/cm9466045229text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The stadium has a remote site and a vendor that is allowed to access the internal network through VPNs. These VPNs permit access to the stadium internetwork via secure, encrypted connections. The stadium also has a web-based e-commerce server that allows customers to buy tickets. This server is protected using <content-link target="{CAF6C66E-14E7-453B-9FEC-A6E417E5A7E4}" type="glossary">SSL</content-link>.</p> <p>The trusted vendor and customers are using IPSec to secure traffic flows into the stadium network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204050502">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm6960301797">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050500/en1204050502/cm6960301797/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1204000000/en1204050000/en1204050500/en1204050502/cm6960301797/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Using NetFlow, diagram the FilmCompany Extranet traffic flows. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1204060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204060100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1204060101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm1174729520">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204060000/en1204060100/en1204060101/cm1174729520.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1204000000/en1204060000/en1204060100/en1204060101/cm1174729520text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Page Summary</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1204070000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1204070100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1204070101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm6418339058">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1204000000/en1204070000/en1204070100/en1204070101/cm6418339058/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1204000000/en1204070000/en1204070100/en1204070101/cm6418339058/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
