<chapter type="" id="en1202000000">
<title><content-text>Gathering Network Requirements</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1202000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm7014742332">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202000000/en1202000100/en1202000101/cm7014742332.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202000000/en1202000100/en1202000101/cm7014742332text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202000102">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm3798934845">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202000000/en1202000100/en1202000102/cm3798934845.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202000000/en1202000100/en1202000102/cm3798934845text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1202010000">
<title><content-text>Introducing Cisco Lifecycle Services</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202010100">
<title><content-text>The Lifecycle of a Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2206938382">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010100/en1202010101/cm2206938382.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010100/en1202010101/cm2206938382text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The world of networking is evolving. Networking is no longer just about connecting computers. Networking has become intelligent and plays a vital role in helping to improve business performance. Businesses are eager to expand their networks. Taking advantage of advances in technology, companies can add new services and increase productivity.</p> <p><b>Cisco Lifecycle Services</b></p> <p>Cisco Lifecycle Services is designed to support evolving networks. Cisco Lifecycle Services is a six-phase approach. Each phase defines the activities required to successfully deploy and operate Cisco technologies. It also details how to optimize performance throughout the lifecycle of a network.</p> <p>The six phases of the Cisco Lifecycle Services are:</p> <p><ul><li>The Prepare Phase</li><li> The Plan Phase</li><li> The Design Phase</li><li> The Implement Phase</li><li> The Operate Phase</li><li> The Optimize Phase</li></ul></p> <p>This process is often referred to as <content-link target="{D6BAEA6D-5DF9-4490-96D3-4C99EEBB2BEC}" type="glossary">PPDIOO</content-link>, based on the first letters of each of the six phases.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7425417073">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010100/en1202010102/cm7425417073.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010100/en1202010102/cm7425417073text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Case Study: Sports Stadium Network</b></p> <p>The management organization of a stadium is working with the NetworkingCompany to renovate and update the stadium network. Over the years, the stadium network has grown. However, little thought was given to overall business goals and infrastructure design. Some new projects went ahead. But the network administrators did not have a realistic understanding of the bandwidth, traffic prioritization, and other requirements needed to support such an advanced and business-critical network. The stadium management now wants to add new high-tech features, but the existing network is not capable of supporting them.</p> <p><b>Phases of the Network Lifecycle</b></p> <p>NetworkingCompany representatives meet with the stadium management to discuss the process they intend to use to design the new network. Although the Design Phase is only one of the phases in the network lifecycle, all of the PPDIOO phases impact the design decisions.</p>  <p>In the Prepare and Plan phases, the network designer and stadium staff identify the business goals and technical requirements of the stadium organization as well as any design constraints. The requirements gathering that occurs during these phases influences the decisions made during the Design Phase.</p> <p>The Implement Phase begins after the approval of the design. It includes the initial integration of the new design into the existing network.</p> <p>During the Operate and Optimize phases, the stadium personnel analyze and monitor the network performance.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010200">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Prepare Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5996993755">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010200/en1202010201/cm5996993755.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010200/en1202010201/cm5996993755text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Prepare Phase</b></p> <p>During the Prepare Phase, the stadium management and NetworkingCompany staff define the following business goals:</p> <p><ul><li> Improve customer experience</li><li> Reduce costs</li><li> Add additional services</li><li> Support company expansion</li></ul></p> <p>These goals provide a foundation for a <content-link target="{F3EAFDCB-29E6-4D64-A19B-AD4B0DE1D9A7}" type="glossary">business case</content-link>. The business case is used to justify the financial investment required to implement the technology change. The company considers possible business constraints, including budget, personnel, company policies, and schedule limitations.</p> <p>After the business case is accepted, the NetworkingCompany staff assists in the development of the high-level technology strategy and solution.</p> <p>This strategy identifies:</p> <p><ul><li> Advanced technologies that support the new network solution </li><li> Current and planned network applications and services, and their priorities based on business goals </li><li> People, processes, and tools required to support the operations and management of the technology solution</li></ul></p> <p>The Prepare Phase is typically done before a company issues a Request For Proposal (<content-link target="{25CDC5C3-96C7-4D3C-8D35-6F9FF8E075CA}" type="glossary">RFP</content-link>) or Request For Quotation (<content-link target="{570C1393-4589-4B18-9765-E2515E0CCF87}" type="glossary">RFQ</content-link>). RFPs and RFQs describe the requirements for the new network. They include information about the process that the company uses to purchase and install networking technologies. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010300">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Plan Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7722012046">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010300/en1202010301/cm7722012046.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010300/en1202010301/cm7722012046text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Plan Phase</b></p> <p>During the Plan Phase, the network designer performs a comprehensive site and operations assessment. This assessment evaluates the current network, operations, and network management infrastructure. </p> <p>The NetworkingCompany staff identifies all physical, environmental, and electrical modifications. They assess the ability of the current operations and network management infrastructure to support the new technology solution. All changes to infrastructure, personnel, processes, and tools must be completed before the implementation of the new technology solution. </p> <p>Custom applications that add to the feature and functionality requirements for the new network are also identified in this phase. The NetworkingCompany staff creates a document that contains all of the design requirements. </p> <p><b>The Project Plan</b></p> <p>In this phase, the NetworkingCompany staff and stadium management create a plan to help manage the project. The project plan includes:</p> <p><ul><li> Tasks</li><li> Timelines and critical milestones</li><li> Risks and constraints</li><li> Responsibilities</li><li> Resources required</li></ul></p> <p>The plan needs to be within the scope, cost, and resource limits established in the original business goals. Both the stadium management and the NetworkingCompany assign individuals to manage the project.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7797618350">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010300/en1202010302/cm7797618350/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010300/en1202010302/cm7797618350/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>From the information provided, identify the business goals and constraints for the FilmCompany. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010400">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Design Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2439436148">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010400/en1202010401/cm2439436148.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010400/en1202010401/cm2439436148text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Design Phase</b></p> <p>In the Design Phase, the NetworkingCompany staff uses the initial requirements determined during the Plan Phase to direct its work.</p> <p>The design requirements document supports the specifications identified in the Prepare and Plan phases for:</p> <p><ul><li> <content-link target="{7316F178-E598-422E-ABF7-676D7D69FC20}" type="glossary">Availability</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{C2327336-F87E-4374-B1F4-8FD3EAB1930F}" type="glossary">Scalability</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{78F37938-DEEE-457F-8956-93A8A51780E8}" type="glossary">Security</content-link></li><li> <content-link target="{56C0A47D-D211-4DE3-BB88-5E4284240E4C}" type="glossary">Manageability</content-link></li></ul></p> <p>The design must be flexible enough to allow for changes or additions as new goals or needs emerge. The technology must be integrated into the current operations and network management infrastructure.</p> <p><b>Planning the Installation</b></p> <p>At the end of the Design Phase, the network designer creates plans that guide the installation and ensure that the end result is what the customer requested. Plans include:</p> <p><ul><li> Configuring and testing connectivity</li><li> Implementing the proposed system</li><li> Demonstrating the functionality of the network</li><li> Migrating network applications</li><li> Validating network operation</li><li> Training end users and support personnel</li></ul></p> <p>During the Design Phase of the stadium network upgrade, the design of the network is completed. Any new equipment and technologies are specified and tested. A review of the proposed design confirms that the business goals are met. A final proposal is generated to continue with the implementation of the network upgrade.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202010402">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm4331794805">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010400/en1202010402/cm4331794805.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010400/en1202010402/cm4331794805text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Full Page </b></p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>MCSA - Write three or four questions about the prepare, plan and design phase.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010500">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Implement Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2613774106">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010500/en1202010501/cm2613774106.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010500/en1202010501/cm2613774106text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Implement Phase</b></p> <p>The Implement Phase begins after the NetworkingCompany completes the design and the customer approves it. The network is built according to the approved design specification. The Implement Phase verifies the success or failure of the network design.</p> <p><b>Testing the New Network</b></p> <p>Testing all or part of a new network solution in a controlled environment helps to identify and resolve any implementation issues before the actual installation.</p> <p>After the issues have been resolved, the NetworkingCompany staff installs the new solution and integrates it into the existing network. When the installation is complete, additional testing is done. </p> <p><content-link target="{F162AD62-AA96-4550-8833-CE1E7D7CB643}" type="glossary">System-level acceptance testing</content-link> checks that the new network meets the business goals and design requirements. The results of this test are recorded and become part of the documentation provided to the customer. Any training required for the stadium staff needs to be completed during this phase.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202010502">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm6717828665">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010500/en1202010502/cm6717828665.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010500/en1202010502/cm6717828665text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the term to the appropriate definition, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010600">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Operate Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4226942682">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010600/en1202010601/cm4226942682.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010600/en1202010601/cm4226942682text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Operate Phase</b></p> <p>The Operate and Optimize phases are ongoing. They represent the day-to-day operations of a network. The stadium staff monitors the network and establishes a <content-link target="{502C27C5-21C4-4509-A844-492D8178F892}" type="glossary">network baseline</content-link>. This monitoring helps the company achieve maximum scalability, availability, security and manageability. </p> <p>After the new network is installed, stadium personnel manage the network to ensure that it is performing to the design specifications outlined in the Prepare and Plan phases.</p> <p><b>Defining Policies and Procedures</b></p> <p>Policies and procedures are needed to handle network issues, such as: </p> <p><ul><li> Security incidents</li><li> Configuration changes</li><li> Equipment purchases</li></ul></p> <p>Updating these policies and procedures after an upgrade reduces downtime, operating costs, and change-related issues. If there are no policies and procedures in place, it is important to create them.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010602">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm8324238949">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010600/en1202010602/cm8324238949/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010600/en1202010602/cm8324238949/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use Cisco Network Assistant to observe traffic.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202010700">
<title><content-text>The Network Lifecycle Optimize Phase</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202010701">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2044766438">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010700/en1202010701/cm2044766438.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010700/en1202010701/cm2044766438text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Optimize Phase</b></p> <p>Optimizing the network is a continuous process. Its purpose is to improve network performance and reliability by identifying and resolving potential network problems before they happen. Doing this ensures that the business goals and requirements of the company are maintained. Common network problems that could be discovered in the Optimize Phase include:</p> <p><ul><li> Feature incompatibilities</li><li> Insufficient link capacity</li><li> Device performance problems when multiple features are enabled</li><li> Scalability of protocols</li></ul></p> <p>As business goals change, the technology strategy and operations may not adapt. At some point, a redesign may be required and the PPDIOO cycle starts again. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202010702">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm1243253729">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010700/en1202010702/cm1243253729.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202010000/en1202010700/en1202010702/cm1243253729text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Page</p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>For each action listed on the left, place a check in the Prepare, Plan, Design, Implement, Operate, OR Optimize Phase column, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1202020000">
<title><content-text>Explaining the Sales Process</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202020100">
<title><content-text>Respond to a Customer Request for a Proposal or Quote</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2738176770">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020100/en1202020101/cm2738176770.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020100/en1202020101/cm2738176770text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a business or organization decides to upgrade or replace their existing network, they usually generate a Request for Proposal (RFP) or a Request for Quote (RFQ). In the PPDIOO model, this occurs at the end of the Prepare phase. RFPs and RFQs include specifications that define the format and content of the expected responses from the potential contractors. It is critical for contractors to follow the instructions contained within the document as accurately as possible. Not following the directions or missing sections of the request could mean that the project is awarded to another contractor.</p> <p>In addition to the response format and content, RFPs and RFQs contain schedules that must be followed. The company that sent out the RFP may reject a late response.</p> <p><b>Responding to the Request</b></p> <p>Each section of the response document should be as detailed as possible. Unless otherwise indicated, the section numbers of the response document should correspond with the section numbers of the request. The response should be written with the target audience in mind. Technical terms and concepts need to be explained where necessary.</p> <p>To ensure that the response document is easy to read, a table of contents is used to organize the material. An introductory letter is included to introduce the material.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020200">
<title><content-text>Attend a Pre-bid Meeting</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1562527089">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020200/en1202020201/cm1562527089.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020200/en1202020201/cm1562527089text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Pre-bid Meeting</b></p> <p>Prior to the deadline for submitting RFP responses, the customer may schedule an informational meeting. This meeting may be referred to as a pre-bid meeting or pre-submittal conference. The purpose of the meeting is to provide:</p> <p><ul><li> An opportunity to review the project scope with the customer </li><li> Additional information and documentation identified, but not included in the original RFP</li><li> Clarification of formatting and project timeline details not included in the original RFP</li></ul></p> <p>The meeting enables the contractor to get an estimate of the number of other companies that are interested in submitting a bid on the project. If a pre-bid meeting is not scheduled, the information or documentation can be requested by contacting the appropriate personnel identified in the RFP.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020300">
<title><content-text>Explain the Request for Proposal (RFP)</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6284161931">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020300/en1202020301/cm6284161931.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020300/en1202020301/cm6284161931text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The RFP</b></p> <p>Businesses usually send a copy of the RFP to contractors. Occasionally the RFPs may be posted on the business web site. Responses to an RFP help the customer compare services, products, pricing, and support offered by the different contractors.</p> <p>Typically an RFP for a network project includes:</p> <p><ul><li> Business goals for the project</li><li> Anticipated project scope</li><li> Information on the existing network and applications</li><li> Requirements for the new network.</li><li> Business, technical, or environmental constraints</li><li> Preliminary schedule with milestones and deliverables</li><li> Legal contractual terms and conditions</li></ul></p> <p>When responding to an RFP, it is important that every item listed on the RFP is answered. The company that sent out the RFP may reject an incomplete proposal. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020400">
<title><content-text>Explain the Request for Quote (RFQ)</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8890316718">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020400/en1202020401/cm8890316718.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020400/en1202020401/cm8890316718text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The RFQ</b></p> <p>Businesses use an RFQ instead of an RFP when the technical specifications of the project are already known. If a business has a skilled networking support staff, the staff can write an RFQ to obtain the costs for the necessary services and equipment. An RFQ is usually much simpler to respond to than an RFP, because the costs associated with an RFQ can easily be obtained or estimated.</p> <p>An RFQ can vary in content but will generally have three main parts. Like an RFP, the RFQ response may have formatting requirements. Proposal deadlines may be strictly enforced. </p> <p>The same guidelines used to respond to an RFP should be followed when responding to an RFQ. Follow all directions precisely and submit the response before the deadline to ensure that it is considered. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202020402">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm6905359517">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020400/en1202020402/cm6905359517.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020400/en1202020402/cm6905359517text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Page Activity</p> <p>Drag the item on the right to the appropriate portion of the RFQ, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020500">
<title><content-text>Explain the Role of the Account Manager</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4877030000">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020500/en1202020501/cm4877030000.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020500/en1202020501/cm4877030000text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When the NetworkingCompany receives the RFP from the StadiumCompany, the task of responding to it is assigned to an account manager. NetworkingCompany account managers are responsible for maintaining a continuing relationship between the company and its customers. This relationship begins when an account manager first contacts a potential customer. It continues throughout all phases of the PPDIOO network lifecyle. Business customers rely on the knowledge and expertise of their account manager to help them determine network requirements. Gaining and keeping a customer's trust is critical to an account manager's success. The account manager assigned to the stadium account is responsible for ensuring a good business relationship between the StadiumCompany and the NetworkingCompany. </p> <p><b>Communications Channel</b></p> <p>The account manager serves as the primary NetworkingCompany contact for stadium management personnel. A good account manager needs excellent interpersonal skills and a thorough knowledge of the customer's business. The account manager communicates with the stadium management through face-to-face meetings, phone calls, email or a combination of more than one method, depending on the customer's preferences. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4456389545">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020500/en1202020502/cm4456389545.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020500/en1202020502/cm4456389545text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Account Manager Responsibilities</b><br/> In some companies, account managers are responsible for contacting all customers and potential customers within a geographic area or territory. Other companies assign account managers to accounts based on the customer's type of business. While specific duties may vary from position to position, most account managers are responsible for: </p> <p><ul><li> Meeting their assigned sales and revenue goals </li><li> Communicating information about new products or technologies to customers and potential customers.</li><li> Directing local sales, service and support teams </li><li> Planning and budgeting for sales and support projects.</li><li> Responding to customer requests for proposals, demonstrations, quotations and information.</li><li> Negotiating and maintaining sales or service contracts</li></ul></p> <p>At the NetworkingCompany, account managers are required to take sales and customer management training, in addition to demonstrating basic networking skills.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020600">
<title><content-text>Explain the Role of the Pre-Sales Systems Engineer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4757554119">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020600/en1202020601/cm4757554119.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020600/en1202020601/cm4757554119text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The NetworkingCompany employs both pre-sales and post-sales technical staff to assist the account manager in providing support for their customers. </p> <p><b>Pre-Sales Systems Engineer</b></p> <p>Pre-sales systems engineers (sometimes called pre-sale technical support engineer) help the account manager and the customer to determine the need for upgrades or additions to the customer's network. Account managers rely on the technical expertise of the pre-sales systems engineers to ensure that any new equipment and services are appropriate for the customer's network needs. In the Plan and Design phases of the PPDIOO lifecycle, pre-sales systems engineers provide assistance to determine the technical requirements and feasibility of proposed network changes. These engineers, as well as network technicians who work with them, are responsible for:</p> <p><ul><li> Evaluating the customer's current network</li><li> Determining if a network upgrade or addition can meet the technical requirements </li><li> Ensuring that the proposed changes can be integrated into the existing customer network</li><li> Testing and evaluating proposed solutions</li></ul></p> <p>The pre-sales systems engineer assists the network designer in identifying problems with the existing network or possible problems that changes to the network may cause. Early identification and problem resolution is pivotal to a successful network upgrade or installation. The pre-sales systems engineer plays a vital role in creating an accurate response document to an RFP. </p> <p>Training requirements for pre-sales systems engineers include network design courses, as well as network technology courses. Many pre-sales systems engineers are required to obtain network design certifications. An example of such certification is the Cisco Certified Design Associate (CCDA).</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020700">
<title><content-text>Explain the Role of the Network Designer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020701">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6704284435">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020700/en1202020701/cm6704284435.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020700/en1202020701/cm6704284435text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A network designer needs a thorough understanding of the capabilities of all types of networking technologies and equipment. These skills enable the designer to provide customers with a network design that meets the customer requirements for scalability, availability, security and manageability. The designer is involved in the Plan and Design phases of the PPDIOO network lifecycle. In some smaller companies, a pre-sales systems engineer may also perform the role of network designer. In larger companies, there may be a team of network designers working on a single project. In this course, a single network designer will be used.</p> <p>A good network designer takes the time to learn about the customer's business, in addition to the customer's network requirements. This helps the designer anticipate changes that might occur as the business grows and succeeds. A designer is responsible for:</p> <p><ul><li> Analyzing customer goals and constraints in order to determine the technical requirements for the new design</li><li> Evaluating the current installed network</li><li> Selecting the technologies and equipment capabilities to meet the defined network requirements</li><li> Diagramming the placement and interconnection of various network devices and services</li><li> Designing and supervising proof-of-concept testing</li><li> Assisting the account manager in preparing presentations to the customer</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020702">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5875910034">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020700/en1202020702/cm5875910034.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020700/en1202020702/cm5875910034text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At the NetworkingCompany, the design staff is made up of highly skilled network professionals. The network designer must stay up to date about technologies, as well as new design recommended practices. </p> <p>The designer is required to obtain network design certifications, in addition to technical networking professional certifications.</p> <p>The designer assigned to the stadium upgrade is a Cisco Certified Design Professional (CCDP). By obtaining this advanced certification, the designer has demonstrated the competencies necessary to design a complex network for the stadium company.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202020800">
<title><content-text>Explain the Role of the Post-Sales Field Engineer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202020801">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8273989408">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020800/en1202020801/cm8273989408.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020800/en1202020801/cm8273989408text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>During the Implementation, Operation, and Optimize phases of the PPDIOO network lifecycle, the post-sales field engineer (sometimes called the post-sales technical support engineer) takes over the technical support responsibility from the pre-sales staff. It is usually a post-sales field engineer who is responsible for the smooth installation of new network equipment. Post-sales field engineers work with the customers to ensure that the network upgrade functions as designed. </p> <p><b>Responsibilities of the Post-Sales Field Engineer</b></p> <p>Responsibilities of the post-sales field engineer include:</p> <p><ul><li> Provide installation assistance and acceptance testing.</li><li> Support and organize troubleshooting of components or systems.</li><li> Resolve technical problems the customer may encounter.</li><li> Provide customer training and assistance with managing and configuring devices.</li></ul></p> <p>The post-sales field engineer helps develop recommended changes to the network design throughout the PPDIOO life cycle. </p> <p>Training requirements for post-sales field engineers include basic and advanced networking technology courses. Some technologies, like IP voice, require the post-sales field engineer to take additional advanced training courses. A Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA) certification is considered a minimum requirement for most post-sales field engineer positions.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202020802">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm3208106875">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020800/en1202020802/cm3208106875.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202020000/en1202020800/en1202020802/cm3208106875text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p> <p>Drag a role to the appropriate activity, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1202030000">
<title><content-text>Preparing for the Design Process</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202030100">
<title><content-text>Working with the Customer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9295293182">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030100/en1202030101/cm9295293182.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030100/en1202030101/cm9295293182text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In designing the new network for the stadium, the NetworkingCompany interacts with personnel from the stadium offices. When the network designer and staff meet with the stadium personnel, it is important that they behave in a professional manner. </p> <p><b>The Importance of Interpersonal Skills</b></p> <p>Good interpersonal skills are critical when interacting with customers. A calm and courteous manner instills confidence in customers. The customer believes that the NetworkingCompany designer and staff can perform the necessary tasks. </p> <p>The following skills are essential when working with clients:</p> <p><ul><li> Listening and accurately summarizing information</li><li> Corresponding with clients in a style, format, and level of detail appropriate for the intended audience</li><li> Presenting well-organized technical material in a logical fashion</li></ul></p> <p>The ability to develop a good rapport with a client is crucial. Establishing a trusted business relationship eliminates many potential problems and contributes enormously to the success of the project for both companies. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202030200">
<title><content-text>Defining the Customer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2632339433">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030200/en1202030201/cm2632339433.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030200/en1202030201/cm2632339433text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To create a comprehensive plan, the network designer needs to understand how the network users interact with the network resources and services. The designer gathers information about all internal and external access to the existing network infrastructure. Without full knowledge of who has access to the network, the designer may overlook some user requirements. As a result, the designer may present a design that is incomplete. Failure to submit an adequate design generates delays and increased costs. </p> <p><b>Identifying Relevant Information</b></p> <p>When gathering information on the infrastructure, the designer works with stadium personnel to identify all user groups. The customer's organizational chart is one of many components the designer must acquire. It is important to look beyond the organizational chart to determine all of the end users and stakeholders who access the customer network. </p> <p>The stadium management identifies the following potential end users:</p> <p><ul><li> Branch and field office staff</li><li> Remote workers</li><li> Sales and support personnel working off site</li><li> Vendors, suppliers, and partners</li><li> Board members</li><li> Consultants and contractors</li><li> Customers </li></ul></p> <p><b>Adding User Access</b></p> <p>The designer also needs to assess the impact of adding new user groups to the network. Some end user groups that currently do not have network access may need access to new stadium network resources in the future. </p> <p>The designer works with stadium management to identify:</p> <p><ul><li> New user groups</li><li> The type of access required</li><li> Where access is allowed</li><li> The overall impact on security </li></ul></p> <p>Including this information in the Plan and Prepare phases helps to ensure an accurate and successful new design. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202030202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4227370877">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030200/en1202030202/cm4227370877/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030200/en1202030202/cm4227370877/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create a network organization structure of the FilmCompany. Include all stakeholders in the structure - internal network users, IT organizations, external customers, suppliers, and partners.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202030300">
<title><content-text>Identifying Business Goals and Priorities</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202030301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2487171950">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030300/en1202030301/cm2487171950.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030300/en1202030301/cm2487171950text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The goal of every business is to be successful. Before beginning any network project, business managers analyze the feasibility of the project based on how it contributes to business success. They must consider:</p> <p><ul><li> Profitability - Can the project reduce costs or help the business avoid costs in the future?</li><li> Business growth and market share - Can the project help the business grow more efficiently or create competitive advantages?</li><li> Customer satisfaction - Can the project improve the customer experience and increase customer loyalty? </li></ul></p> <p> </p> <p>This feasibility analysis enables the business managers to put together a list of high-level goals for the network project. The network designer notes these goals and records any issues or concerns that are mentioned.</p> <p><b>Prioritizing Goals</b></p> <p>In consultation with the stadium management, the designer prioritizes the business goals. The priorities are based on which goals present the best opportunities to contribute to the success of the business. For example, the relative importance of each goal can be rated as a percentage of the overall total of 100. </p> <p>After the NetworkingCompany obtains the list of the prioritized business goals, the Plan Phase begins.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202030302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2290394144">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030300/en1202030302/cm2290394144/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202030000/en1202030300/en1202030302/cm2290394144/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>To ensure that the information gathered is accurate, create a checklist of the business goals of the FilmCompany. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1202040000">
<title><content-text>Identifying Technical Requirements and Constraints</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202040100">
<title><content-text>Defining Technical Requirements</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5321705516">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040101/cm5321705516.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040101/cm5321705516text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After obtaining the prioritized business goals, the network designer determines the network functionality needed to meet each goal. The designer lists the business goals that must be met by the new design and then decides what is required technically to implement each change.</p> <p>Determining the technical requirements enables the designer to establish the scope of the project. These requirements drive the selection of technologies, equipment, and management software.</p> <p>Technical requirements include, but are not limited to:</p> <p><ul><li> Improving network scalability </li><li> Increasing network availability and performance </li><li> Enhancing network security</li><li> Simplifying network management and support</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202040102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8286131215">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040102/cm8286131215.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040102/cm8286131215text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The network designer works with the customer to create a prioritized list of technical requirements. This list provides direction for the following decisions:</p> <p><ul><li> Selecting network equipment</li><li> Choosing protocols</li><li> Designing network services </li></ul></p> <p>This project list defines the project scope.</p> <p>When discussing technical requirements with the customer, the designer considers the technical level of the audience. The customer may not clearly understand technical terms and jargon. Such terms should either be avoided or tailored to the level of detail and complexity that the customer can understand.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202040103">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7424157635">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040103/cm7424157635/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040100/en1202040103/cm7424157635/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use the FilmCompany business goals to create and prioritize the technical requirements for the network.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202040200">
<title><content-text>Identifying Constraints</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9614824962">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040200/en1202040201/cm9614824962.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040200/en1202040201/cm9614824962text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Every company wants to have the most advanced and efficient network available. In reality, various business constraints affect network design. Common constraints include:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Budget</b> - Limited resources may require some compromises in design due to the costs of equipment, software, or other components.</li><li> <b>Company policies</b> - The design must take into account the customer's existing policies regarding protocols, standards, vendors, and applications.</li><li> <b>Scheduling</b> - The project time frame should be aligned with the customer schedules.</li><li> <b>Personnel</b> - The availability of trained personnel at the implementation and operation phases might be a design consideration.</li></ul></p> <p>Constraints can and do affect network design and should be identified early in the PPDIOO lifecycle process. The relative importance of the constraints varies from project to project. Budget constraints are not always the main consideration for a large project.</p> <p>For the stadium network project, the stadium management does not want the implementation to be scheduled during their sports season. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202040202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4720384696">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040200/en1202040202/cm4720384696/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202040000/en1202040200/en1202040202/cm4720384696/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Identify the constraints for the FilmCompany network project.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1202050000">
<title><content-text>Identifying Manageability Design Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202050100">
<title><content-text>Using the Top Down Design Approach</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6648967074">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050100/en1202050101/cm6648967074.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050100/en1202050101/cm6648967074text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are two common approaches for network design: top-down and bottom-up.</p> <p><b>Top-Down</b></p> <p>The top-down approach adapts the network infrastructure to the needs of the organization. Top-down design clarifies the design goals and initiates the design from the perspective of the required applications and network solutions, such as IP telephony, content networking, and video conferencing. The PPDIOO methodology uses the top-down approach.</p> <p><b>Bottom-Up</b></p> <p>A common approach - but one that is not recommended - is the bottom-up design. In this approach, the network designer selects network devices and technologies based on previous experience rather than from an understanding of the organization. Because this approach does not include information on the business goals, the proposed network design may not be able to support the required applications. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202050200">
<title><content-text>Monitoring Network Operations</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5959627511">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050201/cm5959627511.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050201/cm5959627511text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After implementation, it is important to ensure that the network design specifications are met. The stadium network personnel monitor and manage the performance of the network. Network management includes the following functions:</p> <p><ul><li> Managing configuration changes to the network </li><li> Identifying network faults</li><li> Monitoring performance levels</li><li> Providing security and accounting management for individual and group usage of the network</li></ul></p> <p>A typical network management architecture consists of the following elements:</p> <p><ul><li> Network Management System (<content-link target="{C1E3A88B-F0F4-4896-8D39-B5D1A733538B}" type="glossary">NMS</content-link>) - A system that uses an application to monitor and control managed network devices, such as CiscoWorks</li><li> Network Management Protocol - A protocol that facilitates the exchange of information between network devices and the NMS, such as the Simple Network Management Protocol version 3 (<content-link target="{4CECB5F6-F9C6-4E22-9493-4AB56FBBFC11}" type="glossary">SNMP</content-link>v3)</li><li> Managed Devices - Network devices that are managed by an NMS, such as a router or switch</li><li> Management Agents - Software on managed devices that collect and store network management information</li><li> Management Information - Data collected by the NMS</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm1477879469">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050202/cm1477879469.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050202/cm1477879469text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>CiscoWorks LAN Management Solution (LMS) is a suite of powerful management tools that simplify the configuration, administration, monitoring, and troubleshooting of Cisco networks. It integrates these capabilities into a best-in-class solution that provides the following benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> Improves the accuracy and efficiency of the network operations staff </li><li> Increases the overall availability of the network by simplifying configuration and quickly identifying and fixing network problems </li><li> Maximizes network security through integration with access control services and audit of network-level changes </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm8382410012">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050203/cm8382410012/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050200/en1202050203/cm8382410012/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Use a software program to monitor network performance.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202050300">
<title><content-text>Tools for Network Monitoring</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6579582104">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050300/en1202050301/cm6579582104.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050300/en1202050301/cm6579582104text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>SNMP is the most common network management protocol to use. The protocol enables network administrators to gather data about the network and corresponding devices. SNMP management system software is available in tools such as CiscoWorks. SNMP management agent software is often embedded in operating systems on servers, routers, and switches. </p> <p>SNMP has four main components:</p> <p><ul><li> Management station </li><li> Management agents</li><li> Management Information Base (<content-link target="{C0DE6709-70B1-4DFE-9B42-DCD976C0C80E}" type="glossary">MIB</content-link>)</li><li> Network management protocol</li></ul></p> <p>As part of a network management system, SNMP tools can respond to network errors or failures in several ways. Generally, when a network fault occurs, or when predefined thresholds are met, the SNMP tools can react by:</p> <p><ul><li> Sending an alert on the network</li><li> Sending a message to a pager</li><li> Sending an email to an administrator</li></ul></p> <p>Because stadium management may want to offer service level agreements to their vendors, they need to purchase network management software.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202050302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1449902689">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050300/en1202050302/cm1449902689/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1202000000/en1202050000/en1202050300/en1202050302/cm1449902689/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity:</b></p> <p>Investigate the capabilities and reports available in network monitoring software.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1202060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202060100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202060101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm8479714664">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202060000/en1202060100/en1202060101/cm8479714664.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202060000/en1202060100/en1202060101/cm8479714664text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1202060200">
<title><content-text>Critical Thinking</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1202060201">
<content-media type="ActivityCustom" id="cm2154782084">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202060000/en1202060200/en1202060201/cm2154782084.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1202000000/en1202060000/en1202060200/en1202060201/cm2154782084text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1202070000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1202070100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1202070101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm1765685487">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1202000000/en1202070000/en1202070100/en1202070101/cm1765685487/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1202000000/en1202070000/en1202070100/en1202070101/cm1765685487/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge. </p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
