<chapter type="" id="en1209000000">
<title><content-text>Preparing the Proposal</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1209000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1209000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm7940166456">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209000000/en1209000100/en1209000101/cm7940166456.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209000000/en1209000100/en1209000101/cm7940166456text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1209010000">
<title><content-text>Assembling the Existing Proposal Information</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209010100">
<title><content-text>Organizing the Existing Information</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209010101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2479157154">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010100/en1209010101/cm2479157154.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010100/en1209010101/cm2479157154text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After testing the proposed network design, the network designer collects the information gathered from the RFP and previous PPDIOO steps into a network proposal. The proposal typically contains the following sections:</p> <p><ul><li> Executive Summary </li><li> Network Requirements </li><li> Current Network Environment </li><li> Proposed Physical Design</li><li> Proposed Logical Design</li><li> Implementation Plan</li><li> Cost Estimate</li></ul></p> <p>If the proposal is in response to an RFP, the proposal components and Table of Contents are assembled to strictly follow the format requested in the RFP. </p> <p>If there is no written RFP, or if the written RFP does not specify an outline or format, the designer can determine the layout and design of the proposal. In such cases, the proposal layout should be highly readable and aid the reader in locating information. Graphics enhance the readability of a proposal and convey information as well. Text should be legible, typically a serif typeface such as Times Roman, at 10-point to 12-point type. Page margins should be at least 0.5 inches, and page numbers should be included at the top or bottom of each page.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1209010102">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4367230035">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010100/en1209010102/cm4367230035.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010100/en1209010102/cm4367230035text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209010200">
<title><content-text>Integrating the Existing Information</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209010201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5791075142">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010201/cm5791075142.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010201/cm5791075142text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At this point in the stadium project, the NetworkingCompany account manager and the network designer develop a proposal to respond to the RFP of the StadiumCompany. Most source material for the proposal is already available, except for the implementation plan and the cost estimate. </p> <p>The designer edits and organizes the existing information prior to developing the implementation plan and the cost estimate.</p> <p><b>Executive Summary</b></p> <p>Usually, the Executive Summary is written by the account manager assigned to the customer account. It is written from the perspective of the customer and emphasizes how the proposed network creates benefits for the customer organization. The previously identified and prioritized project goals as well as the project scope information are the basis for the Executive Summary. </p> <p><b>Network Requirements and Current Network Environment</b></p> <p>These sections contain information from the Design Requirements document created and approved earlier in the PPDIOO process. The information is included so that the customer can verify that the proposed design meets the agreed-upon requirements.</p> <p><b>Physical and Logical Design</b></p> <p>The designer develops the proposed physical and logical design sections from the proposed design diagrams and the results from the prototype and pilot testing. It is important to include any identified risks in this section, as well as strategies to mitigate the risks. This information helps the customer make informed choices about various design elements.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1238513774">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010202/cm1238513774.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010202/cm1238513774text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>During the proposal assembly process, the network designer and account manager review all of the materials to ensure that they are complete. It is important that the StadiumCompany management and technical staff are able to easily find and understand the material contained in the proposal. A disorganized or incomplete proposal can cause the customer to choose another contractor to complete the project.</p> <p>The designer and account manager work together to complete the implementation planning and to create the cost proposal. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209010203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1110121016">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010203/cm1110121016/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209010000/en1209010200/en1209010203/cm1110121016/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Prepare an outline for the FilmCompany network proposal. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1209020000">
<title><content-text>Developing the Implementation Plan</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209020100">
<title><content-text>The Implementation Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3837437169">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020101/cm3837437169.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020101/cm3837437169text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In the PPDIOO process, the next step after completing the network design is to develop the implementation and migration plan. It is crucial to include as much detail as possible for the network engineers and technicians. </p> <p><b>Implementing the Network Design</b></p> <p>Implementing a network design includes installing hardware, configuring systems, testing the network, and launching the network into production. Each task consists of several steps. Each task also requires the following documentation:</p> <p><ul><li> A description of the task</li><li> References to design documents</li><li> Detailed implementation guidelines</li><li> Detailed rollback guidelines in case of failure</li><li> The estimated time required for implementation</li></ul></p> <p><b>Stadium Design</b></p> <p>For all aspects of the stadium network design, success and failure criteria have been identified and integrated into the design documentation. </p> <p>When implementing a design, the network designer must consider the possibility of a failure, even after a successful pilot or prototype network test. At every step during the implementation, additional testing may be required to ensure that the network operates as designed.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2544479165">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020102/cm2544479165.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020102/cm2544479165text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Customer Approval</b></p> <p>The stadium implementation plan details the work required to accomplish the project goals. The plan includes the customer expectations and the success criteria, for customer approval and project sign-off.</p> <p>As soon as customer approval of the implementation plan is obtained, the installation can begin. </p> <p>The customer is given a detailed list of all devices required and the work to be completed. This list forms part of the implementation plan. A signed copy of this list is maintained by the network designer and account manager.</p> <p>Upon completion of each task, the customer is required to sign off that the work was completed and that the results are as expected.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1209020103">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm7480831647">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020103/cm7480831647.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020103/cm7480831647text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen Activity</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020104">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2999847528">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020104/cm2999847528/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020100/en1209020104/cm2999847528/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create an Implementation Plan for the FilmCompany installation.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209020200">
<title><content-text>Determining the Best Installation Method</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm6840565152">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020201/cm6840565152.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020201/cm6840565152text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are three installation methods that may be used for the implementation:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>New installation-</b> commonly referred to as a <i>green field installation</i></li><li> <b>Phased installation-</b>install components into an existing, functioning network</li><li> <b>Complete replacement-</b>commonly referred to as a <i>fork-lift upgrade</i></li></ul></p> <p><b>New Installation</b></p> <p>In a new installation, there are no current users or currently running applications. This scenario offers many advantages:</p> <p><ul><li> All of the equipment and services can be installed and tested at the same time. </li><li> The implementation plan for a new network is not as complex as for the other two types of installations. </li><li> Schedules are more flexible than when an existing network is in place.</li><li> There is minimal disruption to the company. </li></ul></p> <p><b>Phased Installation into Existing Network</b></p> <p>In a phased installation, portions of the network upgrade are implemented in isolation from other, currently running portions.</p> <p>When installing new network components or technologies into an existing network, great care must be taken not to disrupt services unnecessarily. A phased implementation requires more detailed planning with the customer. The network upgrade is divided into smaller pieces that can be installed and tested quickly. Installing the upgrade in smaller phases causes the least amount of downtime. </p> <p>The disadvantage of this method is that it may require more time and funds to complete.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9966372120">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020202/cm9966372120.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020202/cm9966372120text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Complete Network Replacement</b></p> <p>Sometimes it is necessary to completely replace an existing network. Complete network replacement usually occurs when the network is outdated and cannot be upgraded. In this scenario, the new network is often built alongside the existing network. When the new network is functional, there may be a period of time during which it is tested in parallel with the old network. A date is set to switch over to the new network, and the old network is then dismantled.</p> <p><b>Stadium Installation Method</b></p> <p>Determining the best installation method begins early in the network design phase. The network designer gathers and assesses information on business goals, technical requirements, and design constraints. </p> <p>Two of the StadiumCompany requirements emerge as the main factors that affect the installation method:</p> <p><ul><li> The stadium network services must be available during the upgrade.</li><li> Existing equipment must be used in the new network design.</li></ul></p> <p>As a result, the NetworkingCompany designer recommends a phased installation approach. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020203">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1902360707">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020203/cm1902360707/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020200/en1209020203/cm1902360707/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create a plan using the phased installation approach for the FilmCompany. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209020300">
<title><content-text>Estimating Timelines and Resources</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3372434131">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020301/cm3372434131.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020301/cm3372434131text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The project duration is part of the contractual agreement. To meet the deadlines of the customer the network designer creates a project timeline. The availability of materials, the schedule of the contractor, and the schedule of the customer all affect the start date and the completion date. </p> <p>When creating a project timeline, the network designer must consider the possibility that the project might not begin on the proposed start date. </p> <p>The stadium RFP states that the project must be completed during the off-season for the two teams. This requirement gives the project a timeline of four months.</p> <p><b>NetworkingCompany Resources</b></p> <p>Given the required sets of tasks, the designer estimates what resources are needed to implement the network. To meet the 4-month deadline, the NetworkingCompany may have to increase the number of technicians assigned to the project. It may also be necessary to adjust the sequence of tasks to accommodate the delivery of specific pieces of equipment or the availability of TSP services.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1260899650">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020302/cm1260899650.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020302/cm1260899650text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Estimated Timeline</b></p> <p>The network designer considers several factors when developing a project timeline:</p> <p><ul><li> Equipment order and delivery</li><li> Service installation, such as WAN links</li><li> Customer schedule, including available maintenance and downtime windows </li><li> Availability of appropriate technical personnel</li></ul></p> <p><b>Customer-caused Delays</b></p> <p>Customers often make changes to the requirements during the installation of a project. When changes occur, the vendor uses the timeline to make adjustments to personnel and other available resources. </p> <p>The network designer can also use the timeline documentation to show a customer how delays affect the project completion date. </p> <p><b>Project Management Software</b></p> <p>Project management tools can be used to create a project timeline. </p> <p>Using a software program can prove valuable for:</p> <p><ul><li> Tracking the progress of the project</li><li> Keeping the project on schedule</li><li> Identifying milestones</li><li> Tracking labor assignments and costs</li><li> Alerting the designer if the project is falling behind schedule. </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020303">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5215296557">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020303/cm5215296557/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020300/en1209020303/cm5215296557/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create a timeline for the FilmCompany network installation.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209020400">
<title><content-text>Maintenance Windows and Downtime Planning</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8870910276">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020400/en1209020401/cm8870910276.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020400/en1209020401/cm8870910276text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Maintenance Windows and Downtime</b></p> <p>Maintenance windows and planned downtime need to be included in the installation timeline. If only a few hours a day are available to make network changes, the project timeline must reflect this constraint. Otherwise, the time estimates are not accurate and the project may be late. Scheduling downtime for the network needs to be carefully planned to prevent a major disruption for the customer. </p> <p>Sometimes it is not possible to complete all of the required tasks during an approved maintenance window. If an installation task requires the network, or part of the network, to be down during normal business hours, it is important to obtain permission from the customer. As soon as the time frame is determined and approved, all the people involved need to be notified accordingly.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209020402">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm1820756799">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020400/en1209020402/cm1820756799/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209020000/en1209020400/en1209020402/cm1820756799/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Create a maintenance schedule for the FilmCompany network installation. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1209030000">
<title><content-text>Planning for the Installation</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209030100">
<title><content-text>Creating the Bill of Material</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm3768410651">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030101/cm3768410651.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030101/cm3768410651text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the most important sections of the proposal to the stadium management is the cost estimate. </p> <p>To prepare the cost estimate, the network designer creates a Bill Of Material (<content-link target="{CBFEA1FE-CBA1-44FC-9745-FDEA624B7BB6}" type="glossary">BOM</content-link>). A BOM is a document that details all of the required hardware and components necessary to implement the proposed upgrade. It consists of an itemized list of hardware, software, and other items that must be ordered and installed. The designer uses this list to obtain quotations and to create the equipment orders.</p> <p><b>Ordering Parts</b></p> <p>The designer uses the BOM to order new equipment as well as replacement parts for existing equipment. Therefore, every required item must be included in this list. For example, some routers and switches do not come with mounting brackets. These brackets must be purchased separately. If this information is not included in the BOM, the mounting brackets may be left off the order, which delays the device installation.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4479335085">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030102/cm4479335085.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030102/cm4479335085text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To create the BOM, the network designer looks at each section of the network to determine what pieces of networking equipment are required and what capabilities are needed in each device. There are 21 separate locations within the stadium where networking equipment is to be installed or upgraded:</p> <p><ul><li> 16 wiring closets</li><li> 4 WAN locations </li><li> 1 new data center </li></ul></p> <p>In addition, the wireless design shows 33 locations for AP installation.</p> <p><b>Identifying Additional Devices</b></p> <p>By looking at each area of the network separately, the designer can easily identify any additional devices that are necessary. The list of required new equipment includes: </p> <p><ul><li> 6 Distribution Layer switches</li><li> 2 Core switches</li><li> 1 router for WAN connectivity</li><li> 4 routers for WAN sites</li><li> 2 wireless LAN controllers</li><li> 33 lightweight APs</li></ul></p> <p>When deciding on new equipment, the designer must keep the budget in mind at all times. The designer reviews the choices of equipment with the account manager assigned to the stadium account. This collaboration ensures that the equipment models selected are within the stadium budget constraints and meet current and future business goals.</p> <p><b>Upgrades to Existing Devices</b></p> <p>Existing Cisco Catalyst 2960 switches are incorporated into the proposed design. Each of the 16 wiring closets contains one of these switches. The 2960 switches require redundant fiber connectivity to the Distribution Layer devices. Adding the redundant connections requires purchasing an additional fiber transceiver for each switch. These 16 additional transceivers must be listed on the BOM and included in the proposal.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1752309283">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030103/cm1752309283.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030100/en1209030103/cm1752309283text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Software Requirements</b></p> <p>During the early stages of the stadium design phase, the customer gave the network designer a list of applications that were currently installed. From this information and the network audit, the designer can identify all existing applications.</p> <p><b>Existing Applications</b></p> <p>The list of current applications includes:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Network applications</b> - Microsoft file sharing, printing, DNS, Web Server, scanning and recognition software</li><li> <b>Specialized applications</b> - Ticket scanning and recognition software</li><li> <b>Business applications</b> - Accounting, payroll, event scheduling, lease and rental management, marketing and Customer Relationship Management (<content-link target="{61C9D075-0AD3-4A9C-826B-71A277DC594E}" type="glossary">CRM</content-link>) software</li></ul></p> <p><b>New Applications</b></p> <p>The new applications include: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>Network applications</b> - Network management software</li><li> <b>Specialized applications</b> - Ticket printing, IP security cameras and viewing stations, e-commerce site for ticket purchasing and souvenir sales</li></ul></p> <p>The new applications, installation costs, and required training are added to the BOM with the identified hardware. The designer considers whether the network upgrade requires additional licenses to be purchased for existing software applications.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209030200">
<title><content-text>Recommending SMARTnet Services</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9247285151">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030201/cm9247285151.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030201/cm9247285151text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Warranties</b></p> <p>All new equipment automatically comes with a <content-link target="{E6AE2339-FA98-4717-92B4-F00D04052057}" type="glossary">warranty</content-link> that covers the device. A standard warranty provides the following benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Hardware-</b>Guarantees that the hardware is free of defects in material and workmanship under normal use</li><li> <b>Software-</b>Guarantees that the physical media is free of defects and the software performs to the published specifications.</li></ul></p> <p>However, warranties are limited in duration and in the services that they provide. For example, a software warranty usually guarantees that the software conforms to the published specifications for the product. It is explicitly sold "as is" and does not include any new software releases. Most warranties are limited to the replacement of the defective product and do not include technical or on-site support.</p> <p><b>Additional Service Contracts</b></p> <p>The proposed stadium network includes a mix of both new and older networking equipment. The warranties on some of the older equipment may have expired. To protect the StadiumCompany investment, and to extend the life of the existing equipment, the NetworkingCompany account manager recommends that the stadium management purchase additional maintenance and support contracts.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8618470311">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030202/cm8618470311.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030202/cm8618470311text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>SMARTnet Agreements</b></p> <p>The SMARTnet program is part of a suite of services that Cisco Technical Support Services provides. The SMARTnet program offers the customer service enhancements and maintenance support resources during the term of the contract.</p> <p>A SMARTnet agreement includes:</p> <p><ul><li> Software support on the licensed operating system software</li><li> Access to the Cisco Technical Assistance Center (TAC) 24 hours a day, 7 days a week</li><li> Registered access to Cisco.com for easy access to online technical information and service request management</li><li> <content-link target="{53105623-9A99-4D67-871A-F3E65F4E9048}" type="glossary">Advanced replacement</content-link> of hardware parts</li></ul></p> <p><b>Hardware Replacement Times</b></p> <p>Under the SMARTnet agreement, hardware replacement times can vary depending on the urgency of the customer need and the coverage selected. For example, with a 24x7x2 agreement, replacement parts are delivered within two hours of determining that a part replacement is required. This 2-hour replacement agreement applies any day or time in the week.</p> <p><b>Benefits</b></p> <p>The NetworkingCompany account manager prepares a chart comparing the various SMARTnet agreements to the basic warranty. This comparison is included in the proposal to show the benefits to the customer. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1209030203">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm8910479812">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030203/cm8910479812.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030200/en1209030203/cm8910479812text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p> </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209030300">
<title><content-text>Cisco Technical Services and Support</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8328373698">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030300/en1209030301/cm8328373698.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030300/en1209030301/cm8328373698text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The stadium network upgrade must not require an increase in the number of IT support personnel. The NetworkingCompany account manager and network designer agree that external support options should be presented to the stadium management.</p> <p><b>Cisco Focused Technical Support Services</b></p> <p>Cisco Focused Technical Support Services consists of three levels of coverage that provide a variety of options for the customer.</p> <p>The NetworkingCompany account manager includes information about the Level 2 contract, Cisco High-Touch Technical Support Service, in conjunction with SMARTnet agreements. This Level 2 contract provides priority access to a designated team of engineers who have received in-depth training on the stadium business operations. The engineers use the Cisco Lifecycle as the approach to providing services from the time the stadium design is placed into operation throughout its lifecycle.</p> <p>With a firm knowledge of the stadium network infrastructure and service history, the engineers would be able to speed up the resolution of network issues.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209030400">
<title><content-text>Software IOS Services and Support</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5480119970">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030400/en1209030401/cm5480119970.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030400/en1209030401/cm5480119970text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the business goals of the stadium management company is to simplify the day-to-day management of the stadium network. To accomplish this goal, the NetworkingCompany staff recommends that network management software be installed.</p>  <p><b>Software Application Support Services</b></p> <p>Implementing a CiscoWorks Network Management application or a Cisco IP Telephony solution requires Cisco software products in addition to the networking hardware. Cisco offers Software Application Support Services (SAS) to support the application software.</p> <p>SAS services include around-the-clock access to technical support, application software updates, and a wealth of technical information on Cisco.com. SAS services are designed specifically for Cisco software applications and provide services in addition to the operating system software support.</p> <p>The costs of these software support options, as well as any software licensing costs, are included in the proposal.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209030402">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9376886370">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030400/en1209030402/cm9376886370/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209030000/en1209030400/en1209030402/cm9376886370/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create the BOM and enter the appropriate information into the Costs section of the FilmCompany proposal. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1209040000">
<title><content-text>Creating and Presenting the Proposal</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209040100">
<title><content-text>Finalizing the Proposal</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2120479108">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040100/en1209040101/cm2120479108.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040100/en1209040101/cm2120479108text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The NetworkingCompany account manager uses information from the completed implementation and costing sections to update the Executive Summary. The proposal components are arranged in a binder, based on the order cited in the Table of Contents. </p> <p>A cover page is included at the beginning of the proposal. The cover page contains relevant information describing the proposal, including the RFP or solicitation number and date, the customer contact information, and the vendor name and contact information.</p> <p>The terms of agreement and an acceptance page for customer signatures are included at the end of the proposal. The terms and conditions describe all relevant legal terms and contracts that will be required. These terms and conditions support the supply of goods and services related to network improvements and installations. </p> <p>Important clauses in the terms and conditions include:</p> <p><ul><li> Details about the proposal expiration date </li><li> Obligations of the customer to obtain permission or other consents within their organization </li><li> Obligations of the vendor to provide services and equipment with care and skill </li><li> Dates when completed milestone deliverables are payable </li><li> Interest charged on outstanding payments </li><li> The amount of notice the customer must give to cancel any equipment and service orders </li><li> Details about guarantees (if any) provided by the vendor </li><li> Details about escalating and resolving complaints or issues</li></ul></p> <p>If the proposal is accepted by the customer, an appropriate customer representative signs the Terms and Signatures page.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209040102">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4399628197">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040100/en1209040102/cm4399628197/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040100/en1209040102/cm4399628197/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Compile implementation and costing information created for the FilmCompany.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1209040200">
<title><content-text>Presenting the Proposal</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5069834268">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040200/en1209040201/cm5069834268.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040200/en1209040201/cm5069834268text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After compiling the proposal, the network designer reviews the entire proposal with the NetworkingCompany management. During this stage of the design proposal, the designer must sell the concept to internal NetworkingCompany management and then to the customer. </p> <p>The designer typically develops a presentation to illustrate the proposal. A proposal presentation includes slides or other visual aids to graphically represent the proposal. The presentation, along with the proposal document, is vital to ensuring a successful meeting and increasing the probability of a customer sign-off.</p> <p><b>The Presentation</b></p> <p>The content and presentation format are quite important in a business environment. </p> <p>Presentation tips:</p> <p><ul><li> Every slide should contain a title that summarizes the information presented on the slide.</li><li> Computer presentations should not contain full paragraphs of text. Use a bulleted list or outline format and elaborate on the points during the delivery.</li><li> All type should be legible. Use large fonts, because small fonts are often hard to read.</li><li> Use contrasting colors - either a dark background with light text or a light background with dark text. </li><li> Avoid backgrounds that make the text hard to read. Keep the background simple. </li><li> Do not use ALL CAPS! Their use is unprofessional and they can be difficult to read.</li><li> Include a combination of words, pictures, and graphics. Variety keeps the presentation interesting. </li></ul></p> <p>After the presentation, the customer can accept the proposal in its entirety, request changes, or decline the proposal altogether. </p> <p>Remember that proper preparation before the presentation can mean the difference between customer sign-off and losing the project.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209040202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5983649160">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040200/en1209040202/cm5983649160/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1209000000/en1209040000/en1209040200/en1209040202/cm5983649160/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Present the project proposal to the instructor and the class. Be available to respond to questions from the instructors and students.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1209050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209050100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1209050101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm5111901153">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209050000/en1209050100/en1209050101/cm5111901153.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1209000000/en1209050000/en1209050100/en1209050101/cm5111901153text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1209060000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1209060100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1209060101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm1778525080">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1209000000/en1209060000/en1209060100/en1209060101/cm1778525080/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1209000000/en1209060000/en1209060100/en1209060101/cm1778525080/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
