<chapter type="" id="en1207000000">
<title><content-text>Prototyping the Campus Network</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1207000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1207000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm5519859450">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207000000/en1207000100/en1207000101/cm5519859450.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207000000/en1207000100/en1207000101/cm5519859450text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1207010000">
<title><content-text>Building a Prototype to Validate a Design</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207010100">
<title><content-text>Purpose of a Prototype</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3838851312">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010101/cm3838851312.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010101/cm3838851312text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Prototypes and Pilots</b></p> <p>It is a recommended practice to test any new design before design approval and implementation. Testing provides a <content-link target="{8206BF0B-2B9E-4CF3-BD58-35C6DD3BF9BC}" type="glossary">proof-of-concept</content-link> for the design. The testing phase provides an opportunity to identify parts of the design that do not operate appropriately and redesign them. </p> <p>The proposed stadium network has many design changes. Therefore, the NetworkingCompany designer tests the function of critical areas of the design before creating the final proposal.</p> <p>There are two common methods used to test a network design: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>Building a prototype network</b> - A prototype network consists of only the portion of the network necessary to test a particular function or capability. Prototype networks are separate from the existing network. </li><li> <b>Installing a pilot network</b> - A pilot is a test of new functionality or capability using a portion of the existing network. </li></ul></p> <p>Both methods test the functions of the design that affect the network's ability to meet the high-priority business goals.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9573766106">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010102/cm9573766106.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010102/cm9573766106text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Choosing a Pilot or Prototype</b></p> <p>The decision to create a prototype or a pilot depends on the following factors:</p> <p><ul><li> The type of testing required</li><li> The potential disruption from a pilot on the existing network </li></ul></p> <p>Prototypes are usually easy to configure and control because no active network users are affected. In prototype networks, it is easy to take a device offline, make hardware or configuration changes, and redo the test under different conditions. In a pilot, this type of activity can cause major disruptions in the network. </p> <p><b>When to Create a Pilot?</b></p> <p>Many functions of the proposed network can be tested using prototypes. However, using a pilot is a good option in the following circumstances:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>When the prototype is not big enough to test functionality</b> - Testing the operation of a routing protocol in a network with one hundred routers may not be feasible in a prototype.</li><li> <b>When the performance of the network is dependent on the operation of a specific device or third-party technology</b> - An example is an expensive video scoreboard or a third-party provided WAN link.</li></ul></p> <p>The only major design change that requires a pilot is the installation of the Frame Relay connection to the remote sites. A pilot is a good choice to test this connection because it tests the actual connection quality as well as the device configuration and functionality. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1207010103">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm1519073753">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010103/cm1519073753.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010100/en1207010103/cm1519073753text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p>Look at the network scenarios and decide if a prototype or a pilot is most appropriate. Click in the Prototype or Pilot column for each of the scenarios and then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207010200">
<title><content-text>Creating a Test Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2001384131">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010200/en1207010201/cm2001384131.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010200/en1207010201/cm2001384131text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Building a prototype to test a network design requires a significant amount of planning. The network designer creates a test plan before beginning the process, to ensure that the goals of the test are clear and measurable. A test plan is a document containing several sections.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207010300">
<title><content-text>Verifying the Design Meets Goals and Requirements</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010301">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm3498390263">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010300/en1207010301/cm3498390263.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010300/en1207010301/cm3498390263text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Benefits of Prototyping</b></p> <p>Testing the design with a prototype network plays an important role. It demonstrates to both the customer and the network designer that the network design meets the business goals and technical requirements. It creates an opportunity to compare different design options to see which one performs best. </p> <p>Before beginning tests to verify specific design functionality, the NetworkingCompany staff builds and verifies the prototype network in the test plan. The designer then works with the NetworkingCompany staff to set up and perform the test plan. They discuss the methods for measuring the prototype network functions under different conditions. </p> <p><b>Basic Connectivity </b></p> <p>After connecting all the equipment, the staff tests the prototype network to ensure that it provides basic connectivity. Basic connectivity is achieved when the network is operational and devices are sending and receiving data. Verifying basic connectivity is usually not part of the formal test plan. However, performing this verification ensures that the designer has a functioning network before performing further testing. </p> <p>Methods used to verify basic connectivity include:</p> <p><ul><li> Visually inspecting LED indicators on NICs and networking devices.</li><li> Using console connections to devices to verify the status of the interfaces.</li><li> Using <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> commands to provide information about devices with a direct connection. Router <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> commands commonly used to see locally attached devices include <span class="cmd"><b>show cdp neighbors</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>show ip arp</b></span>.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5281958476">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010300/en1207010302/cm5281958476.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010300/en1207010302/cm5281958476text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Functionality Testing</b></p> <p>When the prototype configuration is complete, the functionality testing can begin. The business goals determine the types of tests that are run on the network. The network designer aligns each business goal with the technical requirements. Doing this helps to determine the best method to demonstrate the network capabilities. </p> <p><b>Choosing a Testing Method</b></p> <p>The primary goals of the stadium management are to improve the customer experience and to ensure customer safety when attending an event at the stadium. </p> <p>One of the technical requirements supporting these goals is the integration of the security camera surveillance video network into the stadium LAN. </p> <p>To demonstrate this functionality, it must be possible to view the surveillance video from a PC located on a different segment of the network. The prototype must show that only the authorized stations can view it. The designer lists what must occur to accomplish this goal: </p> <p><ul><li> Create Access Layer VLANs to isolate the surveillance video from the rest of the network traffic.</li><li> Implement an IP address structure that supports the video network VLANs.</li><li> Trunk the VLANs to the Distribution Layer devices.</li><li> Feed the video streams to the video surveillance server.</li><li> Configure ACLs so that the security video can be viewed from other areas of the stadium by authorized personnel, but not by guest users.</li><li> Implement an authentication mechanism on the video surveillance server to ensure that only the authorized users have access to the security videos.</li></ul></p> <p>The designer creates a checklist to ensure that the network setup and configuration are correct. Each of the elements has to function correctly or the end-to-end performance test fails. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207010400">
<title><content-text>Validating LAN Technologies and Devices</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2089152004">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010401/cm2089152004.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010401/cm2089152004text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are common tools available for analyzing the performance of the prototype network.</p> <p><b>Cisco IOS Commands</b></p> <p>Many aspects of the network operation and performance are observable using Cisco IOS software <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>debug</b></span> commands. The <span class="cmd"><b>show</b></span> commands display the current state of interfaces, protocols, routing tables, CPU and memory utilization, and many other variables. The <span class="cmd"><b>debug</b></span> commands enable the network designer and the NetworkingCompany staff to view the processing of information in real time. Software logging functions save and display valuable information for later analysis.</p> <p><b>IP Utilities and Tools</b></p> <p>Two of the best-known network connectivity and reachability testing commands are <span class="cmd"><b>ping</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span>. Many other utilities and tools can assist in determining the functionality of a network. For example, on a Windows PC, <span class="cmd"><b>netstat</b></span>, <span class="cmd"><b>nslookup</b></span>, <span class="cmd"><b>arp</b></span>, and <span class="cmd"><b>telnet </b></span>can test connectivity and display information from the PC.</p> <p><b>Protocol Analyzers</b></p> <p>In a prototype, protocol analyzers verify that packets and frames contain the correct information. Protocol analyzers help detect the presence of certain traffic types, such as broadcast and ARP, that are difficult to identify without examining data at the packet or frame level. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6857165000">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010402/cm6857165000.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010402/cm6857165000text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Sometimes it is necessary to test network functionality in an environment that cannot be duplicated by the prototype network. In this case, the network designer can use a network simulation tool.</p> <p><b>Network Simulation Tools</b></p> <p>Software tools can test concepts in a simulated environment, similar to the Networking Academy Packet Tracer tool licensed for use in this course. Network topologies and configurations can be created or modified quickly. Simulations can test networks that are too large to build as prototypes. </p> <p>The same IOS, IP tools, and utilities that are used in the actual prototype network can be used to test the simulated network.</p>  <p>The designer and the NetworkingCompany staff determine the appropriate tools to use for each test to demonstrate the network functionality. For example, <span class="cmd"><b>traceroute</b></span> is a very useful tool for showing the route path that a packet takes through a network. However, it is not a good tool for demonstrating the configuration for route summarization.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010403">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1551498915">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010403/cm1551498915/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010403/cm1551498915/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Use different Cisco IOS software and Windows commands. Determine whether those commands provide the information necessary to test network functionality. This activity is based on a preconfigured prototype network.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1207010404">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm4359282600">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010404/cm4359282600.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010400/en1207010404/cm4359282600text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p>Match the test tool to the type of information that it provides.</p> <p><b>Note: A tool may be dragged to more than one box. More than one tool may be dragged to a single box.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207010500">
<title><content-text>Test the Redundancy and Resiliency of the Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010501">
<content-media type="AnimationDual" id="cm4213508047">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010500/en1207010501/cm4213508047.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010500/en1207010501/cm4213508047text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Overcoming Device and Link Failures</b></p> <p>When a business adds applications that need high availability, the network designer adds redundancy to the network. Sometimes this redundancy is added without considering what occurs in an actual network failure. It is important to test how redundant links function during a failure situation. Tests should measure how long a network takes to stabilize after the redundant link becomes active. </p> <p><b>Redundant Links</b></p> <p>Prototype designs use various types of redundant links to test network availability. Redundant links can be used for failover and sometimes, for load balancing during normal operation. </p> <p><b>Load Balancing</b></p> <p>Not all types of redundant links support load balancing. Because of STP operation, simple redundant links between Layer 2 switches cannot be used for load balancing. Equal cost routed links, and Layer 2 and Layer 3 links configured as part of an EtherChannel, can be used to load balance traffic during normal operation. They can also forward traffic in the event of a link failure. </p> <p>The stadium network has two types of redundant links between devices: Layer 2 uplinks and equal cost Layer 3 links.</p>  <p>To test the two types of links, the designer and the NetworkingCompany staff introduce link failures into the topology. By observing the amount of disruption in network service, they can determine how long it takes for the network to resume normal functionality.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207010600">
<title><content-text>Identify Risks or Weaknesses in the Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5519222893">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010600/en1207010601/cm5519222893.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010600/en1207010601/cm5519222893text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Prototypes and simulations can be used to identify risks and weaknesses inherent in the network design. A weakness is a limitation or a flaw in the design. Risks are adverse affects that might occur as a result of the weakness. Risks increase when there are areas in the network that are not optimally designed. These limitations may be due to equipment restrictions or previously identified constraints. </p> <p>Some possible design weaknesses and their associated risks include:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Single points of failure</b> - In areas where there is either limited or no redundancy to provide connectivity, there is a risk that a single device or link failure can impact the entire area.</li><li> <b>Large failure domains</b> - If a single point of failure such as a non-redundant Internet connection, can adversely affect a large portion of the network, the risk that such a failure will have a major impact on the business increases.</li><li> <b>Possible bottlenecks</b> - Some areas may be vulnerable to congestion if traffic volumes increase, creating a risk that response time will seriously degrade.</li><li> <b>Limited scalability</b> - Areas or devices can present scalability problems if the network grows faster than anticipated. The lack of scalability can require a network redesign or costly upgrade. </li><li> <b>Existing staff capabilities</b> - Prototypes sometimes indicate that the network configurations are too complex for the existing staff to support and troubleshoot. In cases like this, a risk exists until staff receives the appropriate training or a new support strategy is in place.</li></ul></p> <p>Weaknesses identified by the network designer and NetworkingCompany staff during the prototype testing phase must be communicated to the customer. It is also important to include what risks might be associated with the identified weaknesses. Communicating the risks enables the customer to anticipate what might occur in the future, and to make contingency plans regarding how to handle these situations if they do arise.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207010602">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9439584711">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010600/en1207010602/cm9439584711/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207010000/en1207010600/en1207010602/cm9439584711/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Analyze a sample test plan and perform a test.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1207020000">
<title><content-text>Prototyping the LAN</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207020100">
<title><content-text>Identify Goals and Requirements Met by LAN Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7109269865">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020100/en1207020101/cm7109269865.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020100/en1207020101/cm7109269865text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Testing the New Design</b></p> <p>A high-priority business goal of the stadium management is to reduce costs by implementing a converged network to support data traffic, IP telephony, and video surveillance. As a result, the new design incorporates significant changes to the stadium LAN. The network designer must decide how to test the various elements of the design to ensure that the goals of the network upgrade are met. The designer decides to test the design using a prototype network.</p> <p><b>What Needs to Be Tested?</b></p> <p>The designer must first decide which network functions need to be included in the prototype test. Because the goal is to create a network that supports data traffic, IP telephony, and video surveillance, it is necessary to test the elements of the design that directly impact that goal. </p> <p>In the stadium network, these elements are:</p> <p><ul><li> Conversion from a flat network to a modular three-layer hierarchy</li><li> Creation of separate VLANs and IP subnets to support the different types of traffic and classes of users</li><li> Implementation of redundant topology</li><li> Configuration of ACLs to ensure that only authorized personnel have access to the stadium resources</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207020200">
<title><content-text>Creating the Test Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4186456179">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020201/cm4186456179.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020201/cm4186456179text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After deciding which business goals and technical requirements can be tested using a prototype of the network, the network designer creates the test plan.</p> <p><b>The Test Plan</b></p> <p>The designer needs to demonstrate functionality of the converged network combining data, IP telephony, and video surveillance traffic. To do this, the designer must decide:</p> <p><ul><li> What types of tests to run</li><li> How much of the network must be built to perform the tests</li><li> How to determine the success or failure of the test</li></ul></p> <p>The designer lists the test outcomes that indicate that the goal of a converged network can be met. The main focus of the test is to show how the new network serves the main business goal. The NetworkingCompany staff tests the individual technical requirements to determine if the network design addresses each goal. They repeat this process for each of the high-priority goals.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8645210692">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020202/cm8645210692.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020202/cm8645210692text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Testing Using a Sample Topology</b></p> <p>The network designer creates a prototype test topology for the stadium that is large enough to demonstrate the operation of the planned network. </p> <p><b>Simulating a Three-Layer Hierarchy</b></p> <p>For the purpose of the prototype, the three-layer hierarchy can be simulated using two Layer 2 devices and four Layer 3 devices. The designer chooses Layer 2 switches to simulate the Access Layer and uses Layer 3 switches or routers to simulate the Distribution and Core Layers. The designer lists all of the devices, and possible substitutions, on the test plan.</p> <p>To ensure that the prototype network is built correctly, the designer makes a checklist for the NetworkingCompany staff to follow. The checklist includes all of the functions that need to be working when the testing begins. It includes any planned changes to the configurations that have to occur during the actual testing.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020203">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm8287809159">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020203/cm8287809159/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020203/cm8287809159/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Perform the Basic Connectivity Test on a prototype network. Create a success criteria checklist.</p> <p>The following document should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1.<content-link target="D4_7.2.2_StadiumPrototypeTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium Prototype Test Plan</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020204">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5634975702">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020204/cm5634975702/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020200/en1207020204/cm5634975702/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Using the FilmCompany network design, create a test plan.</p> <p>The following document should be downloaded to perform this lab activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="Dis4_Lab_7.2.2.4_TestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">LAN Design Test Plan</content-link></p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207020300">
<title><content-text>Validating the Choice of Devices and Topologies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4723192926">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020300/en1207020301/cm4723192926.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020300/en1207020301/cm4723192926text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The existing stadium network is a flat, switched network, with no routing or filtering. The network designer proposes incorporating hierarchical Layer 3 services in addition to Layer 2 switching. The proposed design includes Distribution and Core Layers in the network. The designer recommends these changes to support the scalability and availability requirements.</p> <p><b>Routed Versus Flat Topologies</b></p> <p>The designer wants to demonstrate the differences between flat and hierarchical topologies when link failures occur. This demonstration illustrates why the routed hierarchical topology is a better choice. </p> <p>The modular hierarchal design proposed for the new network permits Access Layer modules to be added without affecting existing users. A large prototype would have to be built to demonstrate this properly. Because this is not practical, the designer decides to use a simulation tool instead of a prototype to illustrate this potential benefit. The simulation tool helps validate the choice of a routed hierarchical topology.</p> <p>The designer creates a test plan for the simulation identical to one that would have been written for a prototype network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020302">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm2773659160">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020300/en1207020302/cm2773659160/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020300/en1207020302/cm2773659160/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Following a test plan, compare the way switched and routed hierarchical networks stabilize after a major link failure.</p> <p>The following documents should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="D4_7.2.3_StadiumRedundancyTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium Redundancy Test Plan</content-link></p> <p>2. <content-link target="PacketTracer_7.2.3_InstallationChecklist.pdf" type="internalfile">Installation Checklist</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207020400">
<title><content-text>Validating the Choice of Routing Protocol</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8056655954">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020400/en1207020401/cm8056655954.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020400/en1207020401/cm8056655954text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Testing the Routing Protocol</b></p> <p>The hierarchical design of the proposed stadium network includes EIGRP as the dynamic routing protocol. The network designer recommends that the EIGRP dynamic routing protocol be configured because it is easy to use and scales well. EIGRP is a proprietary protocol; it cannot be configured on non-Cisco devices. </p> <p>To demonstrate how well a routing protocol converges in the event of a link failure is difficult to do with a prototype network, and is risky to attempt in a pilot network. In a pilot, a single routing protocol misconfiguration can disrupt the entire network. Because of this risk, the designer decides to use the simulator for the routing protocol tests.</p> <p>The designer wants to compare the use of static routes for the redundant links to the use of the EIGRP routing protocol. The test plan outlines a test of static routes first, then the configuration of EIGRP, so that a comparison can be made.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020402">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm8442164226">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020400/en1207020402/cm8442164226/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020400/en1207020402/cm8442164226/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Following a test plan, build and test a multirouter network with redundant links.</p> <p>The following documents should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="D4_7.2.4_StadiumRoutingProtocolTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium Routing Protocol Test Plan</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207020500">
<title><content-text>Validating the IP Addressing Scheme</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7597047334">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020501/cm7597047334.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020501/cm7597047334text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The IP addressing scheme proposed for use in the stadium network can be tested using the prototype network. The network designer recommends a simulation tool to test the IP addressing scheme. Using the simulation tool, the designer can determine if the addressing structure enables summarization and can support the necessary scalability.</p> <p>The designer configures the simulated network with the same number of networking devices as the planned network. The designer then validates the placement of the various subnets and the configuration of the route summarization. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020502">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm3980958055">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020502/cm3980958055/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020502/cm3980958055/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Apply an IP addressing scheme to a Distribution Layer module of the stadium LAN.</p> <p>The following document should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="D4_7.2.5_StadiumIPAddressTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium IP Address Test Plan</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020503">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2337352196">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020503/cm2337352196/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020500/en1207020503/cm2337352196/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Build the FilmCompany prototype network. Perform the tests according to the test plan created earlier in this chapter.</p> <p>Analyze the results to determine success or failure. Complete the Actual Results section of the test plan.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207020600">
<title><content-text>Identify Risks and Weaknesses</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8135777203">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020600/en1207020601/cm8135777203.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020600/en1207020601/cm8135777203text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Recording Risks and Weaknesses</b></p> <p>In the Conclusion section of the test plan, the network designer and the NetworkingCompany staff record their observations and opinions about the results of the testing. An important part of this section is the analysis of risks and weaknesses in the design. In the case of the proposed stadium network, there are a few risks that must be stated. Documenting these risks helps the stadium management make informed decisions about implementing the design. </p> <p>The risks and weaknesses include:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>No redundancy at the Access Layer of the network </b>- Most end user devices attach to a single access switch. This is a single point of failure for the end devices. Due to the higher risk of server loss, the servers in the data center are connected with dual NICs to separate access switches.</li><li> <b>Single ISP for Internet connectivity</b> - If the ISP connection fails, or if there is a problem at the ISP, all Internet connectivity to the stadium network is lost.</li><li> <b>Limited bandwidth to the WAN and Internet</b> - When the requirements for WAN and Internet connectivity increase, bandwidth limitations can cause a bottleneck and reduce application performance.</li><li> <b>Limited fiber connectivity from the wiring closets</b> - Because of this constraint, the number of redundant links from the Access Layer devices is limited to two. Therefore, multiple switches in a wiring closet must share the uplinks.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207020602">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4575918373">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020600/en1207020602/cm4575918373/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207020000/en1207020600/en1207020602/cm4575918373/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Analyze the results of the prototype tests to determine the level of risk in the FilmCompany network.</p> <p>Complete the Conclusions section of the test plan.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1207030000">
<title><content-text>Prototyping the Server Farm</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207030100">
<title><content-text>Identifying Server Farm Goals and Requirements</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1359810202">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030100/en1207030101/cm1359810202.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030100/en1207030101/cm1359810202text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the business goals of the stadium network is to provide better customer service. This goal can be achieved by improving access to the website for viewing schedules, purchasing and printing tickets, and purchasing merchandise. </p> <p>The proposed design recommends relocating the web server, DNS server, and database server to a server farm located in a new data center.</p> <p><b>Server Relocation for the Stadium Network</b></p> <p>Relocating the servers from the stadium management offices to a new data center is a major change in the way the traffic flows in the stadium network. It is a critical piece of the proposed design. The requirements for nearly 100 percent uptime and availability can be better accomplished if the servers are located in a central data center. The data center design is a network module that can be tested in a prototype. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207030200">
<title><content-text>Creating the Test Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2227596715">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030201/cm2227596715.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030201/cm2227596715text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>What Needs to Be Tested?</b></p> <p>In the proposed network design for the stadium, the following elements directly impact the server farm:</p> <p><ul><li> Creation of modular server farm topology</li><li> Implementation of redundant links for server connectivity</li><li> Location of redundant Layer 2 switches for server connectivity</li><li> Use of a per-VLAN rapid spanning tree to shorten the time for redundant switched links to become active after a failure</li><li> Configuration of a flexible IP addressing structure</li><li> Configuration of EIGRP in the data center Core and Distribution Layers</li><li> Configuration of strict traffic filtering policies to prevent unauthorized access</li></ul></p> <p>The network designer decides to build a prototype network. Because the designer does not have multilayer switches available, routers are used to perform the Layer 3 function. The prototype network topology consists of five Layer 2 switches, five Layer 3 devices, and a number of PCs emulating servers running various applications. Using this topology, the NetworkingCompany staff can demonstrate that the business goals and technical requirements can be met with the proposed design. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4310585352">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030202/cm4310585352.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030202/cm4310585352text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The NetworkingCompany staff uses the checklist created by the network designer to build the prototype network. </p> <p><b>Testing the Prototype Network</b></p> <p>After the prototype network is built, the staff executes basic connectivity tests to ensure that the network is configured correctly. They then create a network baseline.</p> <p><b>Baseline Measurements</b></p> <p>It is important to develop the baseline measurements of the prototype network. The results observed during the various tests are then compared to the original configuration. In this way, the staff can identify and record any processes or functions that increase processor usage or decrease available bandwidth.</p> <p>To simulate traffic on the network, the designer recommends running a traffic generator on one of the attached PCs. A traffic generator is a testing tool that simulates various levels of network use. In the case of the server farm prototype, the designer intends to use the tool to simulate network traffic to the web server.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030203">
﻿<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm8465326685">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030203/cm8465326685/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030203/cm8465326685/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Using the checklist created by the network designer, build the prototype network. Perform the Basic Connectivity Test according to the test plan.</p> <p>The following documents should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="D4_7.3.2_StadiumBasicConnectivityTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium Basic Connectivity Test Plan</content-link> </p> <p>2. <content-link target="PacketTracer_7.3.2_InstallationChecklist.pdf" type="internalfile">Installation Checklist</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030204">
﻿<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4712401599">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030204/cm4712401599/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030200/en1207030204/cm4712401599/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create a server farm test plan and prototype installation checklist for the FilmCompany.</p> <p>The following documents should be downloaded to perform the lab activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="Dis4_Lab_7.3.2.4_TestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Server Farm Design Test Plan</content-link> </p> <p>2. <content-link target="Dis4_Lab_7.3.2_Checklist.pdf" type="internalfile">Installation Checklist</content-link></p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207030300">
<title><content-text>Validating Device and Topology Selection</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6644788566">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030301/cm6644788566.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030301/cm6644788566text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The proposed data center design for the stadium network uses a redundant hierarchical topology for the server farm.</p> <p><b>LAN Simulation</b></p> <p>In the LAN simulation tests, the routed links usually converged faster than the STP links in the event of a failure. The network designer therefore chooses to prototype the switched links with Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (<content-link target="{88771053-CE38-4F2E-9126-4C55203BB756}" type="glossary">RSTP</content-link>) to test how quickly the server farm network recovers from a failure. The designer reviews the operation of RSTP with the network technicians before setting up the test.</p> <p>RSTP provides rapid connectivity following the failure of a switch, a switch port, or a LAN. RSTP enables switch port configuration so that the ports can transition to forwarding directly when the switch reinitializes.</p> <p><b>Per VLAN Rapid Spanning Tree Plus </b></p> <p>The RSTP (802.1w) standard assumes only one spanning-tree instance for the entire switched network. This is regardless of the number of VLANs. The Cisco implementation of RSTP is Per VLAN Rapid Spanning Tree Plus (PVRST+). PVRST+ defines a Spanning Tree Protocol that has one instance of RSTP per VLAN. Cisco documentation often refers to this implementation as RSTP.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7128815340">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030302/cm7128815340.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030302/cm7128815340text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Port Roles</b></p> <p>RSTP defines the following port roles:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Root</b><b>-</b> A forwarding port elected for every non-root switch that gives the least-cost path to the root switch.</li><li> <b>Designated</b><b>-</b> A forwarding port elected for every switched LAN segment based on the best bridge protocol data unit (<content-link target="{84513F78-30C6-489D-8079-3ED54477DD70}" type="glossary">BPDU</content-link>). This port is the least-cost path to the root switch from the LAN segment.</li><li> <b>Alternate</b><b>-</b> An alternate path to the root switch for a non-root switch that is different from the path that the root port takes. This port is blocked for forwarding traffic.</li><li> <b>Backup</b><b>-</b> A backup path that provides a redundant, but less desirable, connection to a segment to which another port on the non-root switch already connects. This port is blocked. (Backup ports can only exist where two ports are connected together in a loopback by a point-to-point link or bridge with two or more connections to a shared LAN segment.)</li><li> <b>Disabled</b><b>-</b> A port that has no role within the operation of spanning tree</li></ul></p> <p>Root and designated port roles include the port in the active topology. Alternate and backup port roles exclude the port from the active topology.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4592265804">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030303/cm4592265804.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030303/cm4592265804text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Stadium Network</b></p> <p>The network designer reviews the RSTP operation with the NetworkingCompany staff. The designer creates an installation checklist and a test plan to verify that the switched links can provide the required resiliency. </p> <p>Following the details outlined on the checklist, the NetworkingCompany staff sets up a per-VLAN rapid spanning tree on the Access Layer switches. The staff designates the primary and secondary root bridges to ensure that the network remains stable if new switches are added to the topology. They then introduce failures into the switched topology to observe the results.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1207030304">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm8252489645">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030304/cm8252489645.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030304/cm8252489645text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the port state to the appropriate port role, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030305">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4399976559">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030305/cm4399976559/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030300/en1207030305/cm4399976559/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Configure and test RSTP in a prototype network.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207030400">
<title><content-text>Validating the Security Plan</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9633320446">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030401/cm9633320446.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030401/cm9633320446text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Availability and security are two primary requirements for the stadium server farm network. </p> <p><b>Availability Requirements</b></p> <p>The network designer addresses availability requirements by using redundant links and components where possible. Configuring RSTP for Layer 2 and using EIGRP for Layer 3 ensures quick convergence of the network in the event of a failure.</p> <p><b>Multilayer Security</b></p> <p>The proposed design for the server farm implements multiple layers of security. Utilities and programs protect the servers from viruses and worm attacks and also provide host-based intrusion prevention. Authentication mechanisms allow only authorized users access.</p> <p>At the Access Layer, employing port security and disabling unused ports help prevent the network from unauthorized access.</p> <p>ACLs filter traffic and prevent <content-link target="{0A478ACD-5C9B-4708-8672-CB6AA02097AD}" type="glossary">spoofed</content-link>, or un-requested, traffic from reaching the servers. The ACLs are placed at the point where the server farm connects into the stadium network. </p> <p><b>Firewalls</b></p> <p>Firewalls and firewall feature sets in the Cisco IOS Software provide stateful firewall capability. IPSs protect the network from known threats and abnormal traffic patterns. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030402">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm7626653049">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030402/cm7626653049.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030402/cm7626653049text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Testing the ACL Design</b></p> <p>The network designer decides to test the ACL design and placement because it has the most potential for variability. The designer creates a test plan that lists all of the filtering rules and methods for testing. The designer suggests using a network simulator, rather than a prototype network. The simulator can be configured quickly to contain all of the proposed devices and links.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030403">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1250157017">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030403/cm1250157017/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030400/en1207030403/cm1250157017/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Using a prototype network, apply and test ACLs designed to protect the stadium network server farm from attack and unauthorized access.</p> <p>The following document should be downloaded to perform the Packet Tracer activity:</p> <p>1. <content-link target="D4_7.3.4_StadiumACLTestPlan.pdf" type="internalfile">Stadium ACL Test Plan</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207030500">
<title><content-text>Verify Design Meets Business Goals</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030501">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7203265372">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030500/en1207030501/cm7203265372/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030500/en1207030501/cm7203265372/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Build the FilmCompany prototype network, and perform the tests according to the test plan created in the <i>Creating a Server Farm Test Plan</i> lab activity.</p> <p>Then analyze the results to determine the success or failure of the tests and complete the Actual Results section of the test plan.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1207030600">
<title><content-text>Identify Risks and Weaknesses</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030601">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm4733462321">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030600/en1207030601/cm4733462321.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030600/en1207030601/cm4733462321text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At the conclusion of the server farm prototype and simulation testing, some areas of concern with the proposed design are identified. The network designer is satisfied that the network performs as expected. However, the stadium needs to consider some design changes as the network grows and matures.</p> <p><b>Identified Weakness</b></p> <p>The tests show that the ACLs at the Distribution Layer prevent unauthorized traffic from entering the server farm but are not effective at filtering the traffic within the VLANs themselves. The test traffic between servers in the same VLAN is not restricted. </p> <p><b>Recommendations</b></p> <p>The network design supports server farm and data center growth. The designer recommends that the stadium management consider using multilayer switches at the Access Layer. Multilayer switches provide more flexibility than Layer 2 switches in separating and filtering traffic from users outside the data center. Additionally, multilayer switches provide more flexibility than Layer 2 switches in separating and filtering traffic from devices within the data center itself.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207030602">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9265058643">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030600/en1207030602/cm9265058643/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1207000000/en1207030000/en1207030600/en1207030602/cm9265058643/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Analyze the results of the FilmCompany prototype test and document any risks or weaknesses in the design. Complete the Conclusions section of the test plan.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1207040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207040100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1207040101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm1670368406">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207040000/en1207040100/en1207040101/cm1670368406.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1207000000/en1207040000/en1207040100/en1207040101/cm1670368406text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1207050000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1207050100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1207050101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm6570996327">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1207000000/en1207050000/en1207050100/en1207050101/cm6570996327/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1207000000/en1207050000/en1207050100/en1207050101/cm6570996327/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
