<chapter type="" id="en1201000000">
<title><content-text>Introducing Network Design Concepts</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en1201000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201000100">
<title><content-text>Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201000101">
<content-media type="ChapterIntroduction" id="cm7922697000">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201000000/en1201000100/en1201000101/cm7922697000.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201000000/en1201000100/en1201000101/cm7922697000text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201010000">
<title><content-text>Discovering Network Design Basics</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201010100">
<title><content-text>Network Design Overview</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010101">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm8995467327">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010100/en1201010101/cm8995467327.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010100/en1201010101/cm8995467327text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Computers and information networks are critical to the success of businesses, both large and small. They connect people, support applications and services, and provide access to the resources that keep the businesses running. To meet the daily requirements of businesses, networks themselves are becoming quite complex.</p> <p><b>Network Requirements</b></p> <p>Today, the Internet-based economy often demands around-the-clock customer service. This means that business networks must be available nearly 100 percent of the time. They must be smart enough to automatically protect against unexpected security incidents. These business networks must also be able to adjust to changing traffic loads to maintain consistent application response times. It is no longer practical to construct networks by connecting many standalone components without careful planning and design. </p> <p><b>Building a Good Network</b></p> <p>Good networks do not happen by accident. They are the result of hard work by network designers and technicians, who identify network requirements and select the best solutions to meet the needs of a business. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm5733493820">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010100/en1201010102/cm5733493820.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010100/en1201010102/cm5733493820text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network users generally do not think in terms of the complexity of the underlying network. They think of the network as a way to access the applications they need, when they need them. </p> <p><b>Network Requirements</b></p> <p>Most businesses actually have only a few requirements for their network: </p> <p><ul><li> The network should stay up all the time, even in the event of failed links, equipment failure, and overloaded conditions.</li><li> The network should reliably deliver applications and provide reasonable response times from any host to any host.</li><li> The network should be secure. It should protect the data that is transmitted over it, as well as data stored on the devices that connect to it. </li><li> The network should be easy to modify to adapt to network growth and general business changes.</li><li> Because failures occasionally occur, troubleshooting should be easy. Finding and fixing a problem should not be too time-consuming.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Fundamental Design Goals</b></p> <p>When examined carefully, these requirements translate into four fundamental network design goals:</p> <p><ul><li> Scalability</li><li> Availability</li><li> Security</li><li> Manageability</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201010200">
<title><content-text>The Benefits of a Hierarchical Network Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3045285937">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010201/cm3045285937.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010201/cm3045285937text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To meet the four fundamental design goals, a network must be built on an architecture that allows for both flexibility and growth. </p> <p><b>Hierarchical Network Design</b></p> <p>In networking, a hierarchical design is used to group devices into multiple networks. The networks are organized in a layered approach. The hierarchical design model has three basic layers: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>Core Layer</b> - Connects Distribution Layer devices</li><li> <b>Distribution Layer</b> - Interconnects the smaller local networks</li><li> <b>Access Layer</b> - Provides connectivity for network hosts and end devices</li></ul></p> <p><b>Advantages Over Flat Networks</b></p> <p>Hierarchical networks have advantages over flat network designs. The benefit of dividing a flat network into smaller, more manageable blocks is that local traffic remains local. Only traffic that is destined for other networks is moved to a higher layer.</p> <p>Layer 2 devices in a flat network provide little opportunity to control broadcasts or to filter undesirable traffic. As more devices and applications are added to a flat network, response times degrade until the network becomes unusable.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010202">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm9429645773">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010202/cm9429645773.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010202/cm9429645773text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The <content-link target="{D2CC1E22-2430-4467-887D-D5CA6CDF887B}" type="glossary">Cisco Enterprise Architectures</content-link> can be used to further divide the three-layer hierarchical design into modular areas. The modules represent areas that have different physical or logical connectivity. They designate where different functions occur in the network. This modularity enables flexibility in network design. It facilitates implementation and troubleshooting. Three areas of focus in modular network design are: </p> <p><ul><li> <b>Enterprise Campus</b> - This area contains the network elements required for independent operation within a single campus or branch location. </li><li> <b>Server Farm</b> - A component of the enterprise campus, the data center server farm protects the server resources and provides redundant, reliable high-speed connectivity. </li><li> <b>Enterprise Edge</b> - As traffic comes into the campus network, this area filters traffic from the external resources and routes it into the enterprise network. It contains all the elements required for efficient and secure communication between the enterprise campus and remote locations, remote users, and the Internet.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3029641230">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010203/cm3029641230.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010203/cm3029641230text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The modular framework of the Cisco Enterprise Architectures has the following design advantages:</p> <p><ul><li> It creates a <content-link target="{9625753C-970E-4948-AB3D-40BF92B54A08}" type="glossary">deterministic network</content-link> with clearly defined boundaries between modules. This provides clear demarcation points so that the network designer knows exactly where the traffic originates and where it flows. </li><li> It eases the design task by making each module independent. The designer can focus on the needs of each area separately.</li><li> It provides scalability by allowing enterprises to add modules easily. As network complexity grows, the designer can add new functional modules. </li><li> It enables the designer to add services and solutions without changing the underlying network design. </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201010204">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm2759394055">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010204/cm2759394055.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010200/en1201010204/cm2759394055text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Full Screen Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the characteristics of the hierarchical model and the Cisco Enterprise Architectures to the correct locations, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201010300">
<title><content-text>Network Design Methodologies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4330009543">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010301/cm4330009543.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010301/cm4330009543text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Large network design projects are normally divided into three distinct steps:</p> <p><b>Step 1: </b>Identify the network requirements.</p> <p><b>Step 2: </b>Characterize the existing network.</p> <p><b>Step 3: </b>Design the network topology and solutions.</p> <p><b>Identifying Network Requirements</b></p> <p>The network designer works closely with the customer to document the goals of the project. Goals are usually separated into two categories:</p> <p><ul><li> Business goals - Focus on how the network can make the business more successful</li><li> Technical requirements - Focus on how the technology is implemented within the network.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Characterizing the Existing Network</b></p> <p>Information about the current network and services is gathered and analyzed. It is necessary to compare the functionality of the existing network with the defined goals of the new project. The designer determines whether any existing equipment, infrastructure, and protocols can be re-used, and what new equipment and protocols are needed to complete the design.</p> <p><b>Designing the Network Topology</b></p> <p>A common strategy for network design is to take a <content-link target="{7F6371CE-1310-46DE-A5D1-3B2E6FE510AC}" type="glossary">top-down approach</content-link>. In this approach, the network applications and service requirements are identified, and then the network is designed to support them. </p> <p>When the design is complete, a prototype or proof-of-concept test is performed. This approach ensures that the new design functions as expected before it is implemented.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3039390680">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010302/cm3039390680.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010302/cm3039390680text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A common mistake made by network designers is the failure to correctly determine the scope of the network design project. </p> <p><b>Determining the Scope of the Project</b></p> <p>While gathering requirements, the designer identifies the issues that affect the entire network and those that affect only specific portions. Failure to understand the impact of a particular requirement often causes a project scope to expand beyond the original estimate. This oversight can greatly increase the cost and time required to implement the new design. </p> <p><b>Impacting the Entire Network</b></p> <p>Network requirements that impact the entire network include:</p> <p><ul><li> Adding new network applications and making major changes to existing applications, such as database or DNS structure changes</li><li> Improving the efficiency of network addressing or routing protocol changes</li><li> Integrating new security measures</li><li> Adding new network services, such as voice traffic, <content-link target="{CBA9A180-D87D-43D0-8D0D-DD6632B3F3A6}" type="glossary">content networking</content-link>, and <content-link target="{BD01FC37-10AC-4B49-BAF5-AE7B6246803A}" type="glossary">storage networking</content-link></li><li> Relocating servers to a data center server farm</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201010303">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm9425123460">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010303/cm9425123460.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010303/cm9425123460text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Impacting a Portion of the Network</b></p> <p>Requirements that may only affect a portion of the network include:</p> <p><ul><li> Improving Internet connectivity and adding bandwidth</li><li> Updating Access Layer LAN cabling</li><li> Providing redundancy for key services</li><li> Supporting wireless access in defined areas</li><li> Upgrading WAN bandwidth</li></ul></p> <p>These requirements may not affect many users or require many changes to the installed equipment. It is sometimes possible to integrate design changes into the existing network without disrupting the normal network operations for the majority of network users. This method reduces the costs associated with downtime and speeds the implementation of the network upgrade.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201010304">
<content-media type="ActivityMCSACheckbox" id="cm1713375994">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010304/cm1713375994.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201010000/en1201010300/en1201010304/cm1713375994text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Determine whether the requirement affects the entire network or only a portion of the network by placing a check in the appropriate column. Then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201020000">
<title><content-text>Investigating Core Layer Design Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201020100">
<title><content-text>What Happens at the Core Layer?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7192455594">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020101/cm7192455594.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020101/cm7192455594text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Core Layer is sometimes called the <content-link target="{586A97B5-1F74-4000-8B9A-2DECCF8C3A5D}" type="glossary">network backbone</content-link>. Routers and switches at the Core Layer provide high-speed connectivity. In an enterprise LAN, the Core Layer may connect multiple buildings or multiple sites, as well as provide connectivity to the server farm. The Core Layer includes one or more links to the devices at the enterprise edge in order to support Internet, <content-link target="{E3FA3CEA-9AE5-4109-B978-B384AAE257BD}" type="glossary">Virtual Private Networks (VPNs)</content-link>, <content-link target="{D7E0367B-247E-4464-8161-101729063EA9}" type="glossary">extranet</content-link>, and WAN access.</p> <p>Implementing a Core Layer reduces the complexity of the network, making it easier to manage and troubleshoot. </p> <p><b>Goals of the Core Layer</b></p> <p>The Core Layer design enables the efficient, high-speed transfer of data between one section of the network and another. The primary design goals at the Core Layer are to:</p> <p><ul><li> Provide 100% uptime</li><li> Maximize throughput </li><li> Facilitate network growth</li></ul></p> <p><b>Core Layer Technologies</b></p> <p>Technologies used at the Core Layer include:</p> <p><ul><li> Routers or <content-link target="{24F31B07-E881-4F9F-A9A3-4A1DB90E053B}" type="glossary">multilayer switches</content-link> that combine routing and switching in the same device</li><li> Redundancy and <content-link target="{D8D1836E-0E88-491B-B056-09BEA313FA21}" type="glossary">load balancing</content-link></li><li> High-speed and aggregate links</li><li> Routing protocols that scale well and converge quickly, such as <content-link target="{526A06A5-6D24-45CF-8303-698C51F060EA}" type="glossary">Enhanced Interior Gateway Routing Protocol (EIGRP)</content-link> and <content-link target="{503E0A87-5706-4C41-86E6-928F646A870C}" type="glossary">Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)</content-link> protocol</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2057022317">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020102/cm2057022317.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020102/cm2057022317text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Redundant Links</b></p> <p>Implementing redundant links at the Core Layer ensures that network devices can find alternate paths to send data in the event of a failure. When Layer 3 devices are placed at the Core Layer, these redundant links can be used for load balancing in addition to providing backup. In a flat, Layer 2 network design, <content-link target="{467D1D8E-E245-4C37-B17C-C8DD26355064}" type="glossary">Spanning Tree Protocol (STP)</content-link> disables redundant links unless a primary link fails. This STP behavior prevents load balancing over the redundant links.</p> <p><b>Mesh Topology</b></p> <p>Most Core Layers in a network are wired in either a<content-link target="{1C6EC88C-C8E3-45EE-9FD1-6D8129D28B89}" type="glossary"> full mesh</content-link> or <content-link target="{6D656554-1FB1-4C00-ADB3-39592A87636C}" type="glossary">partial mesh</content-link> topology. A full mesh topology is one in which every device has a connection to every other device. While full mesh topologies provide the benefit of a fully redundant network, they can be difficult to wire and manage and are more costly. For larger installations, a modified partial mesh topology is used. In a partial mesh topology, each device is connected to at least two others, creating sufficient redundancy without the complexity of a full mesh.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020103">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9607373399">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020103/cm9607373399/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020100/en1201020103/cm9607373399/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Create and compare full mesh and partial mesh topologies between routers.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201020200">
<title><content-text>Network Traffic Prioritization</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7629889903">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020200/en1201020201/cm7629889903.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020200/en1201020201/cm7629889903text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Preventing Failures</b></p> <p>The network designer must strive to provide a network that is resistant to failures and can recover quickly in the event of a failure. Core routers and switches can contain: </p> <p><ul><li> Dual power supplies and fans</li><li> A modular chassis-based design</li><li> Additional management modules</li></ul></p> <p>Redundant components increase the cost, but they are usually well worth the investment. Core layer devices should have <content-link target="{E3CD473F-27B2-42A5-817B-6D68DAFAF6CE}" type="glossary">hot-swappable</content-link> components whenever possible. Hot-swappable components can be installed or removed without first having to turn off the power to the device. Using these components reduces repair time and disruption to network services.</p> <p>Larger enterprises often install generators and large <content-link target="{71D8AB96-83AC-4CE7-973E-F683C8AB0E69}" type="glossary">UPS</content-link> devices. These devices prevent minor power outages from causing large-scale network failures.</p> <p><b>Reducing Human Error</b></p> <p>Human errors contribute to network failures. Unfortunately, the addition of redundant links and equipment cannot eliminate these factors. Many network failures are the result of poorly planned, untested updates or additions of new equipment. Never make a configuration change on a production network without first testing it in a lab environment! </p> <p>Failures at the Core Layer cause widespread outages. It is critical to have written policies and procedures in place to govern how changes are approved, tested, installed, and documented. Plan a back-out strategy to return the network to its previous state if changes are not successful.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201020300">
<title><content-text>Network Convergence</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8101003024">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020300/en1201020301/cm8101003024.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020300/en1201020301/cm8101003024text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The choice of a routing protocol for the Core Layer is determined by the size of the network and the number of redundant links or paths available. A major factor in choosing a protocol is how quickly it recovers from a link or device failure.</p> <p><b>Convergence</b></p> <p>Network convergence occurs when all routers have complete and accurate information about the network. The faster the <content-link target="{225296AC-ECAF-4723-B70C-A17BB8C111F9}" type="glossary">convergence time</content-link>, the quicker a network can react to a change in topology. Factors that affect convergence time include:</p> <p><ul><li> The speed at which the routing updates reach all of the routers in the network </li><li> The time that it takes each router to perform the calculation to determine the best paths</li></ul></p> <p><b>Selecting a Routing Protocol</b></p> <p>Most dynamic routing protocols offer acceptable convergence times in small networks. In larger networks, protocols like RIPv2 may converge too slowly to prevent disruption of network services if a link fails. Generally, in a large enterprise network, EIGRP or OSPF provide the most stable routing solution. </p> <p><b>Design Considerations</b></p> <p>Most networks contain a combination of dynamic and static routes. Network designers need to consider the number of routes required to ensure that all destinations in the network are reachable. Large routing tables can take significant time to converge. The design of network addressing and summarization strategies in all layers affects how well the routing protocol can react to a failure.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201020302">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm3667183642">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020300/en1201020302/cm3667183642/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201020000/en1201020300/en1201020302/cm3667183642/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Using the existing topology, add a new LAN segment to observe network convergence.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201030000">
<title><content-text>Investigating Distribution Layer Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201030100">
<title><content-text>What Happens at the Distribution Layer?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9168433615">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030101/cm9168433615.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030101/cm9168433615text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Distribution Layer represents a routing boundary between the Access Layer and the Core Layer. It also serves as a connection point between remote sites and the Core Layer. </p> <p><b>Distribution Layer Routing</b></p> <p>The Access Layer is commonly built using Layer 2 switching technology. The Distribution Layer is built using Layer 3 devices. Routers or multilayer switches, located at the Distribution Layer, provide many functions that are critical for meeting the goals of the network design. These goals include:</p> <p><ul><li> Filtering and managing traffic flows</li><li> Enforcing access control policies</li><li> Summarizing routes before advertising the routes to the Core</li><li> Isolating the Core from Access Layer failures or disruptions </li><li> Routing between Access Layer VLANs</li></ul></p> <p>Distribution Layer devices are also used to manage queues and prioritize traffic before transmission through the campus core.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2984877875">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030102/cm2984877875.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030102/cm2984877875text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Trunks</b></p> <p>Trunk links are often configured between Access and Distribution Layer networking devices. Trunks are used to carry traffic that belongs to multiple VLANs between devices over the same link. The network designer considers the overall VLAN strategy and network traffic patterns when designing the trunk links.</p> <p><b>Redundant Links</b></p> <p>When redundant links exist between devices in the Distribution Layer, the devices can be configured to load balance the traffic across the links. Load balancing increases the bandwidth available for applications.</p> <p><b>Distribution Layer Topology</b></p> <p>Distribution Layer networks are usually wired in a partial mesh topology. This topology provides enough redundant paths to ensure that the network can survive a link or device failure. When the Distribution Layer devices are located in the same wiring closet or data center, they are interconnected using Gigabit links. When the devices are separated by longer distances, fiber cable is used. Switches that support multiple high speed fiber connections can be expensive, so careful planning is necessary to ensure that enough fiber ports are available to provide the desired bandwidth and redundancy.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030103">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9118543637">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030103/cm9118543637/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030100/en1201030103/cm9118543637/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Demonstrate the functions performed by the Distribution Layer devices.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201030200">
<title><content-text>Limiting the Scope of Network Failure</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm7266857799">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030200/en1201030201/cm7266857799.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030200/en1201030201/cm7266857799text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A failure domain defines the portion of the network that is affected when either a device or network application fails.</p> <p><b>Limiting the Size of Failure Domains </b></p> <p>Because failures at the Core Layer of a network have a large impact, the network designer often concentrates on efforts to prevent failures. These efforts can greatly increase the cost to implement the network. In the hierarchical design model, it is easiest and usually least expensive to control the size of a failure domain in the Distribution Layer. In the Distribution Layer, network errors can be contained to a smaller area, thus affecting fewer users. When using Layer 3 devices at the Distribution Layer, every router functions as a gateway for a limited number of Access Layer users. </p> <p><b>Switch Block Deployment</b></p> <p>Routers, or multilayer switches, are usually deployed in pairs, with Access Layer switches evenly divided between them. This configuration is referred to as a building or departmental <content-link target="{229EDF0E-4154-4E2C-BD95-ABB9FF185CC8}" type="glossary">switch block</content-link>. Each switch block acts independently of the others. As a result, the failure of a single device does not cause the network to go down. Even the failure of an entire switch block does not impact a significant number of end users. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030202">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm6487589710">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030200/en1201030202/cm6487589710/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030200/en1201030202/cm6487589710/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Turn off the devices and disable interfaces to see the resulting network failures.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201030300">
<title><content-text>Building a Redundant Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7226692830">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030300/en1201030301/cm7226692830.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030300/en1201030301/cm7226692830text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To reduce downtime, the network designer deploys redundancy in the network. </p> <p><b>Redundancy at the Distribution Layer</b></p> <p>Devices at the Distribution Layer have redundant connections to switches at the Access Layer and to devices at the Core Layer. If a link or device fails, these connections provide alternate paths. Using an appropriate routing protocol at the Distribution Layer, the Layer 3 devices react quickly to link failures so that they do not impact network operations.</p> <p>Providing multiple connections to Layer 2 switches can cause unstable behavior in a network unless STP is enabled. Without STP, redundant links in a Layer 2 network can cause broadcast storms. Switches are unable to correctly learn the ports, so traffic ends up being flooded throughout the switch. By disabling one of the links, STP guarantees that only one path is active between two devices. If one of the links fails, the switch recalculates the spanning tree topology and automatically begins using the alternate link.</p> <p>Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (RSTP), as defined in IEEE 802.1w, builds upon the IEEE 802.1d technology and provides rapid convergence of the spanning tree. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030302">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm9338714813">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030300/en1201030302/cm9338714813.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030300/en1201030302/cm9338714813text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A high volume, enterprise server is connected to a switch port. If that port recalculates because of STP, the server is down for 50 seconds. It would be difficult to imagine the number of transactions lost during that timeframe.</p> <p>In a stable network, STP recalculations are infrequent. In an unstable network, it is important to check the switches for stability and configuration changes. One of the most common causes of frequent STP recalculations is a faulty power supply or power feed to a switch. A faulty power supply causes the device to reboot unexpectedly. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201030400">
<title><content-text>Traffic Filtering at the Distribution Layer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030401">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2816093371">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030401/cm2816093371.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030401/cm2816093371text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><content-link target="{BCF95A18-7A55-4606-B591-CC51A6A2AF31}" type="glossary">Access control lists (ACLs)</content-link> are a tool that can be used at the Distribution Layer to limit access and to prevent unwanted traffic from entering the Core network. An ACL is a list of conditions used to test network traffic that attempts to travel through a router interface. ACL statements identify which packets to accept or which to deny.</p> <p><b>Filtering Network Traffic</b></p> <p>To filter network traffic, the router examines each packet and then either forwards or discards it, based on the conditions specified in the ACL. There are different types of ACLs for different purposes. Standard ACLs filter traffic based on the source address. Extended ACLs can filter based on multiple criteria including:</p> <p><ul><li> Source address</li><li> Destination address</li><li> Protocols</li><li> Port numbers or applications</li><li> Whether the packet is part of an established TCP stream</li></ul></p> <p>Both standard and extended ACLs can be configured as either numbered or named access lists. </p> <p><b>Complex ACLs</b></p> <p>Standard and extended ACLs serve as the basis for other, more complex types of ACLs. Using Cisco IOS software, there are three complex ACL features that can be configured: dynamic, reflexive, and time-based.</p> <p><content-link target="{DC1F789C-5381-4353-BF94-44457BAD4024}" type="glossary">Dynamic ACL</content-link> - requires a user to use Telnet to connect to the router and authenticate. Once authenticated, traffic from the user is permitted. Dynamic ACLs are sometimes referred to as "lock and key" because the user is required to login in order to obtain access.</p> <p><content-link target="{C78A3E0C-F2F8-441F-9C72-9638EB1E5F1B}" type="glossary">Reflexive ACL</content-link> - allows outbound traffic and then limits inbound traffic to only responses to those permitted requests. This is similar to the <span class="cmd"><i>established</i></span> keyword used in extended ACL statements, except that these ACLs can also inspect UDP and ICMP traffic, in addition to TCP.</p> <p><content-link target="{C0FD7132-C81D-4457-A1A3-C81CA8B572EA}" type="glossary">Time-based ACL</content-link> - permits and denies specified traffic based on the time of day or day of the week.</p> <p><b>Placing ACLs</b></p> <p>Traffic that travels into an interface is filtered by the inbound ACL. Traffic going out of an interface is filtered by the outbound access control list. The network designer must decide where to place ACLs within the network to achieve the desired results.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201030402">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm1978774093">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030402/cm1978774093.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030402/cm1978774093text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen <b>Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the correct ACL to the appropriate statement, then click Check.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030403">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm5823348214">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030403/cm5823348214/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030403/cm5823348214/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Place the ACLs onto the appropriate interface in the topology.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030404">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7080422258">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030404/cm7080422258/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030400/en1201030404/cm7080422258/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Create an ACL to meet the conditions specified in the lab.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201030500">
<title><content-text>Routing Protocols at the Distribution Layer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201030501">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm9540683064">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030500/en1201030501/cm9540683064.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030500/en1201030501/cm9540683064text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another important function that occurs at the Distribution Layer is route summarization, also called route aggregation or supernetting.</p> <p><b>Route Summarization</b></p> <p>Route summarization has several advantages for the network, such as:</p> <p><ul><li> One route in the routing table that represents many other routes, creating smaller routing tables</li><li> Less routing update traffic on the network</li><li> Lower overhead on the router</li></ul></p> <p>Summarization can be performed manually or automatically, depending on which routing protocols are used in the network. </p> <p>Classless routing protocols such as RIPv2, <content-link target="{0A299D6F-1868-41D2-8AB0-3512C4AF26AD}" type="glossary">EIGRP</content-link>, OSPF, and <content-link target="{6C7A6B07-84F6-44A4-A778-E4B1A96B1FCE}" type="glossary">IS-IS</content-link>, support route summarization based on subnet addresses on any boundary. </p> <p>Classful routing protocols such as RIPv1, automatically summarize routes on the classful network boundary, but do not support summarization on any other boundaries.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201030502">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDSnapback" id="cm9963972357">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030500/en1201030502/cm9963972357.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201030000/en1201030500/en1201030502/cm9963972357text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>full Screen Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the summary route to the appropriate location.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201040000">
<title><content-text>Investigating Access Layer Design Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201040100">
<title><content-text>What Happens at the Access Layer?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3871921920">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040101/cm3871921920.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040101/cm3871921920text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Access Layer represents the edge of the network where end devices connect. Access Layer services and devices reside inside each building of a campus, each remote site and server farm, and at the enterprise edge. </p> <p><b>Access Layer Physical Considerations</b></p> <p>The Access Layer of the campus infrastructure uses Layer 2 switching technology to provide access into the network. The access can be either through a permanent wired infrastructure or through wireless Access Points. Ethernet over copper wiring poses distance limitations. Therefore, one of the primary concerns when designing the Access Layer of a campus infrastructure is the physical location of the equipment. </p> <p><b>Wiring Closets</b></p> <p>Wiring closets can be actual closets or small telecommunication rooms that act as the termination point for infrastructure cabling within buildings or within floors of a building. The placement and physical size of the wiring closets depends on network size and expansion plans. </p> <p>The wiring closet equipment provides power to end devices such as IP phones and wireless Access Points. Many Access Layer switches have <content-link target="{8F67ED12-5E3B-491A-BAAB-073FC1829DA1}" type="glossary">Power-over-Ethernet (PoE)</content-link> functionality.</p> <p>Unlike a typical wiring closet, inside a server farm or data center the Access Layer devices are typically redundant multilayer switches that combine the functionality of both routing and switching. Multilayer switches can provide firewall and intrusion protection features, as well as Layer 3 functions. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6238446372">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040102/cm6238446372.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040102/cm6238446372text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Impact of Converged Networking</b></p> <p>The modern computer network consists of more than just personal computers and printers connecting to the Access Layer. Many different devices can connect to an IP network, including:</p> <p><ul><li> IP telephones</li><li> Video cameras</li><li> Video conferencing systems</li></ul></p> <p>All of these services can be converged onto a single physical Access Layer infrastructure. However, the logical network design to support them becomes more complex due to considerations such as QoS, traffic segregation, and filtering. These new types of end devices, and the associated applications and services, change the requirements for scalability, availability, security and manageability at the Access Layer.</p> <p><b>The Need for Availability</b></p> <p>In early networks, high availability was usually present only at the network core, enterprise edge, and data center networks. With IP telephony, there is now an expectation that every individual telephone should be available 100% of the time.</p> <p>Redundant components and <content-link target="{379AE309-06C6-4942-8764-B9C6D0EF823F}" type="glossary">failover</content-link> strategies can be implemented at the Access Layer to improve reliability and increase availability for the end devices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4865760570">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040103/cm4865760570.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040103/cm4865760570text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Access Layer Management</b></p> <p>Improving the manageability of the Access Layer is a major concern for the network designer. Access Layer management is crucial due to:</p> <p><ul><li> The increase in the number and types of devices connecting at the Access Layer</li><li> The introduction of wireless access points into the LAN </li></ul></p> <p><b>Designing for Manageability</b></p> <p>In addition to providing basic connectivity at the Access Layer, the designer needs to consider:</p> <p><ul><li> Naming structures</li><li> VLAN architecture</li><li> Traffic patterns</li><li> Prioritization strategies </li></ul></p> <p>Configuring and using network management systems for a large converged network is very important. It is also important to standardize configurations and equipment when possible. </p> <p>Following good design principles improves the manageability and on-going support of the network by:</p> <p><ul><li> Ensuring that the network does not become too complex</li><li> Allowing easy troubleshooting when there is a problem </li><li> Making it easier to add new features and services in the future</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040104">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9714215032">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040104/cm9714215032/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040100/en1201040104/cm9714215032/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Explore different Access Layer functions.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201040200">
<title><content-text>Network Topologies at the Access Layer</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm6928131171">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040200/en1201040201/cm6928131171.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040200/en1201040201/cm6928131171text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most recent Ethernet networks use a star topology, which is sometimes called a hub and spoke topology. In a star topology, each end device has a direct connection to a single networking device. This single networking device is usually a Layer 2 or multilayer switch. A wired star topology in the Access Layer typically has no redundancy from individual end devices to the switch. For many businesses, the cost of additional wiring to create redundancy is usually too high.</p> <p>The advantages of a star topology include:</p> <p><ul><li> Easy installation</li><li> Minimal configuration</li></ul></p> <p>The disadvantages of a star topology are significant:</p> <p><ul><li> The central device represents a single point of failure.</li><li> The capabilities of the central device can limit overall performance for access to the network.</li><li> The topology does not recover in the event of a failure when there are no redundant links.</li></ul></p> <p>Ethernet star topologies usually have a combination of the following wiring:</p> <p><ul><li> Twisted pair wiring to connect to the individual end devices</li><li> Fiber to interconnect the access switches to the Distribution Layer devices</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040202">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm6646027392">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040200/en1201040202/cm6646027392/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040200/en1201040202/cm6646027392/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Create an access layer star topology. </p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201040300">
<title><content-text>How VLANs Segregate and Control Network Traffic</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm8683084691">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040300/en1201040301/cm8683084691.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040300/en1201040301/cm8683084691text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Using VLANs to Segregate Traffic</b></p> <p>Using VLANs and IP subnets is the most common method for segregating user groups and traffic within the Access Layer network. </p> <p><b>VLANs in the Past</b></p> <p>With the introduction of Layer 2 switching, VLANs were used to create end-to-end workgroup networks. The networks connected across buildings or even across the entire infrastructure. End-to-end VLANs are no longer used in this way. The increased number of users and the volume of network traffic that these users generate is too high to be supported.</p> <p><b>VLANs Now</b></p> <p>Today VLANs are used to separate and classify traffic streams and to control broadcast traffic within a single wiring closet or building. Although large VLANs that span entire networks are no longer recommended, they may be required to support special applications, such as wireless roaming and wireless IP phones. </p> <p>The recommended approach is to contain VLANs within a single wiring closet. This approach increases the number of VLANs in a network, which also increases the number of individual IP subnets. It is recommended practice to associate a single IP subnet with a single VLAN. IP addressing at the Access Layer becomes a critical design issue that affects the scalability of the entire network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040302">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm4558397492">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040300/en1201040302/cm4558397492/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040300/en1201040302/cm4558397492/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Monitor traffic passing through a VLAN. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201040400">
<title><content-text>Services at the Network Edge</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1829274045">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040400/en1201040401/cm1829274045.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040400/en1201040401/cm1829274045text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Providing Quality of Service to Network Applications</b></p> <p>Networks must provide secure, predictable, measurable and, at times, guaranteed services. Networks also need mechanisms to control congestion when traffic increases. Congestion is caused when the demand on the network resources exceeds the available capacity.</p> <p>All networks have limited resources. For this reason, networks need QoS mechanisms. The ability to provide QoS depends on traffic classification and the assigned priority.</p> <p><b>Classification</b></p> <p>Before designing QoS strategies, it is necessary to classify applications based on specific delivery requirements. Classifying data at or near the source enables the data to be assigned the appropriate priority as it moves through the entire network. Segregating traffic with similar characteristics into classes, and then marking that traffic, is a function of the network devices at the Access and Distribution Layers. An example of this strategy is to place the voice traffic on an access switch into a single VLAN. The device then marks the traffic originating from the voice VLAN with the highest priority.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201040500">
<title><content-text>Security at the Network Edge</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9589417012">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040500/en1201040501/cm9589417012.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040500/en1201040501/cm9589417012text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Security Risks at the Access Layer</b></p> <p>Many of the security risks that occur at the Access Layer of the network are the result of poorly-secured end devices. User error and carelessness account for a significant number of network security breaches.</p> <p><b>How Can the Network Designer Improve Security?</b></p> <p>Providing adequate security for end devices may not be in the scope of a network design project. Nevertheless, the designer needs to understand the network impact of a security incident, such as a worm or a trojan, at an end device. The designer can then better determine what network security measures to put in place to limit the effects on the network. </p> <p>Permitting network access to only known or authenticated devices limits the ability of intruders to enter the network. It is important to apply wireless security measures that follow recommended practices.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040502">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm7462879567">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040500/en1201040502/cm7462879567/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040500/en1201040502/cm7462879567/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Use the SANS site to identify Internet security threats.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201040600">
<title><content-text>Security Measures</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040601">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7457508730">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040601/cm7457508730.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040601/cm7457508730text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Providing Physical Security</b></p> <p>Physical security of a network is very important. Most network intruders gain physical entry at the Access Layer. On some network devices, like routers and switches, physical access can provide the opportunity to change passwords and obtain full access to devices.</p> <p>Obvious measures, like locking wiring closets and restricting access to networking devices, are often the most effective ways to prevent security breaches. In high risk or easily accessible areas, it may be necessary to equip wiring closets with additional security, such as cameras or motion detection devices and alarms. Some devices, such as keypad locks, can record which codes are used to enter the secured areas.</p> <p><b>Securing Access Layer Networking Devices</b></p> <p>The simple measures below can provide additional security to networking devices at the Access Layer:</p> <p><ul><li> Setting strong passwords</li><li> Using SSH to administer devices</li><li> Disabling unused ports </li></ul></p> <p>Switch port security and <content-link target="{C17C0D47-44EF-4539-B00E-A5EC50A42C60}" type="glossary">network access control</content-link> can ensure that only known and trusted devices have access to the network.</p> <p><b>Recommended Practice on Security</b></p> <p>Security risks cannot be eliminated or prevented completely. Effective risk management and assessment can significantly minimize the existing security risks. When considering security measures, it is important to understand that no single product can make an organization secure. True network security comes from a combination of products, services, and procedures as well as a thorough <content-link target="{5EAE2840-04C3-4FA0-B8A0-021FF3C4EB2C}" type="glossary">security policy</content-link> and a commitment to adhere to that policy.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040602">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5550192515">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040602/cm5550192515/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040602/cm5550192515/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Learn the risks of allowing physical access to the network by unauthorized persons. </p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201040603">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm9146246352">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040603/cm9146246352/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201040000/en1201040600/en1201040603/cm9146246352/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p>Implement port security to prevent unauthorized access.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201050000">
<title><content-text>Investigating Server Farms and Security</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201050100">
<title><content-text>What is a Server Farm?</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050101">
<content-media type="AnimationStepped" id="cm2373365917">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050100/en1201050101/cm2373365917.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050100/en1201050101/cm2373365917text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most enterprise networks provide users with Internet-accessible services, like email and e-commerce. The availability and security of these services is crucial to the success of a business. </p> <p><b>Server Farms</b></p> <p>Managing and securing numerous distributed servers at various locations within a business network is difficult. Recommended practice centralizes servers in <content-link target="{00FFEFE8-FBCE-4B90-B72E-4D60C9DE3968}" type="glossary">server farms</content-link>. Server farms are typically located in computer rooms and <content-link target="{56601A71-2EB1-4076-BBFE-883176F5DFA6}" type="glossary">data centers</content-link>.</p> <p>Creating a server farm has the following benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> Network traffic enters and leaves the server farm at a defined point. This arrangement makes it easier to secure, filter, and prioritize traffic.</li><li> Redundant, high-capacity links can be installed to the servers as well as between the server farm network and the main LAN. This configuration is more cost-effective than attempting to provide a similar level of connectivity to servers distributed throughout the network.</li><li> <content-link target="{D8D1836E-0E88-491B-B056-09BEA313FA21}" type="glossary">Load balancing</content-link> and <content-link target="{379AE309-06C6-4942-8764-B9C6D0EF823F}" type="glossary">failover</content-link> can be provided between servers and between networking devices.</li><li> The number of high-capacity switches and security devices is reduced, helping to lower the cost of providing services.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050102">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1851278763">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050100/en1201050102/cm1851278763/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050100/en1201050102/cm1851278763/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Observe and record the way in which traffic moves to and from the servers on the network.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201050200">
<title><content-text>Security, Firewalls, and DMZs</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicRollovers" id="cm9917889393">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050200/en1201050201/cm9917889393.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050200/en1201050201/cm9917889393text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Data center servers can be the target of malicious attacks and must be protected.</p> <p>Attacks against server farms can result in lost business for e-commerce and business-to-business applications as well as information theft. Both local area networks (LANs) and storage area networks (<content-link target="{3EA564C3-FA06-4680-B247-D77B83563005}" type="glossary">SANs</content-link>) must be secured to reduce the chances of such attacks. Hackers use a variety of tools to inspect networks and to launch intrusion and denial of service (<content-link target="{2B0C9762-0134-428E-B96F-79517BCF3F0B}" type="glossary">DoS</content-link>) attacks. </p> <p><b>Protecting Server Farms Against Attack</b></p> <p>Firewalls are often deployed to provide a basic level of security when internal and external users attempt to access the Internet via the server farm. To properly secure server farms, a more thorough approach must be followed. Such an approach takes advantage of the strengths of the following network products that can be deployed in a server farm:</p> <p><ul><li> Firewalls</li><li> LAN switch security features</li><li> Host-based and network-based intrusion detection and prevention systems</li><li> Load balancers</li><li> Network analysis and management devices</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2176355630">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050200/en1201050202/cm2176355630.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050200/en1201050202/cm2176355630text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Demilitarized Zones</b></p> <p>In the traditional network firewall design, servers that needed to be accessed from external networks were located on a demilitarized zone (<content-link target="{10CC55AF-CA8C-4066-BDB2-4156A746C72D}" type="glossary">DMZ</content-link>). Users accessing these servers from the Internet or other untrusted external networks were prevented from seeing resources located on the internal LAN. LAN users were treated as trusted users and usually had few restrictions imposed when they accessed servers on the DMZ.</p> <p><b>Protecting Against Internal Attacks</b></p> <p>Attacks originating on the internal network are now more common than attacks from external sources. As a result, the design of server farm security is different from the older DMZ model. A layer of firewall features and intrusion protection is required between the servers and the internal networks, as well as between the servers and the external users. An additional security layer between the servers may also be required.</p> <p>The sensitivity of data stored on the servers and contained in the transactions traveling the network determines the appropriate security policy for the design of the server farm.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201050300">
<title><content-text>High Availability</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1151253696">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050300/en1201050301/cm1151253696.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050300/en1201050301/cm1151253696text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Providing High Availability</b></p> <p>In addition to providing an extra layer of security, server farms are usually required to provide high availability for network applications and services. A highly available network is one that eliminates or reduces the potential impact of failures. This protection enables the network to meet requirements for access to applications, systems, and data from anywhere, at any time.</p> <p><b>Building in Redundancy</b></p> <p>To achieve high availability, servers are redundantly connected to two separate switches at the Access Layer. This redundancy provides a path from the server to the secondary switch if the primary switch fails. Devices at the Distribution and Core Layers of the server farm network are also redundantly connected. <content-link target="{C7FE1854-26CA-4A09-9778-C2D9ECCA7DA1}" type="glossary">Spanning Tree Protocols</content-link>, like Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (<content-link target="{A119EDDF-728E-4F5A-AA8C-A51D1256072A}" type="glossary">RSTP+</content-link>), manage redundant Layer 2 links. Hot Standby Router Protocol (HSRP) and routing protocols provide support for Layer 3 redundancy and failover.</p> <p><b>Virtualization</b></p> <p>Many separate logical servers can be located on one physical server. The physical server uses an operating system specifically designed to support multiple virtual images. This feature is known as virtualization. This technology reduces the cost of providing redundant services, load balancing, and failover for critical network services.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201050302">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1484897050">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050300/en1201050302/cm1484897050/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1201000000/en1201050000/en1201050300/en1201050302/cm1484897050/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Packet Tracer Activity</b></p> <p>Set up redundant switch links in a server farm and observe what happens when one device fails.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201060000">
<title><content-text>Investigating Wireless Network Considerations</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201060100">
<title><content-text>Considerations Unique to WLAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201060101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8513538352">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060100/en1201060101/cm8513538352.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060100/en1201060101/cm8513538352text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Understanding Customer Requirements</b></p> <p>Before designing an indoor wireless LAN (<content-link target="{C71E12A9-ADD1-45F9-8B68-B95D8CA2F541}" type="glossary">WLAN</content-link>) implementation, the network designer needs to fully understand how the customer intends to use the wireless network.</p> <p>The designer learns about the network requirements by asking the customer questions. The answers to these questions affect how a wireless network is implemented. Examples of some of these questions are:</p> <p><ul><li> Will wireless roaming be required?</li><li> What authentication for users is needed?</li><li> Will open access (hotspots) be provided for the guests?</li><li> Which network services and applications are available to wireless users?</li><li> What encryption technique can be used?</li><li> Are wireless IP telephones planned?</li><li> Which coverage areas need to be supported?</li><li> How many users are in each coverage area?</li></ul></p> <p>If the designer does not get answers to the questions or fully understand the customer requirements, implementing a wireless LAN will be difficult, if not impossible. For example, the requirements to provide unsecured hotspots are significantly less complex to design than authenticated access to protected internal servers.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201060102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8488015650">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060100/en1201060102/cm8488015650.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060100/en1201060102/cm8488015650text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Physical Network Design</b></p> <p>In typical wireless network designs, most of the effort focuses on the physical coverage areas of the network. </p> <p>The network designer conducts a site survey to determine the coverage areas for the network and to find the optimum locations for mounting wireless Access Points. The site survey results help determine the Access Point hardware, types of antennas, and the desired wireless feature sets. The designer determines that roaming between overlapping coverage areas can be supported.</p> <p><b>Logical Network Design</b></p> <p>Designing the logical network usually causes network designers the most difficulty. Customers often want to provide different levels of access to different types of wireless users. In addition, wireless networks must be both easy to use and secure. Resolving both the desired features and the constraints presents many different ways to design and configure wireless LANs. </p> <p>An example of a complex wireless network design is a business that needs to offer the following services:</p> <p><ul><li> Open wireless access for their visitors and vendors</li><li> Secured wireless access for their mobile employees</li><li> Reliable connectivity for wireless IP phones</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201060200">
<title><content-text>Considerations Unique to WLAN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201060201">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm5741107594">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060200/en1201060201/cm5741107594.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201060000/en1201060200/en1201060201/cm5741107594text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Each type of wireless access requires unique design considerations.</p> <p><b>Open Guest Access</b></p> <p>When visitors and vendors are at a business site, they often require access to email and web sites. This type of access must be convenient to use, and typically is not Wired Equivalent Privacy (<content-link target="{CFAC634A-D1A9-4C9B-AF8E-32D5A019530B}" type="glossary">WEP</content-link>) or Wi-Fi Protected Access (<content-link target="{B3963A28-2C2E-422B-8110-AB65CC8181B3}" type="glossary">WPA</content-link>) encrypted. To help guest users connect to the network, the Access Point service set identifier (<content-link target="{439FDA08-D142-445C-9B0B-F698FCC8FC77}" type="glossary">SSID</content-link>) is broadcast. </p> <p>Many hotspot guest systems use DHCP and a logging server to register and record wireless use. Guest users typically access the wireless network by opening a browser window and agreeing to a specified usage policy. The guest registration system records the user information and hardware address and then begins logging the IP traffic. These systems require an application server to be installed on the same network or VLAN as the Access Points.</p> <p><b>Secured Employee Access</b></p> <p>Some WLAN devices do not support isolated guest access. To secure employee access, use an entirely separate WLAN infrastructure that does not include guest access. The recommended practice is to separate the internal users on a different VLAN.</p> <p>Other wireless implementation recommended practices include:</p> <p><ul><li> Non-broadcast SSID</li><li> Strong encryption</li><li> User authentication</li><li> Virtual Private Network (<content-link target="{304B9119-D073-4F9F-8DF2-456DACFA55D4}" type="glossary">VPN</content-link>) tunneling for sensitive data</li><li> Firewall and intrusion prevention</li></ul></p> <p>In areas where secured wireless is restricted to a few devices, MAC address filtering can be used to limit access.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en1201070000">
<title><content-text>Supporting WANs and Remote Workers</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201070100">
<title><content-text>Design Considerations at the Enterprise Edge</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201070101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9819802387">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070100/en1201070101/cm9819802387.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070100/en1201070101/cm9819802387text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The enterprise edge is the area of the network where the enterprise network connects to external networks. Routers at the enterprise edge provide connectivity between the internal campus infrastructure and the Internet. They also provide connectivity to remote WAN users and services. The design requirements at the enterprise edge differ from those within the campus network. </p> <p><b>Cost of Bandwidth</b></p> <p>Most campus networks are built on Ethernet technology. However, WAN connectivity at the enterprise edge is usually leased from a third-party telecommunications service provider. Because these leased services can be expensive, the bandwidth available to WAN connections is often significantly less than the bandwidth available in the LAN. </p> <p><b>QoS</b></p> <p>The difference in bandwidth between the LAN and the WAN can create bottlenecks. These bottlenecks cause data to be queued by the edge routers. Anticipating and managing the queuing of data requires a Quality of Service (QoS) strategy. As a result, the design and implementation of WAN links can be complicated. </p> <p><b>Security</b></p> <p>Because the users and services accessed through the edge routers are not always known, security requirements at the enterprise edge are critical. Intrusion detection and stateful firewall inspection must be implemented to protect the internal campus network from potential threats.</p> <p><b>Remote Access</b></p> <p>In many cases, the campus LAN services must extend through the enterprise edge to remote offices and workers. This type of access has different requirements than the level of public access provided to users coming into the LAN from the Internet. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201070200">
<title><content-text>Integrating Remote Sites Into the Network Design</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201070201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3227289484">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070201/cm3227289484.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070201/cm3227289484text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Designing a network to support branch locations and remote workers requires the network designer to be familiar with the capabilities of the various WAN technologies. Traditional WAN technologies include:</p> <p><ul><li> Leased lines</li><li> Circuit-switched networks</li><li> Packet-switched networks, such as Frame Relay networks</li><li> <content-link target="{EE43EE47-FA90-4D9D-87F7-055D4282F4A9}" type="glossary">Cell-switched networks</content-link> such as Asynchronous Transfer Mode (<content-link target="{38489E14-964C-449B-A740-F61610B7A1C7}" type="glossary">ATM</content-link>) networks </li></ul></p> <p>In many locations, newer WAN technologies are available, such as:</p> <p><ul><li> Digital Subscriber Line (DSL)</li><li> Metro Ethernet</li><li> Cable modem</li><li> Long-range wireless</li><li> Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS)</li></ul></p> <p>Most WAN technologies are leased on a monthly basis from a telecommunications service provider. Depending on the distances, this type of connectivity can be quite expensive. WAN contracts often include service level agreements (<content-link target="{C1022203-8A87-4C52-8F68-7CD4513096FC}" type="glossary">SLAs</content-link>). These agreements guarantee the service level offered by the service provider. SLAs support critical business applications, such as IP telephony and high-speed transaction processing to remote locations.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201070202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9837604283">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070202/cm9837604283.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070202/cm9837604283text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In many companies, not every employee works on the main site premises. Employees who work offsite can include:</p> <p><ul><li> Remote workers</li><li> Mobile workers </li><li> Branch employees</li></ul></p> <p>Remote workers usually work one or more days a week from home or from another location. Mobile workers may be constantly traveling to different locations or be permanently deployed at a customer site. Some workers are employed at small branch offices. In any case, these employees need to have connectivity to the enterprise network. As the Internet has grown, businesses have turned to it as a means of extending their own networks. </p> <p><b>Virtual Private Networks</b></p> <p>One very common connectivity option, especially for remote workers, is a Virtual Private Network (<content-link target="{304B9119-D073-4F9F-8DF2-456DACFA55D4}" type="glossary">VPN</content-link>) through the Internet. A VPN is a private network that uses a public network to connect remote sites or users together. Instead of using a dedicated, real-world connection, such as leased lines, a VPN uses virtual connections routed through the Internet from the company private network to the remote router or PC.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201070203">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm7132364285">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070203/cm7132364285.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070200/en1201070203/cm7132364285text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen </p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Roll over the photos to view information specific to that remote worker. Drag the connection type to the appropriate remote worker, then click Check. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1201070300">
<title><content-text>Redundancy and Backup Links</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201070301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7370584281">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070300/en1201070301/cm7370584281.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070300/en1201070301/cm7370584281text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Redundant Links</b></p> <p>Redundancy is required on WAN links and is vitally important to ensure reliable connectivity to remote sites and users.</p> <p>Some business applications require that all packets be delivered in a timely fashion. For these applications, dropped connectivity is not an option. Providing redundancy on the WAN and throughout the internetwork ensures high availability for end-to-end applications.</p> <p>For a WAN, backup links provide the required redundancy. Backup links often use different technologies than the primary connection. This method ensures that if a failure occurs in one system, it does not necessarily affect the backup system. </p> <p>For example, a business that uses point-to-point WAN connections to remote sites can use VPNs through the Internet as an alternate strategy for redundancy. DSL, ISDN, and dialup modems are other connectivity options used to provide backup links in the event of a WAN failure. Although the backup links are frequently slower than the primary connections, they can be configured to forward only high-priority data and transactions.</p> <p><b>Load Sharing</b></p> <p>In addition to providing a backup strategy, redundant WAN connections can provide additional bandwidth through load sharing. The backup link can be configured to provide additional bandwidth all of the time or during peak traffic time only. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201070302">
<content-media type="ActivityMCMA" id="cm8514166874">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070300/en1201070302/cm8514166874.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201070000/en1201070300/en1201070302/cm8514166874text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Full Screen </p> <p><b>Activity</b></p> <p>Drag the connectivity option to the appropriate cloud for each network location. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en1201080000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201080100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1201080101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm4119834505">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201080000/en1201080100/en1201080101/cm4119834505.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1201000000/en1201080000/en1201080100/en1201080101/cm4119834505text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en1201090000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1201090100">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1201090101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm8046976434">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1201000000/en1201090000/en1201090100/en1201090101/cm8046976434/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en1201000000/en1201090000/en1201090100/en1201090101/cm8046976434/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Take the chapter quiz to check your knowledge.</p><p><b>Click the quiz icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
