<chapter type="" id="en1210000000">
<title><content-text>Course Summary</content-text></title>
<section type="" id="en1210000000">
<title><content-text>Putting It All Together</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en1210000100">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1210000101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6733702747">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000100/en1210000101/cm6733702747.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000100/en1210000101/cm6733702747text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Networks are essential to almost all successful modern organizations. This is true in nearly every industry you can imagine including healthcare, sports, government agencies, and ISPs. The pre-sales and network design skills you have developed in this course provide the basis for supporting any IT or networking organization, from a small consulting business to a large corporate enterprise. </p> <p>As an IT professional, it will be your job to deliver these vital network services efficiently and without disruption to the business. By competently performing the many networking roles in a professional manner, you will become a valuable contributor to any enterprise.</p> <p>The IT industry is constantly improving and expanding. A successful IT career requires a commitment to lifelong learning. The Cisco Networking Academy offers several courses, such as Cisco Certified Networking Professional (CCNP), that provide the ongoing training that you will need.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1210000200">
<title><content-text>Finding the Right Networking Job</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1210000201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5237889499">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000201/cm5237889499.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000201/cm5237889499text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The final two activities in this curriculum are designed to support your networking job search. The portfolio that you created during this course will help you evaluate your skills and interests. It will also serve as documentation and reference material during your networking career.</p> <p>Many resources are available to help your career search including books, websites, classes, and consultants. Most educational institutions have resources available to help students write resumes, find job openings, and practice interviewing. </p> <p>Employers around the world respect the CCNA curriculum and CCNA certification exam training. As a qualified CCNA, you may want to consider accepting a position outside your own country or a position that requires travel to other countries. Another option is to start your own business.</p> <p>In your job search, you should include these steps:</p> <p><ul><li> Evaluate your skills and strengths.</li><li> Research the types of jobs available that require your strengths.</li><li> Create your resume.</li><li> Send your resume to potential employers and post it with online job search websites.</li><li> Talk with people who work in the type of job you are interested in.</li><li> Talk with people who work for companies that you find desirable.</li><li> Apply and interview for available jobs.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1210000202">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm2616056145">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000202/cm2616056145/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000202/cm2616056145/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Lab Activity</b></p> <p> </p> <p>Research networking jobs that match your skills, strengths, and interests. </p> <p>Create and submit a resume with a cover letter for a networking job that you are interested in.</p><p><b>Click the lab icon to begin.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en1210000203">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm2545198805">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000203/cm2545198805.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000200/en1210000203/cm2545198805text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Imagine that you have submitted your resume to a company and that they have asked you for an interview. </p> <p><b>Question Types</b></p> <p>Expect your interviewer to ask many different types of questions, for example:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Behavioral</b> - How you interact with people and the workplace culture: "Are you available to work longer hours when needed?"</li><li> <b>Hypothetical</b> - How you would handle a particular situation: "What would you do if the building lost power?"</li><li> <b>Leading</b> - A series of questions directed to a specific type of situation: "Have you ever worked in a lab setting?"</li><li> <b>Open-ended</b> - A short question requiring an extended response: "Tell me about your job experience."</li></ul></p> <p><b>Interview Methods</b></p> <p>Many different methods are used for interviews. Common methods include:</p> <p><ul><li> A screening interview over the telephone</li><li> An interview at a career fair </li><li> An interview with one or more people at the hiring company site</li></ul></p> <p>An informational interview is one where you talk with someone at a particular company. You learn about the company and the interviewer learns about you. There is no specific job opening being discussed during an informational interview.</p> <p>By treating every interview as a valuable learning experience, you will increase your job interview skills and your knowledge of hiring practices. After the interview, reflect on what you learned, what went well, and what you want to improve for your next interview.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en1210000300">
<title><content-text>Preparing for the CCNA Exam and Lifelong Learning</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en1210000301">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm1194080777">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000300/en1210000301/cm1194080777.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en1210000000/en1210000000/en1210000300/en1210000301/cm1194080777text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>full screen summary.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
