<transcript lastedited="10.01.08 10:10:33">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.7.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 9 Quiz: Troubleshooting an Enterprise Network<br><br>1.All IP addresses have been correctly configured and all interfaces are up.  Based on the network topology and router output described below, which two statements describe what will occur while testing the network?  (Choose two.)<br>Network Topology<br>In this topology, router RTA is connected via its S0/0 to router RTB's S0/0 port on the network 192.168.10.0/24.  RTA is connected to two switches on the following networks 192.168.30.0/24 and 192.168.80.0/24.  RTB is connected to two switches on the following networks 192.168.50.0/24 and 192.168.20.0/24.  <br>The following output is displayed from RTA's configuration:<br>hostname RTA<br>!<br>router rip<br>network 192.168.30.0<br>network 192.168.80.0<br><br>The following output is displayed from RTB's configuration:<br>hostname RTB<br>!<br>router rip<br>network 192.168.50.0<br>network 192.168.20.0<br><br>A.RTA and RTB are able to ping each others serial interfaces.<br>B.RTA and RTB do not learn any routes from each other through the RIP process.<br>C.RTB has all five of the networks listed in the routing table.<br>D.RTA has all five of the networks listed in the routing table.<br>E.RTA and RTB will have three entries in the route table found via RIP.<br><br>2.Which utility is able to detect and monitor different types of traffic on a network and trigger an alarm when an excessive amount of a specified packet type is seen?<br>A.ping<br>B.SNMP<br>C.tracert<br>D.packet sniffer<br><br>3.Answer this question based on the network topology and router output below.  The network administrator configured the ACL to deny the LAN access to a web server with known viruses.  However, the users can still reach this server.  What could be the cause of the problem?<br><br>Network Topology<br>A switch on network 192.168.1.0/24 is connected to the Fa0/0 of router RTA.  RTA is connected via its Fa0/1 to another switch which connects to a server with the address 172.16.5.5/24.  RTA's ACL's are shown as follows:<br>RTA(config)# access-list 100 deny ip 192.168.1.0 0.0.0.255 host 172.16.5.5<br>RTA(config)# access-list 100 permit ip any any<br>RTA(config)# interface fa0/0<br>RTA(config)# ip access-group 100 out<br><br>A.The access list should specifically deny TCP port 80.<br>B.The access list should be applied inbound on the interface instead of outbound.<br>C.The access list should be a standard access list instead of and extended.<br>D.The access list has the source address and destination address reversed. <br><br>4.Answer this question based on the switch output below.  An administrator has been adding new V LAN's to Sw-2 and notices that the new information is not recognized by Sw-3.  Given the output of the show vtp status command, what is the reason why information is not shared in this VTP domain?<br><br>Sw-1#show vtp status<br>VTP Version:2<br>Configuration Revision: 247<br>Maximum VLANs supported locally: 1005<br>Number of existing VLANs:40<br>VTP Operating Mode:Client<br>VTP Domain Name:Lab_Network<br>VTP Pruning Mode:Enabled<br>VTP V2 Mode:Disabled<br>VTP Traps Generation:Disabled<br>MD5 digest: 0x45 0x52 0xB6 0xFD 0x63 0xC8 0x49 0x80<br>Configuration last modified by 10.10.12.1 at 8-12-08 12:04:42<br><br>Sw-2#show vtp status<br>VTP Version:2<br>Configuration Revision: 247<br>Maximum VLANs supported locally: 1005<br>Number of existing VLANs:40<br>VTP Operating Mode:Server<br>VTP Domain Name:Lab_Network<br>VTP Pruning Mode:Enabled<br>VTP V2 Mode:Disabled<br>VTP Traps Generation:Disabled<br>MD5 digest: 0x45 0x52 0xB6 0xFD 0x63 0xC8 0x49 0x80<br>Configuration last modified by 10.10.12.1 at 8-12-08 12:08:52<br><br>Sw-3#show vtp status<br>VTP Version:2<br>Configuration Revision: 247<br>Maximum VLANs supported locally: 1005<br>Number of existing VLANs:25<br>VTP Operating Mode:Transparent<br>VTP Domain Name:Lab_Network<br>VTP Pruning Mode:Enabled<br>VTP V2 Mode:Disabled<br>VTP Traps Generation:Disabled<br>MD5 digest: 0x45 0x52 0xB6 0xFD 0x63 0xC8 0x49 0x80<br>Configuration last modified by 10.10.12.1 at 8-12-08 13:34:49<br><br>A.The VTP domain is not the same between the switches.<br>B.Sw-3 is configured for transparent mode.<br>C.VTP version 2 has been disabled.<br>D.VTP traps have been disabled.<br><br>5.Answer this question based on the router output below.  Two neighboring routers are not able to establish connectivity.  Based on the output of the debug ppp authentication command, which statement is true?<br><br>03:17:47: Se0/1 PPP: Authorization NOT required<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: O CHALLENGE id 15 len 28 from "R1"<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: I CHALLENGE id 17 len 27 from "R2"<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: Using hostname from configured hostname<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: Using password from AAA<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: O RESPONSE id 17 len 28 from "R1"<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: I RESPONSE id 15 len 27 from "R2"<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 PPP: Sent CHAP LOGIN Request to AAA<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 PPP: Received LOGIN Response from AAA=FAIL<br>03:17:47: Se0/1 CHAP: O FAILURE id 15 len 26 msg is "Authentication failure"<br><br>E.only one side required authentication<br>F.an incorrect hash string is received from the remote router<br>G.the remote location is configured with PAP authentication instead of CHAP<br>H.the authentication methods are incompatible<br><br>6.Answer this question based on the network topology and the switch output below.  The ACME Company implements V LAN's across its network infrastructure to further control the network traffic.  The network administrator issued the show vlan command on SW2 to verify the V LAN configuration.  Which statement is true?<br>Network Topology<br>Router RTA is connected to switch SW2.  SW2 is connected to switches SW1 and SW3.  Engineering is V LAN 10.  Support is V LAN 20, and Sales is V LAN 30. <br><br>SW2# show vlan<br>VLANNameStatusPorts<br>1defaultactiveFa0/3, Fa0/4, Fa0/21,<br>Fa0/22, Fa0/23, Fa0/24<br>10EngineeringactiveFa0/5, Fa0/6, Fa0/7, Fa0/8,<br>Fa0/9<br>20SupportactiveFa0/10, Fa0/11, Fa0/12,<br>Fa0/13, Fa0/14, Fa0/15<br>30SalesactiveFa0/16, Fa0/17, Fa0/18,<br>Fa0/19, Fa0/20<br><br>A.All ports will be participating in V LAN1.<br>B.Traffic in each V LAN will not be seen in other V LAN's.<br>C.The status "active" indicated there are 22 devices currently connected to SW2.<br>D.Since V LAN 1 is the management V LAN, RTA can connect to any port in V LAN 1 to route between different V LAN's.<br><br>7.What is one way to limit the size of a failure domain?<br>A.implement a classless routing protocol<br>B.create redundant paths wherever possible<br>C.backup configuration files<br>D.ensure devices are not-swappable<br><br>8.Answer this question based on the network topology below.  The server was just added to the network and no hosts are able to connect to it.  What could be the problem?<br><br>Network Topology<br>Router RTA is connected via Fa0/0 to a switch.  The switch is connected to two hosts on the 10.10.10.0/24 network with the following IP addresses, 192.168.102.50/27 and 192.168.102.34/27.  RTB is connected via Fa0/0 to a switch.  The switch is connected to a host with the IP address 192.168.102.99/27 and a server with the IP address 192.168.102.127/27.  RTA has a serial connection port S0/0 to RTB port S0/0.<br><br>A.The IP address of the server should be dynamic instead of static.<br>B.The IP address assigned to the server is the network address for this subnetwork.<br>C.The IP address assigned to the server is the broadcast address for this subnetwork.<br>D.The network is not subnetted correctly.<br><br>9.A technician is troubleshooting a loss of connectivity and suspects that and incorrectly configured ACL is the cause.  Which two commands can the technician use to verify that the ACL is incorrectly configured?  (Choose two.)<br>A.show protocols<br>B.show running-config<br>C.show ip route<br>D.show access-lists<br>E.show ip interface<br><br>10.To answer this question, refer to the router output below.  Why is neighboring 192.168.199.137 not a DROTHER?<br><br>Neighbor IDPriStateDead TimeAddressInterface<br>172.16.40.15Full/DR0:00:31172.16.48.1Ethernet0<br>172.16.50.11Full/DROTHER0:00:33172.16.48.10Ethernet0<br>172.16.60.11Full/BDR0:00:33172.16.48.200Ethernet0<br>192.168.199.1371Full/-0:00:33192.168.1.2Serial0/1<br><br>A.It is participating in OSPF over a point interface.<br>B.The network commence if misconfigured on the local router.<br>C.The network commence if misconfigured on the neighbouring router.<br>D.OSPF authentication has been enabled on the local router but not on the neighboring route.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
