<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 18:01:18">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.2  - Types of V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts an overview of voice V LAN's including details and a sample configuration with multiple images.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Router R1, switch S1, and switch S3 are connected. Switch S1 port F0/3 is connected to S3 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. Router R1 interface F0/1 is connected to switch S1 port F0/5 using a straight-through cable.<br><br>A single PC, PC5, connects to an IP phone, which then connects to switch S3 port F0/18 using straight-through cables. <br><br>IP Phones in the Network:<br>Switch S3 port is configured to support voice traffic:<br>- port sends CDP frames to provide information used by the IP phone.<br>- Port forwards frames associated with V LAN 150.<br><br>Switch S1 is configured to support voice traffic:<br>- Uses V LAN 150 for voice V LAN.<br>- Prioritizes voice traffic.<br><br>The Details:<br>Uses the same basic network topology but expands the Cisco IP phone 7960 to show external and internal port connections. A Cisco IP phone contains an integrated three-port 10 /100 switch.<br><br>The S2 switch, IP phone, and PC connections are as follows:<br><br>Switch S2 port F0/18 (connection to IP phone port P1).<br>Switch port configured to support voice traffic:<br>- Instructs phone to tag voice frames with V LAN 150.<br>- Prioritizes voice frames.<br>- Forwards data frame on V LAN 20.<br><br>IP phone port P1 (external connection to switch S2).<br>Configured to send untagged data traffic.<br><br>IP phone port P2 (internal connection to phone ASIC).<br>Configured to tag voice traffic frames with V LAN 150.<br><br>IP phone port P3 (external access port connection to PC5).<br>Configured to send untagged data traffic.<br><br>Sample Configuration:<br>Shown is sample output from the show interfaces FA0/18 switchport command. The highlighted areas in the sample output are:<br><br>Name: FA0/18<br>Access Mode V LAN: 20 (V LAN 0020)<br>Voice V LAN: 150 (V LAN 0150)<br><br>These show the F0/18 interface configured with a V LAN configured for data (V LAN 20), and a V LAN configured for voice (V LAN 150).<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
