<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 13:11:46">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.4  - Controlling Broadcast Domains with V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts controlling broadcast domains with switches and routers. intra-V LAN communication and inter-V LAN communication are demonstrated.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S2 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S3 port F0/3 is connected to S1 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/1. Switch S1 port F0/6 is connected to router R1 interface F0/2, both using straight-through cables.<br><br>There are four PC's in total. PC1 and PC2 connect to switch S2 using ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables. PC4 and PC5 are connected to switch S3 using ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables.<br><br>Router R1 Gateways <br>Port F0/1 - 172.17.10.1 (V LAN 10)<br>Port F0/2 - 172.17.20.1 (V LAN 20)<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.21<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.24<br><br>PC2:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.22<br><br>PC5:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.25<br><br>Animation One: Intra-V LAN (within a V LAN) Communication<br><br>An arrow points to the link between S1 and S2 and to the link between S1 and S3, with the text: V LAN trunks configured to support V LAN's 10 and 20.<br><br>Scenario: PC1 in V LAN 10 wants to communicate with PC4 in V LAN 10. The animation shows:<br>Step One. A broadcast ARP request passes from PC1 in V LAN 10 to switch S2, and then to S1 and S3. The broadcast is sent to all other PC's in V LAN 10. <br>Step Two. PC4 receives the ARP request and sends an ARP reply back to PC1 with its MAC address.<br>Step Three. A unicast frame with data is sent from PC1 in V LAN 10 to switch S2, then to S1 and S3, and finally to PC4.<br><br>Animation Two: Inter-V LAN (between V LAN's) Communication<br><br>Network Topology: <br>Same as Animation 1.<br><br>Scenario: PC1 in V LAN 10 wants to communicate with PC5 in V LAN 20. The animation shows:<br><br>Step One. PC1 sends an ARP request frame for the MAC address of the default gateway R1 via switches S2 and S1.<br><br>Step Two. The router R1 sends an ARP reply frame from its interface configured on V LAN 10.<br><br>Step Three. PC1 then sends a unicast frame with the MAC address of the default gateway to R1. The frame is sent from switch S2 to S1.<br><br>Step Four. The router R1 sends an ARP request frame on V LAN 20 to determine the MAC address of PC5. Switches S1, S2, and S3 broadcast the ARP request frame out ports configured for V LAN 20. PC5 on V LAN 20 receives the ARP request frame from router R1.<br><br>Step Five. PC5 on V LAN 20 sends an ARP reply frame to switch S3. Switches S3 and S1 forward the ARP reply frame to router R1 with the destination MAC address of interface F0/2 on router R1.<br><br>Step Six. Router R1 sends the frame received from PC1 though S1 and S3 to PC5 (on V LAN 20).<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
