<transcript lastedited="12.18.08 08:12:21">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.5.1 Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[9 Questions <br><br>1.What happens when part of a message using TCP is not delivered to the destination host?<br>The sender resends the entire message.<br>The sender sends a request to find out what happened.<br>Nothing. TCP does not check for errors and missing data.<br>The part of the message that is missing is retransmitted.<br><br>2. Match the correct statement to the Service<br>Service:<br>Domain Name Services<br>E-mail<br>File Transfer<br>Dynamic Host Configuration<br>Web Service<br>Telnet<br>Statement:<br>A user types in a URL and a page loads in the client browser.<br>A user uploads new files to his or her website.<br>A user requests a website by typing in its name.<br>A workstation gets its IP address automatically.<br>Internet protocols enable users to send messages to each other over the Internet.<br>A network technician logs into a workstation from a remote site.<br><br>3. Match the items with the corresponding term (Not all items are used)<br>Term:<br>DNS Server<br>Common DNS port number<br>Domain Name<br>Item:<br>47<br>53<br>80<br>cisco.com<br>translates an IP address to a domain name<br>translates a domain name to an IP address<br>linksys@cisco.mail<br><br>4. Refer to the graphic. Which protocol allows you to type www.cisco.com instead of an IP address to open the web page?<br><br>The picture depicts an Internet Explorer Window, www.cisco.com has been typed in the address field and the corresponding page has been loaded.<br>DNS<br>FTP<br>HTML<br>HTTP<br>IM<br>SNMP<br><br>5. Match the Term with its corresponding definition.<br><br>Term:<br>HTML<br>HTTP<br>TTPS<br>web server<br>web client<br><br>Definition:<br>hosts a web page<br>requests a web page<br>used to create web pages<br>secure protocol that uses port 443<br>protocol commonly used by a web browser<br><br>6. Match the Protocol to the corresponding category (Not all protocols are used)<br><br>Category:<br>Protocols Used to Process E-mail<br>Protocols:<br>SMTP<br>FTP<br>POP3<br>HTTP<br>I MAP4<br>HTML<br>DNS<br><br>7. What acronym is associated with making a phone call using the Internet?<br><br>IM<br>HTML<br>HTTP<br>SNMP<br>V o IP<br><br>8. Match the port number to the corresponding protocol.<br><br>Port Numbers:<br>20<br>23<br>53<br>68<br>80<br>110<br>161<br>443<br><br>Protocols:<br>DHCP<br>DNS<br>FTP data<br>HTTP<br>HTTPS<br>POP3<br>SNMP<br>Telnet<br><br>9. Select three protocols that operate at the Application Layer of the O S I model. (Choose three)<br><br>ARP<br>TCP<br>DSL<br>FTP<br>POP3<br>DHCP<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
