<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 10:09:24">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.3.2 - Basic Router C L I show Commands]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts a table of the commonly used Show commands for router information display. The table headings include Full Command, Abbreviation, and Purpose / Information Displayed, listed below from left to right. The commands are categorized by General Use, Routing Related, Interface Related, and Connectivity Related.<br>Full Command Abbreviation Purpose / Information Displayed<br>General Use<br><br>show running-config<br>sh run<br>Displays current config running in RAM. Includes host name, passwords, interface IP addresses, routing protocol activated, DHCP, and NAT configuration. Must be issued in EXEC mode.<br><br>show startup-config<br>sh star<br>Displays backup config in NV RAM.  May be different if running config has not been copied to backup. Must be issued in EXEC mode.<br><br>show version<br>sh ve<br>Displays I O S version, ROM version, router uptime system image file name, boot method, number and type of interfaces installed, amount of RAM, NV RAM and flash, and configuration register value.<br>Routing Related<br><br>show ip protocols<br>sh ip pro<br>Displays information for routing protocols configured including timer settings, version numbers, update intervals, active interfaces, and networks advertised.<br><br>show ip route<br>sh ip ro<br>Displays routing table information including routing code, networks known, admin distance and metric, how they were learned, last update next hop, interface learned via, and any static routes (including default) routes configured.<br>Interface Related<br>Show interfaces (type#)sh int f 0 /0 Displays one or all interfaces with line (protocol) status, bandwidth, delay, reliability, encapsulation, duplex, and I/O statistics.<br><br>Show ip interface brief<br>sh ip int br<br>Displays all interfaces with IP address with interface status (up/down/admin down) and line protocol status (up/down)<br><br>Show protocols<br>sh prot<br>Displays information for routing protocols configured including timer settings, version numbers, update intervals, active interfaces, and networks advertised.<br>Connectivity Related<br><br>Show cdp neighbors detail<br>sh cdp ne<br>Displays information on directly connected devices including Device ID (host name). Local interface where device is connected, capability (R=router), S=switch), platform (eg.2620XM) and port I D or remote device. The details option provides the IP address of the other device as well as the I O S version.<br><br>Show sessions<br>sh ses<br>Displays telnet sessions (V T Y) with remote hosts. Displays session number, host name, and address.<br><br>Show ssh<br>sh ssh<br>Displays s s h server connections with remote hosts.<br>Ping (IP or Hostname)PSends five ICMP echo requests to an IP address or host name (if DNS is available) and displays min and max and average time to respond.<br>Traceroute (IP or host)TrSends echo request with varying T T L. Lists routes (hops) in path and time to respond.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
