<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 16:10:58">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.4.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Three Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br><br>Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the following constraints that should be applied when making a decision on which operating system to use:<br><br>Security <br>Support<br>Politics<br>Cost<br>Availability<br>Resources <br>Platform <br>Use<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>An operating system (OS) is the most significant software application in a PC. It is responsible for enabling the components and software applications to work together. <br>The kernel interacts directly with the hardware; the shell interacts with both the applications and the user. The user interacts with the shell using a command line interface or graphical user interface.<br>A network operating system (NOS) enables a device to share resources among multiple users and to access networked resources as though they were directly connected. The software that enables a network operating system to send and receive data from the network is known as a redirector.<br><br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the different types of hardware environments that an operating system may used on. The hardware environments that are most commonly found in the I T sector are the server, desktop, workstation, and mainframe platforms.  Different operating systems are used in each instance and this is dependent on the intended purpose of the system.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>Perform a pre-installation checklist before installing a new operating system.<br>An operating system is installed in a disk partition, which is a defined section of the hard disk. It is best to decide on partition schemes before installing To participate in a network, a computer requires a network interface card (NIC) configured with an IP address, subnet mask, and default gateway.<br>A network should be well planned, logically organized, and well documented.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a desktop PC with a Windows operating system installed. The OS, when connected to the Internet, will download the most pertinent updates available. Once these updates are downloaded, the PC can be configured to install them automatically.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>Operating system and application software must be kept up to date with the latest revisions, upgrades, or patches.<br>A patch is a piece of program code that corrects a problem or enhances the functionality of an operating system. An operating system can be configured to connect automatically to the manufacturers website, then download and install minor updates without any user intervention.<br>A service pack is a major update to an operating system or software application.<br>Application software can require a patch or update to repair a detected vulnerability in the application. <br>An application patch is generally found on the manufacturers website.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
