<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<p><li>An operating system, OS, is the most important software in a PC. It is responsible for making all of the components and software applications work together.</li><br/><li>The kernel interacts directly with the hardware; the shell interacts with the applications and the user. The user interacts with the shell through the command line interface or a graphical user interface. </li><br/><li>A NOS allows a device to share resources among many users and treat networked resources as though they are directly connected.  The software that enables the NOS to send and receive data from the network is called a redirector.
</li></ul>
]]></text>
</component>


<!-- slide 1 graphic text -->
<component id="s1_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>SECURITY</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>SUPPORT</b>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[<b>POLITICS</b>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[<b>COST</b>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>AVAILABILITY</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>RESOURCES</b>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt07"><text><![CDATA[<b>PLATFORM</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[<b>USE</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Operating System Selection</b>]]></text></component>






<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<p><li>Perform a pre-installation checklist before installing any new OS.</li><br/><li>An OS is installed in a disk partition, which is a defined section of the hard disk. Decide on partition schemes before installing the OS.</li><br/><li>To participate in a network, a computer requires a network interface card (NIC) configured with an IP address, subnet  mask and default gateway.</li><br/><li>A network should be well planned, logically organized and well documented. 
</li></ul>
]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Virtualization</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Clean Install</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Upgrade</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Multi-boot</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Laptop</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Handheld</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s2_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Classes of Computers</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each icon to see the actual device.</b>]]></text>
</component>




<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<p><b>An OS and application software must be kept up to date with the latest revisions, upgrades, or patches.</b>
</li><br/><li>A patch is a piece of program code that corrects a problem or enhances the functionality of an OS. An OS can be configured to connect automatically to the manufacturer’s web site, download and install minor updates without any user intervention.</li><br/><li>Service packs are major updates to an OS or software application.</li><br/><li>Application software can also require patches and updates to repair a detected vulnerability in the application.</li><br/><li>Applications patches are generally found through the manufacturer’s website.
]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s3_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Why and When to Apply Patches</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s3_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>I have a patch - I feel better now]]></text></component>





<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p><b>Before installing a wireless network, an installation plan should be created. Once the installation plan is complete, proceed with the following steps:</b>
</li><br/><li>Gather user requirements to determine the appropriate standard to use, bandwidth requirements, coverage areas, existing implementations, and cost.</li><br/><li>A site survey should be done to determine the optimum number and location of APs required to compensate for interference, environmental issues and to satisfy.</li><br/><li>No single security measure will keep your wireless network completely secure; combining multiple techniques will strengthen the integrity of your security </li><br/><li>The wireless client SSID must match the SSID configured on the AP. Additionally, encryption keys and authentication keys must also match.</li><br/><li>Once the wireless network is properly configured, a full configuration backup should be performed on wireless devices.</li><br/><li>The firmware OS of the device might need to be upgraded as new operating system features are developed or bugs are fixed.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_title">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Computer System</b>]]></text>
</component>



</textcomponents>