<transcript lastedited="10.15.08 12:10:07">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.5.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Four Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br> <br>Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts troubleshooting techniques based on the O S I model: top-down, divide-and-conquer, and bottom-up.<br><br>Diagram 1 text:<br><br>This chapter discussed the process of identifying, locating, and correcting problems that occur.<br>Gathering information and verifying that the problem exists are important first steps in the troubleshooting process.<br>When troubleshooting, there are several structured troubleshooting techniques that can be used, including top-down, bottom-up, divide-and-conquer. <br>Less structured techniques include trial and error, and substitution.<br>Experienced troubleshooters tend to rely on experience and less structured techniques for troubleshooting issues.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts troubleshooting utilities: i p config, ping, netstat, trace rt, and n s lookup.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>There are several tools available to help in the troubleshooting process. <br>Physical problems are concerned mainly with the hardware of devices as well as cabling connections.<br>Physical issues are often detected using the senses.  <br>A number of software utility programs are available that can help identify network problems. <br>Some of the most common software utilities used for troubleshooting include i p config, ping, trace rt, n s lookup, and netstat.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts the Linksys WRT300N with L E D's. <br><br>Diagram 3 text<br>There are several issues to check for when troubleshooting wired and wireless networks.  <br>L E D lights are used to indicate the current state or activity of a piece of equipment or connection. <br>For wired devices, check physical connectivity and cabling issues including:  wrong cable type, bad termination, physical damage, and port placement.<br>For a wireless client, connectivity problem such as: A/B/G/N compatibility, overlapping channels, signal strength, and interference should be examined. Also, check the SSID, authentication and encryption settings.<br>On both wired and wireless clients, check the IP configuration of the client, including IP address, subnet mask, default gateway and DNS information.<br>Verify connectivity between the ISR and the ISP by checking the router status page in the ISR to ensure that an IP address is assigned by the ISP and the connection is good.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts network documentation, a pen, and a calculator.<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>There are several sources of help when troubleshooting issues.<br>Documentation such as topology maps, network diagrams and addressing schemes, assists the troubleshooting effort.<br>Outside resources available to help with troubleshooting include: previously kept documentation, online FAQ's, colleagues and other network professionals, Internet forums.<br>A helpdesk is a group of individuals with the knowledge and tools required to help diagnose and correct common problems.<br>First, second and third-level helpdesk support is often available with escalation procedures in place to help solve issues.<br>It is important to document all steps taken in the troubleshooting process, including interaction with the helpdesk.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
