<transcript lastedited="10.31.08 08:10:38">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.2.4  - Layer 2 and Layer 3 Switching]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Activity 1<br>The diagram depicts an activity in which you must match the correct switching type to the number of bytes read by the incoming frame before it is forwarded. <br><br>Number of bytes read:<br>A: 6 bytes.<br>B: 64 bytes.<br>C: All bytes.<br><br>Switching method:<br>One.	Store and forward.<br>Two.	Fast forward.<br>Three.	Fragment free.<br><br>Activity 2<br>The diagram depicts two network topologies to compare symmetric and asymmetric switches.<br>Diagram 1:<br>Topology A consists of three PC's and a server connected to a switch. PC1 is connected to switch port F0/6, PC2 is connected to switch port F0/18, PC3 is connected to switch port F0/12, and the server is connected to switch port G i 1/1.<br>Topology B is identical to Topology A with the following exception: The server is connected to switch port F0/1.<br><br>Refer to Topologies A and B to complete the sentences, replacing BLANK with the words provided.<br>A.	Topology A.<br>B.	Topology B.<br>C.	Symmetric.<br>D.	Asymmetric.<br><br>BLANK is an example of a or an BLANK switch, which provides connections between ports with the same bandwidth. BLANK is a or an BLANK LAN switch, which provides switched connections between ports of different bandwidth.<br><br>Activity 3<br>Complete the sentences replacing BLANK with the words provided. Not all words are used. Some BLANKs may have more than one correct answer.<br>A. asymmetric.<br>B. physical.<br>C. data link.<br>D. IP.<br>E. port based.<br>F. shared.<br>G. multicast.<br>H. store and forward.<br>I. cut through.<br>J. network.<br>K. broadcast.<br>L. MAC.<br>M. unicast.<br>N. symmetric.<br><br>Because of the low latency of most modern switches, BLANK is better suited for most switch environments.<br>A network manager must evaluate the needed amount of bandwidth for connections between devices to accommodate the data flow of network-based applications when deciding the type of switch to select. However, most current switches are BLANK switches because they offer the greatest flexibility.<br>In BLANK memory buffering, frames are stored in queues that are linked to specific incoming interfaces.<br>In BLANK memory buffering, all frames are deposited into a common memory buffer that all ports on the switch use.<br>A Layer 2 LAN switch performs switching and filtering based on the O S I BLANK Layer BLANK address.<br>A Layer 3 switch operates at the BLANK Layer and uses BLANK address information for switch-forwarding decisions.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
