<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 13:01:13">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.5.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question One. How many physical interfaces are required to perform inter-V LAN routing with each method indicated?<br>Answer:<br>A. Traditional inter-V LAN routing: One port per V LAN.<br>B. Router-on-a-stick: One trunk port.<br>C. Multilayer switching: No physical interfaces.<br><br>Question Two. Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/0 as an 8 0 2 dot 1Q trunk. PC1 is connected to switch S1 port F0/11, has an IP address of 172.17.10.21, and is part of V LAN 10. PC3 is connected to switch S1 port F0/6, has an IP address of 172.17.30.23, and is part of V LAN 30.<br><br>Logical subinterfaces defined on R1 interface F0/0: <br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 10, IP address 172.17.10.1<br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 30, IP address 172.17.30.1<br><br>Assume that V LAN's 10 and 30 are defined on switch S1. To enable inter-V LAN routing for V LAN's 10 and 30, list the appropriate configurations for interface F0/0 on router R1 and interface F0/5 on switch S1.<br><br>Answer:<br>R1(config)#interface f0/0 dot 10<br>R1(config-sub i f)#encapsulation dot 1Q 10<br>R1(config-sub i f)#i p address 172.17.10.1 255.255.255.0<br>R1(config-sub i f)#interface f 0/0.30<br>R1(config-sub i f)#encapsulation dot 1Q 30<br>R1(config-sub i f)#i p address 172.17.30.1 255.255.255.0<br><br>S1 (config) # interface f0/8<br>S1 (config-i f) # switchport mode trunk<br><br>Question Three. Refer to the following diagram description to answer the question. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Switch S1 port F0/5 is connected to router R1 interface F0/0 as an 8 0 2 dot 1Q trunk. PC1 is connected to switch S1 port F0/11, has an IP address of 172.17.10.21, and is part of V LAN 10. PC3 is connected to switch S1 port F0/6, has an IP address of 172.17.30.23, and is part of V LAN 30.<br><br>Logical subinterfaces defined on R1: <br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 10, IP address 172.17.10.1<br>Subinterface F0/0 dot 30, IP address 172.17.30.1<br><br>PC1 cannot communicate with PC3. List some issues that may be causing the lack of communication.<br><br>Answer:<br>A. There is a native V LAN mismatch on the trunk link.<br>B. The wrong IP address is configured on a particular subinterface on interface F0/0 on router R1.<br>C. Trunking is not enabled on interface F0/5 of switch S1.<br>D. The TCP/IP settings on PC1 or PC3 are wrong.<br>E. Interface F0/11 or F0/6 is assigned to the wrong V LAN on switch S1.<br>F. The encapsulation command is missing on one of the subinterfaces of F0/0 on router R1.<br>G. Interface V LAN 1 is not configured as a subinterface on interface F0/0 of router R1.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
