<transcript lastedited="10.08.08 09:10:12">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.7.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 3 Quiz: Switching in an Enterprise Network<br><br>1.Which devices can be connected to a V LAN trunk?  (Choose three.)<br>A.a switch<br>B.a hub<br>C.a router<br>D.a server with a special NIC<br>E.a CSU/DSU<br>F.a repeater<br><br>2.What happens when there is a topology change on a network that utilizes S T P?  (Choose two)<br>A.User traffic is disrupted until recalculation is complete<br>B.The switch recomputes the Spanning Tree topology after the network recovers.<br>C.All ports are placed in learning state until convergence has occurred.<br>D.A delay of up to 50 seconds is incurred for convergence of the new spanning tree topology.<br>E.User data is forwarded while BPDU's are exchanged to recompute the topology.<br><br>3.This question refers to a network topology.  Use this topology to answer the question.<br>Network Topology<br>Router R1's F A 0 /0 is connected to Switch SW_1.  SW_1 is connected to two hosts.  One host is on V LAN 30 and one host is on V LAN 40. <br>Which set of commands should be used for configure the router to provide communication between the two hosts connected to the switch?<br>A.<br>R_1(config)# interface v lan 30<br>R_1(config-if)# switchport mode trunkdot1q<br>R_1(config-if)# interface v lan 40<br>R_1(config-if)# switchport mode trunkdot1q<br><br>B.<br>R_1(config)# interface fastethernet 0/0<br>R_1(config-if)# mode trunkdot1q 30 40<br>R_1(config-if)# ip address 192.168.1.1 255.255.255.0<br><br>C.<br>R_1(config)# interface v lan 30<br>R_1(config-if)# ip address 192.168.30.1 255.255.255.0<br>R_1(config-if)# no shutdown<br>R_1(config-if)# interface v lan 40<br>R_1(config-if)# ip address 192.168.40.1 255.255.255.0<br>R_1(config-if)# no shutdown<br><br>D.<br>R_1(config)# interface fastethernet 0/0<br>R_1(config-if)# no shutdown<br>R_1(config-if)# interface fastethernet 0/0.3<br>R_1(config-if)# encapsulationdot1q 30<br>R_1(config-if)# ip address 192.168.30.1 255.255.255.0<br>R_1(config-if)# interface fastethernet 0/0.4<br>R_1(config-if)#encapsulationdot1q 40<br>R_1(config-if)#ip address 192.168.40.1 255.255.255.0<br><br>4.How do Layer 3 switches differ from traditional routers?<br>A.Layer 3 switches are used in LAN's, while routers are used in WAN's.<br>B.Layer 3 switches use A S I C'S for routing , while routers are software based.<br>C.Layer 3 switches never perform routing lookups, while routers must always perform them.<br>D.Layer 3 switches forward packets based on MAC address only, while routers use IP addresses for forwarding.<br><br>5.Match the switching method to the description.  (Not all options are used.)<br>Switching Methods<br>store and forward<br>fragment-free<br>multilayer<br>cut-through<br>adaptive cut-through<br>fast-forward<br><br>Descriptions<br>recalculates the C R C value<br>subdivides into two other methods<br>low cost latency but may forward collision fragments<br>reads the first 64 bytes of the frame before forwarding<br>compares the number of errors found to a threshold value<br><br>6.Which two problems are caused by redundant links in a switched network?  (Choose two.)<br>routing table corruption<br>switching loops<br>broadcast storms<br>routing loops<br>corrupt forwarding information base<br><br>7.This question refers to a network topology.  Use this topology to answer the question.<br>Network Topology<br>This network topology consists of four switches connected to one another in a row.  Switch 1 is functioning in server mode.  Switch 2 is functioning in client mode.  Switch 3 is functioning in transparent mode.  Switch 4 is functioning in server mode.<br>The switches in the network topology are interconnected by trunked links and are configured with the VTP modes shown.  A new V LAN is added to Switch1.  Which three actions will occur?  (Choose three.)<br><br>A.Switch 1 will not add the V LAN to its V LAN database and will pass the updates to Switch 2.<br>B.Switch3 will pass the VTP update to Switch 4.<br>C.Switch3 will add the V LAN to its V LAN database.<br>D.Switch4 will add the V LAN to its V LAN database.<br>E.Switch4 will not receive the update.<br>F.Switch2 will add the V LAN to its V LAN database and pass the update to Switch 3.<br><br>8.What two criteria does S T P use to elect the route bridge in a redundantly switched network?  (Choose two.)<br>A.amount of switch RAM<br>B.bridge priority<br>C.switching speed<br>D.number of switch ports<br>E.switch MAC address<br>F.switch location<br><br>9.Following a link failure, when does R S T P allow ports to move to the forwarding state?<br>A.in less than a second<br>B.in two seconds<br>C.in 30 seconds<br>D.in 50 second<br>E.in 90 seconds<br><br>10.In what two ways does the use of V LAN's benefit an organization?  (Choose two.)<br>A.by centralizing departmental staff and network resources together in a single physical area<br>B.by allowing organization flexibility grouping users together by function instead of physical location<br>C.by allowing logical separation of voice and other critical traffic from the rest of the data traffic<br>D.by reducing the number of broadcast domains in an enterprise network<br>E.by reducing network management costs by replacing many Layer 2 devices with a few Layer 3 devices<br>F.by eliminating the need for routing traffic in large networks<br><br>11.Access 1 is a new switch that is to be connected as a VTP client to the network once it has been configured.  Given the output generated by the VTP server switch Dist-2, which series of configuration commands would successfully introduce the client switch into the VTP domain?  Use the output below to answer this question.<br><br>Dist-2# show vtp status<br>VTP version : 2<br>Configuration Revision: 11<br>Maximum V LAN's supported locally : 250<br>Number of existing V LAN's: 10<br>VTP Operating Mode : Server<br>VTP Domain Name : MYCORP<br>VTP Pruning Mode : Disabled<br>VTP V2 Mode : Enabled<br>VTP Traps Generation : Disabled<br>MDS digest: 0x0B 0xA5 0xDF 0xA7 0x52 0xBD 0x93 0x4D<br>Configuration last modified by 172.16.0.32 at 3-1-93 03:56:18<br>Local updater ID is 172.16.0.22.on interface V11 (lowest number V LAN interface 4)<br><br>Dist-2# show vtp password<br>VTP Password: ITrustYou<br>Dist-2#<br><br>A.<br>Access1(config)# vtp mode client<br>Access1(config)# vtp domain mycorp<br>Access1(config)# vtp password ITrustYou<br><br>B.<br>Access1(config)# vtp mode client<br>Access1(config)# vtp domain MYCORP<br>Access1(config)# vtp version 2<br>Access1(config)# vtp password ITrustYou<br><br>C.<br>Access1(config)# vtp mode client <br>Access1(config)# vtp domain mycorp<br>Access1(config)# vtp password ITrustYou<br><br>D.<br>Access1(config)# vtp mode client<br>Access1(config)# vtp domain Mycorp<br>Access1(config)# vtp version 2<br>Access1(config)# vtp password ITrustYou<br><br>12.What elements will exist in a converged switched network running spanning tree?  (Choose two.)<br>A.all non-designated ports forwarding<br>B.one root bridge per network<br>C.one root port per non-route bridge<br>D.multiple designated ports per segment<br>E.one designated port per network<br><br>13.How often are spanning-tree BPDU's sent by default?<br>A.every second<br>B.every two seconds<br>C.every three seconds<br>D.every four seconds<br><br>14.A router is configured to connect to a trunked uplink as shown.  A packet is received on the FastEthernet 0/ 1 physical interface from V LAN 1.  The packet destination address is 192.168.1.85.  What will the router do with the packet?  Use the output below to answer this question.<br><br>RA(config)# interface fastethernet 0/1<br>RA(config-if)# no shutdown<br>RA(config-if)# interface fastethernet 0/1.1<br>RA(config-subif)# encapsulation dot1q 1<br>RA(config-subif)# ip address 192.168.1.62 255.255.255.224<br>RA(config-if)# interface fastethernet 0/1.2<br>RA(config-subif)# encapsulation dot1q 2<br>RA(config-subif)# ip address 192.168.1.94 255.255.255.224<br>RA(config-if)# interface fastethernet 0/1.3<br>RA(config-subif)# encapsulation dot1q 3<br>RA(config-subif)# ip address 192.168.1.126 255.255.255.224<br>RA(config-subif)# exit<br><br>A.The router will ignore the packet because the source and destination are on the same broadcast domain.<br>B.The router will forward the packet out interface FastEthernet 0 /1.1.<br>C.The router will forward the packet out interface FastEthernet 0 /1.2.<br>D.The router will forward the packet out interface FastEthernet 0 /1.3.<br>E.The router will drop the packet because no network that includes the destination address is attached to the router.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
