<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 13:11:24">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.4  - Controlling Broadcast Domains with V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts controlling broadcast domains with V LAN's and Layer 3 forwarding.<br><br>Image description: The photograph shows a front view of a Catalyst Layer 3 switch. An equal sign associates it with an icon of a Layer 3 switch. <br><br>Animation description: Layer 3 Forwarding Example<br>Network Topology:<br>There are two Layer 2 switches (S2 and S3) and one Layer 3 switch (S1). Switch S2 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S3 port F0/3 is connected to S1 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. <br><br>There are four PC's total. PC1 and PC2 connect to switch S2 through ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables. PC4 and PC5 are connected to switch S3 through ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables.<br><br>Switch S1 Switch Virtual Interfaces (S V I's):<br>S V I for V LAN 10<br>S V I for V LAN 20<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.21<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.24<br><br>PC2:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.22<br><br>PC5:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.25<br><br>An arrow points to the links between S2 and S1 and between S3 and S1 with the text: V LAN trunks configured to support V LANs 10 and 20.<br><br>Scenario: PC1 in V LAN 10 wants to communicate with PC5 in V LAN 20.<br><br>Step One. PC1 sends an ARP request broadcast on V LAN 10. S2 forwards the ARP request out all ports configured for V LAN 10.<br><br>Step Two. Switch S1 forwards the ARP request out all ports configured for V LAN 10, including the S V I for V LAN 10. Switch S3 forwards the ARP request out all ports configured for V LAN 10. <br><br>Step Three. The S V I for V LAN 10 in switch S1 knows the location of V LAN 20. The S V I for V LAN 10 in switch S1 sends an ARP reply back to PC1 with this information.<br><br>Step Four. PC1 sends data destined for PC5 as a unicast frame through switch S2 to the S V I for V LAN 10 in switch S1.<br><br>Step Five. The S V I for V LAN 20 sends an ARP request broadcast out all switch ports configured for V LAN 20. Switch S3 sends that ARP request broadcast out all switch ports configured for V LAN 20.<br><br>Step Six. PC5 on V LAN 20 sends an ARP reply. Switch S3 sends that ARP reply to S1. Switch S1 forwards the ARP reply to the S V I for V LAN 20.<br><br>Step Seven. The S V I for V LAN 20 forwards the data sent from PC1 in a unicast frame to PC5 using the destination address it learned from the ARP reply in step 6.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
