<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 19:11:00">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.4.6  - RSTP Port States and Port Roles]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts the RSTP STP proposal and agreement process. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Four switches, S1, S2, S3, and S4, are interconnected with no redundant paths. Switch S2 port F0/2 is connected to S4 port F0/2. Switch S2 port F0/3 is connected to S3 port F0/1, and switch S3 port F0/4 is connected to S1 port F0/4. Switch S1 is the root bridge. <br><br>When the animation starts, a new link is added between switches S1 port F0/5 and S4 port F0/5, which creates a potential for switching loops.<br><br>Animation Sequence:<br>One. Switches S1 and S4 start a proposal and agreement process.<br>Two. Switch S1 sends S4 a proposal BPDU.<br>Three. Synchronization begins for switches S1 and S4.<br>Four. Switch S4 sends S1 an agreement.<br>Five. Synchronization ends for switches S1 and S4.<br>Six. Switches S4 and S2 start a proposal and agreement process.<br>Seven. Switch S4 sends S2 a proposal BPDU.<br>Eight. Synchronization begins for switches S4 and S2.<br>Nine. Synchronization continues for switches S4 and S2.<br>Ten. A BPDU is exchanged between S2 and S3.<br>Eleven. Switch S3 compares the local B ID to the B ID in the proposal BPDU from S2.<br>Twelve. Switch S3 blocks F0/4 and turns port F0/1 to designated discarding.<br>Thirteen. S3 determines that the B ID in the proposal BPDU from S2 is higher.<br>Fourteen. S3 sends back an agreement BPDU with its lower B ID to S2.<br>Fifteen. Switch S2 changes port F0/3 to alternate discarding.<br>Sixteen. Switch S3 changes port F0/1 to designated forwarding and port F0/4 to root port forwarding.<br>Seventeen. A BPDU is exchanged between switches S3 and S1.<br>Eighteen. Switch S1 compares the local B ID to the B ID in the proposal BPDU from S3.<br>Nineteen. Switch S1 blocks F0/5 and turns port F0/4 to designated discarding.<br>Twenty. S1 determines that the B ID in the proposal BPDU from S3 is higher.<br>Twenty One. S1 sends back an agreement BPDU with its lower B ID to S3.<br>Twenty Two. Switch S1 changes ports F0/4 and F0/5 to designated forwarding.<br><br>When the animation ends, the switch ports roles are as follows:<br><br>Switch S1 Port F0/4: Designated (Forwarding)<br>Switch S1 Port F0/5: Designated (Forwarding)<br>Switch S2 Port F0/2: Root (Forwarding)<br>Switch S2 Port F0/3: Alternate (Discarding)<br>Switch S3 Port F0/1: Designated (Forwarding)<br>Switch S3 Port F0/4: Root (Forwarding)<br>Switch S4 Port F0/2: Designated (Forwarding)<br>Switch S4 Port F0/5: Root (Forwarding)]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
