<transcript lastedited="03.27.09 10:03:46">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[10.8.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Determine the IP addresses that are usable for hosts on the subnetworks of the 200.100.50.0/28 network.<br>Addresses:<br>200.100.50.25<br>200.100.50.80<br>200.100.50.100<br>200.100.50.143<br>200.100.50.208<br>200.100.50.170<br>200.100.50.90<br>200.100.50.79<br><br>Categories:<br>Usable for host address<br>Not usable for host address<br><br>2.When is a straight-through cable used in a network?<br>A.When connecting a router through the console port<br>B.When connecting one switch to another switch<br>C.When connecting a host to a switch<br>D.When connecting a router to another router<br><br>3.Refer to the topology description below to answer the question. <br>Topology description:<br>Router R1 is connected to a CSU/DSU. The CSU/DSU is connected to one side of a network cloud. Router R2 is connected to another CSU/DSU. This CSU/DSU is connected to the opposite side of the network cloud.<br><br>Which function is a unique responsibility of the DCE devices shown in the exhibit?<br>A.Transmission of data<br>B.Reception of data<br>C.Clocking for the synchronous link<br>D.Noise cancellation in transmitted data<br><br>4.A router that terminates a serial WAN link is typically a D T E device. Under which circumstance would a router be configured as a DCE device?<br>A.A router cannot be configured as a DCE device.<br>B.When connecting a router directly to an analog device.<br>C.When performing a back-to-back router scenario in a test environment.<br>D.When the clock rate from the service provider cannot be matched by the router.<br><br>5.Which of the following are private IP addresses? (Choose three.)<br>A.10.1.1.1<br>B.172.32.5.2<br>C.192.167.10.10<br>D.172.16.4.4<br>E.192.168.5.5<br>F.224.6.6.6<br><br>6.Match the slash-format prefix number with the decimal mask number to subnet the last octet.<br>Slash-format prefix numbers:<br>/24<br>/25<br>/26<br>/27<br>/28<br>/29<br>/30<br><br>Decimal mask numbers:<br>128<br>252<br>224<br>0<br>248<br>192<br>240<br><br>7.Refer to the topology description to answer the question. <br>Topology description.<br>Router R1 interface FA0 is connected to router R2 interface FA0.<br><br>What type of cable connects the two routers together without any intermediary device?<br>A.Console<br>B.Rollover<br>C.Crossover<br>D.Straight-through<br><br>8.When setting the COM port properties for a PC, which option defines the default port configuration settings used to establish a direct serial connection between a computer and a Cisco networking device?<br>A.19,200 bps, 8 data bits, no parity, 1 stop bit, no flow control<br>B.9600 bps, 8 data bits, even parity, 2 stop bits, hardware flow control<br>C.9600 bps, 16 data bits, odd parity, 1 stop bit, hardware flow control<br>D.19,200 bps, 8 data bits, even parity, 1 stop bit, hardware flow control<br>E.9600 bps, 8 data bits, no parity, 1 stop bit, no flow control<br><br>9.Which three UTP cable lengths are specified by ANSI/T IA/EIA-568-B standards? (Choose three.)<br>A.Total end-to-end length of up to 100 meters<br>B.Up to 110 meters total end-to-end length<br>C.Horizontal cabling maximum of 90 meters<br>D.Up to 10 meters for interconnecting patch panels<br>E.Up to 5 meters for interconnecting patch panels<br>F.Up to 10 meters for connecting individual devices to wall jacks<br><br>10.What primary factor should be addressed before using wireless technology?<br>A.FFC address assignment<br>B.Selecting an Auto-MDIX capable switch<br>C.Power supply redundancy<br>D.Identify and if possible minimize sources of RFI]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
