<transcript lastedited="12.18.08 08:12:30">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[10 Questions ]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1. Which two statements are true regarding IP packets? (Choose two)<br>They are also called frames.<br>They are also called segments.<br>They are also called datagrams.<br>They have a header that contains a source and destination IP address.<br>They are addressed using a source and destination MAC address.<br>2. Number the steps in the order they are performed, for a host to send data over the Internet.<br>Data arrives at source host ISP POP.<br>Data arrives at destination host ISP POP.<br>Host data is divided into packets.<br>Source host ISP router forwards data out onto the Internet.<br>Destination host ISP uses destination IP address to deliver data to host.<br>Source host ISP decides whether data needs local or remote services.<br>3. Select the true statement regarding the ping and tracert commands.<br>Tracert shows each hop, while ping shows a destination reply only.<br>Tracert uses IP addresses: ping does not.<br>Both ping and tracert can show results in a graphical display<br>Ping shows whether the transmission is successful tracert does not.<br><br>4. Match the term to it's corresponding definition.<br>Terms<br>EMI <br>coax cable <br>ScTP <br>Fiber optic circuit <br>cladding <br>crosstalk<br><br>Definitions<br>uses a BNC connector<br>used inside fiber-optic cabling to reflect light<br>noise created by an electrical environment<br>uses two fibers: one to transmit, one to receive<br>expensive type of twisted-pair cabling<br>signal from one cable interferes with another<br><br>5. Where do ISP's get the public addresses that they assign to end users?<br>ISP's create the addresses themselves.<br>ISP's are assigned addresses through the RFC.<br>ISP's obtain their addresses automatically.<br>ISP's obtain addresses blocks from registry organizations.<br><br>6. Refer to the graphic description below. Which symbol would represent the Internet when a packet is travelling from a source to a destination through many network devices?<br><br>Symbols:<br>Host<br>Cloud<br>Router<br>Cable<br><br>Graphic:<br>The picture depicts two host computer, which connect to the Internet from different locations, Both hosts connect to the Internet cloud through a Router. The center of the picture represents the Internet, It has 7 interconnected routers in a Mesh Topology. The hosts and routers are interconnected using cables.<br><br>7. Match the terms to the corresponding categories (2 terms each category).<br>Categories:<br>UTP<br>Fiber<br>Coax<br>Terms:<br>uses light<br>uses eight wires<br>used by cable TV<br>used for long distances at high speeds<br>used for cable and satellite Internet connectivity<br>most common cabling used with modern Ethernet<br><br>8. What are three characteristics of UTP cabling? (Choose three)<br>uses light to transmit data<br>susceptible to EMI and RFI<br>commonly used between buildings<br>easiest type of networking cable to install<br>most commonly used type of networking cable<br>commonly used for Internet connectivity by a cable TV provider<br><br>9. Match the characteristic to the corresponding category (3 terms each category).<br>Categories:<br>Home<br>Internet Service Provider<br><br>Characteristic:<br>provides limited services to a few users<br>provides transport services to a large number of users<br>contains many different devices<br>contains few devices<br>requires robust equipment<br>purchases Internet connectivity<br><br>10. Match the statement to the corresponding category. True or false (3 terms each category).<br><br>Categories:<br>True<br>False<br><br>Statement<br>Fiber cable is used in networking.<br>Coax is easier to install than UTP.<br>Multimode is a type of fiber network cable.<br>Fiber connectivity is common in home networking.<br>Category 3 is commonly used for UTP data connectivity.<br>Coax cabling allows many signals to be combined to be transmitted<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
