<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:25">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.5.1 - Summary and Review]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[This is a review and is not a quiz. Questions and answers are provided. <br>Question One. Match each term with the correct description.<br><br>A.	VTP Domain.<br>B.	VTP Advertisements.<br>C.	VTP Modes.<br>D.	VTP Server.<br>E.	VTP Client.<br>F.	VTP Transparent.<br>G.	VTP Pruning.<br><br>One. One IP subnet to many V LAN's.<br>Two. One V LAN to many IP subnets.<br>Three. Two IP subnets to one V LAN.<br>Four. Two V LAN's to one IP subnet.<br>Five. One IP subnet to one V LAN.<br>Six. Varies with the model of Cisco Catalyst switch.<br>Seven. Default for a Catalyst switch; advertises V LAN configurations to other VTP-enabled switches.<br><br>Answers:<br>A = Five.<br>B = Six.<br>C = One.<br>D = Seven.<br>E = Four.<br>F = Two.<br>G = Three.<br><br>Question Two. List the default VTP configuration on a Catalyst switch for VTP version, VTP domain name, VTP mode, configuration revision number, and number of V LAN's.<br>Answer:<br>VTP Version = 1<br>VTP Domain Name = null<br>VTP Mode = Server<br>Config Revision = 0<br>V LAN's = 1<br><br>Question Three. <br>Refer to the diagram descriptions for Figures 1 and 2 provided here.<br><br>Diagram descriptions:<br>Figure 1 - There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S1 is connected to S2 and S3. PC1, PC2, and PC3 are connected to switch S2. PC4, PC5, and PC6 are connected to switch S3. Switch S1 is a VTP server. Switches S2 and S3 are VTP clients.<br><br>S1 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>S2 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>S3 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>Figure 2 - There are four switches, S1, S2, S3, and S4. Switch S1 is connected to S2 and S3. Switch S3 is connected to S4, a VTP client. PC1, PC2, and PC3 are connected to switch S2. PC4, PC5, and PC6 are connected to switch S3.<br><br>S1 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>S2 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>S3 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>S4 text: <br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 35<br>V LAN's: 30, 40<br><br>Figure 1 shows a converged VTP domain. In Figure 2, switch S4 is trunked to switch S3. The VTP information residing in switch S4 is displayed. Which conclusions can be made after VTP has converged when switch S4 is added?<br><br>A.	PC1 cannot communicate with PC2.<br>B.	PC2 cannot communicate with PC4.<br>C.	PC4 cannot communicate with PC5.<br>D.	The names of V LAN's can be determined.<br>Answer: A, B, C]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
