<transcript lastedited="01.26.09 11:01:10">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[11.1.5 - Using C L I Help]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts C L I hot keys and shortcuts.<br><br>C L I Editing:<br>-Tab - Completes a partial command name entry.<br>-Backspace - Erases the character to the left of the cursor.<br>-Ctrl-D - Erases the character at the cursor.<br>-Ctrl-K - Erases all characters from the cursor to the end of the command line.<br>-Escape D - Erases all characters from the cursor to the end of the word.<br>-Ctrl-U or Ctrl-X - Erases al characters from the cursor back to the beginning of the command line.<br>-Ctrl-W - Erases the word to the left of the cursor.<br>-Ctrl-A - Moves the cursor to the beginning of the line.<br>-Left Arrow or Ctrl-B - Moves the cursor one character to the left.<br>-Escape B - Moves the cursor back one word to the left.<br>-Escape F - Moves the cursor forward one word to the right.<br>-Right Arrow or Ctrl-F - Moves the cursor one character to the right.<br>-Ctrl-E - Moves the cursor to the end of command line.<br>-Up Arrow or Ctrl-P - Recalls a command in the history buffer, beginning with the most recent commands.<br>-Ctrl-R or Ctrl-I or Ctrl-L - Redisplays the system prompt and command line after a console message is received.<br><br>Note: The Delete key, used to erase to the right of the cursor, is not recognized by terminal programs.<br><br>At the More prompt:<br>-Enter key - Displays the next line.<br>-Space Bar - Displays the next screen.<br>-Any alphanumeric key - Returns to the EXEC prompt.<br><br>Break keys:<br>-Ctrl-C - When in any configuration mode, ends the configuration mode and returns to privileged EXEC mode. When in setup mode, goes back to the command prompt. <br>-Ctrl-Z - When in any configuration mode, ends the configuration mode and returns to privileged EXEC mode.<br>-Ctrl-Shift-6 - All-purpose break sequence. Stops DNS lookups, trace routes, pings.<br><br>Control keys - Press and hold the Ctrl key and then press the specified letter key.<br>Escape sequences - Press and release the Escape key, and then press the letter key.]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
