<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 19:11:45">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.4.6  - RSTP Port States and Port Roles]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the RSTP port roles. <br><br>Network Topology:<br>Three switches, S1, S2, and S3, are interconnected in a full mesh. Switch S1 port F0/2 is connected to S2 port F0/2. Switch S1 port F0/6 is connected to S2 port F0/6. Switch S2 port F0/3 is connected to S3 port F0/1, and switch S3 port F0/4 is connected to S1 port F0/4. Switch S1 is the root bridge. <br><br>F = Forwarding<br>DIS = Discarding<br><br>Root Ports (F): Switches S2 port F0/2 and S2 port F0/2.<br>The root port is the switch port on every non-root bridge that is the chosen path to the root bridge. A switch can only have one root port. The root port assumes the forwarding state in a stable active topology. The diagram depicts the root port as port F0/2 on switch S2 and port F0/4 on switch S3.<br><br>Designated Ports (F): Switch S1 ports F0/2 and F0/4, and switch S3 port F0/1.<br>Each segment has at least one switch port that is the designated port. The diagram depicts ports F0/1 on switch S3 and F0/2 on switch S1 as the designated ports. <br>In a stable active topology, the switch with the designated port receives frames on the segment that are destined for the root bridge. Each segment can only have one designated port. The designated port assumes the forwarding state. Therefore, F0/1 on switch S3 and F0/2 and F0/4 on switch S1 are in the forwarding state. All switches connected to a given segment listen to all BPDU's and determine the switch that will be the designated switch for a particular segment.<br><br>Alternate Ports (DIS): Switch S2 port F0/3.<br>The alternate port is a switch port that offers an alternate path toward the root bridge. Port F0/3 on switch S2 is in the alternate role. The alternate port assumes a discarding state in a stable active topology. An alternate port is present on non-designated switches and transitions to a designated port if the current designated path fails.<br><br>Backup Ports (DIS): Switch S2 port F0/6.<br>The backup port is an additional switch port on the designated switch with a redundant link to the segment for which the switch is designated. A backup port has a higher port ID than the designated port on the designated switch. The backup port assumes the discarding state in a stable active topology. The diagram depicts port F0/6 on switch S2 as the backup port, and it has assumed the discard role.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
