<transcript lastedited="11.06.08 06:11:40">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.1.5  - Planning the Wireless LAN]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts three activities.<br><br>Activity One: <br>The diagram depicts an activity in which you match the facts provided with the correct i e e e 8 0 2 dot 11 W LAN standard. Some facts may be used more than once.<br><br>Year Standard Ratified:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b. <br>8 0 2 dot 11a. <br>8 0 2 dot 11g. <br>8 0 2 dot 11n. <br><br>RF Band:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b. <br>8 0 2 dot 11a. <br>8 0 2 dot 11g. <br>8 0 2 dot 11n. <br><br>Modulation:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b. <br>8 0 2 dot 11a. <br>8 0 2 dot 11g.<br>8 0 2 dot 11n. <br><br>Data Rate:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b. <br>8 0 2 dot 11a. <br>8 0 2 dot 11g. <br>8 0 2 dot 11n. <br><br>Range:<br>8 0 2 dot 11b. <br>8 0 2 dot 11a. <br>8 0 2 dot 11g. <br>8 0 2 dot 11n. <br><br>Facts to match to W LAN standard:<br>- 150 feet, or 35 meters.<br>- 2008.<br>- Up to 11 Megabits per second.<br>- M I M O.<br>- 5 Gigahertz.<br>- 2003.<br>- Unconfirmed.<br>- OFDM and DSSS.<br>- Up to 54 Megabits per second.<br>- 1999.<br>- DSSS.<br>- OFDM.<br>- 2.4 Gigahertz.<br>- 230 feet, or 70 meters.<br>- 248 Megabits per second.<br><br>Activity Two: <br>The diagram depicts an activity in which you must select the appropriate word or phrase to complete the BLANK in the sentence. <br><br>Sentence:<br>One. The BLANK enables a client station capable of sending and receiving RF signals.<br><br>Two. An BLANK connects wireless clients to the wired LAN.<br><br>Three: Wireless clients that are at the maximum range and opposite sides of an access point will not be able to reach each other or detect each others transmissions. This is known as the BLANK problem.<br><br>Four. BLANK was developed to solve the hidden node problem. When enabled, the AP will allocate the medium to a requesting station for as long as required to complete the transmission.<br><br>Five. Desktops located in an existing, non-wired facility can have a wireless BLANK installed.<br><br>Six. A BLANK like the WRT300N performs the role of access point, Ethernet switch, and router.<br><br>Seven. In the 1990's, wireless NIC's for laptops were cards that slipped into the BLANK slot. <br><br>Word/Phrase:<br>- Access points.<br>- Hidden node.<br>- Wireless router.<br>- RTS/CTS.<br>- Wireless NIC.<br>- PCMCIA.<br>- PCI NIC.<br><br>Activity Three: <br>The diagram depicts an activity in which you must select the appropriate word, phrase or number to complete the BLANK in the sentence. Not all answers are used.<br><br>Sentence:<br>One. When a Linksys access point is configured to allow both 8 0 2 dot 11b and 8 0 2 dot 11g clients, it is operating in BLANK mode.<br><br>Two. The 2.4 Gigahertz band is broken down into BLANK channels for North America and BLANK channels for Europe.<br><br>Three. Best practice for W LAN's that require multiple access points are to use non-overlapping channels. If there are three adjacent access points, use channels BLANK, BLANK, and BLANK.<br><br>Four. The fundamental building block of the i e e e 8 0 2 dot 11 wireless LAN architecture is the BLANK.<br><br>Five. When a single BSS provides insufficient RF coverage, one or more can be joined through a common distribution system into an BLANK.<br><br>Six. The BLANK allows multiple access points in an E S S to appear to be a single BSS.<br><br>Seven. The W LAN network uses BLANK to advertise its presence, whereas W LAN clients use BLANK to find a W LAN network.<br><br>Word, Phrase or number:<br>Common distribution system.<br>Mixed service set.<br>Beacons.<br>Mixed.<br>Probes.<br>Basic service set.<br>Extended service area.<br>Choices for numbers include:<br>1, 5, 6, 7, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14 and 15.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
