<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 19:09:07">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[8.6.1 - Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Diagram 1, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts a router directly connected to a switch. The switch is connected to four computers on an internal network. <br><br>Diagram 1 text<br><br>Traffic filtering is the process of analyzing the contents of a packet to determine if the packet should be allowed or blocked.<br>ACL's enable management of traffic and security access to and from a network and its resources.<br>There are three types of ACL's: Standard, Extended, and Named ACL.<br>ACL's filter traffic based on source and destination IP address, application, and protocol.<br>Apply an ACL to a router interface to examine packets that are inbound or outbound.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts four lines of information as listed below.<br><br>Wild-card masks that permit a single host<br>172.16.22.87 0.0.0.0<br>host 172.22.8.17<br><br>Wild-card mask that permits a range of hosts for a /24 network:<br>172.16.22.0 0.0.0.255<br><br>Wild-card mask that permits an entire /16 network:<br>172.16.0.0 0.0.255.255<br><br>Wild-card mask that permits an entire /8 network:<br>10.0.0.0 0.255.255.255<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br><br>Using a wild-card mask provides flexibility, and can block a range of addresses or whole networks with one statement.<br>The wild-card mask compares the incoming address to a comparison address to determine which bits match.<br>To determine the wild-card mask, subtract the decimal subnet mask for an address or range from the all-255s mask (255.255.255.255).<br>There is implied deny any statement at end of the ACL.<br>The keyword any refers to all hosts and the keyword host refers to an individual IP address.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br><br>The diagram depicts ACL Processing and Creation Guidelines.<br>Standard ACL's filter on source IP address, and are placed as close to the destination as possible.<br>Extended ACL's can filter on source and destination addresses, as well as on protocol and port number, and should be placed as close to the source as possible.<br>Decide placement of ACL's based on type of ACL and requirements.<br>Each interface supports one ACL per direction per protocol.<br>Create an ACL using a unique identifier and apply either inbound or outbound on an interface using the IP access-group command.<br>The show IP interface, show access-lists and show running-config commands allow a network administrator to view all ACL's that have been configured on a router.<br>Named ACL's offer all the functionality and advantages of Standard and Extended ACL's.<br>ACL's restrict VTY access to increase network security. The access-class command is used to apply VTY ACL.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br><br>Configuring only one access list per protocol per direction.<br>Apply standard access lists closest to the destination.<br>Apply extended access lists closest to the source.<br>Use the correct number range for the type of list.<br>Determine the inbound or outbound direction looking at the port from inside the router.<br>Process statements sequentially from the top of the list to the bottom.<br>Deny packet if no match is found.<br>Enter the Access list statements in order from specific to general.<br>Configure an ACL with a permit statement or all traffic will be denied.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br><br><br>The diagram depicts the image of an Ethernet frame. The frame consists of the following:<br>MAC address head-er<br>IP head-er addresses<br>TCP head-er ports<br>Data<br>FCS<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>Extended ACL's filter source and destination IP addresses, protocol, and the destination application port numbers in a frame.<br>ACL's filter a range of ports using gt, lt, or range operators.<br>Use the established parameters to filter traffic that is a response to a request.<br>The order in which the statements are written has an impact on how the router performs.<br>There are different ways to approach writing ACL's: permit specific traffic first and then deny general traffic or deny specific traffic first then permit general traffic.<br>Network administrators account for NAT when creating and applying ACL's.<br>Apply ACL's directly to V LAN interfaces just as with physical interfaces.<br><br>Diagram 5, Image<br><br>The image depicts a map of the world focused on GMT, Greenwich Mean Time. The relevant information is shown in a summary:<br><br>Diagram 5 text<br><br>An ACL statement captures the number of matches and displays them at the end of each statement matched.<br>Logging gives additional details on packets permitted or denied. To activate logging add the log option to the end of each ACL statement.<br>Add the deny IP any any log to monitor the number of packets that are not matched by previous ACL statements.<br>The process if logging events, places an additional load on the router.<br>The log contents can be sent to an external syslog server.<br>Always set the service timestamp for logging and be sure the router date and time are set correctly, so that Log files display the proper stamp.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
