<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 19:09:57">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.1.4 - Troubleshooting Process]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the O S I Model and examples of common problems that can exist at each layer.<br> <br>O S I Model<br><br>Application Layer, Layer 7.<br>Associated with specific services such as FTP and DNS. <br>If resources are unreachable or unusable, while the Physical, Data Link, Network, and Transport Layers are functional, the problem is associated with this layer. <br><br>Presentation Layer, Layer 6.<br>Responsible for data representation. <br>Includes compression and encryption. <br>If data is being reliably transmitted across the network but is unreadable on the receiving end, suspect the Presentation Layer. <br>Verify that any encryption keys match and are properly configured. <br><br>Session Layer, Layer 5.<br>Responsible for establishing, maintaining, and terminating end-to-end communication sessions between applications. <br>Related to synchronization and flow control. <br>An application server failing during a communication session, could generate problems at the Session Layer. <br><br>Transport Layer, Layer 4.<br>Uses port numbers to identify the type of traffic being carried in the conversation. <br>Misconfigured ACL's are a common problem at the Transport Layer. <br><br>Network Layer, Layer 3.<br>Involved with logical addressing and best path determination. <br>Layer 3 addressing and routing problems are associated with the Network Layer. <br>The most common problems are improperly configured addresses and improper routing information. <br>Misconfigured ACL's are an issue at the Network Layer. <br><br>Data Link Layer, Layer 2.<br>Concerned mainly with the encapsulation of data. <br>Mismatched encapsulation is one of the most common issues at the Data Link Layer. <br>Includes improper conversion of Layer 2 encapsulation as the frames move across the network.<br>Improperly configured switch ports and Layer 2 addressing issues are also common. <br>Misconfigured V LAN's can generate problems at Layer 2, Data Link Layer. <br><br>Physical Layer, Layer 1.<br>Concerned with physical connectivity. <br>Common issues include damaged or improper cabling, physical damage to ports and power issues. <br>In wireless networks, antennas are physical layer devices as is the RF medium. <br>Any loss in signal strength or interference is considered a Layer 1, Physical Layer, problem. <br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
