<transcript lastedited="10.08.08 12:10:45">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.5.1 - Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Chapter 7 Quiz: Implementing Enterprise WAN Links<br><br>1.What three parameters are defined by WAN standards?  (Choose three.)<br>A.flow control<br>B.vendor<br>C.IP addressing<br>D.encapsulation<br>E.physical addressing<br>F.routing protocol<br><br>2.Which two layers of the O S I model describe WAN standards?  (Choose two.)<br>A.Session<br>B.Network<br>C.Physical <br>D.Transport<br>E.Data Link<br>F.Application<br><br>3.What are two characteristics of a CSU/DSU?  (Choose two.)<br>A.used for digital transmission<br>B.used for wireless transmission<br>C.installed at central office <br>D.often integrated into router's interface card<br>E.part of an integrated services router<br><br>4. Match the WAN connection term to the correct definition.<br><br>WAN Connection Terms<br>packet Switching<br>circuit Switching<br>cell switching<br>SVC<br>PVC<br><br>Definitions<br>virtual circuit that is dynamically established between two points when a router requests a transmission.<br>establishes a connection between end nodes before forwarding data and ensures dedicated bandwidth through the length of transmission<br>virtual circuit that provides a permanent path to forward data between two points<br>packets from multiple organizations are switched over the same links<br><br>5.What two statements describe the Cisco implementation of High-Level Data Link Control protocol?  (Choose two.)<br>A.is a data link layer protocol<br>B.provides retransmission and windowing<br>C.supports multiple protocols on a single link<br>D.uses the same frame format as standard HDLC<br>E.is the default encapsulation on Cisco LAN interfaces<br><br>6.What two services allow the router to map data link layer addresses to network layer addresses in a Frame Relay network?  (Choose two.)<br>A.ARP<br>B.ICMP<br>C.Proxy ARP<br>D.Inverse ARP<br>E.LMI status messages<br><br>7.What is used to identify a destination for a frame in a Frame Relay network?<br>A.C I R<br>B.DLCI<br>C.FECN<br>D.BECN<br><br>8.Which three statements are true regarding LCP?  (Choose three.)<br>A.It is responsible for negotiating link establishment. <br>B.It negotiates options for Layer 3 protocols running over PPP.<br>C.It uses MD5 encryption while negotiating link establishment parameters.<br>D.It terminates the link upon user request or the expiration of an inactivity timer.<br>E.It can test the link to determine if link quality is sufficient to bring up the link.<br>F.It monitors the link for congestion and dynamically adjusts the acceptable window size.<br><br>9.To answer this question refer to the Network Topology and router output. Network Topology<br>Router RTR_A is linked to router RTR_B via a serial link.  The output from both routers appears as follows:<br><br>Router A<br>hostname RTR_A<br>!<br>enable gateway<br>username RTR_B password fortress<br>!<br>interface serial 0/0/0<br>IP address 10.10.10.1 255.255.255.252<br>encapsulation ppp<br>ppp authentication chap<br><br>Router B<br>hostname RTR_B<br>!<br>enable fortress<br>interface serial 0/0/0<br>IP address 10.10.10.2 255.255.255.252<br>encapsulation ppp<br>ppp authentication chap<br><br>Which command must be added to router RTR_B to allow router RTP_A to authenticate using CHAP?<br>A.RTR_B(config)# enable secret gateway<br>B.RTR_B(config)# enable secret fortress<br>C.RTR_B(config)# username RTR_B password fortress<br>D.RTR_B(config)# username RTR_A password fortress<br>E.RTR_B(config)# username RTR_B password gateway<br><br>10.What are two features of the CHAP protocol?  (Choose two.)<br>A.exchanges random challenge number during the session to verify identity<br>B.disconnects the PPP session if authentication fails<br>C.sends authentication password to verify identity<br>D.requires different passwords on each device<br>E.initiates a two-way handshake<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
