<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_activity">
<text><![CDATA[<B><font size = '+2'>Activity</font></B><BR/><BR/>Identify the command that can provide the information indicated.<BR/><BR/><B>Drag the command to the correct statement.</B>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition1">
<text><![CDATA[1.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You suspect there is a problem with the current router configuration and want to see the backup configuration to compare it.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition2">
<text><![CDATA[2.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You are on a call with Cisco tech support and you need to tell them the name of router IOS system image file. You also need to know the amount of RAM, NVRAM and flash in the router.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition3">
<text><![CDATA[3.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You are running the RIP routing protocol and need to know the timer settings, update intervals and what active interfaces and networks are currently being advertised.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition4">
<text><![CDATA[4.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>Your users cannot get to a particular network. You need to know if the router has a route to that network and how it was learned.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition5">
<text><![CDATA[5.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You suspect there is a problem with a serial interface on the router. You want to see the bandwidth, encapsulation and I/O statistics.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition6">
<text><![CDATA[6.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You need to get a quick list of interfaces on the router with their IP addresses and status. You do not need to see the subnet mask.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition7">
<text><![CDATA[7.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You think the serial interface of the router at a remote site has in incorrectly configured IP address. You want to find out the model number of the router, the IOS version the router is running and the IP address of the remote interface.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition8">
<text><![CDATA[8.  <TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='17'>You have used telnet to connect to several different routers and wish to see what connections you have open.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_reset">
<text><![CDATA[Reset]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_definition">
<text><![CDATA[<B>Scenario / Information Needed</B>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_term">
<text><![CDATA[<B>Command to Use</B>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_completedTitle">
<text><![CDATA[<B>Correct</B>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_completed">
<text><![CDATA[You have identified the correct command. Click Next to continue.]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>