<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 09:09:24">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[1.1.2 - Traffic Flow in the Enterprise Network]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the Cisco Enterprise Architectures with three sub-blocks, labeled Enterprise Campus, Enterprise Edge, and Service Provider Edge. There are also two smaller blocks, labeled Enterprise Branch and EnterpriseTeleworker. The following information is included for each block:<br>Cisco Enterprise Architectures<br>Enterprise Campus<br>Building Access - Two Layer 3 switches<br>This Access Layer module contains Layer 2 or Layer 3 switches to provide the required port density. Implementation of V LAN's and trunk links to Building Distribution Layer occurs here. Redundancy to Building Distribution switches is important.<br>Building Distribution - Two Layer 2 / 3 distribution switches <br>This Distribution Layer module aggregates building access using Layer 3 devices. Routing, access control, and Q o S are performed at this layer. It is critical to provide redundancy in this area.<br>Campus Core - Two Layer 2 / 3 distribution switches, directly connected with multiple links.  <br>This Core Layer module provides high-speed interconnectivity between Distribution Layer modules, data center server farms, and the Enterprise Edge. Redundancy, fast convergence, and fault tolerance are the focus of the design in this area.<br>Server Farm and Data Center - Two servers and a single computer, Network Management takes place here. <br>This module provides high-speed connectivity and protection for servers. It is critical to provide security, redundancy, and fault tolerance in this area.<br>Management - This critical area monitors performance by monitoring device and network availability.<br>Enterprise Edge<br>E-Commerce - One departmental server and router<br>Internet Connectivity - One departmental server and router<br>WAN and Metro Ethernet Site-to-Site VPN - One router<br>Remote Access and VPN - One bridge and one switch<br>This module extends the enterprise services to remote sites and enables the enterprise to use Internet and partner resources. It provides Q o S, policy enforcement, service levels, and security.<br>Service Provider Edge<br>ISP A - Defined as multiple networking devices<br>ISP B - Defined as multiple networking devices<br>Frame Relay / A T M /Metro Ethernet - Defined as multiple networking devices<br>PSTN - Defined as multiple networking devices<br>Enterprise Connection<br>Enterprise Branch - One Layer 2 / 3 distribution switch<br>Enterprise Teleworker - One desktop computer<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
