<chapter type="" id="en0904000000">
<title><content-text>Distance Vector Routing Protocols</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en0904000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904000100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904000101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9143789873"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904000000/en0904000100/en0904000101/cm9143789873.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904000000/en0904000100/en0904000101/cm9143789873text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Introduction</b></p> <p>The dynamic routing chapters of this course focus on Interior Gateway Protocols (IGPs). As discussed in Chapter 3, IGPs are classified as either distance vector or link-state routing protocols.</p> <p>This chapter describes the characteristics, operations, and functionality of distance vector routing protocols. There are advantages and disadvantages to using any type of routing protocol. Therefore, the conditions influencing the operation of distance vector protocols and the pitfalls of distance vector protocol operation - along with remedies to overcome such pitfalls - are described. Understanding the operation of distance vector routing is critical to enabling, verifying, and troubleshooting these protocols.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904010000">
<title><content-text>Introduction to Distance Vector Routing Protocols</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904010100">
<title><content-text>Distance Vector Routing Protocols</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5211114105"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010100/en0904010101/cm5211114105.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010100/en0904010101/cm5211114105text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Dynamic routing protocols help the network administrator overcome the time-consuming and exacting process of configuring and maintaining static routes. For example, can you imagine maintaining the static routing configurations of the 28 routers shown in the figure? What happens when a link goes down? How do you ensure that <content-link target="cg2491080382" type="glossary">redundant paths</content-link> are available? Dynamic routing is the most common choice for large networks like the one shown. </p> <p>Distance vector routing protocols include RIP, IGRP, and EIGRP.</p> <p><b>RIP</b></p> <p>Routing Information Protocol (RIP) was originally specified in RFC 1058. It has the following key characteristics:</p> <ul><li> Hop count is used as the metric for path selection. </li> <li> If the hop count for a network is greater than 15, RIP cannot supply a route to that network.</li> <li> Routing updates are broadcast or multicast every 30 seconds, by default. </li></ul> <p><b>IGRP</b></p> <p>Interior Gateway Routing Protocol (IGRP) is a proprietary protocol developed by Cisco. IGRP has the following key design characteristics:</p> <ul><li> Bandwidth, delay, load and reliability are used to create a composite metric. </li> <li> Routing updates are broadcast every 90 seconds, by default. </li> <li> IGRP is the predecessor of EIGRP and is now obsolete.</li></ul> <p><b>EIGRP</b></p> <p>Enhanced IGRP (EIGRP) is a Cisco proprietary distance vector routing protocol. EIGRP has these key characteristics: </p> <ul><li> It can perform unequal cost load balancing. </li> <li> It uses <content-link target="cg5832746935" type="glossary">Diffusing Update Algorithm (DUAL)</content-link> to calculate the shortest path. </li> <li> There are no periodic updates as with RIP and IGRP. Routing updates are sent only when there is a change in the topology.</li></ul></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904010200">
<title><content-text>Distance Vector Technology</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6393632174"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010200/en0904010201/cm6393632174.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010200/en0904010201/cm6393632174text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Meaning of Distance Vector</b></p> <p>As the name implies, distance vector means that routes are advertised as vectors of distance and direction. Distance is defined in terms of a metric such as hop count and direction is simply the next-hop router or exit interface. </p> <p>A router using a distance vector routing protocol does not have the knowledge of the entire path to a destination network. Instead the router knows only:</p> <ul><li> The direction or interface in which packets should be forwarded and</li> <li> The distance or how far it is to the destination network</li></ul> <p>For example, in the figure, R1 knows that the distance to reach network 172.16.3.0/24 is 1 hop and that the direction is out the interface S0/0/0 toward R2.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010202">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm3456621042"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010200/en0904010202/cm3456621042.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010200/en0904010202/cm3456621042text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Operation of Distance Vector Routing Protocols</b></p> <p>Some distance vector routing protocols call for the router to periodically broadcast the entire routing table to each of its neighbors. This method is inefficient because the updates not only consume bandwidth but also consume router CPU resources to process the updates. </p> <p>Distance vector routing protocols share certain characteristics.</p> <p><b>Periodic Updates </b>are sent at regular intervals (30 seconds for RIP and 90 seconds for IGRP). Even if the topology has not changed in several days, periodic updates continue to be sent to all neighbors.</p> <p><b>Neighbors </b>are routers that share a link and are configured to use the same routing protocol. The router is only aware of the network addresses of its own interfaces and the remote network addresses it can reach through its neighbors. It has no broader knowledge of the network topology. <b>Routers using distance vector routing are not aware of the network topology.</b></p> <p><b>Broadcast Updates </b>are sent to 255.255.255.255. Neighboring routers that are configured with the same routing protocol will process the updates. All other devices will also process the update up to Layer 3 before discarding it. Some distance vector routing protocols use multicast addresses instead of broadcast addresses.</p> <p><b>Entire Routing Table Updates </b>are sent, with some exceptions to be discussed later, periodically to all neighbors. Neighbors receiving these updates must process the entire update to find pertinent information and discard the rest. Some distance vector routing protocols like EIGRP do not send periodic routing table updates.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904010300">
<title><content-text>Routing Protocol Algorithms</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6606786680"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010300/en0904010301/cm6606786680.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010300/en0904010301/cm6606786680text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>The Purpose of the Algorithm</b></p> <p>At the core of the distance vector protocol is the algorithm. The algorithm is used to calculate the best paths and then send that information to the neighbors.</p> <p>An algorithm is a procedure for accomplishing a certain task, starting at a given initial state and terminating in a defined end state. Different routing protocols use different algorithms to install routes in the routing table, send updates to neighbors, and make path determination decisions.</p> <p>The algorithm used for the routing protocols defines the following processes:</p> <ul><li> Mechanism for sending and receiving routing information.</li> <li> Mechanism for calculating the best paths and installing routes in the routing table. </li> <li> Mechanism for detecting and reacting to topology changes.</li></ul> <p> </p> <p>In the animation, R1 and R2 are configured with a routing protocol. The algorithm sends and receives updates. Both R1 and R2 then glean new information from the update. In this case, each router learns about a new network. The algorithm on each router makes its calculations independently and updates the routing table with the new information. When the LAN on R2 goes down, the algorithm constructs a "triggered" update and sends it to R1. R1 then removes the network from the routing table. Triggered updates will be discusses later in this chapter.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904010400">
<title><content-text>Routing Protocol Characteristics</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5104895888"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010400/en0904010401/cm5104895888.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010400/en0904010401/cm5104895888text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Routing Protocols Characteristics</b></p> <p>Routing protocols can be compared based on the following characteristics:</p> <ul><li> <b>Time to Convergence</b> - Time to convergence defines how quickly the routers in the network topology share routing information and reach a state of consistent knowledge. The faster the convergence, the more preferable the protocol. Routing loops can occur when inconsistent routing tables are not updated due to slow convergence in a changing network.</li> <li> <b>Scalability</b> - Scalability defines how large a network can become based on the routing protocol that is deployed. The larger the network is, the more scalable the routing protocol needs to be.</li> <li> <b>Classless (Use of VLSM) or Classful</b> - Classless routing protocols include the subnet mask in the updates. This feature supports the use of <content-link target="cg6461978161" type="glossary">Variable Length Subnet Masking (VLSM)</content-link> and better route summarization. Classful routing protocols do not include the subnet mask and cannot support VLSM.</li> <li> <b>Resource Usage</b> - Resource usage includes the requirements of a routing protocol such as memory space, CPU utilization, and link bandwidth utilization. Higher resource requirements necessitate more powerful hardware to support the routing protocol operation in addition to the packet forwarding processes.</li> <li> <b>Implementation and Maintenance</b> - Implementation and maintenance describes the level of knowledge that is required for a network administrator to implement and maintain the network based on the routing protocol deployed.</li></ul> <p>The advantages and disadvantages of distance vector routing protocols are shown in the table.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904010402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4515860153"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010400/en0904010402/cm4515860153.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904010000/en0904010400/en0904010402/cm4515860153text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Routing Protocol Learning Check</b></p> <p>In the figure, all the routing protocols discussed in the course are compared based on these characteristics. Although IGRP is no longer supported by the IOS, it is shown here to compare it with the Enhanced version. Also, although the IS-IS routing protocol is covered in the CCNP courses, it is shown here because it is a commonly used interior gateway protocol.</p> <p>Study the figure, and then click the Reset button to empty the table. Drag and drop the appropriate characteristics to each routing protocol. Based on the information previously discussed, you should be able to identify the advantages and disadvantages of distance vector routing protocols.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904020000">
<title><content-text>Network Discovery</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904020100">
<title><content-text>Cold Start</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904020101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6311061526"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020100/en0904020101/cm6311061526.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020100/en0904020101/cm6311061526text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When a router <i>cold starts</i> or powers up, it knows nothing about the network topology. It does not even know that there are devices on the other end of its links. The only information that a router has is from its own saved configuration file stored in NVRAM. Once a router boots successfully, it applies the saved configuration. As described in Chapter 1 and Chapter 2, if the IP addressing is configured correctly, then the router will initially discover its own directly connected networks.</p> <p><b>Initial Network Discovery</b></p> <p>In the example in the figure, after a cold start and before the exchange of routing information, the routers initially discover their own directly connected networks and subnet masks. This information is added to their routing tables:</p> <p><b>R1</b></p> <ul><li> 10.1.0.0 available through interface FastEthernet 0/0 </li> <li> 10.2.0.0 available through interface Serial 0/0/0</li></ul> <p><b>R2</b></p> <ul><li> 10.2.0.0 available through interface Serial 0/0/0 </li> <li> 10.3.0.0 available through interface Serial 0/0/1</li></ul> <p><b>R3</b></p> <ul><li> 10.3.0.0 available through interface Serial 0/0/1 </li> <li> 10.4.0.0 available through interface FastEthernet 0/0</li></ul> <p><b>Play the animation to watch this initial discovery of connected networks for R1.</b> With this initial information, the routers start to exchange routing information.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904020200">
<title><content-text>Initial Exchange of Routing Information</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904020201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2898643623"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020200/en0904020201/cm2898643623.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020200/en0904020201/cm2898643623text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>If a routing protocol is configured, the routers begin exchanging routing updates. Initially, these updates only include information about their directly connected networks. Upon receiving an update, the router checks it for new information. Any routes that are not currently in its routing table are added.</p> <p><b>Initial Exchange</b></p> <p>Play the animation to see R1, R2, and R3 start the initial exchange. All three routers send their routing tables to their neighbors, which at this point only contains the directly connected networks. Each router processes updates in the following manner:</p> <p><b>R1</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about network 10.1.0.0 out the Serial0/0/0 interface</li> <li> Sends an update about network 10.2.0.0 out the FastEthernet0/0 interface</li> <li> Receives update from R2 about network 10.3.0.0 with a metric of 1</li> <li> Stores network 10.3.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 1</li></ul> <p><b>R2</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about network 10.3.0.0 out the Serial 0/0/0 interface</li> <li> Sends an update about network 10.2.0.0 out the Serial 0/0/1 interface</li> <li> Receives an update from R1 about network 10.1.0.0 with a metric of 1</li> <li> Stores network 10.1.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 1</li> <li> Receives an update from R3 about network 10.4.0.0 with a metric of 1</li> <li> Stores network 10.4.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 1</li></ul> <p><b>R3</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about network 10.4.0.0 out the Serial 0/0/1 interface</li> <li> Sends an update about network 10.3.0.0 out the FastEthernet0/0</li> <li> Receives an update from R2 about network 10.2.0.0 with a metric of 1</li> <li> Stores network 10.2.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 1</li></ul> <p>After this first round of update exchanges, each router knows about the connected networks of their directly connected neighbors. However, did you notice that R1 does not yet know about 10.4.0.0 and that R3 does not yet know about 10.1.0.0? Full knowledge and a converged network will not take place until there is another exchange of routing information.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904020300">
<title><content-text>Exchange of Routing Information</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904020301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2009435717"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020300/en0904020301/cm2009435717.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020300/en0904020301/cm2009435717text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>At this point the routers have knowledge about their own directly connected networks and about the connected networks of their immediate neighbors. Continuing the journey toward convergence, the routers exchange the next round of periodic updates. Each router again checks the updates for new information.</p> <p><b>Next Update</b></p> <p>Play the animation to see R1, R2, and R3 send the latest routing table to their neighbors. Each router processes updates in the following manner:</p> <p><b>R1</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about network 10.1.0.0 out the Serial 0/0/0 interface.</li> <li> Sends an update about networks 10.2.0.0 and 10.3.0.0 out the FastEthernet0/0 interface.</li> <li> Receives an update from R2 about network 10.4.0.0 with a metric of 2.</li> <li> Stores network 10.4.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 2.</li> <li> Same update from R2 contains information about network 10.3.0.0 with a metric of 1. There is no change; therefore, the routing information remains the same.</li></ul> <p><b>R2</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about networks 10.3.0.0 and 10.4.0.0 out of Serial 0/0/0 interface.</li> <li> Sends an update about networks 10.1.0.0 and 10.2.0.0 out of Serial 0/0/1 interface.</li> <li> Receives an update from R1 about network 10.1.0.0. There is no change; therefore, the routing information remains the same.</li> <li> Receives an update from R3 about network 10.4.0.0. There is no change; therefore, the routing information remains the same.</li></ul> <p><b>R3</b></p> <ul><li> Sends an update about network 10.4.0.0 out the Serial 0/0/1 interface.</li> <li> Sends an update about networks 10.2.0.0 and 10.3.0.0 out the FastEthernet0/0 interface.</li> <li> Receives an update from R2 about network 10.1.0.0 with a metric of 2.</li> <li> Stores network 10.1.0.0 in the routing table with a metric of 2.</li> <li> Same update from R2 contains information about network 10.2.0.0 with a metric of 1. There is no change; therefore, the routing information remains the same.</li></ul> <p><b>Note:</b> Distance vector routing protocols typically implement a technique known as <content-link target="cg3251675130" type="glossary">split horizon</content-link>. Split horizon prevents information from being sent out the same interface from which it was received. For example, R2 would not send an update out Serial 0/0/0 containing the network 10.1.0.0 because R2 learned about that network through Serial 0/0/0. This mechanism will be explained in more detail later in this chapter.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904020400">
<title><content-text>Convergence</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904020401">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4322105010"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020400/en0904020401/cm4322105010.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904020000/en0904020400/en0904020401/cm4322105010text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The amount of time it takes for a network to converge is directly proportional to the size of that network. In the animation, a branch router in Region 4 (B2-R4) is cold starting. The animation shows the propagation of new routing information as updates are sent between neighboring routers. It takes five rounds of periodic update intervals before most of the branch routers in Regions 1, 2, and 3 learn about the new routes advertised by B2-R4. Routing protocols are compared based on how fast they can propagate this information - their speed to convergence.</p> <p>The speed of achieving convergence consists of:</p> <ul><li> How quickly the routers propagate a change in the topology in a routing update to its neighbors. </li> <li> The speed of calculating best path routes using the new routing information collected.</li></ul> <p>A network is not completely operable until it has converged, therefore, network administrators prefer routing protocols with shorter convergence times.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904030000">
<title><content-text>Routing Table Maintenance</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904030100">
<title><content-text>Periodic Updates: RIPv1 and IGRP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904030101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4501148513"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030100/en0904030101/cm4501148513.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030100/en0904030101/cm4501148513text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Maintaining the Routing Table</b></p> <p>Many distance vector protocols employ periodic updates to exchange routing information with their neighbors and to maintain up-to-date routing information in the routing table. RIP and IGRP are examples of two such protocols. </p> <p>In the animation, the routers are periodically sending the routing table to neighbors. The term <i>periodic updates</i> refers to the fact that a router sends the complete routing table to its neighbors at a predefined interval. For RIP, these updates are sent every 30 seconds as a broadcast (255.255.255.255) whether or not there has been a topology change. This 30-second interval is a route update timer that also aids in tracking the age of routing information in the routing table. </p> <p>The age of routing information in a routing table is refreshed each time an update is received. This way information in the routing table can be maintained when there is a topology change. Changes may occur for several reasons, including:</p> <ul><li> Failure of a link</li> <li> Introduction of a new link</li> <li> Failure of a router</li> <li> Change of link parameters</li></ul></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904030102">
<content-media type="InteractiveGraphicHotspots" id="cm8821870465"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030100/en0904030102/cm8821870465.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030100/en0904030102/cm8821870465text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>RIP Timers</b></p> <p>In addition to the update timer, the IOS implements three additional timers for RIP:</p> <ul><li> Invalid</li> <li> Flush</li> <li> Holddown</li></ul> <p><b>Invalid Timer.</b> If an update has not been received to refresh an existing route after 180 seconds (the default), the route is marked as invalid by setting the metric to 16. The route is retained in the routing table until the flush timer expires.</p> <p><b>Flush Timer. </b>By default, the flush timer is set for 240 seconds, which is 60 seconds longer than the invalid timer. When the flush timer expires, the route is removed from the routing table.</p> <p><b>Holddown Timer.</b> This timer stabilizes routing information and helps prevent routing loops during periods when the topology is converging on new information. Once a route is marked as unreachable, it must stay in holddown long enough for all routers in the topology to learn about the unreachable network. By default, the holddown timer is set for 180 seconds. The holddown timer is discussed in more detail later in this chapter.</p> <p><b>Click <span class="cmd">show ip route </span>in the figure.</b></p> <p>The timer values can be verified with two commands: <span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span> and <span class="cmd"><b>show ip protocols</b></span>. Notice in the output from <span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span> that each route learned through RIP shows the elapsed time since the last update, expressed in seconds. </p> <p><b>Click <span class="cmd">show ip protocols </span>in the figure.</b></p> <p>This information is also repeated in the <span class="cmd">show ip protocols</span> output under the heading <span class="cmd">Last Update</span>. The <span class="cmd"><b>show ip protocols</b></span> command details when this router, R1, is due to send out its next round of updates. It also lists the invalid, holddown, and flush timer default values.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904030200">
<title><content-text>Bounded Updates: EIGRP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904030201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm2852931343"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030200/en0904030201/cm2852931343.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030200/en0904030201/cm2852931343text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Unlike other distance vector routing protocols, EIGRP does not send periodic updates. Instead, EIGRP sends <content-link target="cg4471473624" type="glossary">bounded updates</content-link> about a route when a path changes or the metric for that route changes. When a new route becomes available or when a route needs to be removed, EIGRP sends an update only about that network instead of the entire table. This information is sent only to those routers that need it.</p> <p>EIGRP uses updates that are:</p> <ul><li> Non-periodic because they are not sent out on a regular basis.</li> <li> Partial updates sent only when there is a change in topology that influences routing information. </li> <li> Bounded, meaning the propagation of partial updates are automatically bounded so that only those routers that need the information are updated.</li></ul> <p><b>Note: </b>More details on how EIGRP operates will be presented in Chapter 9.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904030300">
<title><content-text>Triggered Updates</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904030301">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7549282981"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030300/en0904030301/cm7549282981.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030300/en0904030301/cm7549282981text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To speed up the convergence when there is a topology change, RIP uses triggered updates. A triggered update is a routing table update that is sent immediately in response to a routing change. Triggered updates do not wait for update timers to expire. The detecting router immediately sends an update message to adjacent routers. The receiving routers, in turn, generate triggered updates that notify their neighbors of the change. </p> <p>Triggered updates are sent when one of the following occurs:</p> <ul><li> An interface changes state (up or down)</li> <li> A route has entered (or exited) the "unreachable" state</li> <li> A route is installed in the routing table</li></ul> <p>Using only triggered updates would be sufficient if there were a guarantee that the wave of updates would reach every appropriate router immediately. However, there are two problems with triggered updates:</p> <ul><li> Packets containing the update message can be dropped or corrupted by some link in the network.</li> <li> The triggered updates do not happen instantaneously. It is possible that a router that has not yet received the triggered update will issue a regular update at just the wrong time, causing the bad route to be reinserted in a neighbor that had already received the triggered update.</li></ul> <p><b>Play the animation to see how a network topology change is propagated through the network.</b> When network 10.4.0.0 becomes unavailable and router 3 becomes aware of that, it sends out the information to its neighbors. The information is then propagated through the network.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904030400">
<title><content-text>Random Jitter</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904030401">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7343288441"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030400/en0904030401/cm7343288441.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904030000/en0904030400/en0904030401/cm7343288441text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Issues with Synchronized Updates</b></p> <p>When multiple routers transmit routing updates at the same time on multi-access LAN segments (as shown in the animation), the update packets can collide and cause delays or consume too much bandwidth. </p> <p><b>Note</b>: Collisions are only an issue with hubs and not with switches.</p> <p>Sending updates at the same time is known as the synchronization of updates. Synchronization can become a problem with distance vector routing protocols due to their usage of periodic updates. As more routers' timers become synchronized, more collisions of updates and more delays occur in the network. Initially, the updates of routers will not be synchronized. But over time, the timers across a network will become globally synchronized.</p> <p><b>The Solution</b></p> <p>To prevent the synchronization of updates between routers, the Cisco IOS uses a random variable, called RIP_JITTER, which subtracts a variable amount of time to the update interval for each router in the network. This random jitter, or variable amount of time, ranges from 0% to 15% of the specified update interval. In this way, the update interval varies randomly in a range from 25 to 30 seconds for the default 30-second interval.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904040000">
<title><content-text>Routing Loops</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904040100">
<title><content-text>Definition and Implications</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040101">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm7226242261"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040100/en0904040101/cm7226242261.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040100/en0904040101/cm7226242261text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>What is a Routing Loop?</b></p> <p>A routing loop is a condition in which a packet is continuously transmitted within a series of routers without ever reaching its intended destination network. A routing loop can occur when two or more routers have routing information that incorrectly indicates that a valid path to an unreachable destination exists.</p> <p>The loop may be a result of:</p> <p> </p> <ul><li> Incorrectly configured static routes</li> <li> Incorrectly configured route <content-link target="cg6329240526" type="glossary">redistribution</content-link> (redistribution is a process of handing the routing information from one routing protocol to another routing protocol and is discussed in CCNP-level courses)</li> <li> Inconsistent routing tables not being updated due to slow convergence in a changing network</li> <li> Incorrectly configured or installed discard routes </li></ul> <p>Distance vector routing protocols are simple in their operations. Their simplicity results in protocol drawbacks like routing loops. Routing loops are less of a problem with link-state routing protocols but can occur under certain circumstances.</p> <p><b>Note: </b>The IP protocol has its own mechanism to prevent the possibility of a packet traversing the network endlessly. IP has a Time-to-Live (TTL) field and its value is decremented by 1 at each router. If the TTL is zero, the router drops the packet.</p> <p><b>What are the Implications of Routing Loops?</b></p> <p>A routing loop can have a devastating effect on a network, resulting in degraded network performance or even a network downtime. </p> <p>A routing loop can create the following conditions:</p> <p> </p> <ul><li> Link bandwidth will be used for traffic looping back and forth between the routers in a loop.</li> <li> A router's CPU will be strained due to looping packets.</li> <li> A router's CPU will be burdened with useless packet forwarding that will negatively impact the convergence of the network.</li> <li> Routing updates may get lost or not be processed in a timely manner. These conditions would introduce additional routing loops, making the situation even worse.</li> <li> Packets may get lost in "black holes."</li></ul> <p>Play the animation to view a possible routing loop scenario in which mechanisms to prevent such loops do not exist.</p> <p>As you can see, routing loops eat up bandwidth and also router resources, resulting in a slow or even unresponsive network.</p> <p>There are a number of mechanisms available to eliminate routing loops, primarily with distance vector routing protocols. These mechanisms include: </p> <ul><li> Defining a maximum metric to prevent <content-link target="cg9223787049" type="glossary">count to infinity</content-link></li> <li> Holddown timers</li> <li> Split horizon</li> <li> <content-link target="cg5926288786" type="glossary">Route poisoning</content-link> or <content-link target="cg8124883934" type="glossary">poison reverse</content-link></li> <li> Triggered updates</li></ul> <p>Triggered updates were discussed in the previous section. The other loop avoidance mechanisms are discussed later in this chapter.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040102">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm1797405272"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040100/en0904040102/cm1797405272/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040100/en0904040102/cm1797405272/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Use the Packet Tracer Activity to experience how a routing loop might occur with misconfigured static routes.</p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon for more details.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040200">
<title><content-text>Problem: Count to Infinity</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040201">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4594421111"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040200/en0904040201/cm4594421111.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040200/en0904040201/cm4594421111text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Count to infinity is a condition that exists when inaccurate routing updates increase the metric value to "infinity" for a network that is no longer reachable.</b> The animation shows what happens to the routing tables when all three routers continue to send inaccurate updates to each other.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040300">
<title><content-text>Setting a Maximum</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4704444237"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040300/en0904040301/cm4704444237.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040300/en0904040301/cm4704444237text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>To eventually stop the incrementing of the metric, <b>"infinity" is defined by setting a maximum metric value</b>. For example, RIP defines infinity as 16 hops - an "unreachable" metric. Once the routers "count to infinity," they mark the route as unreachable.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040400">
<title><content-text>Preventing Routing Loops with Holddown Timers</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040401">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4646952885"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040400/en0904040401/cm4646952885.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040400/en0904040401/cm4646952885text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Earlier you learned that distance vector protocols employ triggered updates to speed up the convergence process. Remember that in addition to triggered updates, routers using distance vector routing protocols also send periodic updates. Let's imagine that a particular network is unstable. The interface resets as <b>up</b>, then <b>down</b>, then <b>up</b> again in rapid succession. The route is flapping. Using triggered updates, the routers might react too quickly and unknowingly create a routing loop. A routing loop could also be created by a periodic update that is sent by the routers during the instability. Holddown timers prevent routing loops from being created by these conditions. Holddown timers also help prevent the count to infinity condition.</p> <p><b>Holddown timers are used to prevent regular update messages from inappropriately reinstating a route that may have gone bad.</b> Holddown timers instruct routers to hold any changes that might affect routes for a specified period of time. If a route is identified as <b>down</b> or possibly down, any other information for that route containing the same status, or worse, is ignored for a predetermined amount of time (the holddown period). This means that routers will leave a route marked as <i>unreachable</i> in that state for a period of time that is long enough for updates to propagate the routing tables with the most current information.</p> <p><b>Holddown timers work in the following way:</b></p> <p>1. A router receives an update from a neighbor indicating that a network that previously was accessible is now no longer accessible.</p> <p>2. The router marks the network as possibly down and starts the holddown timer.</p> <p>3. If an update with a better metric for that network is received from any neighboring router during the holddown period, the network is reinstated and the holddown timer is removed.</p> <p>4. If an update from any other neighbor is received during the holddown period with the same or worse metric for that network, that update is ignored. Thus, more time is allowed for the information about the change to be propagated.</p> <p>5. Routers still forward packets to destination networks that are marked as possibly down. This allows the router to overcome any issues associated with intermittent connectivity. If the destination network truly is unavailable and the packets are forwarded, black hole routing is created and lasts until the holddown timer expires. </p> <p><b>Play the animation to see an example of the holddown process.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040500">
<title><content-text>Split Horizon Rule</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040501">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6472667750"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040500/en0904040501/cm6472667750.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040500/en0904040501/cm6472667750text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Another method used to prevent routing loops caused by slow convergence of a distance vector routing protocol is split horizon. <b>The split horizon rule says that a router should not advertise a network through the interface from which the update came.</b> </p> <p>Applying split horizon to the previous example of route 10.4.0.0 produces the following actions:</p> <ul><li> R3 advertises the 10.4.0.0 network to R2.</li> <li> R2 receives the information and updates its routing table.</li> <li> R2 then advertises the 10.4.0.0 network to R1 out S0/0/0. R2 does not advertise 10.4.0.0 to R3 out S0/0/1, because the route originated from that interface.</li> <li> R1 receives the information and updates its routing table.</li> <li> Because of split horizon, R1 also does not advertise the information about network 10.4.0.0 back to R2.</li></ul> <p>Complete routing updates are exchanged, with the exception of routes that violate the split horizon rule. The results look like this:</p> <ul><li> R2 advertises networks 10.3.0.0 and 10.4.0.0 to R1.</li> <li> R2 advertises networks 10.1.0.0 and 10.2.0.0 to R3.</li> <li> R1 advertises network 10.1.0.0 to R2.</li> <li> R3 advertises network 10.4.0.0 to R2.</li></ul> <p><b>Play the animation to see this process.</b></p> <p>Notice that R2 sends different routing updates to R1 and R3.</p> <p><b>Note:</b> Split horizon can be disabled by an administrator. Under certain conditions, this has to be done to achieve the proper routing. These conditions are discussed in later courses.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040600">
<title><content-text>Split Horizon with Poison Reverse or Route Poisoning</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040601">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm4645000737"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040600/en0904040601/cm4645000737.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040600/en0904040601/cm4645000737text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Route Poisoning </b></p> <p>Route poisoning is yet another method employed by distance vector routing protocols to prevent routing loops. <b>Route poisoning is used to mark the route as unreachable in a routing update that is sent to other routers. </b>Unreachable is interpreted as a metric that is set to the maximum. For RIP, a poisoned route has a metric of 16.</p> <p><b>Play the animation to see route poisoning in effect. </b></p> <p> </p> <p>The following process occurs:</p> <ul><li> Network 10.4.0.0 becomes unavailable due to a link failure. </li> <li> R3 poisons the metric with a value of 16 and then sends out a <content-link target="cg7301905064" type="glossary">triggered update</content-link> stating that 10.4.0.0 is unavailable.</li> <li> R2 processes that update. Because the metric is 16, R2 invalidates the routing entry in its routing table. </li> <li> R2 then sends the poison update to R1, indicating that route is unavailable, again by setting the metric value to 16. </li> <li> R1 processes the update and invalidates the routing entry for 10.4.0.0 in its routing table.</li></ul> <p>Route poisoning speeds up the convergence process as the information about 10.4.0.0 spreads through the network more quickly than waiting for the hop count to reach "infinity".</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040602">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm5691241443"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040600/en0904040602/cm5691241443.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040600/en0904040602/cm5691241443text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Split Horizon with Poison Reverse</b></p> <p>Poison reverse can be combined with the split horizon technique. The method is called split horizon with poison reverse. <b>The rule for split horizon with poison reverse states when sending updates out a specific interface, designate any networks that were learned on that interface as unreachable.</b></p> <p>The concept of split horizon with poison reverse is that explicitly telling a router to ignore a route is better than not telling it about the route in the first place.</p> <p><b>Play the animation to see an example of the split horizon with poison reverse in effect.</b></p> <p>The following process occurs:</p> <ul><li> Network 10.4.0.0 becomes unavailable due to a link failure. </li> <li> R3 poisons the metric with a value of 16 and then sends out a triggered update stating that 10.4.0.0 is unavailable. </li> <li> R2 processes that update, invalidates the routing entry in its routing table, and immediately sends a poison reverse back to R3. </li></ul> <p>Poison reverse is a specific circumstance that overrides split horizon. It occurs to ensure that R3 is not susceptible to incorrect updates about network 10.4.0.0. </p> <p><b>Note</b>: Split horizon is enabled by default. However split horizon with poison reverse may not be the default on all IOS implementations.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en0904040700">
<title><content-text>IP and TTL</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904040701">
<content-media type="AnimationPartialScreen" id="cm6043053576"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040700/en0904040701/cm6043053576.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904040000/en0904040700/en0904040701/cm6043053576text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Time to Live (TTL) is an 8-bit field in the IP header that limits the number of hops a packet can traverse through the network before it is discarded. </b>The purpose of the TTL field is to avoid a situation in which an undeliverable packet keeps circulating on the network endlessly. With TTL, the 8-bit field is set with a value by the source device of the packet. The TTL is decreased by one by every router on the route to its destination. If the TTL field reaches zero before the packet arrives at its destination, the packet is discarded and the router sends an Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP) error message back to the source of the IP packet. </p> <p>The animation shows that even in the case of a routing loop packets will not loop endlessly in the network. Eventually the TTL value will be decreased to 0 and the packet will be discarded by the router.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904050000">
<title><content-text>Distance Vector Routing Protocols today</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904050100">
<title><content-text>RIP and EIGRP</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904050101">
<content-media type="ActivityDnDCheckReset" id="cm2106242849"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904050000/en0904050100/en0904050101/cm2106242849.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904050000/en0904050100/en0904050101/cm2106242849text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>For distance vector routing protocols, there really are only two choices: RIP or EIGRP. The decision about which routing protocol to use in a given situation is influenced by a number of factors including: </p> <ul><li> Size of the network</li> <li> Compatibility between models of routers</li> <li> Administrative knowledge required</li></ul> <p><b>RIP</b></p> <p>Over the years, RIP has evolved from a classful routing protocol (RIPv1) to a classless routing protocol (RIPv2). RIPv2 is a standardized routing protocol that works in a mixed vendor router environment. Routers made by different companies can communicate using RIP. It is one of the easiest routing protocols to configure, making it a good choice for small networks. However, RIPv2 still has limitations. Both RIPv1 and RIPv2 have a route metric that is based only on hop count and which is limited to 15 hops.</p> <p>Features of RIP:</p> <ul><li> Supports split horizon and split horizon with poison reverse to prevent loops.</li> <li> Is capable of load balancing up to six equal cost paths . The default is four equal cost paths.</li></ul> <p>RIPv2 introduced the following improvements to RIPv1:</p> <ul><li> Includes the subnet mask in the routing updates, making it a classless routing protocol.</li> <li> Has authentication mechanism to secure routing table updates.</li> <li> Supports variable length subnet mask (VLSM).</li> <li> Uses multicast addresses instead of broadcast.</li> <li> Supports manual route summarization.</li></ul> <p><b>EIGRP</b></p> <p>Enhanced IGRP (EIGRP) was developed from IGRP, another distance vector protocol. EIGRP is a classless, distance vector routing protocol with features found in link-state routing protocols. However, unlike RIP or OSPF, EIGRP is a proprietary protocol developed by Cisco and only runs on Cisco routers.</p> <p>EIGRP features include:</p> <ul><li> Triggered updates (EIGRP has no periodic updates).</li> <li> Use of a <content-link target="cg4943667766" type="glossary">topology table</content-link> to maintain all the routes received from neighbors (not only the best paths).</li> <li> Establishment of adjacencies with neighboring routers using the EIGRP hello protocol.</li> <li> Support for VLSM and manual route summarization. These allow EIGRP to create hierarchically structured large networks.</li></ul> <p>Advantages of EIGRP:</p> <ul><li> Although routes are propagated in a distance vector manner, the metric is based on minimum bandwidth and cumulative delay of the path rather than hop count.</li> <li> Fast convergence due to Diffusing Update Algorithm (DUAL) route calculation. DUAL allows the insertion of backup routes into the EIGRP topology table, which are used in case the primary route fails. Because it is a local procedure, the switchover to the backup route is immediate and does not involve the action in any other routers.</li> <li> Bounded updates mean that EIGRP uses less bandwidth, especially in large networks with many routes. </li> <li> EIGRP supports multiple Network layer protocols through Protocol Dependent Modules, which include support for IP, IPX, and AppleTalk.</li></ul></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en0904060000">
<title><content-text>Lab Activities</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904060100">
<title><content-text>Lab Activities</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904060101">
<content-media type="ActivityLab" id="cm5872906315"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904060000/en0904060100/en0904060101/cm5872906315/" mime="application/pdf" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0904000000/en0904060000/en0904060100/en0904060101/cm5872906315/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In this lab activity, you recreate a network based only on the outputs from the <span class="cmd"><b>show ip route</b></span> command. Then, to verify your answer you configure the routers and check the actual routing table to the routing table shown in the lab documentation.</p><p><b>Click on the lab icon for more details.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en0904070000">
<title><content-text>Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904070100">
<title><content-text>Summary and Review</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904070101">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm4424452996"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070101/cm4424452996.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070101/cm4424452996text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Summary</b></p> <p>One way of classifying routing protocols is by the type of algorithm they use to determine the best path to a destination network. Routing protocols can be classified as distance vector, link state, or path vector. Distance vector means that routes are advertised as vectors of distance and direction. Distance is defined in terms of a metric such as hop count and direction is simply the next-hop router or exit interface. </p> <p>Distance vector routing protocols include:</p> <ul><li> RIPv1</li> <li> RIPv2</li> <li> IGRP</li> <li> EIGRP</li> </ul> <p>Routers that use distance vector routing protocols determine best path to remote networks based on the information they learn from their neighbors. If Router X learns of two paths to the same network, one through Router Y at 7 hops, and another route through Router Z at 10 hops, the router will choose the shorter path using Router Y as the next-hop router. Router X has no knowledge of what the network looks like beyond Routers Y and Z, and can only make its best path decision based on the information sent to it by these two routers. Distance vector routing protocols do not have a map of the topology as do link state routing protocols.</p> <p>Network discovery is an important process of any routing protocol. Some distance vector routing protocols such as RIP go through a step-by-step process of learning and sharing routing information with their neighbors. As routes are learned from one neighbor, that information is passed on to other neighbors with an increase in the routing metric.</p> <p>Routing protocols also need to maintain their routing tables to keep them current and accurate. RIP exchanges routing table information with its neighbors every 30 seconds. EIGRP, another distance vector routing protocol, does not send these periodic updates and only sends a "bounded" update when there is a change in the topology and only to those routers that need that information. EIGRP is discussed in a later chapter.</p> <p>RIP also uses timers to determine when a neighboring router is no longer available, or when some of the routers may not have current routing information. This is typically because the network has not yet converged due to a recent change in the topology. Distance vector routing protocols also use triggered updates to help speed up convergence time.</p> <p>One disadvantage of distance vector routing protocols is the potential for routing loops. Routing loops can occur when the network is in an unconverged state. Distance vector routing protocols use holddown timers to prevent the router from using another route to a recently down network until all of the routers have had enough time to learn about this change in the topology. </p> <p>Split horizon and split horizon with poison reverse are also used by routers to help prevent routing loops. The split horizon rule states that a router should never advertise a route through the interface from which it learned that route. Split horizon with poison reverse means that it is better to explicitly state that this router does not have a route to this network by poisoning the route with a metric stating that the route is unreachable.</p> <p>Distance vector routing protocols are sometime referred to as "routing by rumor", although this can be somewhat of a misnomer. Distance vector routing protocols are very popular with many network administrators as they are typically easily understood and simple to implement. This does not necessarily mean link-state routing protocols are any more complicated or difficult to configure. Unfortunately, link-state routing protocols have received this somewhat unwarranted reputation. We will learn in later chapters that link-state routing protocols are as easy to understand and configure as distance vector routing protocols.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0904070102">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm9797318836"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070102/cm9797318836.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070102/cm9797318836text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904070103">
<content-media type="ActivityPKA" id="cm9101922813"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070103/cm9101922813/" mime="application/packettracer" scale="true" type="directory" width="0" height="0" external="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070103/cm9101922813/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Packet Tracer Skills Integration Challenge Activity for this chapter is very similar to the activity you completed at the end of Chapter 3. The scenario is slightly different, allowing you to better practice your skills. In this activity, you build a network from the ground up. Starting with an addressing space and network requirements, you must implement a network design that satisfies the specifications. Then implement an effective static routing configuration.</p> <p><content-link target="E2_PTAct_4_7_1_Directions.pdf" type="internalfile">Packet Tracer Skills Integration Instructions (PDF)</content-link></p><p><b>Click the Packet Tracer icon for more details.</b></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en0904070104">
<content-media type="ChapterSummary" id="cm4803813685"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070104/cm4803813685.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en0904000000/en0904070000/en0904070100/en0904070104/cm4803813685text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>To Learn More</b></p> <p>Understanding the distance vector algorithm is not difficult. There are many book and online sources that show how algorithms such as the Bellman-Ford algorithm are used in networking. There are several web sites devoted to explaining how these algorithms work. Seek out some of the resources and familiarize yourself with how this algorithm works.</p> <p>Here are some suggested resources:</p> <ul><li> <i>Interconnections, Bridges, Routers, Switches, and Internetworking Protocols</i>, by Radia Perlman</li> <li> <i>Cisco IP Routing</i>, by Alex Zinin</li> <li> <i>Routing the Internet</i>, by Christian Huitema</li></ul></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterQuiz" id="en0904080000">
<title><content-text>Quiz</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en0904080100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Quiz</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en0904080101">
<content-media type="ChapterQuiz" id="cm6089441792"><title><content-text></content-text></title><media ref="en0904000000/en0904080000/en0904080100/en0904080101/cm6089441792/" mime="" scale="true" type="directory" width="100%" height="100%" external="en0904000000/en0904080000/en0904080100/en0904080101/cm6089441792/icontext.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
