<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 13:11:28">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.4  - Controlling Broadcast Domains with V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts controlling network broadcast domains with V LAN segmentation. The action of broadcast frames with and without V LAN segmentation is demonstrated.<br><br>Animation One: Network Broadcasts with No V LAN Segmentation.<br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S2 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S3 port F0/3 is connected to S1 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. <br><br>There are six PC's in total. PC1, PC2, and PC3 connect to switch S2 using ports F0/11, F0/18 and F0/6, respectively, using straight-through cables. PC4, PC5, and PC6 are connected to switch S3 using ports F0/11, F0/18, and F0/6, respectively, using straight-through cables.<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN<br>172.17.40.21/24<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN<br>172.17.40.24 /24<br><br>PC2:<br>Student V LAN<br>172.17.40.21 /24<br><br>PC5:<br>Student V LAN<br>172.17.40.25 /24<br><br>PC3:<br>Guest V LAN<br>172.17.40.23 /24<br><br>PC6:<br>Guest V LAN<br>172.17.40.25 /24<br><br>The animation shows a broadcast coming from PC1 to switch S2. Switch S2 sends the broadcast to other PC's on S2 as well as switches S1 and S3. Switch S3 sends the broadcast to all PC's connected to it.<br><br>Animation Two: Network Broadcasts with V LAN Segmentation.<br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S2 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S3 port F0/3 is connected to S1 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. <br><br>There are four PC's in total. PC1 and PC2 connect to switch S2 using ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables. PC4 and PC5 are connected to switch S3 using ports F0/11 and F0/18, respectively, using straight-through cables.<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.21 /24<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.24 /24<br><br>PC2:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.22 /24<br><br>PC5:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.25 /24<br><br>An arrow points to the links between S1 and S2 and to the links between S1 and S3 with the text: V LAN trunks configured to support V LAN 10, 20.<br><br>The animation shows a broadcast coming from PC1 in V LAN 10 to switch S2, and then to S1 and S3. The broadcast is only sent to other PC's (in this case PC4) in V LAN 10. PC's in V LAN 20 (PC2 and PC5) do not see the broadcast.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
