<transcript lastedited="10.15.08 09:10:35">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[6.4.1 Summary]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[Four Diagrams, Slider Graphic<br><br>Diagram 1, Image<br>The diagram depicts two technicians working on networking devices.<br><br>Diagram 1 text<br>This chapter discussed the client/server relationship for common network services, such as HTTP, FTP, DNS, DHCP, and email.<br><br>Servers are hosts that run software to enable them to provide services to other hosts over the network.<br>Application protocols determine how servers and clients interact and exchange information with each other.<br>Transport protocols, such as Transport Control Protocol (TCP) and User Datagram Protocol (UDP), define port numbers to manage the individual conversations between servers and clients.<br>Internet Protocol (IP) specifies how data is encapsulated into packets and the logical addressing.<br>Network access protocols, such as Ethernet, describe two primary functions: data link management and physical network transmissions.<br><br>Diagram 2, Image<br>The diagram depicts a server farm, with a router, switch, and the following types of servers: DNS, Telnet, email, DHCP, web, and FTP.<br><br>Diagram 2 text<br>Domain Name Server (DNS)<br>Service that provides the IP address of a website URL or domain name so a host can connect to it.<br>DNS names are registered and organized on the Internet within specific high level groups, or domains.<br>Some of the most common high level domains on the Internet are .com, .e d u, and .net.<br>Dynamic Host Configuration (DHCP) Server<br>Service that assigns an IP address, subnet mask, default gateway, and other information to a client.<br>File Transfer (FTP) Server<br>Service that allows for download and upload of files between a client and server.<br><br>Diagram 3, Image<br>The diagram depicts a Port Number table with the following fields: Destination Port Number, Abbreviation, and Definition.<br><br>Diagram 3 text<br>Email Server<br>Service that sends, receives, and stores mail in user mailboxes located on the server.<br>Uses Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) to send mail. Clients use Post Office Protocol (POP3), or Internet Mail Access Protocol (I MAP4) to retrieve mail.<br>Recipients are specified using the user@ x y z.com format.<br>Web Server<br>Service that is used to transfer information between Web clients and Web servers.<br>Most web pages are accessed using Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP), from servers using port 80.<br>HTTP is not a secure service. Requests for secure HTTP are sent to port 443. These requests require the use of https colon //.<br>TELNET<br>Service that allows administrators to login to a host from a remote location and control the host as though they were logged on locally.<br>Instant Messaging<br>IM client software is loaded on the host computers. Once IM clients authenticate with the server, they can send messages to other clients in real-time, or transfer video, music, and speech files.<br>IP Telephony<br>An Internet telephony client uses peer-to-peer technology similar to that used by instant messaging.<br>IP telephony makes use of Voice over IP (V o IP) technology, which uses IP packets to carry digitized voice as data.<br><br>Diagram 4, Image<br>The diagram depicts the TCP/IP protocol stack, with the following protocols:<br>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)<br>Transmission Control Protocol (TCP)<br>Internet Protocol (IP)<br>Ethernet Protocol <br><br>The diagram also depicts the O S I Reference Model, with the following layers:<br>Application Layer<br>Presentation Layer<br>Session Layer<br>Transport Layer<br>Network Layer<br>Data Link Layer<br>Physical Layer<br><br>Diagram 4 text<br><br>A protocol stack organizes the protocols as a layered hierarchy, with each higher level protocol depending on the services of the protocols shown in the lower levels.<br>The benefits to using a layered approach include the following:<br>Assists and simplifies protocol design.<br>Allows products from different vendors to work together.<br>Prevents technology or capability changes in one layer from affecting other layers above and below.<br>When sending messages, the protocol stack on a host operates from top to bottom. Each layer encapsulates information and passes it to the layer below. The process is reversed on the receiving host.<br>Two hierarchical network models are the O S I model (7 layers) and the TCP/IP model (4 layers).<br>The O S I model includes all functions, or tasks, associated with Internetwork communications, not just those related to the TCP/IP protocols.<br>The O S I model is considered the primary reference model for inter-computer communications.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
