<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 18:01:50">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[2.7.1 - Chapter Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[1.Refer to the following command and error message to answer the question:<br>R2#clock set 19:56:00  04  8<br>Note: A caret is under the number 8 in the above command and the following error message is displayed:<br>Percent sign: invalid input detected at caret marker.<br><br>What does the error message signify?<br>A.A parameter is missing.<br>B.The command was entered in the wrong C L I mode.<br>C.The data of one of the parameters is incorrect.<br>D.The command is ambiguous.<br><br>2.What is the effect of entering the banner login #Authorized Personnel Only!# command?<br>A.#Authorized Personnel Only!# appears after the user logs in.<br>B.Authorized Personnel Only! appears only when the user makes a Telnet connection.<br>C.#Authorized Personnel Only!# appears only when the user enters global configuration mode.<br>D.Authorized Personnel Only! appears before the username and password login prompts for any connection.<br><br>3.Match the command to the appropriate description.<br><br>Commands:<br>A. Switchport port-security violation protect.<br>B. Switchport port-security violation restrict.<br>C. Switchport port-security violation shutdown.<br>D. Switchport port-security mac-address sticky.<br>E. Switchport port-security maximum.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Frames with unknown source addresses are dropped and notification is sent.<br>Two. Frames with unknown source addresses are dropped and no notification is sent.<br>Three. Frames with unknown source address make the port err disabled and notification is sent.<br>Four. Defines the number of MAC addresses associated with a port.<br>Five. Allows dynamically learned MAC addresses to be stored in the running configuration.<br><br>4.Refer to the MAC address table described here to answer the question. <br>MAC Address Table:<br>Station MAC: 00-00-3D-1F-11-01, Interface: Three <br>Station MAC: 00-00-3D-1F-11-02, Interface: Four<br>Station MAC: 00-00-3D-1F-11-03, Interface: One<br><br>An Ethernet switch has developed the MAC address table described above. What action does the switch take when it receives the frame with the destination MAC address 00-00-3D-1F-11-03 and the source MAC address 00-00-3D-1F-11-01?<br>A.Forward the frame out all interfaces.<br>B.Forward the frame out all interfaces except Interface Three.<br>C.Discard the frame.<br>D.Forward the frame out Interface One.<br>E.Forward the frame out Interface Two.<br>F.Forward the frame out Interface Three.<br><br>5.Refer to the following command output to answer the question. <br> <br>Switch: show version<br>Note: Some output has been omitted.<br>Complied Wed 18-May-05 22:31<br>Running Standard Image<br>24 FastEthernet / i e e e 8 0 2 dot 3 interfaces<br>2 Gigabit Ethernet FastEthernet / i e e e 8 0 2 dot 3 interfaces<br>32K bytes of flash-simulated non-volatile configuration memory<br><br>What can be determined from the command output?<br>A.The system has 32 KB of NV RAM.<br>B.The switch has 24 physical ports.<br>C.The system was last restarted on May 18, 2005.<br>D.The Cisco I O S is a non-standard image.<br><br>6.What does pressing Ctrl P on the command line do?<br>A.Begins context checking.<br>B.Accesses symbolic translation.<br>C.Accesses the command history buffer.<br>D.Initiates command prompting.<br><br>7.What advantage does SSH offer over Telnet when remotely connecting to a device?<br>A.Encryption.<br>B.More connection lines.<br>C.Connection-oriented services.<br>D.Username and password authentication.<br><br>8.Refer to the following network topology diagram description to answer the question:<br>-PC A and PC B connect to Hub 1. Hub 1 connects to Switch 1. Switch 1 connects to Router 1. Router 1 connects to Router 2 with a WAN link.<br>-PC C and PC D connect to Switch 2. Switch 2 connects to Router 1. <br>-PC E and PC F connect to Switch 3. Switch 3 connects to Router 2. <br>-PC G and PC H connect to Switch 4. Switch 4 connects to Router 2.<br><br>How many collision and broadcast domains are presented in the network?<br>A.Eight collision domains and two broadcast domains.<br>B.Eight collision domains and three broadcast domains.<br>C.Eleven collision domains and four broadcast domains.<br>D.Thirteen collision domains and two broadcast domains.<br><br>9.Match the term to the appropriate description.<br>Terms:<br>A. MAC address flooding.<br>B. DHCP starvation.<br>C. CDP attacks.<br>D. Telnet attack.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Broadcasting requests for IP addresses with spoofed MAC addresses.<br>Two. Using proprietary Cisco protocols to gain information about a switch.<br>Three. The attacker fills the switch Content Addressable Memory (CAM) table with invalid MAC addresses.<br>Four. Using brute force password attacks to gain access to a switch.<br><br>10.Which three statements are true about the Carrier Sense Multiple Access with Collision Detection (CSMA/CD) technology? (Choose three.)<br>A.In an Ethernet LAN domain, each station continuously listens for traffic on the medium to determine when gaps between frame transmissions occur and then sends the frame.<br>B.In an Ethernet LAN domain, stations may begin transmitting any time they detect that the network is quiet (that is, there is no traffic). <br>C.In the CSMA/CD process, priorities are assigned to particular stations, and the station with the highest priority transmits the frame on the medium.<br>D.If a collision occurs in an Ethernet LAN domain, transmitting stations stop transmitting and wait a random length of time before attempting to retransmit the frame.<br>E.If a collision occurs in an Ethernet LAN domain, only the station with the highest priority continues to transmit and the rest of the stations wait a random length of time before attempting to retransmit the frame.<br>F.In an Ethernet LAN domain, all stations execute a backoff algorithm based on their assigned priorities before they transmit frames on the medium.<br><br>11.How does the Ethernet switch process the incoming traffic using port-based memory buffering?<br>A.The frames are stored in queues that are linked to specific incoming ports.<br>B.The frames are stored in queues that are linked to specific outgoing ports.<br>C.The frames are transmitted to the outgoing port immediately.<br>D.The frames are stored in queues that are linked to the common memory area.<br><br>12.What are two key features of an Ethernet switch with Layer 2 capabilities? (Choose two.)<br>A.Full-duplex operation.<br>B.Broadcast and multicast traffic management.<br>C.Security through access lists.<br>D.Layer 3 routing functions.<br>E.Filtering based on MAC address.<br>F.Network address translation (NAT).<br><br>13.The network administrator wants to configure an IP address on a Cisco switch. How does the network administrator assign the IP address?<br>A.In privileged EXEC mode.<br>B.On the switch interface FastEthernet0/0.<br>C.On the management V LAN.<br>D.On the physical interface connected to the router or next-hop device.<br><br>14.Why should a default gateway be assigned to a switch?<br>A.To have remote connectivity to the switch via such programs as Telnet and ping.<br>B.To send frames through the switch to the router.<br>C.To pass frames generated from workstations and destined for remote networks to a higher level.<br>D.To access other networks from the command prompt of the switch.<br><br>15.Which two tasks does auto-negotiation in an Ethernet network accomplish? (Choose two.)<br>A.Sets the link speed.<br>B.Sets the IP address.<br>C.Sets link duplex mode.<br>D.Sets MAC address assignments on the switch port.<br>E.Sets the ring speed.<br><br>16.What is the effect of entering the SW1 (config-i f)#duplex full command on a Fast Ethernet switch port?<br>A.The connected device communicates in two directions, but only one direction at a time. <br>B.The switch port returns to its default configuration.<br>C.If the connected device is also set for full duplex, it participates in collision-free communication.<br>D.The efficiency of this configuration is typically rated at 50 to 60 percent.<br>E.The connected device should be configured as half duplex.<br><br>17.Which term describes the time delay of a frame sent from a source device and received on a destination device?<br>A.Bandwidth.<br>B.Latency.<br>C.Attenuation.<br>D.Time-To-Live.<br>E.Frame checksum.<br><br>18.Match the command to the correct description. Not all commands have a description.<br><br>Commands:<br>A. Copy startup-config running-config.<br>B. Copy running-config tftp.<br>C. Copy tftp startup-config.<br>D. Copy tftp running-config.<br>E. Copy startup-config tftp.<br>F. Copy running-config startup-config.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Copy the current running configuration to a TFTP server.<br>Two. Save the current running configuration as the startup configuration.<br>Three. Restore a configuration from a TFTP server to the running configuration.<br>Four. Restore the startup configuration to the running system.<br><br>19.Match the command to the description as required to secure access to the console port on a switch. Not all commands are used.<br><br>Commands:<br>A. Enable.<br>B. Configure terminal.<br>C. Line v t y 0 4.<br>D. Line con 0.<br>E. Password Cisco.<br>F. Username admin password Cisco.<br>G. Login.<br><br>Descriptions:<br>One. Enter global configuration mode.<br>Two. Enter configuration mode for the console line.<br>Three. Set a password.<br>Four. Permit login.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
