<transcript lastedited="10.13.08 18:10:00">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.8.1 Quiz]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[12 Questions <br><br>1.The diagram depicts an IP telephone connected to a switch. Also connected to the switch are two computers, directly connected to one of the computers is a standalone printer.<br><br>Refer to the description above. What two types of devices are the printer and the IP phone? (Choose two.)<br><br>The IP phone is a peripheral.<br>The IP phone is a host.<br>The IP phone is a network device.<br>The printer is a peripheral.<br>The printer is a host.<br>The printer is a network device.<br><br><br>2. Determine if the characteristics listed are an advantage or disadvantage of a peer to peer network.<br><br>Advantages<br>Disadvantages<br><br>Provide minimal security.<br>No centralized administration.<br>Inexpensive.<br>Potential impact on performance.<br>Easy to set up.<br>No special hardware.<br><br>3.List whether the statements below are related to a Logical Topology Map or a Physical Topology Map. <br><br>Logical Topology Map<br>Physical Topology Map<br><br>Shows wiring installations.<br>Shows location of networking devices.<br>Shows host names and host addresses.<br>Shows group information and applications used.<br>Shows location of each host and how they connect to the network.<br>Shows location of broadcast and collision domains.<br><br>4. Match the situation with the correct type of message that would be used.<br><br>Unicast<br>Multicast<br>Broadcast<br><br>A host device sends a hello message to all computers on the network.<br>A host device sends an email to another host device.<br>A host device joins a group to receive video conferencing.<br>A host device requests a web page and displays the results.<br>A host device sends out an ARP request looking for the MAC address for a specific IP address.<br>A router forwards its routing table to a specific group of routers on the network.<br><br><br>5. Which two statements accurately describe a router ARP table and routing table? (Choose two)<br><br>The ARP table contains information about individual devices, not networks.<br>The ARP table contains information about networks, not individual devices.<br>The ARP table contains information about networks and individual devices.<br>The routing table contains information about individual devices, not networks.<br>The routing table contains information about networks, not individual devices.<br>The routing table contains information about networks and individual devices.<br><br>6.What process can a user perform on the host so that a folder on a remote server is treated as if it were a local resource?<br><br>mapping a drive<br>sharing a drive<br>enabling a remote user<br>setting share permissions<br><br>7.Determine if the tasks performed would be considered the role of a client, server, or both.  Match the task with the role of Client, Server or Both Client and Server.<br><br>Client<br>Server<br>Client and Server<br><br>Share files with another device.<br>Download a music file from a website.<br>Play a video game with a friend across a network.<br>Participate in a videoconference with another computer.<br>Connect to an e learning site to learn networking<br>Store e-mail and deliver it upon request.<br><br>8.The diagram depicts two switches named Switch A and Switch B directly connected to each other. H1 and H2 are directly connected to switch A and H3 and H4 are directly connected to switch B.<br><br>Refer to the description above. If H1 on Switch A needs to forward to H3 on Switch B, which MAC address is used as the destination MAC within the frame?<br><br>MAC address of H1<br>MAC address of Switch A<br>MAC address of Switch B<br>MAC address of H3<br><br>9.The diagram depicts two network segments, LAN A and LAN B, directly connect to Router1 via Switch1 and Switch2. Computer1 is located on Switch1 and Computer10 is located on Switch2.<br><br>Refer to the description above.  When Router1 receives a message with a source address of Computer1 on LAN A and a destination address of Computer10 on LAN B, what will be the action of Router 1?<br><br><br>The router checks its ARP table to determine where to forward the packet to reach Computer10.<br>The router checks it ARP table to determine the appropriate IP address of Computer10.<br>The router checks its routing table to determine where to forward the packet to reach Computer10.<br>The router checks its routing table to determine the appropriate MAC address of Computer10.<br><br>10.Which three pieces of information are included in a network physical map? (Choose three)<br><br>IP addressing scheme.<br>Computer naming scheme.<br>Location and length of cable runs.<br>Physical location of all networking devices.<br>Location and size of broadcast and collision domains.<br>Hardware configuration of end devices such as hosts and services.<br><br>11.When using Windows XP, which command shows information about the computer, including IP address, subnet mask, default gateway, and additional details about DHCP and DNS?<br><br>i p config<br>win i p cfg<br>i p config/all<br>win i p cfg/all<br><br>12.In what area of a network can traffic from other hosts cause a sending host to stop transmitting, then wait a random amount of time before resending a message?<br>access layer<br>broadcast domain<br>collision domain<br>distribution layer<br>peer to peer network<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
