<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[<b>Click each port type for more information.</b>]]></text></component><component id="ID_box01"><text><![CDATA[These connectors are commonly used for both the keyboard and the mouse. They have a very compact design and are keyed to allow the plugs to be inserted in the correct orientation only.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box02"><text><![CDATA[The Universal Serial Bus allows the connection of many different devices and supports hot swapping and PnP technology. Devices can be plugged into the USB port and are recognized and configured by the operating system. An increasing number of USB devices are becoming available. These devices now include; mice, keyboards, sound cards, speakers, NICs, modems and external storage devices.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box03"><text><![CDATA[Serial ports were originally designed as a twenty-five pin male connector (DB25) but only nine wires were actually used. The original DB25 connector took up quite a bit of space and has been widely replaced by a more compact nine pin connector (DB9). Both DB25 and DB9 connectors can be found on modern computers and are used to connect devices such as modems. They may also be used to connect a printer or mouse but this is becoming less common. This port can also be used to connect two computers to transfer data between them.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box04"><text><![CDATA[The parallel port was designed to connect a printer to the PC. It is a 25-pin connector but has a female gender. Parallel ports are also commonly used to connect printers, external tape drives and CD or DVD drives to the host computer. This port can also be used to connect two computers to transfer data between them.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box05"><text><![CDATA[The 15-pin video connector is standard on most personal computers. This is designed to connect to either VGA or super-VGA monitors. Most PCs use a DB15HD connector which has three rows of five pins.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box06"><text><![CDATA[The RJ-11 connector is the connector used by telephone companies in many areas of the world. This connector is usually found on a modem and is used to connect the computer to the telephone network.]]></text></component><component id="ID_box07"><text><![CDATA[The RJ-45 connector is the standard connector used for Ethernet networks. This connector is used to connect the computer into a Local Area Network (LAN) or to connect it to an external modem such as those provided by cable and DSL companies for high-speed Internet access.]]></text></component><component id="Box01title">	<text>PS/2</text></component><component id="PS/2">	<text>PS/2</text></component><component id="Box02title">	<text>USB</text></component><component id="USB">	<text>USB</text></component><component id="Box03title">	<text>Serial</text></component><component id="Serial">	<text>Serial</text></component><component id="Box04title">	<text>Parallel</text></component><component id="Parallel">	<text>Parallel</text></component><component id="Box05title">	<text>VGA</text></component><component id="VGA">	<text>VGA</text></component><component id="Box06title">	<text>RJ-11</text></component><component id="RJ-11">	<text>RJ-11</text></component><component id="Box07title">	<text>RJ-45</text></component><component id="RJ-45">	<text>RJ-45</text></component></textcomponents>