<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 11:09:38">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.1 - Switching and Network Segmentation]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts an activity in which you must determine how the switch forwards a frame based on the Source MAC and Destination MAC addresses, and information in the switch MAC table.<br><br>Help Popup<br>This activity quizzes you on your knowledge of how a frame is forwarded on a switch. <br><br>You are given the physical topology and the MAC address table of the switch. You are also given a frame that consists of a source and destination MAC address. The computer-generated activities will have a source and destination pair using one of the addresses shown on the topology.<br><br>One.Your goal is to determine how the switch will handle this frame given the MAC addresses table shown.<br>Two.You will select the port numbers to indicate where, if any, the switch will forward the frame.<br>Three.Then you will indicate how the switch will handle the frame. For example, flooded to all ports or dropped.<br><br>Additional Help:<br>FF is a broadcast MAC address and is forwarded to all ports, with the exception of the origin port.<br><br>A frame is flooded to all ports, except the origin, only if the switch does not have the destination MAC within the MAC table.<br>The switch will only add a new MAC address to the MAC table based on the source MAC address. If the source MAC address is already in the table, nothing is added or learned. If the source MAC address is not in the table, the address will be added.<br><br>A switch will drop a frame if the destination and source devices are both connected to the same port and the switch has the destination MAC address in the MAC table. In this activity, this occurs on the single port connected to the hub with two host devices.<br><br>The activity is dynamic and it is possible to create new practice problems. An example is presented below.<br><br>Determine how the switch forwards a frame based on the Source MAC and Destination MAC addresses and information in the switch MAC table. Answer the questions using the information provided below. <br><br>The switch is connected to four hosts. Host 0A is connected to port F A 1. Host 0B is connected to port F A 3. Host 0C is connected to port F A 5, and host 0D is connected to port F A 7. Port F A 9 is connected to a hub. The hub is connected to host 0E and host 0F.<br><br>Information about the frame:<br>Preamble: blank.<br>Destination MAC: 0D.<br>Source MAC: 0A.<br>Length: blank.<br>Encapsulate: blank.<br>End of frame: blank.<br><br>The MAC table for the switch is as follows:<br>F A 3 is connected to 0B.<br>F A 7 is connected to 0D.<br>F A 9 is connected to 0E.<br>All the other ports have blank entries.<br><br>One.Where will the switch forward the frame? (Choices: F A 1 to F A 12)<br>Two.When the switch forwards the frame, which of the following statements are true? <br><br>A. Switch adds the source MAC address to the MAC table.<br>B. Frame is a broadcast frame and will be forwarded to all ports.<br>C. Frame is a unicast frame and will be sent to specific ports only.<br>D. Frame is a unicast frame and will be flooded to all ports.<br>E. Frame is a unicast frame but it will be dropped at the switch.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
