<textcomponents>
<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Physical Security]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Secure Passwords]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Enable SSH]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[Monitor]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[Disable Http]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[Disable Ports]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[Port Security]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Disable Telnet]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle1">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Physical Security</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtInst">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over the various security measures for more information.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody1">
<text><![CDATA[Switches are a critical link in the network. Secure them physically, by mounting them in a rack and installing the rack in a secure room. Limit access to authorized network staff.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle2">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Secure Passwords</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody2">
<text><![CDATA[Configure all passwords (user mode, privilege mode and VTY access) with a minimum of six non-repeating characters. Change passwords on a regular basis. Never use words found in a dictionary. Use the enable secret command for privileged level password protection, since it uses advanced encryption techniques. Encrypt all passwords in the display of the running configuration file using the IOS command: <font face='_typewriter'><b>service password-encryption.</b></font>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle3">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Enable SSH for Secure Remote VTY Access</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody3">
<text><![CDATA[SSH is a client server protocol used to login to another device over a network. It provides strong authentication and secure communication over insecure channels.  SSH encrypts the entire login session, including password transmission.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle4">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Monitor Access and Traffic</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody4">
<text><![CDATA[Monitor all traffic passing through a switch to ensure that it complies with company policies. Additionally, record the MAC address of all devices connecting to a specific switch port and all login attempts on the switch. If the switch detects malicious traffic or unauthorized access, take action according to the security policy of the organization. ]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle5">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Disable http Access</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody5">
<text><![CDATA[Disable http access so that no-one enters the switch and modifies the configuration via the Web. The command to disable http access is <font face='_typewriter'><b>no ip http server.</b></font>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txtTitle6">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Disable Unused Ports</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody6">
<text><![CDATA[Disable all unused ports on the switch to prevent unknown PCs or wireless access points from connecting to an available port on the switch. Accomplish this by issuing a <font face='_typewriter'><b>shutdown</b></font> command on the interface. ]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle7">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Enable Port Security</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody7">
<text><![CDATA[Port security restricts access to a switch port to a specific list of MAC addresses. Enter the MAC addresses manually or have the switch learn them dynamically. The specific switch port associates with the MAC addresses allowing only traffic from those devices. If a device with a different MAC address plugs into the port, the switch automatically disables the port.  ]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtTitle8">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Disable Telnet</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txtBody8">
<text><![CDATA[A telnet connection sends data over the public network in clear text. This includes usernames, passwords and data. Disable telnet access to all networking devices by not configuring a password for any VTY sessions at login.]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>