<textcomponents>


<component id="ID_inst">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Click each sense for a description of how it can be used in troubleshooting.</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
 


<component id="Sight_title">
	<text>The Sense of Sight</text>
</component>


<component id="Sight_body">
	<text><![CDATA[Vision is used to detect problems such as improperly connected or poorly constructed cables, including:<ul><br/><br/><li>cables which are not connected</li><li>cables connected to the wrong port</li><li>loose cable connections</li><li>damaged cables and connectors</li><li>Use of the wrong type of cable</li></ul><br/>Vision also allows us to view the condition and function of various network devices with LEDs.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="Smell_title">
	<text>The Sense of Smell</text>
</component>
<component id="Smell_body">
	<text><![CDATA[Smell can alert troubleshooters to components which are overheating. The smell of burning insulation or components is very distinct and is a sure sign that something is seriously wrong.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="Touch_title">
	<text>The Sense of Touch</text>
</component>
<component id="Touch_body">
	<text><![CDATA[Troubleshooters can use touch to feel for overheated components as well as to detect mechanical problems with devices such as cooling fans. These devices usually create a small vibration in the component that can be detected using touch. The absence of this vibration or the presence of excessive amounts of vibration can indicate that the cooling fan has failed or is about to do so.]]> </text>
</component>
<component id="Hearing_title">
	<text>The Sense of Hearing</text>
</component>
<component id="Hearing_body">
	<text>Hearing is used to detect major problems such as electrical issues and the proper operation of cooling fans and disk drives. All devices have characteristic sounds and any change from the normal sounds usually indicate a problem of some sort. </text>
</component>

<component id="The sense of sight">
	<text>The Sense of Sight</text>
</component>

<component id="The sense of Smell">
	<text>The Sense of Smell</text>
</component>

<component id="The sense of Touch">
	<text>The Sense of Touch</text>
</component>

<component id="The sense of Hearing">
	<text>The Sense of Hearing</text>
</component>

</textcomponents>