<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_title01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Network Security Wheel</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<table header='top' headerstyle='black' bordercolor='#CCCCCC' borderwidth='1' shadow='false' shadowcolor='#000000' glow='true' glowcolor='#808080' cellpadding='4'>
	<tr>
		<td bgcolor='#DDDDDD' glow='false' glowcolor='#FCA92E' valign='top' type='dynamic'><font color="#ffffff"><b>Network Security is a continous process built around a security policy.:</b></font></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td bgcolor='#F2F2F2' glow='false' glowcolor='#FCA92E' valign='top' type='dynamic'><ul><li><b>Step 1:</b> Secure the system. This involves implementing security devices such as firewalls, identification authentication systems, and virtual private networks (VPNs) with the intent to prevent unauthorized access to network systems.</li><li><b>Step 2:</b> Monitor the network for violations and attacks against the corporate security policy. Violations can occur within the secured perimeter of the network from a disgruntled employee or from a hacker outside the network. Monitoring the network with a real-time intrusion detection system can ensure that the security devices in Step 1 have been configured properly.</li><li><b>Step 3:</b> Test the effectiveness of the security safeguards in place. Use various tools to identify the security posture of the network with respect to the security procedures that form the hub of the Security Wheel.</li><li><b>Step 4:</b> Improve corporate security. Collect and analyze information from the monitoring and testing phases to make security improvements.</li><li><b>Step 5:</b> All four steps should be repeated on a continuous basis and should be incorporated into updated versions of the corporate security policy.</li></ul></td>
	</tr>
</table>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Secure</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Monitor</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Test</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Improve</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Security<br/>Policy</b>]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>