<textcomponents>


<component id="ID_prompt">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click each symptom button to learn about some possible causes of that symptom.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_btn01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Performance lower than baseline</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Loss of connectivity</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>High collision counts</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Network bottlenecks or congestion</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>High CPU utilization rates</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_btn06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Console error messages</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_osi01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>7 Application</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_osi02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>6 Presentation</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_osi03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>5 Session</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_osi04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>4 Transport</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_osi05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>3 Network</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_osi06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>2 Data Link</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_osi07">
<text><![CDATA[<b>1 Physical</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Performance lower than baseline</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Inadequate cable or poor terminations can result in errors that increase the rate of retransmissions.</li><li>Electrical interference may cause poor performance over copper links.</li><li>Cabling that exceeds the recommended standard distance limitations can cause attenuation problems.</li><li>In a wireless network, interference or a significant increase in traffic can cause network responses to degrade.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title02">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Loss of connectivity</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Intermittent loss can be caused by power-related problems, such as a failing UPS or power supply, resulting in a device reboot or temporary link or device failure.</li><li>Loose connections and tension on the connectors and wires can also cause intermittent loss.</li><li>For wireless coverage areas, intermittent connectivity can be caused by overlapping wireless channels.</li><li>Complete loss can be caused by a cable connection failure or a failed device or interface.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>High collision counts</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Average collision counts on shared media should generally be below 1% of total traffic.</li><li>Collision-based problems are often traced to a single source, such as a bad uplink cable on a hub or switch port, or a link that is exposed to external electrical noise.</li><li>Too many hosts on a single shared segment can contribute to high collision rates.</li><li>Duplex mismatches between devices can cause collisions to be recorded on a switch link.</li><li>A full-duplex switch port should have no collisions.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Network bottlenecks or congestion</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<li>When congestion occurs, frames can be dropped.</li><li>Unexpected high rates of traffic on devices or cables not designed to handle the load can cause congestion.</li><li>Malware, such as Trojans and worms can cause Layer 1 devices and cabling to become congested.</li><li>A protocol analyzer can assist in finding the source of high traffic related problems.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>High CPU utilization rates</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<li>High CPU utilization indicates that a device is operating at or exceeding its design limits.</li><li>CPU overloading can cause a device to shut down or fail.</li>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Console error messages</b>]]></text>
</component>


<component id="ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Error messages reported on the device console can indicate a Physical Layer problem.</li><li>Messages indicating that a device or protocol is down indicate interface or cabling problems.</li>]]></text>
</component>



</textcomponents>

