<transcript lastedited="01.06.09 07:01:00">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.2.1  - The Spanning Tree Algorithm]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts normal STP operation and how STP compensates for network failure.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Three switches, S1, S2, and S3, are interconnected in a full mesh. <br>Switch S1 port F0/1 is connected to S2 port F0/1 (Trunk 1).<br>Switch S2 port F0/2 is connected to S3 port F0/2 (Trunk 2).<br>Switch S3 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/2 (Trunk 3).<br>Switch S1 port F0/3 is connected to PC4 with IP address 172.17.10.27.<br>PC1, PC2, and PC3 are connected to switch S2 ports F0/11, F0/18, and F0/6, respectively.<br>The PC1 IP address is 172.17.10.21, the PC2 IP address is 172.17.10.22, and the PC3 IP address is 172.17.10.23.<br><br>Normal STP operation:<br>Animation sequence:<br>One. PC1 sends a broadcast to switch S2.<br><br>Two. Switch S2 forwards the broadcast out all switch ports, except the originating port and the port associated with Trunk 2.<br><br>Three. Switch S1 forwards the broadcast out all ports, except the originating port.<br><br>Four. Switch S3 receives the frame but does not continue to forward it back to switch S2 because of the blocked port.<br><br><br>STP compensates for network failure:<br>Animation sequence:<br>One. PC1 sends a broadcast to switch S2.<br><br>Two. Switch S2 forwards the broadcast out all switch ports, except the originating port and the port associated with Trunk 2.<br>Three. Switch S1 forwards the broadcast out all ports, except the originating port. Switch S3 receives the frame but does not continue to forward it back to switch S2 because of the blocked port.<br><br>Four. PC1 sends a broadcast frame to switch S2. The trunk link between switches S2 and S1 has failed.<br><br>Five. Switch S3 unblocks the port for Trunk 2, and switch S2 blocks the port for Trunk 1. Switch S2 forwards the broadcast out all switch ports, except the originating port and the failed link for Trunk 1.<br><br>Six. Switch S3 forwards the broadcast out all available switch ports, except the originating port.<br><br>Seven. Switch S1 forwards the broadcast out all available switch ports, except for the originating port and the port for Trunk 1, because it is not available while the link is down.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
