<textcomponents>


<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<table header='top' headerstyle='black' bordercolor='#CCCCCC' borderwidth='1' shadow='false' shadowcolor='#000000' glow='true' glowcolor='#808080' cellpadding='2'>
	    	<tr>
	  	  	<td bgcolor='#F2F2F2' glow='false' glowcolor='#FCA92E' valign='top' type='dynamic'><font  color="#FFFFFF"><b>In this chapter you have learned:</b></font></td></tr>
	<tr>
		<td bgcolor='#DDDDDD' glow='false' glowcolor='#FCA92E' valign='top' type='dynamic'><ul><li>Evolving standards, including 802.11a, b, g and now draft n, allow powerful applications, such as voice, to be deployed as mobility services over wireless LANs.</li><li>A single access point, connected to the wired LAN, provides a basic service set to client stations that associate to it. Multiple access points that share a service set identifier combine to form an extended service set.</li><li>Wireless LANs can be detected by any radio enabled client device, and therefore potentially allow access to attackers that may not have had access to a wired-only network.</li><li>Methods such as MAC address filtering and SSID masking can be part of a security best practice, but these methods alone are easily overcome by a determined attacker. PSK2 Enterprise with 802.1x authentication should be the minimum security used in an enterprise wireless LAN.</li><li>Both access points and wireless NICs must be configured with similar parameters, such as SSID, before association is possible.</li><li>When you configure a wireless LAN, ensure that the devices have the latest firmware so that they can all be configured correctly and with the latest available settings, for instance PSK2 Enterprise.</li><li>If wireless devices are disconnecting from the wireless LAN, check channel settings and check for interference from devices such as microwave ovens and cordless phones.</li></ul></td>
  </tr>
</table>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_title"><text><![CDATA[<b></b>]]></text>
</component>
</textcomponents>
