<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">
<text>
<![CDATA[<b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b>]]>
</text>
</component> 

<component id="ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>This chapter described the Internet as a worldwide collection of computer networks, cooperating with each other to exchange information using common standards. In order to access the Internet you must connect through an ISP.</b>
<ul><li>An ISP is a company that provides the connections and support to access the Internet.</li><br/><li>ISPs support small to large geographic areas.</li><br/><li>ISPs provide services such as e-mail, web pages, IP Telephony and DNS.</li><br/><li>Individual computers and local networks connect to the ISP at a Point of Presence (POP).</li><br/><li>Connection to the ISP can be done via dial-up, DSL, cable, wireless or satellite.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

 <component id="ID_txt01_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>PC</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt02_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>IP</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt03_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>ISP</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt04_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>Internet</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt05_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>Hardware</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt06_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>Software</b>]]></text>
   </component>
   <component id="ID_txt07_02">
      <text><![CDATA[<b>Connectivity</b>]]></text>
   </component>

<component id="ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[
<ul><li>The most important protocol of the Internet is the Internet Protocol (IP).</li><br/><li>The Internet Protocol formats packets into packets that range from 46 to 1500 bytes in length for Ethernet networks and that must contain a valid source and destination IP address.</li><br/><li>IP addresses must be unique on the Internet.</li><br/><li>Every ISP has a control facility for their network, known as the Network Operations Center (NOC) which usually controls traffic flow and houses services such as email and web hosting.</li><br/><li><b>Ping</b> and <b>tracert</b> are utilities that test connectivity to a destination device.
</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[
<ul><li>On network diagrams, a cloud is often used to represent the Internet without showing the details of the connections. </li><br/><li>In the Internet cloud, routers are used to provide alternate paths from source to destination.</li><br/><li>ISPs must be able to accept and deliver information to end users and other ISPs using a variety of technologies.</li><br/><li>Networking devices used in ISPs are high-end, high-speed devices with redundancy.</li><br/><li>An ISP must consider the physical requirements, such as power and air conditioning, of the networking equipment, and the servers it houses.</li></ul>
]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<b>For communication to occur a channel must be present to carry the signals. In the networked world, the medium is usually a physical cable:</b><ul>
<li>Network cables are grouped into two categories: copper cables that carry electrical signals and fiber cables which carry light waves.</li><br/><li>Copper wire, such as UTP and coaxial cable, is extremely vulnerable to both electro-magnetic (EMI) and radio frequency interference (RFI).  Fiber optic cable is made of glass or plastic and is immune to EMI and RFI.</li><br/><li>Unshielded Twisted Pair (UTP) cable is used on most Ethernet networks.</li><br/><li>Coaxial cable, used frequently for cable TV and Internet, has an extremely large bandwidth capacity which allows many signals to be combined or multiplexed together.</li><br/><li>Fiber optic cable can provide a tremendous amount of bandwidth and is suitable for use as backbone cables.
</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>	

    <component id="s4_ID_txt01">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Twisted Pair</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="s4_ID_txt02">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Coaxial Cable</b>]]></text>
	</component>
    <component id="s4_ID_txt03">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Fiber Optic</b>]]></text>
	</component>
	    <component id="s4_ID_txt04">
		<text><![CDATA[<b>Roll over each picture for more information.</b>]]></text>
	</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Cabling standards are guidelines for the installation and testing of cables to ensure acceptable performance as technology evolves.</li><br/><li>TIA/EIA twisted pair termination schemes are T568A and T568B.</li><br/><li>Different types of cables have different wiring schemes.  Common UTP cable types are straight-through, crossover, and rollover.</li><br/><li>Cable testers check for continuity, open terminations, shorts, split pairs and reversed pairs. A cable meter tests for attenuation and crosstalk.</li><br/><li>Cabling best practices help to reduce the number of cable errors and problems that can be encountered and can save a great amount of time, money and frustration.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>	


</textcomponents>