<textcomponents>


<!-- Slide 1  -->
<component id="ID_txt01a">
<text><![CDATA[<b>This chapter discussed various networking threats such as information theft, Identity theft, data loss and manipulation and disruption of service.</b>
<br/><ul><li>Hackers are intruders who gain access to a network through software vulnerabilities, hardware attacks or through the carelessness of network users.</li><br/><li>Attacks can come from both internal and external sources.  Internal attacks account for 70% of security incidents.</li><br/><li>Social engineering is a group of techniques used to deceive internal users into performing specific actions or revealing confidential information.</li><br/><li>Three types of social engineering attacks are: pretexting, phishing, and vishing. 
</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Overview & Social Engineering</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt02">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Hi this is Amy from the help desk. We need to upgrade the software on your computer after work hours. What is  your user ID and password? You can change the password tomorrow when you log in.</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt03">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Ok, my user ID and password are...</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt04">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Social Engineer</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s1_ID_txt05">
  <text><![CDATA[]]></text> 
  </component>
  <component id="s1_ID_txt06">
    <text><![CDATA[<b>Unsuspecting Employee<br>at Xyz Corporation.</b>]]></text> 
  </component>


<!-- Slide 2  -->
<component id="ID_txt02a">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>There are other threats to the security of networks and computers, in addition to social engineering attacks.</b>
</li><li>Viruses are programs that once activated spread by modifying other programs or files, causing damage to files, or erasing them completely.</li><br/><li>A worm is similar to a virus except it runs independently and spreads by resending itself as an e-mail attachment or part of a network message.</li><br/><li>A Trojan horse is a program that appears legitimate. Once initiated, it can damage a hard drive or create a back door into a system allowing hackers to gain access.</li></ul>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b> Viruses, worms and Trojan horses</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s2_ID_txt02">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Spyware, Tracking Cookies</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s2_ID_txt03">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Spam<br/></b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s2_ID_txt04">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Denial of Service</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
  
  
  
<!-- Slide 3  -->  
<component id="ID_txt03">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Effective network security comes from a combination of products and services, combined with a thorough security policy and a commitment to adhere to that policy.</b>
<ul><li>A security policy should include identification and authentication policies, password policies, acceptable use policies, remote access policies, and incident handling procedures.</li><br/><li>All users of the network must support and follow the security policy in order for it to be effective.</li><br/><li>Tools and applications used in securing a network include:</li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Software patches and updates</textformat></li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Virus protection</textformat></li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Spyware protection</textformat></li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Spam blockers</textformat></li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Pop-up blockers</textformat></li><br/><li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='25'>Firewalls</textformat></li><br/><li>Keep software applications up-to-date with the latest security patches and updates to help deter threats.</li><br/><li>Antivirus software, installed on every computer, detects and removes known viruses, worms and Trojan horses.</li><br/><li>Anti-spam software identifies spam and places it into a junk folder or deletes it.</li></ul>]]></text> 
  </component>

<component id="s3_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Firewall</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s3_ID_txt02">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Spam Filter</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s3_ID_txt03">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Patches and Updates<br/></b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s3_ID_txt04">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Anti-Spyware</b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s3_ID_txt05">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Popup Blocker<br/></b>]]></text> 
  </component>
<component id="s3_ID_txt06">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>Anti-Virus</b>]]></text> 
  </component>





<!-- Slide 4  -->
<component id="ID_txt04">
  <text><![CDATA[<b>A firewall controls the traffic between networks and helps prevent unauthorized access. Firewall products use various techniques for determining what is permitted or denied access to a network.</b>
• Packet Filtering controls access based on IP or MAC addresses.<br><br>• Application / Web Site Filtering controls access based on the application.<br><br>• Statefull Packet Inspection (SPI) ensures incoming packets are legitimate responses to requests from internal hosts. SPI can recognize and filter out attacks such as DoS.<br><br>• A DMZ is an area of the network that is accessible to both internal and external users.<br><br>• If the wireless access point is unsecured, anyone who connects to it is considered part of the internal network and is on the protected side of the firewall.<br><br>• Vulnerability analysis tools (security scanners) help identify areas where attacks might occur and offer guidance on steps that can be taken.]]></text> 
  </component>
  





</textcomponents>
