<textcomponents><component id="ID_txt01"><text><![CDATA[Authentication]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt02"><text><![CDATA[Callback]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt03"><text><![CDATA[Compression]]></text></component><component id="ID_txt04"><text><![CDATA[Multilink]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle"><text><![CDATA[Authentication]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody"><text><![CDATA[Authentication options require that the calling side of the link enter information to ensure the caller has the permission to make the call. Peer routers exchange authentication messages. Two authentication choices are Password Authentication Protocol (PAP) and Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol (CHAP).]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle2"><text><![CDATA[Callback]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody2"><text><![CDATA[With this LCP option, a Cisco router can act as a callback client or as a callback server. The client makes the initial call, requests that it be called back, and terminates its initial call. The callback router answers the initial call and makes the return call to the client based on information configured in its memory.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle3"><text><![CDATA[Compression]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody3"><text><![CDATA[Compression options increase the effective throughput on PPP connections by reducing the amount of data in the frame that travels across the link. The protocol decompresses the frame at its destination. Two compression protocols available in Cisco routers are Stacker and Predictor.]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtTitle4"><text><![CDATA[Multilink]]></text></component><component id="ID_txtBody4"><text><![CDATA[This alternative provides load balancing over the PPP router interfaces.]]></text></component><component id="ID_inst"><text><![CDATA[Roll over the LCP options to view a description of the features of the option.]]></text></component></textcomponents>