<transcript lastedited="09.25.08 18:09:50">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[7.2.2 - HDLC and PPP]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts the various options of the LCP negotiation process. Each process and a description of some devices used during the process are listed below.<br><br>Authentication<br>The diagram depicts a switch that is linked to the CSU/DSU, or modem, that is linked by a serial connection to the network cloud. The network cloud is linked by a serial connection to a second CSU/DSU, or modem, and then to a computer. The flow of information is from the CSU/DSU, or modem, to the computer.<br><br>For authentication, the calling side of the link is required to enter specific information to ensure that the caller has the permission to make the call. Peer routers exchange authentication messages. Two authentication options are Password Authentication Protocol (PAP) and Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol (CHAP).<br><br>Callback<br>The diagram depicts a switch that is linked to a CSU/DSU, or modem, that is linked by a serial connection to the network cloud. The network cloud is linked by a serial connection to a second CSU/DSU, or modem, and then to a computer. <br><br>With this LCP, a Cisco router can act as a callback client or as a callback server. The client makes the initial call requests that it be called back, and terminates its initial call.  The callback router answers the initial call and makes the return call to the client based on information configured in its memory.<br><br>Compression<br>The diagram depicts two switches at the opposite ends of a network. Between the switches are two compression devices that compress information on the fly between the networks. The flow of information in the diagram is in both directions through the network. Compression options increase the effective throughput on PPP connections by reducing the amount of data in the frame that travels across the link. The protocol decompresses the frame at its destination. Two compression protocols available in Cisco routers are Stacker and Predictor.<br><br>Multilink<br>The diagram depicts three computers directly connected to a switch and then to a multilink device that provides load balancing over the PPP router interfaces.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
