<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_instructions">
<text>
<![CDATA[<b>Click through the buttons for summary information.</b>]]>
</text>
</component> 

<component id="slide01">
<text><![CDATA[<li>End users evaluate the performance of the network based on the availability and responsiveness of their applications.</li><br/><li>The measurement of application performance should combine user satisfaction with normal technical metrics, such as throughput on the  network, or the number of successful transactions.</li><br/><li>There are four main types of network applications communication patterns:<br/></li><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='60'><li>Client-to-client</li><li>Client-to-distributed server</li><li>Client-to-server farm</li><li>Client-to-enterprise edge</li></textformat><br/><li>The first step in characterizing applications on an existing network is to gather information through a number of methods, including input from the customer staff, the results of a network audit, and an analysis of the network traffic.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Client-Server Farm</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="s1_ID_body03">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Typical client-server farm applications include the following:</b><br>Organizational mail servers (such as Lotus Notes and Microsoft Exchange)<br><br>Common file servers (such as Novell, Microsoft, and Sun)<br><br>Common database servers for organizational applications (such as Sybase, Oracle, and IBM)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Stadium</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Application Server</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Active Directory Server</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[<b>DHCP/DNS Server</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s1_ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Stadium</b>]]></text>
</component>



<component id="slide02">
<text><![CDATA[<li>The choice of hardware installed in the network can affect the performance of the applications.</li><br/><li>Hardware delays can be caused by the processing time that the device takes to filter and forward the traffic.</li><br/><li>Delays can be caused by devices that do not have enough processing power or memory to handle the traffic loads generated by modern applications.</li><br/><li>The top-down approach adapts the design of the physical infrastructure to the needs of the network applications.</li><br/><li>When adding a new application, the network designer needs to consider the impact on the performance of existing applications.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[Internet]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Ticket Sales Office]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[VPN (over DSL)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[ISP2 192.168.4.1/24]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[ISP1 192.168.2.254]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[ISP3 192.168.5.1/24]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[Vendor (Souvenir Shop)]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Edge Router 192.168.2.1]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[Stadium Management Switch 192.168.2.4]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[Team Switch 192.168.2.2]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[Vendor Switch 192.168.2.5]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[Luxury Suites Switch 192.168.2.3]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt13">
<text><![CDATA[192.168.2.0/22]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt14">
<text><![CDATA[Web<br>DHCP<br>E-Commerce<br>Accounting]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt15">
<text><![CDATA[Stadium LAN Devices]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt16">
<text><![CDATA[Payroll Accounting]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt17">
<text><![CDATA[Team Services Devices]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt18">
<text><![CDATA[Accounting]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt19">
<text><![CDATA[Vendor Services Devices]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s2_ID_txt20">
<text><![CDATA[Luxury Suites Services Devices]]></text>
</component>



<component id="s2_ID_inst">
<text><![CDATA[Roll over the highlighted network elements to see how they can affect application performance.]]></text>
</component>




<component id="slide03">
<text><![CDATA[<li>Application traffic types and the mix of applications on the network determine the bandwidth and throughput requirements of the network design.</li><br/><li>Common network application categories include:
<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='60'><li>Transaction-processing applications</li><li>Real-time streaming and voice applications</li><li>File transfer and email applications</li><li>HTTP and web applications</li><li>Microsoft domain services</li></textformat><br/><li>Transaction processing requires the network to provide high availability, fast response times and secure transmission methods.</li><br/><li>In order to produce high quality output, streaming and IP telephony applications cannot tolerate delays. These applications present unique requirements to the network designer.</li><br/><li>Real-time transport protocol (RTP) and real-time transport control protocol (RTCP) are two protocols that support applications that have delay-sensitive delivery requirements.</li><br/><br/><br/></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s3_ID_txt01">
    
<text><![CDATA[<font size='14'>Video on Demand</font>]]></text> 
 
 </component>


<component id="s3_ID_txt02">
     
<text><![CDATA[<font size='14'>Streaming Video</font>]]></text> 

  </component>


<component id="slide04">
<text><![CDATA[<li>File transfer and email applications use large packet sizes and can put high volumes of traffic on the network at unpredictable intervals.This traffic can interfere with the delivery of delay-sensitive applications like voice and video.</li><br/><li>Reliability and availability are more important for file transfer and email applications than sensitivity to traffic delays.</li><br/><li>Security and reliability are the primary concerns in a network supporting high volume web traffic.  Redundant components and data  paths can provide the necessary reliability for business web servers.</li><br/><li>There are design considerations when supporting Microsoft Domain Services on a campus network.  Active Directory requires DNS services  to be active on the Microsoft domain controllers and a number of specific TCP and UDP ports to be open between the servers and clients.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s4_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[File Server]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s4_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Mail Server]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s4_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Web Server]]></text> 
</component>


<component id="slide05">
<text><![CDATA[<li>The primary goal of QoS is to provide priority, including dedicated bandwidth, controlled jitter and latency, and reduced packet loss.</li><br/><li>QoS does not actually create more bandwidth. QoS uses traffic queues to manage bandwidth use to support the applications, such as IP telephony, that are the most sensitive to delays.</li><br/><li>There are three basic steps to ensure that traffic is properly prioritized:</li><br/><TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='60'>Step 1: Identify Traffic Requirements<br/>Step 2: Define Traffic Classes<br/>Step 3: Define QoS Policies</textformat>
<li>When designing a network to support IP telephony, there are a number of new components that must be considered. These include the phones, IP gateways, and call control units.</li><br/><li>Voice over IP (VoIP) services can be used on voice enabled routers to convert traditional voice traffic to IP packets for transmission over WAN connections.  This can be done to eliminate long distance call charges for calls between branch locations.</li><br/><li>IP telephony replaces standard telephones with IP phones that immediately convert voice traffic to IP packets. These systems use call  control units, such as Cisco Unified Communications Manager, to set up and route calls between phones.</li><br/><li>Live streaming video and video-on-demand have different traffic requirements. Broadcast video may be multicast as it happens, while video-on-demand is usually unicast on request.</li><br/><br/><br/><br/></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="s5_ID_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[IP]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[IP Phone]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Call Agent]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[MCU]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[Application Server]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[Voice Gateway]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt07">
<text><![CDATA[Gatekeeper]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt08">
<text><![CDATA[Voice Gateway]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt09">
<text><![CDATA[PSTN]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt10">
<text><![CDATA[Software Telephone]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt11">
<text><![CDATA[Video Endpoint]]></text> 
</component>
<component id="s5_ID_txt12">
<text><![CDATA[IP Phone]]></text> 
</component>

</textcomponents>