<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 15:11:22">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[4.3.2  - Troubleshooting VTP Configurations]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts issues associated with an incorrect revision number. Cisco I O S C L I commands are provided to reset and verify the revision number.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S1 is connected to S2 and S3. Switch S1 is a VTP server, and switches S2 and S3 are VTP clients. The VTP server switch S4, which has a higher revision number, is added to the topology by attaching it to S3.<br><br>PC1, PC2, and PC3 are connected to switch S2. PC4, PC5, and PC6 are connected to switch S3.<br><br>Switch S1:<br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>Switch S2:<br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>Switch S3:<br>VTP Domain = cisco1<br>Revision number = 17<br>V LAN's: 10, 20<br><br>PC1:<br>IP address 172.17.10.21<br>V LAN 10<br><br>PC2:<br>IP address 172.17.20.22<br>V LAN 20<br><br>PC3:<br>IP address 172.17.10.23<br>V LAN 10<br><br>PC4:<br>IP address 172.17.20.24<br>V LAN 20<br><br>PC5:<br>IP address 172.17.20.25<br>V LAN 20<br><br>PC6:<br>IP address 172.17.20.26<br>V LAN 20<br><br>Incorrect Revision Number:<br>Animation Sequence.<br>When the animation starts, switches S1, S2, and S3 are synchronized with a VTP domain of cisco1, a revision number of 17, and V LAN's 10 and 20 defined.<br><br>VTP server switch S4 with a VTP domain of cisco1, a revision number of 35, and V LAN's 30 and 40 defined, is connected to switch S3.<br><br>VTP summary advertisements announce the arrival of a VTP-enabled switch with the highest revision number in the network.<br><br>The animation shows how switch S3, switch S1, and finally switch S2 all reconfigure themselves to the incorrect configuration found in switch S4. The new configuration consists of a VTP domain of cisco1, a revision number of 35, and V LAN's 30 and 40 defined.<br><br>The incorrect V LAN's are not supported, and the ports no longer forward traffic from the computers.<br><br>Reset Revision Number:<br>Before adding a switch to a VTP-enabled network, reset the revision number on the switch using these commands:<br>Enter global configuration mode.<br>#configure terminal<br><br>Configure the VTP domain name.<br>(config)#vtp domain domain-name<br><br>Here is an example showing how to reset the revision number on switch S4:<br>S4(config)#vtp domain test<br>S4(config)#vtp domain cisco1<br><br><br>Verify the Revision Number:<br>S4#show vtp status<br>VTP Version					: 2<br>Configuration Revision			: 0<br>Maximum V LAN's supported locally	: 64<br>Number of existing V LAN's		: 5<br>VTP Operating Mode			: Server<br>VTP Domain Name				: cisco1<br>VTP Pruning Mode				: Disabled<br>VTP V2 Mode				: Disabled<br>VTP Traps Generation			: Disabled<br>MD5 digest			: 0x7D 0x5A 0xA6 0x0E 0x9A 0x72 0xA0 0x3A<br>Configuration last modified by 0.0.0.0 at 0-0-00 00:00:00<br>S4#]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
