<transcript lastedited="09.26.08 14:09:46">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[9.3.3 - OSPF Issues]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts a network, and shows a screen capture of several OSPF show commands.<br><br>Network Topology<br>There are three routers, R1, R2, and R3. <br>R1 is connected to R2 via Serial link (R1: S0/0/0, R2:S0/0/0, Network: 172.20.1.0 /30)<br>R1 is connected to R3 via Serial link (R1: S0/0/1, R3: S0/0/1, Network: 172.20.1.4 /30)<br>R2 is connected to R3 via Serial link (R2: S0/0/1, R3: S0/0/0, Network: 172.20.1.8 /30)<br>R1 has network 192.168.1.0 /24 attached to the F A 0 /0 interface<br>R2 has network 192.168.2.0 /24 attached to the F A 0 /0 interface<br>R3 has network 192.168.3.0 /24 attached to the F A 0 /0 interface<br><br>Only the highlighted parts of each command from R1 are shown below. All other output from the commands is omitted. Complete outputs are available in the Hands-on Labs or Packet Tracer Activities.<br><br>show IP OSPF<br>Displays information about the OSPF routing process, areas, number of interfaces, authentication, and how often the SPF algorithm executes. SPF executions indicate a change in the topology, such as a router being added or a network link going down.<br>R1# show IP OSPF<br>Routing Process "OSPF1" with ID 192.168.1.1<br><br>Area BACKBONE (0)<br>Number of interfaces in this area is 3<br>Area has no authentication<br>SPF algorithm last executed 00:08:48.240 ago<br>SPF algorithm executed 6 times<br><br>show IP OSPF neighbor<br>Displays neighbor ID, the IP addresses of the neighbor interfaces, and the interface on which they were learned. Useful for troubleshooting adjacency problems.<br>R1# show IP OSPF neighbor<br>Neighbor ID - 192.168.3.1<br>Pri - 0<br>State - FULL/ - <br>Dead Time - 00:00:31<br>Address - 172.20.1.6<br>Interface - Serial0/0/1<br><br>Neighbor ID - 192.168.2.1<br>Pri - 0<br>State - FULL/ - <br>Dead Time - 00:00:37<br>Address - 172.20.1.2<br>Interface - Serial0/0/0<br><br>show IP OSPF interface<br>Displays Router ID, Network Type, link cost, State, Interface priority, DR ID, Timer intervals configured, and Neighbor adjacency information.<br>R1# show IP OSPF interface<br>FastEthernet 0 /0 is up, line protocol is up<br>Internet Address 192.168.1.1 /24, Area 0<br>Process ID 1, Router ID 192.168.1.1, Network Type Broadcast, Cost: 1<br><br>Neighbor Count is 0, Adjacent neighbor count is 0<br><br>Serial0/0/1 is up, line protocol is up<br>Process ID 1, Router ID 192.1668.1.1, Network Type POINT_TO_POINT, Cost: 6<br><br>debug IP OSPF events<br>Displays real-time OSPF exchanges between neighbors, including hellos and LSA<br>R1# debug IP OSPF events<br>*Sep 14 17:23:00.351: OSPF: Send hello to 224.0.0.5 area 0 on Serial0/0/1 from 172.20.1.5<br>*Sep 14 17:23:00.655: OSPF: Rcv hello from 192.168.3.1 area 0 from Serial0/0/1 1<br><br>debug IP OSPF packet<br>Displays real-time information for each OSPF packet received.<br>R1# debug IP OSPF packet<br>(No output is highlighted here for this command.)<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
