<transcript lastedited="11.03.08 13:11:24">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[3.1.2  - Types of V LAN's]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The diagram depicts four network traffic types: network management, IP telephony, IP multicast, and normal data.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>There are three switches, S1, S2, and S3. Switch S2 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/1 using a crossover cable. Switch S3 port F0/3 is connected to S1 port F0/3 using a crossover cable. Router R1 interface F0/1 is connected to switch S1 port F0/5 using a straight-through cable. A relational database and a Web/TFTP server are connected to R1 using crossover cables.<br><br>There are seven PC's in total. PC0 connects to switch S1 using port F0/18. PC1 and PC3 connect directly to switch S2 using ports F0/11 and F0/6, respectively. PC2 connects to an IP phone, which connects to switch S2 port F0/18.<br><br>PC4 and PC6 connect directly to switch S3 using ports F0/11 and F0/6, respectively. PC5 connects to an IP phone, which connects to switch S3 using port F0/18.<br><br>Relational Database:<br>V LAN 50<br>172.17.50.253 /24<br><br>Web/TFTP Server:<br>V LAN 50<br>172.17.50.254 /24<br><br>PC0:<br>Management V LAN 99<br>172.17.40.21 /24<br><br>PC1:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.21 /24<br><br>PC4:<br>Faculty V LAN 10<br>172.17.10.24 /24<br><br>PC2:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.22 /24<br>Voice V LAN 150<br><br>PC5:<br>Student V LAN 20<br>172.17.20.25 /24<br>Voice V LAN 150<br><br>PC3:<br>Guest V LAN 30<br>172.17.30.23 /24<br><br>PC6:<br>Guest V LAN 30<br>172.17.30.26 /24<br><br>Network Management:<br>Cables are highlighted between PC0 and switch S1 and from S1 to S2, S1 to S3 and from S1 to R1.<br><br>IP Telephony:<br>The cables are highlighted switches S1 to S2, S1 to S3, and S1 to R1. Switch S2 port F0/18 and switch S3 port F0/18, each of which connects to an IP phone, are also highlighted.<br><br>IP Multicast:<br>Cables are highlighted from switch S2 to PC1 and PC2. Cables are highlighted from S1 to S2, S1 to S3, and S1 to R1. The cable from R1 to the Web/TFTP server is highlighted as well as the cables from switch S3 to PC4 and PC5.<br><br>Normal Data:<br>Cables are highlighted between all devices, except between PC0 and switch S1.<br>]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
