<transcript lastedited="11.05.08 18:11:20">
<title><content-text><![CDATA[5.3.2  - Step 1. Electing a Root Bridge]]></content-text></title>
<brief><content-text><![CDATA[The animation depicts STP convergence step 1: electing a root bridge.<br><br>Network Topology:<br>Three switches, S1, S2, and S3, are interconnected in a full mesh.<br>Switch S1 port F0/1 is connected to S2 port F0/1 (Trunk 1).<br>Switch S2 port F0/2 is connected to S3 port F0/2 (Trunk 2).<br>Switch S3 port F0/1 is connected to S1 port F0/2 (Trunk 3).<br><br>All switches are initially labeled "root bridge" and the following information applies.<br><br>Switch S1:<br>F0/1 BPDU<br>Root ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Bridge ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>Switch S2:<br>F0/1 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 32769.000A00111111<br>Bridge ID: 32769.000A00111111<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>F0/2 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 32769.000A00111111<br>Bridge ID: 32769.000A00111111<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>Switch S3:<br>F0/2 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 32769.000A00222222<br>Bridge ID: 32769.000A00222222<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>Animation sequence:<br>One. Switch S2 forwards BPDU frames out all switch ports. The BPDU frame contains S2's bridge ID and root ID, indicating that switch S2 is the root bridge.<br><br>Two. Switch S3 compares the received root ID with its own and identifies switch S2 as the lower root ID. Switch S3 updates its root ID with the root ID of switch S2. Switch S3 now considers switch S2 the root bridge. Switch S3 updates the path cost to 19, because the BPDU was received on a Fast Ethernet port.<br><br>Three. Switch S1 compares the root ID with its own and identifies its own root ID as the lower root ID. Switch S1 keeps its root ID as the root ID and does not increment the path cost to the root. Switch S1 still considers itself the root bridge.<br><br>Four. Switch S3 forwards BPDU frames out all switch ports. The BPDU frame has the switch S2 root ID populated, indicating that switch S2 is the root bridge.<br><br>Five. Switch S2 compares the received BPDU root ID with its own and identifies that it matches its own. Switch S2 continues to think it is the root bridge. Switch S2 does not update the path cost.<br><br>Six. Switch S1 compares the received BPDU root ID with its own and identifies that its own is lower. Switch S1 continues to think it is the root bridge. Switch S1 does not update the path cost.<br><br>Seven. Switch S1 forwards BPDU frames out all switch ports. The BPDU frame has the switch S1 bridge ID and root ID populated, indicating that switch S1 is the root bridge.<br><br>Eight. Switch S3 compares the received root ID with its own and identifies switch S1 as the lower root ID. Switch S3 updates its root ID with the root ID of switch S1. Switch S3 now considers switch S1 as the root bridge. Switch S3 updates the path cost to 19, because the BPDU was received on a Fast Ethernet port.<br><br>Nine. Switch S2 compares the received root ID with its own and identifies switch S1 as the lower root ID. Switch S2 updates its root ID with the root ID of switch S1.<br><br>Ten. Switch S2 now considers switch S1 the root bridge. Switch S2 updates the path cost to 19, because the BPDU was received on a Fast Ethernet port.<br><br>After BPDU's have been exchanged, switch S1 is elected the root bridge and the following information applies:<br><br>Switch S1 (root bridge):<br>F0/1 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Bridge ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>F0/2 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Bridge ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>Switch S2:<br>F0/2 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Bridge ID: 32769.000A00111111<br>Path Cost = 19<br><br>Switch S3:<br>F0/1 BPDU:<br>Root ID: 24577.000A00333333<br>Bridge ID: 32769.000A00222222<br>Path Cost = 19]]></content-text></brief>
<full><content-text><![CDATA[FULL - NOT FOR PRODUCTION]]></content-text></full>
</transcript>
